<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Exchanges of information extracted from criminal records (debate)</en>
    <fr>Echanges d'informations extraites du casier judiciaire entre les États membres (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="66" id="366" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="66" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Agustín Díaz de Mera García Consuegra, on behalf of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, on the proposal for a Council framework decision on the organisation and content of the exchange of information extracted from criminal records between Member States C6-0052/2006.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de M. Díaz de Mera García Consuegra, au nom de la commission des libertés civiles, de la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="219">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires intérieures, sur la proposition relative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="276">à</DiscourseConnective> l'organisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="293">et</DiscourseConnective> au contenu des échanges d'informations extraites du casier judiciaire entre les États membres - C6-0052/2006 -.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="389" id="368" name="Agustín Díaz de Mera García Consuegra ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="389" docOffset="2">
      <en>rapporteur. - (ES) Mr President, Commissioner, I would like to thank all of my colleagues in the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs for their cooperation on this report and particularly the shadow rapporteurs, Mrs Buitenweg, Mrs Vălean and Mrs Grabowska.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (ES) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, je voudrais remercier tous mes collègues de la commission des libertés civiles, de la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="569">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires intérieures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="597">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur collaboration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="621">à</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="635">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> les rapporteurs fictifs, Mmes Buitenweg, Vălean <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="698">et</DiscourseConnective> Grabowska.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="664" docOffset="3">
      <en>Information on criminal convictions circulates between Member States under the mechanisms of the European Convention on Mutual Assistance on Criminal Matters of 1959, <Alignment alignment="891" annotation_id="831">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="831" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are serious difficulties with that mechanism.</en>
      <fr>Les informations sur les condamnations pénales circulent entre les États membres selon les mécanismes de la convention européenne d'entraide judiciaire en matière pénale de 1959, <Alignment alignment="2977" annotation_id="891">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="891" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces mécanismes présentent de sérieuses failles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="887" docOffset="4">
      <en>These deficiencies were demonstrated dramatically by the case of Fourniret, a French man sentenced in the 1980s to seven years in prison for the rape of a minor and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1052" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> released after just two.</en>
      <fr>Ces failles ont été révélées de manière dramatique par le cas Fourniret, un Français qui avait été condamné dans les années 1980 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1073">à</DiscourseConnective> sept ans de prison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1094">pour</DiscourseConnective> le viol d'une mineure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1121">et</DiscourseConnective> qui avait été libéré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1145">après</DiscourseConnective> seulement deux ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1082" docOffset="5">
      <en>We would discover years later that, between his release and his re-arrest in June 2003, Fourniret had murdered nine girls and was suspected of killing a further twelve.</en>
      <fr>Nous allions découvrir des années <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1205">plus tard</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1215">que</DiscourseConnective>, entre sa libération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1240">et</DiscourseConnective> sa nouvelle arrestation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1267">en</DiscourseConnective> juin 2003, Fourniret avait assassiné neuf filles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1319">et</DiscourseConnective> était soupçonné d'en avoir tué douze autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1251" docOffset="6">
      <en>He had managed to evade judicial action for more than 14 years, simply by changing his residence from one Member State to another, <Alignment alignment="1508" annotation_id="1382">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1382" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1386" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">furthermore</DiscourseConnective>, to top everything, he even managed to get a job in a school.</en>
      <fr>Il avait réussi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1383">à</DiscourseConnective> échapper à une action en justice pendant plus de 14 ans, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1442">simplement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1453">en</DiscourseConnective> changeant son domicile d'un État membre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1496">à</DiscourseConnective> un autre, <Alignment alignment="1382" annotation_id="1508">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1508" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1512">pour</DiscourseConnective> couronner le tout, il avait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1545">même</DiscourseConnective> réussi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1557">à</DiscourseConnective> trouver un emploi dans une école.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1460" docOffset="7">
      <en>It was clear that the mechanisms for exchanging information on criminal records had to be modified and improved.</en>
      <fr>Il était évident <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1610">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il fallait modifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1633">et</DiscourseConnective> améliorer les mécanismes d'échange d'informations extraites du casier judiciaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1573" docOffset="8">
      <en>The proposal for a Council framework decision intends to replace the information exchange mechanisms regulated in Article 22 of the Convention of 1959 and repeal the decision of 21 November 2005, all with a view to guaranteeing that the Member State of nationality is in a position to provide a correct, rapid and exhaustive response to requests for information that it receives with regard to convictions of its nationals.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de décision-cadre du Conseil vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1767">à</DiscourseConnective> remplacer les mécanismes d'échange d'informations prévus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1826">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 22 de la Convention de 1959 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1866">et</DiscourseConnective> à annuler la décision du 21 novembre 2005, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1912">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1931">que</DiscourseConnective> l'État membre de nationalité est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1968">en</DiscourseConnective> mesure de fournir une réponse correcte, rapide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2018">et</DiscourseConnective> exhaustive aux demandes d'informations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2060">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il reçoit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2073">en</DiscourseConnective> rapport avec les condamnations de ses citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1997" docOffset="9">
      <en>Of the measures included in the Council's proposal, we must highlight the following:</en>
      <fr>Parmi les mesures incluses dans la proposition du Conseil, nous devons souligner les suivantes:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2082" docOffset="10">
      <en>the principle of centralising information is retained;</en>
      <fr>le principe de centralisation des informations est maintenu;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2137" docOffset="11">
      <en>a framework is established for contributing to, designing and implementing a computerised system for the exchange of information on criminal convictions, based on the use of a standard European format that makes it possible to exchange information in a standard, computerised and easily translatable form by means of automated mechanisms;</en>
      <fr>un cadre est établi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2301">pour</DiscourseConnective> contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2317">à</DiscourseConnective> concevoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2329">et</DiscourseConnective> mettre en œuvre un système informatisé d'échange d'informations extraites du casier judiciaire, qui se fonde sur l'utilisation d'un format européen standardisé permettant d'échanger des informations d'une manière standardisée, informatisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2572">et</DiscourseConnective> aisée à traduire, par le recours à des mécanismes automatisés;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2476" docOffset="12">
      <en>the principle of obligatory forwarding to the Member State of nationality is taken up, eliminating the dispensation of notification <Alignment alignment="2762" annotation_id="2608">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2608" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the person <Alignment alignment="14075" annotation_id="2624">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2624" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> has the nationality of the Member State passing the sentence; <Alignment alignment="2879" annotation_id="2691">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2691" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, finally,</en>
      <fr>le principe de la transmission obligatoire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2681">à</DiscourseConnective> l'État membre de nationalité est prévu, supprimant la dispense de notification <Alignment alignment="1450" annotation_id="2762">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2762" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la personne possède <Alignment alignment="2624" annotation_id="2790">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2790" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la nationalité de l'État membre sur le territoire duquel elle a été condamnée; <Alignment alignment="2691" annotation_id="2879">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2879" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2883">enfin</DiscourseConnective>,</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2705" docOffset="13">
      <en>the obligation to conserve the information forwarded to the State of nationality is laid down.</en>
      <fr>l'obligation de conserver les informations transmises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2944">à</DiscourseConnective> l'État de nationalité est imposée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2800" docOffset="14">
      <en>With regard to the parliamentary measures proposed, I would highlight the following:</en>
      <fr>Quant aux mesures proposées par le Parlement, je voudrais souligner les suivantes:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2885" docOffset="15">
      <en>with a view to guaranteeing the integrity and authenticity of the information forwarded, the Member State handing down the conviction shall be considered to be the owner or proprietor of the data relating to the sentences passed by their courts and tribunals;</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3064">dans le but de</DiscourseConnective> garantir l'intégrité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3100">et</DiscourseConnective> l'authenticité des informations transmises, l'État membre de condamnation doit être considéré comme le détenteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3216">ou</DiscourseConnective> le propriétaire des données relatives aux condamnations prononcées par ses cours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3300">et</DiscourseConnective> tribunaux;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3145" docOffset="16">
      <en>the future framework Decision must provide for a range of additional guarantees in the field of the protection of personal data;</en>
      <fr>la future décision-cadre doit apporter une série de garanties complémentaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3392">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de protection des données à caractère personnel;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3274" docOffset="17">
      <en>with regard to the definition of convictions, for the sake of consistency with other reports by this Parliament, the definition contained in the report by my esteemed friend and colleague, Mr Demetriou, must be retained;</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3452">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la définition des condamnations, il convient de conserver, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3530">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer la cohérence avec d'autres rapports de ce Parlement, la définition contenue dans le rapport de mon estimé ami <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3653">et</DiscourseConnective> collègue, M. Demetriou;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3495" docOffset="18">
      <en>the inclusion of sentences in the register of criminal records of the Member State where the sentence was passed is a prior obligation, <Alignment alignment="3819" annotation_id="3631">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3631" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it guarantees the authenticity and accuracy of the information forwarded; the information on sentences will <Alignment alignment="3176" annotation_id="3745">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3745" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> only be forwarded <Alignment alignment="18119" annotation_id="3773">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3773" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">once</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it has been registered, but not before;</en>
      <fr>l'inscription des condamnations dans le registre des casiers judiciaires de l'État membre de condamnation est une obligation sine qua non, <Alignment alignment="3631" annotation_id="3819">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3819" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle garantit l'authenticité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3852">et</DiscourseConnective> l'exactitude des informations transmises; les informations relatives aux condamnations ne seront <Alignment alignment="3745" annotation_id="3952">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3952" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> transmises que <Alignment alignment="3773" annotation_id="3972">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3972" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles auront été enregistrées, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4010">et</DiscourseConnective> pas avant;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3818" docOffset="19">
      <en>it must be made clear that the deletion of criminal records depends not just on completing the sentence, but also on compliance with other additional conditions, such as fulfilling the civil responsibilities arising from the crime, <Alignment alignment="4293" annotation_id="4050">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4050" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not re-offending within the time period laid down in law;</en>
      <fr>il est indispensable de préciser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4057">que</DiscourseConnective> la suppression de casiers judiciaires dépend <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4106">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> de l'accomplissement de la peine, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4154">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4159">également</DiscourseConnective> du respect d'autres conditions complémentaires, telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4224">que</DiscourseConnective> le fait d'assumer les responsabilités civiles découlant du délit <Alignment alignment="4050" annotation_id="4293">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4293" sense="Expansion.Alternative">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de ne pas récidiver durant la période imposée par la législation;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4111" docOffset="20">
      <en>it is necessary to establish clearly which legal framework will regulate the deletion of data, that is to say, whether the legislation of the Member State where the sentence is passed is applicable, or that of the State of nationality of the convicted person.</en>
      <fr>il est nécessaire de désigner clairement le cadre juridique qui régira la suppression des données, c'est-à-dire, qu'il faut déterminer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4497">si</DiscourseConnective> l'on applique la législation de l'État membre de condamnation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4562">ou</DiscourseConnective> celle de l'État de nationalité de la personne condamnée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4371" docOffset="21">
      <en>With regard to the conditions for use, Mr Frattini, I genuinely share your concern regarding personal data.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4622">Pour</DiscourseConnective> ce qui est des conditions d'utilisation, Monsieur Frattini, je partage réellement votre préoccupation concernant les données à caractère personnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4479" docOffset="22">
      <en>The proposal is much more restrictive than the provisions in force in the field of judicial cooperation in criminal matters, which is justified by the speed with which information on criminal records can become out of date.</en>
      <fr>La proposition est bien plus restrictive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4816">que</DiscourseConnective> les dispositions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4837">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur dans le domaine de l'entraide judiciaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4889">en</DiscourseConnective> matière pénale, ce qui se justifie par la vitesse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4942">à</DiscourseConnective> laquelle les informations extraites du casier judiciaire peuvent devenir obsolètes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4703" docOffset="23">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5028" annotation_id="4703">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4703" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, each time information on a person's criminal record is required for the purposes of a new criminal procedure, it will be necessary to submit a new request for information.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4703" annotation_id="5028">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5028" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, chaque fois que des informations extraites du casier judiciaire d'une personne sont requises aux fins d'une nouvelle procédure pénale, il sera nécessaire d'introduire une nouvelle demande d'informations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4886" docOffset="24">
      <en>I would like to end, Mr President, by calling upon the honourable Members to vote in favour of the proposed report, <Alignment alignment="5356" annotation_id="5002">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5002" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I thank you for listening.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais terminer, Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5293">en</DiscourseConnective> demandant aux députés de voter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5327">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur du rapport proposé <Alignment alignment="5002" annotation_id="5356">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5356" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je vous remercie de m'avoir écouté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5033" id="369" name="Panayiotis Demetriou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5033" docOffset="25">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (EL) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the proposal we are debating this evening is a necessary step towards the development of judicial and police cooperation between the Member States of the European Union, a step towards promoting the strategy to develop an area of justice and security <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5372" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I congratulate Commissioner Frattini on promoting proposals such as we are examining today, which promote the Hague programme.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (EL) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5484">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, la proposition que nous débattons ce soir est une étape nécessaire vers le développement de la coopération judiciaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5616">et</DiscourseConnective> policière entre les États membres de l'Union européenne, une étape vers la promotion de la stratégie de création de l'espace de justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5755">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité. Je félicite à cet égard le commissaire Frattini de promouvoir des propositions telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5857">que</DiscourseConnective> celle que nous examinons aujourd'hui, qui soutient le programme de La Haye.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5503" docOffset="26">
      <en>Recording convictions and passing them on for recording in the Member State of which the convict is a national and exchanges of information on convictions in general will undoubtedly help in combating both national and cross-border crime.</en>
      <fr>L'inscription des condamnations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5969">et</DiscourseConnective> la transmission des informations les concernant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6020">pour</DiscourseConnective> enregistrement dans l'État membre de nationalité, de même que, de manière plus générale, les échanges d'informations relatives à des condamnations, permettront sans aucun doute de lutter contre la criminalité nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6244">et</DiscourseConnective> transfrontalière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5742" docOffset="27">
      <en>There are, of course, gaps in the proposal.</en>
      <fr>Bien entendu, la proposition présente des lacunes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5786" docOffset="28">
      <en>There is no Community method for regulating the question of recording administrative convictions which, in most Member States are not entered in the criminal records.</en>
      <fr>Il n'existe pas de méthode communautaire permettant de réglementer la question de l'inscription des condamnations administratives, qui, dans la plupart des États membres, ne sont pas inscrites dans les casiers judiciaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5953" docOffset="29">
      <en>There is no Community regulation of the question of recording convictions extracted from criminal records.</en>
      <fr>Il n'existe pas de règlement communautaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6582">pour</DiscourseConnective> la question de l'inscription des condamnations extraites des casiers judiciaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6060" docOffset="30">
      <en>Unfortunately, the variety of national regulations is still needed.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6669">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, la diversité des réglementations nationales est toujours nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6128" docOffset="31">
      <en>There is still no approximation whatsoever of laws even on these procedural issues.</en>
      <fr>Il n'existe toujours aucune approximation des législations, y compris sur ces questions de procédure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6212" docOffset="32">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6857" annotation_id="6212">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6212" sense="Comparison.Concession">Nonetheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the coupling of national systems for recording and using information on convictions in the framework proposal goes some way towards dealing with the lack of a single Community policy on all aspects of the matter.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6212" annotation_id="6857">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6857" sense="Comparison.Concession">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la combinaison des systèmes nationaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6906">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> l'inscription <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6930">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'utilisation des informations relatives aux condamnations dans le cadre de la proposition signifie, dans une certaine mesure, que l'on remédie au manque de politique communautaire commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7125">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous les aspects de cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6438" docOffset="33">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7166" annotation_id="6438">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6438" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we must emphasise the need for respect for the right to protection of personal data, not only theoretically, but also in practice.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6438" annotation_id="7166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7166" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous devons souligner le besoin de respecter le droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7231">à</DiscourseConnective> la protection des données à caractère personnel, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7282">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> en théorie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7308">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> dans la pratique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6578" docOffset="34">
      <en>This will become clear in the natural course of events.</en>
      <fr>Cela s'avérera évident <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7360">par la suite</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6634" docOffset="35">
      <en>We hope that respect for this right will be real and constant.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7388">que</DiscourseConnective> le respect de ce droit sera effectif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7429">et</DiscourseConnective> constant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6697" docOffset="36">
      <en>I support the report by my honourable friend Mr Díaz de Mera <Alignment alignment="7492" annotation_id="6758">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6758" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I congratulate him on the interest which he has always demonstrated in the European Parliament in the promotion of this strategy to create an area of freedom, security and justice.</en>
      <fr>Je soutiens le rapport de mon ami M. Díaz de Mera <Alignment alignment="6758" annotation_id="7492">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7492" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je le félicite de l'intérêt dont il a toujours fait preuve au Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7576">pour</DiscourseConnective> la promotion de cette stratégie de création de l'espace de liberté, de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7661">et</DiscourseConnective> de justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6943" docOffset="37">
      <en>I believe that the report will be supported by a large majority in Parliament tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7685">que</DiscourseConnective>, lors du vote de demain, le rapport sera soutenu par une large majorité du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7031" id="370" name="Genowefa Grabowska">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7031" docOffset="38">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (PL) Mr President, the Member States have their own guidelines for collecting data on those convicted in criminal trials. Sentencing data is stored in national criminal registers.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, les États membres possèdent leurs propres instructions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7882">pour</DiscourseConnective> la collecte des données relatives aux personnes condamnées au pénal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7241" docOffset="39">
      <en>Each Member State is responsible for the central storage and management of information on court sentences.</en>
      <fr>Les données concernant les condamnations sont conservées dans les registres nationaux des condamnations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7348" docOffset="40">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6978" annotation_id="7348">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7348" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we are crossing national borders ever more frequently <Alignment alignment="8131" annotation_id="7411">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7411" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="8135" annotation_id="7416">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7416" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are no angels, we sometimes come into conflict with the criminal law system in another Member State, and are tried and sentenced there.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7348" annotation_id="8061">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8061" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous traversons les frontières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8103">de plus</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8111">en plus</DiscourseConnective> fréquemment <Alignment alignment="7411" annotation_id="8131">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8131" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="7416" annotation_id="8135">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8135" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne sommes pas des anges, nous sommes parfois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8191">en</DiscourseConnective> conflit avec le système pénal d'un autre État membre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8247">et</DiscourseConnective> nous sommes jugés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8268">et</DiscourseConnective> condamnés dans cet État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7558" docOffset="41">
      <en>What should we do with these sentences?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8296">Que</DiscourseConnective> devons-nous faire avec ces condamnations?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7598" docOffset="42">
      <en>Should we register them <Alignment alignment="3408" annotation_id="7622">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7622" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not?</en>
      <fr>Devons-nous les enregistrer <Alignment alignment="7622" annotation_id="8370">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8370" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7630" docOffset="43">
      <en>The Member States have different, not very cohesive practices <Alignment alignment="8450" annotation_id="7692">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7692" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is why we need to harmonise this field.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres ont des pratiques différentes et pas très cohérentes, <Alignment alignment="7692" annotation_id="8450">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8450" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8453">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous devons harmoniser ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7741" docOffset="44">
      <en>We need closer cooperation between judicial bodies, we need a better and more efficient exchange of information <Alignment alignment="4406" annotation_id="7853">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7853" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we need to ensure that the Member States exchange accurate, comprehensive and exhaustive information in response to each request for information from criminal records.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons besoin d'une coopération plus étroite entre les organismes judiciaires, nous avons besoin d'un échange d'informations de meilleure qualité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8653">et</DiscourseConnective> plus efficace <Alignment alignment="7853" annotation_id="8670">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8670" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons nous assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8698">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres échangent des informations exactes, complètes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8766">et</DiscourseConnective> exhaustives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8781">en</DiscourseConnective> réponse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8792">à</DiscourseConnective> chaque demande d'informations relatives à des casiers judiciaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8025" docOffset="45">
      <en>This is what the framework decision proposal aims to do.</en>
      <fr>C'est ce que vise la proposition de décision-cadre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8082" docOffset="46">
      <en>We need a European system for exchanging information in a standardised, computerised format, where interpretation is facilitated by automated procedures and a standardised format.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons besoin d'un système européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8953">pour</DiscourseConnective> pouvoir échanger des informations dans un format standardisé et informatisé dont l'interprétation est facilitée par des procédures automatisées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9102">et</DiscourseConnective> un format standardisé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8262" docOffset="47">
      <en>That is why my political group support this report. <Alignment alignment="9183" annotation_id="8314">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8314" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, my group does have one serious doubt concerning the report, which discusses judicial cooperation and the exchange of information.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9128">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> mon groupe politique appuie ce rapport, <Alignment alignment="8314" annotation_id="9183">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9183" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> émet malgré tout un sérieux doute concernant ce document, qui traite de la coopération judiciaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9286">et</DiscourseConnective> des échanges d'informations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8453" docOffset="48">
      <en>Bearing in mind the importance of telling the whole truth, respect for the rights of and fairness towards the victims of the terrorist attacks in Spain on 11 March, we would like to express our concern regarding the choice of rapporteur for this report.</en>
      <fr>Compte tenu de l'importance de révéler toute la vérité, de respecter les droits des victimes des attentats du 11 mars <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9436">en</DiscourseConnective> Espagne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9447">et</DiscourseConnective> de leur rendre justice, nous voudrions exprimer notre préoccupation concernant le choix du rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9552">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8707" docOffset="49">
      <en>He has <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8714" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> drawn up other reports on the issue of police and judicial cooperation in criminal matters.</en>
      <fr>M. Díaz de Mera a rédigé d'autres rapports sur la question de la coopération policière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9656">et</DiscourseConnective> judiciaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9670">en</DiscourseConnective> matière pénale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8811" docOffset="50">
      <en>The European Parliament must be seen to be an institution based on the principle of transparency and which serves the citizens.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen doit être considéré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9731">comme</DiscourseConnective> une institution qui est fondée sur le principe de la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9803">et</DiscourseConnective> qui sert les intérêts des citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8939" docOffset="51">
      <en>That is why the authors of specific reports cannot be seen, in view of their activities at a national level, to be controversial figures.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle les auteurs de rapports spécifiques, étant donné leurs activités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9937">à</DiscourseConnective> l'échelon national, ne peuvent pas être considérés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9990">comme</DiscourseConnective> des personnalités controversées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9077" docOffset="52">
      <en>To conclude, I would like to indicate that my political group welcomes the good compromise that has been achieved in this report.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10029">Pour conclure</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais indiquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10065">que</DiscourseConnective> mon groupe politique se félicite du bon compromis trouvé dans ce rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9207" docOffset="53">
      <en>We support this report <Alignment alignment="10169" annotation_id="9230">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9230" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we intend to vote in favour of it.</en>
      <fr>Nous soutenons le rapport <Alignment alignment="9230" annotation_id="10169">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10169" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avons l'intention de voter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10199">en</DiscourseConnective> sa faveur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9269" docOffset="54">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="10226" annotation_id="9272">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9272" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> believe that the implementation of this decision will mean that Member States will trust each other more, <Alignment alignment="10335" annotation_id="9383">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9383" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that this much-needed basis of trust will <Alignment alignment="10393" annotation_id="9429">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9429" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> apply to criminal proceedings.</en>
      <fr>Nous pensons <Alignment alignment="9272" annotation_id="10226">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10226" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10232">que</DiscourseConnective> la mise en œuvre de cette décision entraînera un niveau de confiance accru entre les États membres <Alignment alignment="9383" annotation_id="10335">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10335" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10338">que</DiscourseConnective> cette base de confiance indispensable s'appliquera <Alignment alignment="9429" annotation_id="10393">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10393" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aux procédures pénales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9465" id="372" name="Jaromír Kohlíček">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9465" docOffset="55">
      <en>on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group. - (CS) Ladies and gentlemen, the report by Mr Díaz de Mera García Consuegra rightly notes that information on investigations shared between countries should have a standardised format <Alignment alignment="10675" annotation_id="9681">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9681" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> should be shared as flexibly as possible.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. - (CS) Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10469">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, le rapport de M. Díaz de Mera García Consuegra souligne, à juste titre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10555">que</DiscourseConnective> les informations relatives aux enquêtes communes à plusieurs pays devraient se présenter dans un format standardisé <Alignment alignment="9681" annotation_id="10675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10675" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être partagées d'une manière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10707">aussi</DiscourseConnective> flexible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10722">que</DiscourseConnective> possible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9727" docOffset="56">
      <en>The report is <Alignment alignment="10752" annotation_id="9741">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9741" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aimed at ensuring the exchange of other information that in certain situations may prove useful.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport vise <Alignment alignment="9741" annotation_id="10752">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10752" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10762">à</DiscourseConnective> assurer l'échange d'autres informations qui peuvent s'avérer utiles dans d'autres situations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9843" docOffset="57">
      <en>Every time such information is exchanged there are, of course, potential pitfalls: at the very least there are the different legal systems in the Member States and the different classifications of the same acts.</en>
      <fr>Chaque fois que ce type d'échanges se produit, il existe bien sûr des embûches potentielles: citons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10958">au moins</DiscourseConnective> les différents systèmes juridiques des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11020">et</DiscourseConnective> les différentes classifications des mêmes faits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10055" docOffset="58">
      <en>In extreme cases this may involve the boundary between a crime and a minor misdemeanour.</en>
      <fr>Dans des cas extrêmes, cela peut concerner la limite entre un crime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11140">et</DiscourseConnective> une infraction mineure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10144" docOffset="59">
      <en>Personally, I am not happy that Mr Díaz de Mera García Consuegra was appointed rapporteur for this report despite being accused of non-cooperation with the Spanish police in connection with misleading information implicating ETA in the Madrid train attack.</en>
      <fr>Personnellement, je ne me réjouis pas de ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11211">que</DiscourseConnective> M. Díaz de Mera García Consuegra ait été désigné comme rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11281">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11297">alors qu'</DiscourseConnective>il a été accusé de refus de coopération avec la police espagnole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11371">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de fausses informations impliquant l'ETA dans l'attentat ayant visé un train à Madrid.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10401" docOffset="60">
      <en>Where is the political and human responsibility of the former head of the Spanish police?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11467">Qu'en</DiscourseConnective> est-il de la responsabilité politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11511">et</DiscourseConnective> humaine de l'ancien chef de la police espagnole?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10491" docOffset="61">
      <en>To conclude, my group has significant reservations regarding this report.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11563">En</DiscourseConnective> conclusion, mon groupe formule des réserves significatives à l'égard de ce rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10565" id="373" name="Carlos Coelho">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10565" docOffset="62">
      <en>(PT) Mr President, I must begin by referring to the last speech.</en>
      <fr>(PT) Monsieur le Président, je dois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11686">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> faire référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11715">à</DiscourseConnective> l'intervention précédente.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10630" docOffset="63">
      <en>It is unacceptable here in this Chamber for attempts to be made at curtailing the parliamentary and political rights of any MEP whose rights have not been curtailed either by decision of this Parliament or by legal decision in his or her own country.</en>
      <fr>Il est inacceptable, dans ce Parlement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11784">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on tente de réduire les droits parlementaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11836">et</DiscourseConnective> politiques des députés dont les droits n'ont été restreints par aucune décision de ce Parlement, ni par aucune décision juridique de leur propre pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10881" docOffset="64">
      <en>We cannot accept this kind of political persecution of Mr Diaz De Mera Consuegra, who has a distinguished record in combating crime and defending justice as a professional in his own Member State <Alignment alignment="12243" annotation_id="11077">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11077" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> who has been an outstanding Member of this House.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pouvons pas accepter ce genre de persécution politique de M. Díaz de Mera García Consuegra, qui possède une expérience professionnelle remarquable en matière de lutte contre la criminalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12187">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense de la justice dans son propre État membre <Alignment alignment="2415" annotation_id="12243">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12243" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui a été un député exceptionnel de ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11131" docOffset="65">
      <en>The report before us today is further proof of his political ability and of the rigour that has characterised both his parliamentary work and his professional life.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport que nous examinons aujourd'hui est une nouvelle preuve de sa compétence politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12389">et</DiscourseConnective> de la rigueur qui a caractérisé tant son travail parlementaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12455">que</DiscourseConnective> sa vie professionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11296" docOffset="66">
      <en>I should like to say to Mr Frattini that I am firmly behind everything he said in relation to the Council's attitude.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais dire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12500">à</DiscourseConnective> M. Frattini <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12514">que</DiscourseConnective> je soutiens fermement tout ce qu'il a déclaré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12564">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de l'attitude du Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11414" docOffset="67">
      <en>This measure is a much-needed one, <Alignment alignment="12630" annotation_id="11449">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11449" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is a great shame that the Council did not go further, in terms of both trust between the Member States and Parliament's involvement.</en>
      <fr>Cette mesure est indispensable <Alignment alignment="11449" annotation_id="12630">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12630" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est tout à fait honteux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12660">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil ne soit pas allé plus loin, tant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12708">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la confiance entre les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12764">qu'</DiscourseConnective>au niveau de la participation du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11589" docOffset="68">
      <en>In any event, I share everything that other speakers have said regarding the need to look into criminal background in detail and regarding the fact that the sharing of this information between the Member States constitutes a value-added in combating crime, in terms of identifying suspects, supporting criminal investigations and determining the severity of a punishment.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12811">En tout cas</DiscourseConnective>, je partage tout ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12843">que</DiscourseConnective> les autres orateurs ont affirmé sur la nécessité d'examiner l'historique pénal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12926">en</DiscourseConnective> détail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12936">et</DiscourseConnective> sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12951">que</DiscourseConnective> l'échange de ces informations entre les États membres constitue une valeur ajoutée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13038">pour</DiscourseConnective> la lutte contre la criminalité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13075">s'</DiscourseConnective>agissant d'identifier les suspects, de soutenir les enquêtes pénales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13146">et</DiscourseConnective> de déterminer la sévérité d'une peine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11961" docOffset="69">
      <en>I should like to finish by saying that I <Alignment alignment="17527" annotation_id="12002">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12002" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> agree with those who say that the Council must act more quickly in adopting, on the one hand, the framework decision on procedural guarantees for suspects and defendants in criminal proceedings and, on the other, the framework decision on data protection in the third pillar, for which the rapporteur was Mrs Roure, a further essential element in striking an appropriate balance in the legal measures in the sector.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais terminer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13209">en</DiscourseConnective> disant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13219">que</DiscourseConnective> je suis <Alignment alignment="12002" annotation_id="13231">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13231" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'accord avec les personnes qui estiment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13282">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil doit agir plus rapidement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13323">en</DiscourseConnective> adoptant, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13336">d'une part</DiscourseConnective>, la décision-cadre sur les garanties procédurales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13397">pour</DiscourseConnective> les suspects <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13415">et</DiscourseConnective> les défendeurs dans le cadre des procédures pénales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13470">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13474">d'autre part</DiscourseConnective>, la décision-cadre sur la protection des données dans le cadre du troisième pilier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13571">pour</DiscourseConnective> laquelle le rapporteur était Mme Roure et qui constitue un autre élément essentiel dans la recherche d'un équilibre approprié parmi les mesures juridiques de ce secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12423" id="374" name="Agustín Díaz de Mera García Consuegra">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12423" docOffset="70">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, I have requested the floor in order to rebut some unacceptable personal remarks, <Alignment alignment="13858" annotation_id="12523">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12523" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I have essentially requested the floor in order to thank my colleague, Mr Coelho, who has spoken not just as a friend, but also with knowledge of the facts.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, j'ai demandé la parole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13797">pour</DiscourseConnective> réfuter certaines remarques personnelles inacceptables, <Alignment alignment="8693" annotation_id="13858">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13858" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13868">surtout</DiscourseConnective> demandé la parole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13894">pour</DiscourseConnective> remercier mon collègue M. Coelho, qui a parlé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13945">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13962">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>ami, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13975">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13986">en</DiscourseConnective> connaissance de cause.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12684" docOffset="71">
      <en>I will just make one comment demanding a correction and an apology from Mr Kohlíček.</en>
      <fr>Je ne formulerai qu'un seul commentaire afin de demander une rectification <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14087">et</DiscourseConnective> des excuses de la part de M. Kohlícek.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12769" docOffset="72">
      <en>Mr Kohlíček, the only possible explanations for your extremely unfortunate comments tonight in this House are ignorance, bad faith or some immoral purpose.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur Kohlícek, les seules explications possibles concernant vos remarques extrêmement regrettables de ce soir, dans ce Parlement, sont l'ignorance, la mauvaise foi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14297">ou</DiscourseConnective> un but immoral.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12925" docOffset="73">
      <en>I am sure, Mr Kohlíček, that you have heard - I hope you have heard - of something called presumption of innocence.</en>
      <fr>Je suis certain, Monsieur Kohlícek, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14352">que</DiscourseConnective> vous avez entendu parler - j'espère que vous en avez entendu parler - de ce que l'on appelle la présomption d'innocence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13041" docOffset="74">
      <en>I am sure you have heard of the European Union's Charter of Fundamental Rights and Article 48 thereof. I am sure you have heard of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights of 1948 and Article 11 thereof.</en>
      <fr>Je suis sûr que vous avez entendu parler de la charte des droits de l'homme de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14575">et</DiscourseConnective> de son article 48; je suis certain que vous avez entendu parler de la déclaration universelle des droits de l'homme de 1948 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14702">et</DiscourseConnective> de son article 11.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13246" docOffset="75">
      <en>I do not imagine that you are familiar - <Alignment alignment="14763" annotation_id="13287">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13287" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is no reason why you should be familiar - with Article 24 of the Spanish Constitution.</en>
      <fr>Je ne pense pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14740">que</DiscourseConnective> vous connaissiez - <Alignment alignment="13287" annotation_id="14763">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14763" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il n'y a aucune raison pour que vous le connaissiez - l'article 24 de la Constitution espagnole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13384" docOffset="76">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="22000" annotation_id="13384">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13384" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> all free and democratic Constitutions contain their Article 48, Article 11 or Article 24.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13384" annotation_id="14863">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14863" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, toute constitution libre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14899">et</DiscourseConnective> démocratique contient l'article 48, l'article 11 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14951">ou</DiscourseConnective> l'article 24 dont je viens de parler.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13478" docOffset="77">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="15001" annotation_id="13480">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13480" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hope that, <Alignment alignment="15011" annotation_id="13501">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13501" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you are in a position to understand what the presumption of innocence means, <Alignment alignment="15097" annotation_id="13583">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13583" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in particular, <Alignment alignment="15124" annotation_id="13603">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13603" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you are in a position to properly understand a case about which, to judge from what you have said, you clearly know absolutely nothing, you will be capable of making a private and public apology, <Alignment alignment="15362" annotation_id="13804">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13804" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I shall be willing to accept it.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <Alignment alignment="13480" annotation_id="15001">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15001" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15006">que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="13501" annotation_id="15011">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15011" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous serez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15030">en</DiscourseConnective> mesure de comprendre ce que signifie la présomption d'innocence <Alignment alignment="13583" annotation_id="15097">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15097" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15101">plus particulièrement</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="13603" annotation_id="15124">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15124" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous serez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15143">en</DiscourseConnective> mesure de comprendre correctement une affaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15192">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de laquelle - à en juger d'après ce que vous avez déclaré - vous ne savez manifestement absolument rien, vous pourrez présenter des excuses privées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15349">et</DiscourseConnective> publiques <Alignment alignment="13804" annotation_id="15362">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15362" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je serai disposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15382">à</DiscourseConnective> les accepter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13841" docOffset="78">
      <en>Yours was an unfortunate and unacceptable intervention with which to end the debate tonight, Mr Kohlíček.</en>
      <fr>Votre intervention était regrettable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15435">et</DiscourseConnective> inacceptable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15451">pour conclure</DiscourseConnective> le débat ce soir, Monsieur Kohlícek.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13947" docOffset="79">
      <en>(Applause from the right and from the centre)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements de la droite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15533">et</DiscourseConnective> du centre)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13993" id="375" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13993" docOffset="80">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14015" docOffset="81">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
