<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>9.</en>
    <fr>9.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>European Road Safety Action Programme - Mid-Term Review (vote)</en>
    <fr>Programme d'action européen pour la sécurité routière - Bilan à mi-parcours (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="66" docOffset="2">
    <en>- following the vote</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="88">Après</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="87" id="078" name="Hannes Swoboda">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="87" docOffset="3">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, it may be that we did not inform you in good time, <Alignment alignment="236003" annotation_id="157">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="157" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this report is the latest from Mrs Hedkvist Petersen, and its subject matter, road safety, something in which she has always taken a great interest.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, il se peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="141">que</DiscourseConnective> nous ayons omis de vous informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="178">en</DiscourseConnective> temps utile, <Alignment alignment="157" annotation_id="194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="194" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="202">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit ici du dernier rapport de Mme Hedkvist Petersen, traitant d'un sujet qui lui tient particulièrement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="309">à</DiscourseConnective> cœur depuis toujours, la sécurité routière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="310" docOffset="4">
      <en>We would like to take this opportunity to thank Mrs Hedkvist Petersen for the work she has done in this House over recent years.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons profiter de cette occasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="398">pour</DiscourseConnective> remercier le rapporteur du travail qu'elle a accompli au sein de cette Assemblée durant ces dernières années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="439" docOffset="5">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="450" id="164" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="450" docOffset="6">
      <en>Mrs Hedkvist Petersen, such lively applause entitles the President to thank you, with quite especial warmth, for the work you have done and to wish you all the best in every way.</en>
      <fr>Madame Hedkvist Petersen, pareils applaudissements autorisent le Président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="607">à</DiscourseConnective> vous remercier, avec un plaisir tout particulier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="659">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail que vous avez accompli, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="699">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="702">à</DiscourseConnective> vous souhaiter bonne chance dans tout ce que vous entreprendrez par la suite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="629" docOffset="7">
      <en>I extend to you the warmest congratulations on this splendid report and wish you, personally, all the best.</en>
      <fr>Toutes mes félicitations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="807">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport exceptionnel. À titre personnel, je vous souhaite bonne chance pour la suite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
