<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>European order for payment procedure (debate)</en>
    <fr>Procédure européenne d'injonction de payer (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="46" id="193" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="46" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the recommendation for second reading, on behalf of the Committee on Legal Affairs, on the Council common position (07535/3/2006 C6-0227/2006 for adopting a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council creating a European order for payment procedure (Rapporteur: Arlene McCarthy).</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle la recommandation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="93">pour</DiscourseConnective> la deuxième lecture, au nom de la commission des affaires juridiques, concernant la position commune arrêtée par le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="222">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> l'adoption du règlement du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="278">et</DiscourseConnective> du Conseil instituant une procédure européenne d'injonction de payer (07535/3/2006 - C6-0227/2006 - (Rapporteur: Arlene McCarthy).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="356" id="194" name="Arlene McCarthy ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="356" docOffset="2">
      <en>rapporteur. - Mr President, Commissioner, almost 12 months ago we first gave our approval to the European payment order, a new law to assist in simplified debt recovery for businesses and citizens owed money in another EU Member State.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, il y a environ 12 mois, nous avons, pour la première fois, donné notre accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="557">à</DiscourseConnective> l'injonction de payer européenne, une nouvelle loi visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="617">à</DiscourseConnective> instaurer un système simplifié de recouvrement des créances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="679">pour</DiscourseConnective> les entreprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="700">et</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens à qui l'on doit de l'argent dans un autre État membre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="592" docOffset="3">
      <en>Today, a year later, the committee's view has not changed.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, c'est-à-dire un an <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="803">plus tard</DiscourseConnective>, la position de la commission n'a pas changé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="651" docOffset="4">
      <en>We believe that we need this pragmatic and practical EU law, in particular to ensure that businesses and citizens have an affordable system to recover those debts owed to them.</en>
      <fr>Nous pensons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="872">que</DiscourseConnective> cette disposition législative européenne pragmatique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="929">et</DiscourseConnective> concrète nous est nécessaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="962">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> si l'on veut garantir aux entreprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1015">et</DiscourseConnective> aux citoyens un système de recouvrement des créances abordable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="828" docOffset="5">
      <en>Why?</en>
      <fr>Pourquoi?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="833" docOffset="6">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="833" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Because</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="1098" annotation_id="841">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="841" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">until</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this law comes into force, recovery of debts from another EU State is a costly legal process.</en>
      <fr>Parce <Alignment alignment="841" annotation_id="1098">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1098" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">tant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette disposition ne sera pas entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1144">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur, le recouvrement de créances dans un autre État membre restera une procédure judiciaire onéreuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="941" docOffset="7">
      <en>In some cases, money spent on lawyers <Alignment alignment="1313" annotation_id="979">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="979" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> administrative costs exceeds the amount owed to the individual.</en>
      <fr>Dans certains cas, l'argent dépensé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1289">en</DiscourseConnective> honoraires d'avocats <Alignment alignment="979" annotation_id="1313">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1313" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> frais administratifs dépasse le montant de la créance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1047" docOffset="8">
      <en>More significantly, studies and experience show that companies which do not get their debts paid are at risk of collapsing, with knock-on effects not just in terms of job losses, but also for other SMEs in the supply chain.</en>
      <fr>Plus significatif encore, des études <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1408">et</DiscourseConnective> des expériences démontrent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1438">que</DiscourseConnective> les sociétés qui ne parviennent pas à se faire rembourser leurs créances risquent de s'effondrer, entraînant ainsi des répercussions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1575">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de pertes d'emplois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1606">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1616">pour</DiscourseConnective> d'autres PME dans la chaîne de distribution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1271" docOffset="9">
      <en>Out of between 30 and 40 billion invoices in Europe each year, as many as 1 billion default and turn into debt cases.</en>
      <fr>Sur un <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1673">total</DiscourseConnective> de 30 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1685">à</DiscourseConnective> 40 milliards de factures émises chaque année <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1732">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe, un milliard d'entre elles ne sont pas réglées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1789">et</DiscourseConnective> deviennent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1803">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> des créances.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1389" docOffset="10">
      <en>Interim Justicia carried out a survey on payment practices in 16 European countries some 10 years ago.</en>
      <fr>Interim Justicia a réalisé une enquête quant aux pratiques de paiement dans 16 pays européens il y a environ 10 ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1492" docOffset="11">
      <en>The average delay <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1510" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> was just 14 days.</en>
      <fr>Le délai moyen de paiement était à l'époque de 14 jours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1533" docOffset="12">
      <en>By the end of 2003, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1553" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>, this had not declined, but risen to 16 days.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1997">À</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'année 2003, ce délai n'avait pas diminué, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2053">mais</DiscourseConnective> plutôt augmenté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2074">pour</DiscourseConnective> atteindre 16 jours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1607" docOffset="13">
      <en>According to a World Bank study, 'Doing Business in 2004: Understanding Regulation', the Nordic countries have the most efficient and effective legal systems of the countries surveyed.</en>
      <fr>Selon une étude réalisée par la Banque mondiale, "Faire des affaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2168">en</DiscourseConnective> 2004: comprendre la réglementation", de tous les pays sondés, les pays nordiques disposent des systèmes juridiques les plus efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1792" docOffset="14">
      <en>They take the least time to reach a solution <Alignment alignment="2408" annotation_id="1837">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1837" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> keeping costs low.</en>
      <fr>En effet, ce sont les systèmes de ces pays qui mettent le moins de temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2379">pour</DiscourseConnective> parvenir à une solution <Alignment alignment="1837" annotation_id="2408">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2408" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> entraînant des frais peu élevés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1862" docOffset="15">
      <en>Italy is one of the countries with the longest delays worldwide.</en>
      <fr>Au contraire, l'Italie est le pays qui présente les délais les plus longs au monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1927" docOffset="16">
      <en>The explanation it is said lies in the lax appeal process, which allows proceedings to be disrupted at any point during a trial.</en>
      <fr>L'explication résiderait dans la procédure de recours laxiste, qui permet d'interrompre les procédures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2636">en</DiscourseConnective> cours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2645">à</DiscourseConnective> tout moment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2056" docOffset="17">
      <en>Spain, <Alignment alignment="2671" annotation_id="2063">
          <Alignment alignment="2671" annotation_id="2063">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2063" sense="Comparison.Contrast">by contrast</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, has one of the most complex legal systems, which generates higher costs and leads to longer court proceedings.</en>
      <fr>L'Espagne, <Alignment alignment="2063" annotation_id="2671">
          <Alignment alignment="2063" annotation_id="2671">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2671" sense="Comparison.Contrast">par contre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, possède l'un des systèmes juridiques les plus complexes, ce qui génère des frais plus élevés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2776">et</DiscourseConnective> entraîne des procédures plus longues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2187" docOffset="18">
      <en>My own Member State, the UK, has some three systems operating for payments, again creating confusion for businesses or the public.</en>
      <fr>Mon État membre, la Grande-Bretagne, possède trois systèmes de paiement, ce qui est encore une fois synonyme de confusion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2939">pour</DiscourseConnective> les entreprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2960">et</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2318" docOffset="19">
      <en>Extensive differences in legal regulation of overdue payment recovery <Alignment alignment="3093" annotation_id="2388">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2388" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> lead to uncertainties, especially in EU trade, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2445" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> the additional costs prevent the EU's aim of equal opportunities for market access for both local and EU operating companies.</en>
      <fr>Des différences importantes dans le domaine de la réglementation juridique des recouvrements de créances entraînent <Alignment alignment="2388" annotation_id="3093">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3093" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des incertitudes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3116">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> dans le commerce européen. De plus, les frais supplémentaires engendrés entravent la réalisation de l'objectif communautaire de l'égalité des chances dans l'accès au marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3304">pour</DiscourseConnective> les sociétés locales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3330">et</DiscourseConnective> les sociétés opérant à l'échelon de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2575" docOffset="20">
      <en>It is clear that a lack of enforcement systems for payments undermines the internal market and business confidence <Alignment alignment="3502" annotation_id="2690">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2690" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that, <Alignment alignment="3506" annotation_id="2700">
          <Alignment alignment="3506" annotation_id="2700">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2700" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">as a result</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, SMEs have continued to experience cash flow problems caused by late payments.</en>
      <fr>Il est clair <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3388">que</DiscourseConnective> l'absence de systèmes d'exécution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3426">pour</DiscourseConnective> les paiements sape le marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3470">et</DiscourseConnective> la confiance des entreprises <Alignment alignment="2690" annotation_id="3502">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3502" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="2700" annotation_id="3506">
          <Alignment alignment="2700" annotation_id="3506">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3506" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, que les PME restent confrontées à des difficultés de trésorerie du fait des paiements tardifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2791" docOffset="21">
      <en>The European payment order will <Alignment alignment="3663" annotation_id="2823">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2823" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> apply to individual citizens who work or live in another Member State <Alignment alignment="3736" annotation_id="2898">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2898" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> who can <Alignment alignment="3751" annotation_id="2910">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2910" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> take advantage of this new law.</en>
      <fr>L'injonction de payer européenne s'appliquera <Alignment alignment="2823" annotation_id="3663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3663" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aux citoyens travaillant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3698">ou</DiscourseConnective> résidant dans un autre État membre <Alignment alignment="2898" annotation_id="3736">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3736" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui peuvent <Alignment alignment="2910" annotation_id="3751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3751" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> se prévaloir de cette nouvelle réglementation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2947" docOffset="22">
      <en>Of course, the high and expanding volume of trade within the EU and the increased movement of people raise the likelihood that more and more businesses may become involved in cross-border litigation.</en>
      <fr>Bien entendu, le volume élevé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3838">et</DiscourseConnective> en pleine expansion des échanges commerciaux au sein de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3902">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les mouvements accrus des citoyens augmentent la probabilité de voir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3981">de plus</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3989">en plus d'</DiscourseConnective>entreprises impliquées dans des litiges transfrontaliers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3147" docOffset="23">
      <en>There is a risk that citizens may not be inclined to assert their rights because of the obstacles they face, particularly in dealing with the legal system in another Member State and with unfamiliar procedures and unknown costs.</en>
      <fr>Le risque existe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4074">que</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens ne soient pas enclins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4113">à</DiscourseConnective> faire valoir leurs droits à cause des obstacles auxquels ils doivent faire face, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4196">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> face au système juridique d'un autre État membre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4261">à</DiscourseConnective> des procédures étrangères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4289">et</DiscourseConnective> à des coûts inconnus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3376" docOffset="24">
      <en>It is essential, <Alignment alignment="4314" annotation_id="3393">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3393" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, that the EU provide for a judicial area where private individuals and businesses can have access to justice and redress in the case of an uncontested claim.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3393" annotation_id="4314">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4314" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'UE crée un espace judiciaire dans lequel les entreprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4388">et</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens bénéficient d'un accès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4427">à</DiscourseConnective> la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4440">et</DiscourseConnective> à un système de réparation dans le cas d'une créance incontestée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3561" docOffset="25">
      <en>This procedural law will help facilitate that access.</en>
      <fr>Cette loi procédurale contribuera à faciliter cet accès.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3615" docOffset="26">
      <en>The payment order introduces a practical EU-level instrument for obtaining an enforceable decision <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3714" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I believe in this way we can demonstrate to citizens that the EU is delivering a practical tool to assist them with redress and remedies.</en>
      <fr>L'injonction de payer introduit un instrument concret au niveau européen permettant d'obtenir une décision applicable. Je pense que, grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4705">à</DiscourseConnective> cela, nous pouvons démontrer aux citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4749">que</DiscourseConnective> l'UE est en train de produire un instrument concret <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4805">pour</DiscourseConnective> les aider dans le domaine des réparations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4852">et</DiscourseConnective> des recours qui s'offrent à eux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3856" docOffset="27">
      <en>I want to put on record my thanks to members of the committee, in particular the shadows, Mr Wieland, who is here this evening, and Mrs Wallis, who cannot be here.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais remercier les membres de la commission et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4942">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> rapporteurs fictifs, M. Wieland, qui est parmi nous ce soir, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5018">et</DiscourseConnective> Mme Wallis, qui n'a pu se joindre à nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4020" docOffset="28">
      <en>They have not only supported my approach but have made useful and constructive proposals for amendments at every stage of the procedure.</en>
      <fr>Ils ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5071">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> soutenu mon approche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5107">mais</DiscourseConnective> m'ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5118">également</DiscourseConnective> proposé des amendements utiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5159">et</DiscourseConnective> constructifs tout au long des différentes étapes de la procédure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4157" docOffset="29">
      <en>The committee consulted with key protagonists <Alignment alignment="5293" annotation_id="4203">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4203" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we believe we focused on the core issues.</en>
      <fr>La commission a consulté les protagonistes majeurs de ce dossier <Alignment alignment="4203" annotation_id="5293">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5293" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous pensons que nous sommes restés concentrés sur les questions clés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4249" docOffset="30">
      <en>Both my shadows were concerned to ensure that the forms and the annex, the bones of the proposal, were simple enough for businesses to be able to fill them out with minimum bureaucracy.</en>
      <fr>Mes deux rapporteurs fictifs ont travaillé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5410">dans le but de</DiscourseConnective> veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5438">que</DiscourseConnective> les formulaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5458">et</DiscourseConnective> les annexes, l'ossature même de la proposition, soient suffisamment simples <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5537">pour</DiscourseConnective> permettre aux entreprises de les remplir avec un minimum de contraintes administratives.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4435" docOffset="31">
      <en>Only time and experience will tell <Alignment alignment="5674" annotation_id="4470">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4470" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this has been achieved.</en>
      <fr>Seuls le temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5646">et</DiscourseConnective> l'expérience nous diront <Alignment alignment="4470" annotation_id="5674">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5674" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous y sommes parvenus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4497" docOffset="32">
      <en>That is why, under the new comitology procedures, Parliament needs to be consulted and informed of any changes the Commission would like to make to the system.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5701">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>, conformément aux nouvelles procédures de comitologie, le Parlement doit être consulté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5803">et</DiscourseConnective> informé de tout changement que la Commission voudrait apporter au système.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4657" docOffset="33">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="5893" annotation_id="4665">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4665" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to thank the British Presidency, in particular the Minister Baroness Ashton, who was instrumental in helping us to make progress on the clear drafting of this law.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="4665" annotation_id="5893">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5893" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remercier la présidence britannique, et tout spécialement le ministre, Mme la baronne Ashton, qui a apporté une contribution déterminante à la rédaction claire de cette loi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4839" docOffset="34">
      <en>So now, Commissioner, at second reading we are down to the last few details.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6077">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>, Monsieur le Commissaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6118">en</DiscourseConnective> deuxième lecture, nous en sommes aux quelques derniers détails.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4916" docOffset="35">
      <en>Mrs Wallis is concerned that the Commission should seriously address the potential discrimination affecting citizens and businesses where EEA members can participate in the single market, but cannot be a party to the EPO.</en>
      <fr>Selon Mme Wallis, la Commission doit sérieusement aborder le problème des discriminations potentielles que peuvent subir les citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6319">et</DiscourseConnective> les entreprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6338">lorsque</DiscourseConnective> les membres de l'EEE ont la possibilité de participer au marché unique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6418">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6427">à</DiscourseConnective> l'OEB.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5138" docOffset="36">
      <en>I hope the Commission will address this issue.</en>
      <fr>J'espère que la Commission s'occupera de ce problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5185" docOffset="37">
      <en>The forms should be user-friendly and simple <Alignment alignment="6527" annotation_id="5230">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5230" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we would <Alignment alignment="6553" annotation_id="5243">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5243" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like the Commission to take on board our amendment in this area.</en>
      <fr>Les formulaires doivent être simples <Alignment alignment="5230" annotation_id="6527">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6527" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> faciles d'utilisation. <Alignment alignment="5243" annotation_id="6553">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6553" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voudrions que la Commission prenne bonne note de notre amendement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6639">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5318" docOffset="38">
      <en>Finally, <Alignment alignment="6659" annotation_id="5327">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5327" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we started this process a year ago and since the Commission's original proposal, we now have a new institutional agreement, with effect from July 2006.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6652">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="5327" annotation_id="6659">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6659" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">depuis</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le commencement de cette procédure il y a un an <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6714">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6717">depuis</DiscourseConnective> la proposition initiale de la Commission, nous disposons à présent d'un nouvel accord institutionnel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6825">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6836">depuis</DiscourseConnective> juin 2006.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5485" docOffset="39">
      <en>The committee and Parliament insist that the new regulatory scrutiny procedure and rule should be respected in this legislation and on the payment order.</en>
      <fr>La commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6868">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement insistent sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6906">que</DiscourseConnective> la nouvelle procédure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6932">et</DiscourseConnective> règle d'examen réglementaire doit être respectée dans cette législation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7007">et</DiscourseConnective> concernant l'injonction de payer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5639" docOffset="40">
      <en>Commissioner, let me say how much we have appreciated the cooperation of your departments in this area.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, permettez-moi de vous dire combien nous avons apprécié la coopération de vos services dans ce dossier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5743" docOffset="41">
      <en>I hope that, together with the Finnish Presidency, we can sign off the European payment order and begin the process of putting it into law across all the Member States of the EU, <Alignment alignment="7397" annotation_id="5922">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5922" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> businesses and citizens can be confident of operating in the internal market in the knowledge that the failure to pay a debt does not end up in endless court proceedings with no outcome.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7181">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pourrons, en collaboration avec la présidence finlandaise, mettre la dernière main à l'injonction de payer européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7308">et</DiscourseConnective> commencer à l'inscrire dans le droit de tous les États membres de l'UE de telle sorte <Alignment alignment="5922" annotation_id="7397">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7397" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les entreprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7417">et</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens puissent évoluer en toute confiance au sein du marché intérieur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7498">tout en</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7506">sachant que</DiscourseConnective> le non-paiement d'une créance n'entraînera pas des démarches juridiques interminables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7604">et</DiscourseConnective> infructueuses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6117" docOffset="42">
      <en>Thanks to the European Union, there is now a simple and user-friendly system for speedy payment of debts which, I believe, will drive forward the internal market for SMEs and boost the EU economy.</en>
      <fr>Grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7628">à</DiscourseConnective> l'UE, il existe à présent un système facile d'utilisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7688">pour</DiscourseConnective> le paiement accéléré des créances qui, je pense, stimulera le marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7772">pour</DiscourseConnective> les PME <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7785">et</DiscourseConnective> dynamisera l'économie de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6314" id="195" name="Franco Frattini">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6314" docOffset="43">
      <en>Mr President, first of all, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Mrs McCarthy, warmly for her work and her efforts to bring this project, which is very important for our citizens, to a satisfactory conclusion.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7894">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> remercier chaleureusement le rapporteur, Mme McCarthy, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7962">pour</DiscourseConnective> son travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7979">et</DiscourseConnective> ses efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7994">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> mener à bien ce projet, qui est de la plus haute importance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8064">pour</DiscourseConnective> nos concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6525" docOffset="44">
      <en>Like the rapporteur, I would <Alignment alignment="8124" annotation_id="6554">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6554" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to thank the former United Kingdom Presidency, particularly Baroness Ashton, for the work done in moving ahead with this important project.</en>
      <fr>À l'instar du rapporteur, je voudrais <Alignment alignment="6554" annotation_id="8124">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8124" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remercier l'ancienne présidence britannique et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8181">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> la baronne Ashton, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8215">pour</DiscourseConnective> les progrès réalisés dans ce projet important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6704" docOffset="45">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8267" annotation_id="6704">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6704" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you know, this regulation on the European order for payment procedure aims at facilitating the mass recovery of uncontested claims in Europe.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6704" annotation_id="8267">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8267" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez tous, ce règlement sur la procédure européenne d'injonction de payer vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8361">à</DiscourseConnective> faciliter en masse le recouvrement de créances incontestées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8423">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6849" docOffset="46">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="8451" annotation_id="6855">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6855" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> very important, <Alignment alignment="8481" annotation_id="6876">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6876" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it will allow all creditors in Europe to recover their claims in a uniform way and more rapidly and cheaply than in ordinary court proceedings.</en>
      <fr>Ce règlement est <Alignment alignment="6855" annotation_id="8451">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8451" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vraiment très important, <Alignment alignment="6876" annotation_id="8481">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8481" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il permet à tous les créanciers d'Europe de récupérer leurs créances de manière uniforme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8574">et</DiscourseConnective> ce, plus rapidement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8597">et</DiscourseConnective> à moindres frais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8617">que</DiscourseConnective> dans le cas des procédures judiciaires ordinaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7023" docOffset="47">
      <en>It will <Alignment alignment="8695" annotation_id="7031">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7031" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> alleviate the burden on the courts by removing from ordinary proceedings those claims where the debtor does not contest the debt.</en>
      <fr>Ce règlement permettra <Alignment alignment="7031" annotation_id="8695">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8695" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'alléger la charge des tribunaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8739">en</DiscourseConnective> ôtant des procédures ordinaires les cas de créances incontestées par le débiteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7166" docOffset="48">
      <en>The proposal potentially concerns all citizens and economic operators in Europe.</en>
      <fr>La proposition concerne potentiellement tous les citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8882">et</DiscourseConnective> tous les acteurs de la vie économique européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7247" docOffset="49">
      <en>A European order for payment can circulate freely in Europe and will be enforced automatically.</en>
      <fr>Une injonction de payer européenne peut circuler librement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8994">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9004">et</DiscourseConnective> sera exécutée automatiquement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7343" docOffset="50">
      <en>There will be <Alignment alignment="9049" annotation_id="7357">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7357" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> no need to request a declaration of enforcement - the 'exequatur' - in the Member State of enforcement.</en>
      <fr>Il ne sera <Alignment alignment="7357" annotation_id="9049">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9049" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> plus nécessaire de demander une déclaration constatant la force exécutoire - "exequatur" - dans l'État membre d'exécution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7471" docOffset="51">
      <en>Concerning the amendments, I can accept the third amendment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7531" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> proposed.</en>
      <fr>En ce qui concerne les amendements, j'accepte le troisième amendement dans sa forme actuelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7544" docOffset="52">
      <en>On the second amendment, I can accept the compromise amendment on the comitology procedure, which is in line with the Council decision taken in July 2006.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9271">Pour</DiscourseConnective> ce qui est du deuxième amendement, j'accepte l'amendement de compromis sur la procédure de comitologie, qui est conforme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9397">à</DiscourseConnective> la décision du Conseil prise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9428">en</DiscourseConnective> juillet 2006.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7699" docOffset="53">
      <en>On the first amendment, <Alignment alignment="9473" annotation_id="7723">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7723" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I understand the reason and the concern expressed by the committee, I think that we should not at this stage reopen the question of the definition of a cross-border case, adopted at first reading by the Council and the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9445">Pour</DiscourseConnective> le premier amendement, <Alignment alignment="7723" annotation_id="9473">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9473" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je comprenne le motif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9504">et</DiscourseConnective> l'inquiétude exprimés par la commission, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9557">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne faut pas, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9576">à</DiscourseConnective> ce stade de la procédure, rouvrir la question de la définition d'un cas transfrontalier, adopté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9674">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture par le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9709">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7969" docOffset="54">
      <en>At the same time, I can confirm that the Commission is available and willing to look more closely into the effects of the regulation for parties domiciled in third countries and, in particular, states of the European Economic Area.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9735">En même temps</DiscourseConnective>, je <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9753">puis</DiscourseConnective> confirmer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9768">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission est prête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9796">et</DiscourseConnective> disposée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9808">à</DiscourseConnective> examiner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9819">de plus</DiscourseConnective> près les effets du règlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9856">pour</DiscourseConnective> les parties domiciliées dans des pays tiers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9905">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9908">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> dans les États de l'espace économique européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8201" docOffset="55">
      <en>I am ready to give very careful consideration to any proposals.</en>
      <fr>Je suis prêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9984">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre sérieusement en considération toute proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8265" id="196" name="Rainer Wieland">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8265" docOffset="56">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (DE) Mr President, the rapporteur, Mrs McCarthy, has set out the essentials of why this matters in economic terms.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, le rapporteur, Mme McCarthy, a exposé l'essentiel des raisons de l'importance de cette procédure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10195">en</DiscourseConnective> termes économiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8413" docOffset="57">
      <en>This European order for payment procedure represents a major step forward in the application of laws across borders, and, in particular, a step forward for business, which has a particular interest in the legal soundness of claims being established without delay, in the prompt assignment of title, and in this claim being capable of being enforced, without further cost-intensive procedures, in the country of the debtor.</en>
      <fr>Cette procédure européenne d'injonction de payer fait considérablement progresser l'application transfrontalière des lois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10340">et</DiscourseConnective> est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10347">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> une avancée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10374">pour</DiscourseConnective> les entreprises, qui vouent un intérêt particulier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10430">pour</DiscourseConnective> le bon sens juridique qui permet de régler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10478">sans</DiscourseConnective> délai les créances, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10503">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'attribution rapide de titre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10539">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10542">pour</DiscourseConnective> la possibilité d'honorer cette créance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10586">sans</DiscourseConnective> procédures coûteuses supplémentaires dans le pays du débiteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8836" docOffset="58">
      <en>It has to be said, <Alignment alignment="10667" annotation_id="8855">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8855" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - <Alignment alignment="10679" annotation_id="8864">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8864" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is to this that I want to give particular attention - that legal relationships across borders will become increasingly important to private citizens, who find it particularly difficult to enforce claims across borders, whether such claims are contentious <Alignment alignment="10963" annotation_id="9126">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9126" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not.</en>
      <fr>Il faut dire <Alignment alignment="8855" annotation_id="10667">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10667" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - <Alignment alignment="8864" annotation_id="10679">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10679" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10688">à</DiscourseConnective> cela <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10695">que</DiscourseConnective> je veux porter une attention particulière - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10743">que</DiscourseConnective> les relations juridiques transfrontalières vont devenir de plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10811">en plus</DiscourseConnective> importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10831">pour</DiscourseConnective> les particuliers, qui ont beaucoup de mal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10878">à</DiscourseConnective> faire respecter des créances transfrontalières, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10928">que</DiscourseConnective> ces créances soient contestées <Alignment alignment="9126" annotation_id="10963">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10963" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9134" docOffset="59">
      <en>Today, it is undisputed claims that we are discussing, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9189" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that is why this first step is so important.</en>
      <fr>Nous parlons aujourd'hui des créances incontestées, c'est la raison pour laquelle cette <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11059">première étape</DiscourseConnective> est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11078">si</DiscourseConnective> importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9238" docOffset="60">
      <en>Private individuals find the business of getting what they are entitled to complicated enough <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9332" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> it is, <Alignment alignment="11170" annotation_id="9342">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9342" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they have serious problems with getting claims enforced in a country other than their own; this instrument will make things easier for them.</en>
      <fr>Les particuliers trouvent qu'il est suffisamment compliqué d'obtenir leur dû <Alignment alignment="9342" annotation_id="11170">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11170" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils ont de sérieuses difficultés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11206">à</DiscourseConnective> faire honorer leurs créances dans un autre pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11256">que</DiscourseConnective> le leur; cet instrument leur facilitera la vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9487" docOffset="61">
      <en>A form that even an ordinary member of the public can complete will make it possible for claims to be enforced relatively simply and without great expense.</en>
      <fr>Un formulaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11322">que</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11326">même</DiscourseConnective> une personne ordinaire peut remplir permettra la récupération des créances relativement facilement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11430">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11433">sans</DiscourseConnective> grandes dépenses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9643" docOffset="62">
      <en>Another consideration is that constant reference has been made to businesses and to creditors, but not enough has been said about the debtors.</en>
      <fr>Autre remarque: on parle toujours des entreprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11506">et</DiscourseConnective> des créditeurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11525">mais</DiscourseConnective> on ne parle pas suffisamment des débiteurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9786" docOffset="63">
      <en>Systems have been introduced in the Member States of the European Union - not least in the one from which I come - to make the establishment of such claims a positively economical business, not least for those who owe the money.</en>
      <fr>Des systèmes ont été mis en place dans les États membres de l'Union européenne - entre autres dans mon pays d'origine - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11694">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire du remboursement de ces créances une entreprise économiquement positive, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11778">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11793">pour</DiscourseConnective> ceux qui doivent de l'argent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10015" docOffset="64">
      <en>The debtor who is willing - but perhaps not able - to pay up, can agree reasonable repayments with the creditor, who has an interest in establishing title and <Alignment alignment="12008" annotation_id="10174">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10174" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> preventing the debt from lapsing, <Alignment alignment="12048" annotation_id="10216">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10216" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in the absence of a contested case, fewer costs are incurred.</en>
      <fr>Le débiteur qui souhaite -, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11856">mais</DiscourseConnective> qui ne peut peut-être pas - rembourser, peut négocier des remboursements raisonnables avec le créditeur, qui trouve un intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11988">à</DiscourseConnective> établir un titre, <Alignment alignment="10174" annotation_id="12008">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12008" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> éviter la disparition de la dette, <Alignment alignment="10216" annotation_id="12048">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12048" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12052">en</DiscourseConnective> l'absence de litige, les coûts engendrés sont plus faibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10283" docOffset="65">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="12121" annotation_id="10289">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10289" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in the interests of all parties that we should make cross-border legal proceedings speedy, efficient and affordable.</en>
      <fr>C'est <Alignment alignment="10289" annotation_id="12121">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12121" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans l'intérêt de toutes les parties <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12163">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons rendre les procédures juridiques transfrontalières rapides, efficaces <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12249">et</DiscourseConnective> abordables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10416" id="197" name="Andrzej Jan Szejna">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10416" docOffset="66">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (PL) Mr President, late payments are the main cause of insolvency, which threatens the survival of businesses, especially small and medium-sized ones.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, les retards de paiements sont la principale cause d'insolvabilité, qui menace la survie des entreprises, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12421">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> les petites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12448">et</DiscourseConnective> moyennes entreprises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10597" docOffset="67">
      <en>They jeopardise the operations and solvency of these businesses, often resulting in the loss of many jobs.</en>
      <fr>Ils mettent en péril les acticités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12508">et</DiscourseConnective> la solvabilité de ces entreprises, entraînant souvent la perte de nombreux emplois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10704" docOffset="68">
      <en>Swift and efficient debt recovery <Alignment alignment="12641" annotation_id="10738">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10738" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> no legal dispute is involved is <Alignment alignment="12692" annotation_id="10775">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10775" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vitally important for business entities in the European Union. It helps to preserve jobs.</en>
      <fr>Le recouvrement rapide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12618">et</DiscourseConnective> efficace des dettes <Alignment alignment="10738" annotation_id="12641">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12641" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aucune action juridique n'est en cours est <Alignment alignment="10775" annotation_id="12692">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12692" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'une importance vitale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12721">pour</DiscourseConnective> les entreprises de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10875" docOffset="69">
      <en>The Member States have attempted to solve the problem of large-scale debt recovery in the case of undisputed claims, generally by simplifying proceedings regarding payment orders.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres ont tenté de régler le problème du recouvrement de dettes à grande échelle dans le cas de créances incontestées, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12896">en</DiscourseConnective> simplifiant les procédures d'injonction de payer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11055" docOffset="70">
      <en>There are, <Alignment alignment="12959" annotation_id="11066">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11066" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, significant differences between national provisions and the way individual procedures operate.</en>
      <fr>Il existe <Alignment alignment="11066" annotation_id="12959">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12959" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des différences considérables entre les dispositions nationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13033">et</DiscourseConnective> la façon dont les diverses procédures fonctionnent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11170" docOffset="71">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13088" annotation_id="11170">
          <Alignment alignment="13088" annotation_id="11170">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11170" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">As a result</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the latter may be inadmissible or impossible to apply in cross-border situations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11170" annotation_id="13088">
          <Alignment alignment="11170" annotation_id="13088">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13088" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">En conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> de quoi, ces dernières peuvent s'avérer inadmissibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13157">ou</DiscourseConnective> impossibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13172">à</DiscourseConnective> appliquer dans des situations transfrontalières.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11265" docOffset="72">
      <en>It is therefore appropriate to respond positively to the proposed regulation setting up a European procedure for payment orders.</en>
      <fr>Il faut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13231">donc</DiscourseConnective> répondre positivement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13258">à</DiscourseConnective> la proposition de règlement instituant une procédure européenne d'injonction de payer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11394" id="198" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11394" docOffset="73">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11416" docOffset="74">
      <en>The vote will take place on Wednesday at 12.30 p.m.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu mercredi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13393">à</DiscourseConnective> 12h30.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
