<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>34.</en>
    <fr>34.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Reporting and documentation requirements in the case of merger and divisions (</en>
    <fr>Obligations en matière de rapports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39">et</DiscourseConnective> de documentation en cas de fusions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="77">ou</DiscourseConnective> de scissions (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="83" docOffset="2">
    <en>Before the vote on the amended resolution:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="97">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote sur la résolution modifiée:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="126" id="134" name="Charlie McCreevy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="126" docOffset="3">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the Commission welcomes the adoption of the Weber report endorsed in the compromise text on simplified reporting and documentation requirements in the case of mergers and divisions of public limited liability companies.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la Commission salue l'adoption du rapport Weber entérinée dans le texte de compromis sur la simplification des obligations en matière de rapports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="340">et</DiscourseConnective> de documentation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="360">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de fusions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="378">ou</DiscourseConnective> de scissions de sociétés anonymes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="388" docOffset="4">
      <en>Even <Alignment alignment="622" annotation_id="393">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="393" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commission had gone even further in its original proposal, this will maintain a very significant part of the savings potential of the original Commission proposal, which amounts to EUR 172 million per year.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="413" annotation_id="416">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="416" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission avait été plus loin dans sa proposition originale, ce texte préservera une part tout à fait significative du potentiel d'économies de ladite proposition, à hauteur de 172 millions d'euros par an.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="611" docOffset="5">
      <en>The agenda on administrative burden reduction is advancing, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="671" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this will contribute to the potential for growth and help Europe on the way to recovery.</en>
      <fr>Le traitement de la réduction des charges administratives progresse, ce qui alimentera le potentiel de croissance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="748">et</DiscourseConnective> aidera l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="767">à</DiscourseConnective> retrouver le chemin de la croissance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
