<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Loss at sea of migrants' boats off the Libyan coast (debate)</en>
    <fr>Naufrages de migrants près des côtes libyennes (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="61" id="216" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="61" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the Commission statement on the loss at sea of migrants' boats off the Libyan coast.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle la déclaration de la Commission sur les naufrages de migrants près des côtes libyennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="163" id="217" language="FR" name="Jacques Barrot">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="163" docOffset="2">
      <en>Madam President, the European Commission was dismayed to learn of the loss, on Sunday evening in the Mediterranean, off the coast of Libya, of a ship carrying migrants bound for Europe.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - Madame la Présidente, la Commission européenne a pris connaissance avec consternation du naufrage, dimanche soir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="315">en</DiscourseConnective> Méditerranée, au large de la Libye, d'une embarcation de migrants en route <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="393">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="349" docOffset="3">
      <en>According to some sources, this ship had 257 people on board, the vast majority of whom are missing.</en>
      <fr>Selon certaines sources, cette embarcation comptait 257 personnes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="474">à</DiscourseConnective> bord, dont la plus grande partie est portée disparue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="450" docOffset="4">
      <en>The Commission wishes to express its compassion for the victims of this human disaster and its anger in the face of this tragedy. It was doubtless caused by many factors, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="621" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> the primary responsibility must lie with those criminal organisations that are directing this deadly illegal traffic from the coasts of Libya <Alignment alignment="834" annotation_id="767">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="767" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> who are growing rich at the cost of human misery.</en>
      <fr>La Commission tient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="550">à</DiscourseConnective> exprimer sa compassion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="575">pour</DiscourseConnective> les victimes de ce désastre humain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="615">et</DiscourseConnective> sa colère face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="633">à</DiscourseConnective> ce drame dont les causes sont sans doute multiples et dont la responsabilité première incombe aux organisations criminelles qui dirigent, à partir des côtes libyennes, ce trafic clandestin meurtrier <Alignment alignment="767" annotation_id="834">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="834" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="841">s'</DiscourseConnective>enrichissent ainsi aux dépens de la misère humaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="821" docOffset="5">
      <en>The Commission finds it intolerable that this phenomenon, which seems to be intensifying over the course of the years, continues to grow.</en>
      <fr>La Commission estime intolérable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="928">que</DiscourseConnective> ce phénomène, qui tend <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="955">à</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="957">s'</DiscourseConnective>intensifier au fil des années, continue de se développer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="959" docOffset="6">
      <en>It invites all the parties concerned to mobilise their efforts to bring it to an end.</en>
      <fr>Elle invite toutes les parties concernées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1059">à</DiscourseConnective> mobiliser leurs efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1085">afin de</DiscourseConnective> le faire cesser.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1045" docOffset="7">
      <en>Libya has an essential role to play here.</en>
      <fr>La Libye a ici un rôle essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1143">à</DiscourseConnective> jouer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1087" docOffset="8">
      <en>It must make a more determined and effective commitment to the fight against the traffickers operating on its territory, to the prevention of illegal departures from its coasts, to the search and rescue of ships in distress in the waters under its control, and to the offer of international protection to those migrants who require it, in accordance with its obligations under the 1969 OAU convention on the protection of refugees, to which it is a signatory.</en>
      <fr>Elle doit s'engager de façon plus déterminée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1197">et</DiscourseConnective> efficace dans la lutte contre les trafiquants actifs sur son territoire, dans la prévention des départs clandestins à partir de ses côtes, dans la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1357">et</DiscourseConnective> le sauvetage en mer des navires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1392">en</DiscourseConnective> détresse dans les eaux relevant de sa compétence, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1445">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que dans l'offre d'une protection internationale aux migrants qui en ont besoin, conformément à ses obligations en vertu de la Convention panafricaine de 1969 sur la protection des réfugiés, dont elle est signataire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1547" docOffset="9">
      <en>Over the last few years, the European Commission has asked the Libyan authorities several times to assume their responsibilities and to introduce effective measures, in cooperation with the European Union and its Member States.</en>
      <fr>Au cours des dernières années, la Commission européenne a demandé à maintes reprises aux autorités libyennes d'assumer leurs responsabilités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1809">et</DiscourseConnective> de mettre en place des mesures efficaces, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1854">en</DiscourseConnective> coopération avec l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1893">et</DiscourseConnective> ses États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1775" docOffset="10">
      <en>I have to say that we have offered increased financial assistance to Libya, <Alignment alignment="26376" annotation_id="1851">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1851" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is evident that the Libyan authorities need to use this assistance to improve the fight against the trafficking of migrants and others on their territory and to strengthen the controls at their southern border.</en>
      <fr>Je dois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1923">dire que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons proposé une assistance financière croissante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1988">à</DiscourseConnective> la Libye, <Alignment alignment="7977" annotation_id="2000">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2000" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est évident qu'il faut que les autorités libyennes utilisent cette assistance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2086">pour</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la lutte contre le trafic de migrants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2139">et</DiscourseConnective> d'êtres humains sur leur territoire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2178">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2181">pour</DiscourseConnective> renforcer les contrôles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2210">à</DiscourseConnective> leur frontière méridionale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2069" docOffset="11">
      <en>The Libyan authorities must <Alignment alignment="2272" annotation_id="2097">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2097" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> develop a system for receiving migrants that complies with international law.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités libyennes doivent <Alignment alignment="2097" annotation_id="2272">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2272" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> développer un système d'accueil des migrants dans le respect du droit international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2180" docOffset="12">
      <en>It is true that the European Union is ready to cooperate and to contribute to the interception and, <Alignment alignment="37367" annotation_id="2280">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2280" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> necessary, to the rescue of ships in the Mediterranean.</en>
      <fr>Il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2375">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne est prête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2408">à</DiscourseConnective> coopérer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2419">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2422">à</DiscourseConnective> contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2435">à</DiscourseConnective> l'interception <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2452">et</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="2280" annotation_id="2456">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2456" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nécessaire, au secours des navires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2494">en</DiscourseConnective> Méditerranée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2339" docOffset="13">
      <en>The launch, in the coming months, of Nautilus and Hermes, the two naval operations organised and financed by Frontex, the European external borders agency, will cost around EUR 24 million.</en>
      <fr>Le lancement, dans les prochains mois, des deux opérations navales Nautilus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2587">et</DiscourseConnective> Hermès, organisées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2609">et</DiscourseConnective> financées par Frontex, notre agence européenne des frontières extérieures, coûtera environ 24 millions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2528" docOffset="14">
      <en>The Commission invites all the Member States of the European Union to cooperate in the implementation of these two actions.</en>
      <fr>La Commission invite tous les États membres de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2782">à</DiscourseConnective> coopérer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2793">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en œuvre de ces deux actions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2652" docOffset="15">
      <en>The Member States must <Alignment alignment="27076" annotation_id="2675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2675" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> show solidarity in practice with Italy and Malta, which are very exposed to the flow of migrants from Libya.</en>
      <fr>Il faut <Alignment alignment="8179" annotation_id="2841">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2841" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que les États membres manifestent leur solidarité concrète envers l'Italie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2922">et</DiscourseConnective> Malte, qui sont très exposées aux flux migratoires en provenance de Libye.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2789" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12518" annotation_id="2789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2789" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Libya must assume its responsibilities as regards the readmission of illegal migrants who have crossed its territory.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2789" annotation_id="3000">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3000" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il faudra bien que la Libye assume ses responsabilités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3058">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de réadmission des migrants irréguliers ayant transité par son territoire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2920" docOffset="17">
      <en>We have noted that the Italian authorities believe it will be possible, from 15 May, to begin joint patrols with the Libyan navy in Libyan territorial waters with the aim of intercepting or assisting illegal vessels.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons pris acte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3165">du fait que</DiscourseConnective> les autorités italiennes estimaient possible de lancer, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3233">à</DiscourseConnective> partir du 15 mai prochain, des patrouilles conjointes avec la marine libyenne, dans les eaux territoriales de la Libye, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3355">en vue d'</DiscourseConnective>intercepter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3376">ou</DiscourseConnective> de secourir les embarcations clandestines.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3137" docOffset="18">
      <en>We welcome the support given by the Italian authorities to the development of Libyan naval capacities for this purpose.</en>
      <fr>Nous saluons le soutien apporté par les autorités italiennes au développement des capacités navales de la Libye <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3534">à</DiscourseConnective> cet effet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3257" docOffset="19">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18257" annotation_id="3257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3257" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in addition to these emergency measures, the Commission believes that a priority action must be applied to the whole human dimension of these problems.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3257" annotation_id="3547">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3547" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> au-delà de ces mesures d'urgence, la Commission estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3607">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une action prioritaire doit être donnée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3650">à</DiscourseConnective> toute la dimension humaine de ces problèmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3418" docOffset="20">
      <en>Migrants who entrust their lives to unscrupulous traffickers are, in the vast majority of cases, people fleeing war or persecution.</en>
      <fr>Les migrants qui confient leur vie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3732">à</DiscourseConnective> des trafiquants sans scrupules sont, dans leur vaste majorité, des personnes qui fuient la guerre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3832">ou</DiscourseConnective> la persécution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3550" docOffset="21">
      <en>We hope that the events of recent days will create an awareness, in all of our Member States, of how serious this problem is, <Alignment alignment="40740" annotation_id="3676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3676" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that, together with the Member States and with the support of the European Parliament, we can <Alignment alignment="11926" annotation_id="3774">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3774" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> prepare a Stockholm Programme that dedicates a large part of its priorities to this global approach to migration.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3867">que</DiscourseConnective> les événements de ces derniers jours suscitent, dans l'ensemble de nos États membres, une prise de conscience de la gravité du problème, <Alignment alignment="4736" annotation_id="4008">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4008" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4011">que</DiscourseConnective> nous puissions <Alignment alignment="1053" annotation_id="4030">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4030" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, avec les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4060">et</DiscourseConnective> avec l'appui du Parlement européen, préparer un programme de Stockholm qui devra consacrer une grande partie de ses priorités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4189">à</DiscourseConnective> cette approche globale en termes de migration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3893" docOffset="22">
      <en>The global approach is necessary for drawing up a long-term strategy for managing migratory flows that will take greater account of the circumstances and requirements of countries of origin.</en>
      <fr>L'approche globale est nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4272">pour</DiscourseConnective> élaborer une stratégie à long terme de gestion des flux migratoires qui prenne davantage en compte les situations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4391">et</DiscourseConnective> les besoins des pays d'origine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4084" docOffset="23">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="27359" annotation_id="4084">
          <Alignment alignment="22749" annotation_id="4084">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4084" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, this strategy must allow us to go further in the dialogue with the African partners, especially in the framework of the Rabat Process, in the framework of the relationship between the European Union and the African Union.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4084" annotation_id="4426">
          <Alignment alignment="4084" annotation_id="4426">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4426" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">D'autre part</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, cette stratégie doit permettre d'approfondir le dialogue avec les partenaires africains, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4529">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans le cadre du processus de Rabat, dans le cadre des relations entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4629">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Union africaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4319" docOffset="24">
      <en>Together we must identify joint responses to this challenge and <Alignment alignment="35213" annotation_id="4383">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4383" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> seize the opportunities offered by legal migration, which could, <Alignment alignment="1849" annotation_id="4453">
          <Alignment alignment="14653" annotation_id="4453">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4453" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, be an opportunity both for Europe and for countries of origin.</en>
      <fr>Il faut identifier ensemble des réponses communes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4701">à</DiscourseConnective> ce défi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4711">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="4383" annotation_id="4714">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4714" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> saisir les chances qu'offre une migration régulière qui peut, <Alignment alignment="4453" annotation_id="4782">
          <Alignment alignment="7598" annotation_id="4782">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4782" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en effet</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, être une opportunité à la fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4823">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4837">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4840">pour</DiscourseConnective> les pays d'origine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4525" docOffset="25">
      <en>This strategy must <Alignment alignment="9824" annotation_id="4544">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4544" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mobilise additional resources by increasing cooperation with countries of origin and of transit in order to strengthen their capacity for dismantling human trafficking organisations and for dealing with migrants in a dignified way in which their rights are respected.</en>
      <fr>Cette stratégie doit <Alignment alignment="4544" annotation_id="4886">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4886" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mobiliser des ressources additionnelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4932">en</DiscourseConnective> intensifiant la coopération avec les pays d'origine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4987">et</DiscourseConnective> de transit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5001">pour</DiscourseConnective> renforcer leur capacité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5030">à</DiscourseConnective> démanteler les organisations de trafiquants d'êtres humains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5092">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à traiter dignement les migrants dans le respect dans leurs droits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4817" docOffset="26">
      <en>Finally this strategy must allow us to manage and organise the arrival of legitimate asylum seekers on Member States' territory more effectively by further integrating the development of refugee protection capacities in our cooperation with third countries.</en>
      <fr>Cette stratégie doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5190">enfin</DiscourseConnective> permettre de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5209">mieux</DiscourseConnective> gérer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5221">et</DiscourseConnective> d'ordonner l'arrivée, sur le territoire des États membres, des personnes demandant légitimement l'asile, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5329">en</DiscourseConnective> intégrant davantage le développement des capacités en matière de protection des réfugiés dans la coopération avec les pays tiers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5075" docOffset="27">
      <en>Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, two weeks ago I went to Lampedusa and Malta.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5493">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs les Députés, je me suis rendu, il y a quinze jours, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5558">à</DiscourseConnective> Lampedusa <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5570">et</DiscourseConnective> à Malte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5159" docOffset="28">
      <en>I must say that I was able to see and hear for myself the tragedies of those people who are encouraged in this way by unscrupulous smugglers to risk their lives by crossing maritime areas.</en>
      <fr>Je dois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5590">dire que</DiscourseConnective> j'ai pu constater de mes yeux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5629">et</DiscourseConnective> de mes oreilles les drames de ces personnes qui sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5685">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> incitées par des passeurs sans scrupules à traverser, au risque de leur vie, les espaces maritimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5348" docOffset="29">
      <en>I think I can say that we must, in the light of this latest incident, take these problems very seriously and awaken an essential awareness in each of our Member States of the gravity, and growth too, of these phenomena, which are putting people's lives at risk in appalling conditions.</en>
      <fr>Je crois pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5808">dire que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons là, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5833">à</DiscourseConnective> la suite de ce dernier incident, prendre très au sérieux ces problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5906">et</DiscourseConnective> susciter, au sein de chacun de nos États membres, une prise de conscience indispensable de la gravité, de l'accélération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6030">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, de ces phénomènes, qui mettent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6068">en</DiscourseConnective> danger la vie de personnes humaines dans des conditions effroyables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5634" docOffset="30">
      <en>This is why I would like to thank the European Parliament for having requested this statement from the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Voilà pourquoi je remercie le Parlement européen d'avoir bien voulu solliciter de la Commission cette déclaration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5749" docOffset="31">
      <en>I have made it to the best of my knowledge and belief, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5804" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I repeat before Parliament my personal commitment in the coming months to avoiding a repeat of such tragedies.</en>
      <fr>Je la fais en mon âme et conscience en redisant au Parlement l'engagement personnel qui sera le mien dans les mois qui viennent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6383">pour</DiscourseConnective> éviter le retour de telles tragédies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5919" id="218" language="ES" name="Agustín Díaz de Mera García Consuegra">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5919" docOffset="32">
      <en>Madam President, today we feel collective grief and sorrow for the death of so many immigrants who were hopeful, desperate, and also perhaps deceived.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, nous éprouvons aujourd'hui une peine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6485">et</DiscourseConnective> une tristesse collective en raison de la mort de tant d'immigrants qui étaient pleins d'espoir, qui étaient désespérés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6608">et</DiscourseConnective> qui peut-être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6625">aussi</DiscourseConnective> ont été trompés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6070" docOffset="33">
      <en>They are innocent victims of a situation that they did not choose, of circumstances that were imposed upon them.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont les victimes innocentes d'une situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6696">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils n'avaient pas choisie, les victimes de circonstances qui leur ont été imposées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6183" docOffset="34">
      <en>I know the problem well.</en>
      <fr>Je connais bien le problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6208" docOffset="35">
      <en>The Mediterranean and the Atlantic Canary seaboard have become pathways towards a non-existent 'El Dorado' for many people who have nothing, full of risks in transit, and frustrations and penalties upon arrival.</en>
      <fr>La Méditerranée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6828">et</DiscourseConnective> le littoral des Canaries sont devenus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6869">pour</DiscourseConnective> beaucoup de gens qui n'ont rien des voies de passage vers un Eldorado inexistant, remplies de dangers pendant la traversée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6997">et</DiscourseConnective> de frustrations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7016">et</DiscourseConnective> de sanctions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7032">à</DiscourseConnective> l'arrivée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6420" docOffset="36">
      <en>The European Union and the Member States have to be more sensitive to avoid such tragedies.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7064">et</DiscourseConnective> les États membres doivent être plus sensibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7113">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>éviter de telles tragédies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6512" docOffset="37">
      <en>We do a lot <Alignment alignment="7171" annotation_id="6524">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6524" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it achieves nothing.</en>
      <fr>Nous faisons beaucoup, <Alignment alignment="6524" annotation_id="7171">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7171" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela ne sert à rien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6549" docOffset="38">
      <en>The results are extremely harsh, <Alignment alignment="19122" annotation_id="6582">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6582" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have seen on the coasts of Libya, and must make us consider the limited effectiveness of our policies.</en>
      <fr>Les résultats sont extrêmement durs, <Alignment alignment="6582" annotation_id="7234">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7234" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous l'avons vu sur les côtes libyennes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7281">et</DiscourseConnective> doivent nous faire réfléchir à l'efficacité limitée de nos politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6691" docOffset="39">
      <en>There are no magic recipes for finding absolutely effective solutions to such tragedies, <Alignment alignment="31100" annotation_id="6780">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6780" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are persistent and determined policies.</en>
      <fr>Il n'y a pas de recettes magiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7389">pour</DiscourseConnective> trouver des solutions absolument efficaces <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7437">à</DiscourseConnective> de telles tragédies, <Alignment alignment="6780" annotation_id="7460">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7460" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il y a des politiques persistantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7500">et</DiscourseConnective> déterminées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6830" docOffset="40">
      <en>We have to encourage solid policies of cooperation with countries of origin and of transit; cooperation and collaboration must be two sides of the same coin.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons encourager des politiques solides de coopération avec les pays d'origine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7601">et</DiscourseConnective> de transit; coopération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7628">et</DiscourseConnective> collaboration doivent être les deux faces de la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7679">même</DiscourseConnective> pièce.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6988" docOffset="41">
      <en>We need to better organise and publicise the benefits of legal immigration in a concerted way, even in times of crisis.</en>
      <fr>Il est nécessaire que nous organisions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7730">mieux</DiscourseConnective> l'immigration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7750">et</DiscourseConnective> que nous fassions connaître les avantages d'une immigration légale concertée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7831">même en</DiscourseConnective> temps de crise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7108" docOffset="42">
      <en>We must collaborate and cooperate with the countries of origin and transit regarding the control of their borders, on the basis of detailed agreements.</en>
      <fr>Il faut que nous collaborions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7885">et</DiscourseConnective> coopérions avec les pays d'origine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7923">et</DiscourseConnective> de transit en ce qui concerne le contrôle de leurs frontières, sur la base d'accords détaillés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7260" docOffset="43">
      <en>We must <Alignment alignment="5303" annotation_id="7268">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7268" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hunt out traffickers from their networks with intelligence and specialised forces, and at the same time toughen up criminal laws in the destination countries.</en>
      <fr>Le renseignement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8039">et</DiscourseConnective> des forces spécialisées doivent <Alignment alignment="14506" annotation_id="8074">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8074" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous permettre de découvrir les réseaux de trafiquants, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8140">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8144">parallèlement</DiscourseConnective>, il nous faut durcir les législations pénales des pays de destination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7432" docOffset="44">
      <en>We need to better equip the External Borders Fund; EUR 1 820 million over seven years is clearly an insufficient amount by any stretch of the imagination.</en>
      <fr>Il est indispensable de doter davantage le Fonds pour les frontières extérieures; 1 820 millions d'euros sur sept ans représentent, de toute évidence, un montant qui ne peut en aucune manière être considéré comme suffisant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7587" docOffset="45">
      <en>We must <Alignment alignment="8466" annotation_id="7595">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7595" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> successfully strengthen Frontex, and ensure that the catalogue of equipment, CRATE (Centralised Record of Available Technical Equipment), is not a statement of intention, but rather an efficient tool for the coordinated control and surveillance of the critical pressure points of clandestine activity.</en>
      <fr>Il nous faut <Alignment alignment="7595" annotation_id="8466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8466" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> renforcer efficacement Frontex <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8507">et</DiscourseConnective> nous assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8523">que</DiscourseConnective> le catalogue d'équipements, CRATE (Liste centralisée d'équipements techniques disponibles), n'est pas une déclaration d'intention, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8658">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8663">plutôt</DiscourseConnective> un instrument efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8693">pour</DiscourseConnective> la coordination du contrôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8726">et</DiscourseConnective> de la surveillance des points névralgiques de l'activité clandestine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7902" docOffset="46">
      <en>Commissioner, Nautilus, Hermes and EUR 24 million mean more commitment and more equipment.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, Nautilus, Hermès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8841">et</DiscourseConnective> 24 millions d'euros impliquent davantage d'engagement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8898">et</DiscourseConnective> davantage d'équipement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7993" docOffset="47">
      <en>We should stop saying 'we must', <Alignment alignment="8969" annotation_id="8026">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8026" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="12613" annotation_id="8030">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8030" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> take on this tough responsibility, with or without global agreement.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions cesser de dire "il faut que", <Alignment alignment="8026" annotation_id="8969">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8969" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="2344" annotation_id="8972">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8972" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> accepter cette dure responsabilité, avec <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9018">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9021">sans</DiscourseConnective> accord global.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8102" id="219" name="Pasqualina Napoletano">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8102" docOffset="48">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (IT) Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, we are talking about a loss of more than 500 lives: the greatest tragedy at sea since the Second World War.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (IT) Madame la Présidente, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9101">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, nous parlons ici de la disparition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9150">de plus</DiscourseConnective> de 500 personnes: la plus grande tragédie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9200">en</DiscourseConnective> mer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9207">depuis</DiscourseConnective> la Seconde Guerre mondiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8284" docOffset="49">
      <en>The numbers are shocking, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8310" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> yet Europe and its governments seem distracted.</en>
      <fr>Les chiffres sont terribles, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9271">pourtant</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9289">et</DiscourseConnective> ses gouvernements semblent ne pas s'en préoccuper.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8362" docOffset="50">
      <en>Some countries, including Italy, thought they had protected themselves by signing bilateral agreements such as the recent treaty with Libya; that is not so.</en>
      <fr>Certains pays dont l'Italie, pensaient s'être mis à l'abri <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9402">en</DiscourseConnective> signant des accords bilatéraux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9436">comme</DiscourseConnective> ce traité récent avec la Libye; mais ce n'est pas le cas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8519" docOffset="51">
      <en>The agreement in question brings together very diverse issues, such as the recognition of crimes perpetrated during the colonial era, with promises of investment, in exchange for commitments to control migration.</en>
      <fr>L'accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9509">en</DiscourseConnective> question regroupe des problèmes très différents comme, par exemple, la reconnaissance des crimes perpétrés pendant la période coloniale, accompagnée de promesses d'investissement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9692">en</DiscourseConnective> échange d'engagements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9717">pour</DiscourseConnective> contrôler la migration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8732" docOffset="52">
      <en>Today, it seems the very mirage of Italian investments in Libya is attracting thousands of young people from West Africa.</en>
      <fr>À présent, il semble que le mirage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9781">même</DiscourseConnective> d'investissements italiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9813">en</DiscourseConnective> Libye attire des milliers de jeunes d'Afrique occidentale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8854" docOffset="53">
      <en>It is easy to predict that <Alignment alignment="26499" annotation_id="8881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8881" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the promised USD 5 billion does not arrive, then it is people who will arrive.</en>
      <fr>Il n'est pas difficile de prédire <Alignment alignment="12512" annotation_id="9909">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9909" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les cinq milliards de dollars n'arrivent pas, ce seront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9972">alors</DiscourseConnective> les personnes qui arriveront.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8963" docOffset="54">
      <en>What can we say <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8979" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> about French interests in Niger, linked to the stockpiling of uranium, which is stirring up a war among the Tuareg and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9103" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> favouring the people traffickers?</en>
      <fr>Et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10011">que</DiscourseConnective> dire des intérêts français au Niger, liés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10057">à</DiscourseConnective> l'exploitation de l'uranium, qui attise une guerre avec les Touaregs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10128">et</DiscourseConnective> favorise de la sorte les trafiquants d'êtres humains?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9142" docOffset="55">
      <en>What is more, all this is taking place in broad daylight, documented by journalists.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10185">En plus</DiscourseConnective>, tout ceci a lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10211">à</DiscourseConnective> la lumière du jour et fait l'objet de reportages journalistiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9227" docOffset="56">
      <en>What this means is that certain European governments are playing with fire.</en>
      <fr>Cela signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10293">que</DiscourseConnective> certains gouvernements européens jouent avec le feu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9303" docOffset="57">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6936" annotation_id="9303">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9303" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> all this does not change, and fast, <Alignment alignment="26921" annotation_id="9342">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9342" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europe does not decide to act with positive policies in keeping with our values, it will not be enough to mute the news <Alignment alignment="11020" annotation_id="9465">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9465" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are doing at present.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9303" annotation_id="10350">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10350" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tout ceci ne change pas, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10378">et</DiscourseConnective> rapidement, <Alignment alignment="9428" annotation_id="10393">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10393" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Europe ne se décide pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10422">à</DiscourseConnective> agir par des politiques positives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10458">en</DiscourseConnective> accord avec nos valeurs, il ne suffira pas de mettre une sourdine aux informations, <Alignment alignment="9465" annotation_id="10545">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10545" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous sommes en train de le faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9493" docOffset="58">
      <en>The Mediterranean is becoming a mass grave, far from the rhetorical images that describe it.</en>
      <fr>La Méditerranée est en train de devenir une fosse commune, à mille lieues des images idylliques qui la décrivent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9586" docOffset="59">
      <en>Let us remember <Alignment alignment="28037" annotation_id="9602">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9602" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that this sea is linked to the fate of Europe itself.</en>
      <fr>Souvenons-nous <Alignment alignment="9602" annotation_id="10714">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10714" sense="Comparison.Contrast">pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10723">que</DiscourseConnective> cette mer est liée au destin de l'Europe elle-même.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9663" id="221" language="FR" name="Gérard Deprez">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9663" docOffset="60">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, on behalf of my group I would <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9729" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> like to pay my respects to these latest victims of poverty, criminal exploitation and state cynicism.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe ALDE. - Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, moi aussi, au nom de mon groupe, je veux m'incliner devant ces nouveaux morts victimes de la misère, de l'exploitation criminelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10974">et</DiscourseConnective> du cynisme d'État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9836" docOffset="61">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10996" annotation_id="9836">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9836" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, compassion is not enough.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9836" annotation_id="10996">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10996" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la compassion ne suffit pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9871" docOffset="62">
      <en>We need to see things <Alignment alignment="1308" annotation_id="9893">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9893" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they really are.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons regarder la réalité <Alignment alignment="9893" annotation_id="11062">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11062" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> face.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9913" docOffset="63">
      <en>The reality, Mr President, is that the real southern borders of the European Union are no longer truly in Europe, they are now on the African continent.</en>
      <fr>La réalité, Monsieur le Président, c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11112">que</DiscourseConnective> les vraies frontières méridionales de l'Union européenne ne sont plus vraiment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11195">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe, elles sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11217">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> sur le continent africain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10066" docOffset="64">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7585" annotation_id="10066">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10066" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">Once</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the boats have left African shores, the unfortunate passengers no longer have a choice, dare I say it, between death, <Alignment alignment="3142" annotation_id="10189">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10189" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the conditions are adverse, or having the status of illegal immigrants, with the poverty that comes with it, if by chance they do reach European shores, before, in the majority of cases, being deported.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10066" annotation_id="11255">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11255" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">Dès que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les embarcations ont quitté le rivage africain, les malheureux passagers n'ont plus que le choix, si l'on ose dire, entre la mort, <Alignment alignment="10189" annotation_id="11394">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11394" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les conditions sont contraires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11429">ou</DiscourseConnective> le statut d'irréguliers, avec son cortège de misère, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11485">si</DiscourseConnective> par chance ils arrivent à atteindre le rivage européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11544">avant</DiscourseConnective>, la plupart du temps, d'en être expulsés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10395" docOffset="65">
      <en>These repeated tragedies will not stop <Alignment alignment="16924" annotation_id="10434">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10434" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">until</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Union has the power and the will to negotiate real partnership agreements with the countries of origin and transit that include at least three elements: reliable border controls, but also, and above all, a significant supply of legal immigration and a substantial co-development section.</en>
      <fr>Ces drames à répétition ne cesseront que <Alignment alignment="38" annotation_id="11633">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11633" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne aura le pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11676">et</DiscourseConnective> la volonté de négocier, avec les pays d'origine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11727">et</DiscourseConnective> de transit, de véritables accords de partenariat qui comporteront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11796">au moins</DiscourseConnective> trois éléments: certes, un contrôle sérieux des frontières, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11865">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11876">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11879">surtout</DiscourseConnective> une offre significative d'immigration légale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11932">et</DiscourseConnective> un volet substantiel de codéveloppement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10741" docOffset="66">
      <en>Without these agreements, Mr President, the cemeteries of the sea are going to keep filling up for a long time to come, despite our flimsy and powerless bursts of compassion.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11976">Faute de</DiscourseConnective> tels accords, Monsieur le Président, pendant longtemps encore les cimetières marins ne vont pas cesser de se remplir, malgré le souffle fragile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12129">et</DiscourseConnective> impuissant de notre compassion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10916" id="222" language="FR" name="Hélène Flautre">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10916" docOffset="67">
      <en>Mr President, who were they?</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. - Monsieur le Président, qui étaient-ils?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10945" docOffset="68">
      <en>How many were there?</en>
      <fr>Combien étaient-ils?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10966" docOffset="69">
      <en>Where had they come from?</en>
      <fr>D'où venaient-ils?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10992" docOffset="70">
      <en>Were there children, women, refugees?</en>
      <fr>Y avait-il des enfants, des femmes, des réfugiés?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11030" docOffset="71">
      <en>Did coastguards hamper the boats' journey?</en>
      <fr>Des garde-côtes ont-ils entravé la route des bateaux?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11073" docOffset="72">
      <en>Did fishermen cross their path?</en>
      <fr>Des pêcheurs ont-ils passé leur chemin?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11105" docOffset="73">
      <en>So many unanswered questions.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12418">Autant</DiscourseConnective> de questions sans réponses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11135" docOffset="74">
      <en>The human cost of the tragedy is not known, <Alignment alignment="19144" annotation_id="11179">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11179" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hundreds perished, joining the thousands of migrants who have drowned in the Mediterranean.</en>
      <fr>Le bilan humain du drame n'est pas connu, <Alignment alignment="4122" annotation_id="12495">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12495" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils sont des centaines à avoir péri, à avoir rejoint les milliers de migrants morts noyés dans la Méditerranée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11275" docOffset="75">
      <en>Let us have the decency, <Alignment alignment="11102" annotation_id="11300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11300" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we do tonight, not to blame the weather.</en>
      <fr>Ayons la décence - <Alignment alignment="11300" annotation_id="12631">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12631" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous l'avons ce soir - de ne pas accuser la météo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11344" docOffset="76">
      <en>Hundreds of migrants have taken the route to exile in inhuman and highly dangerous conditions.</en>
      <fr>Des centaines de migrants ont pris le chemin de l'exil dans des conditions inhumaines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12771">et</DiscourseConnective> hautement périlleuses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11439" docOffset="77">
      <en>Why is that?</en>
      <fr>Pourquoi?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11452" docOffset="78">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="12807" annotation_id="11458">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11458" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are fleeing devastated regions, <Alignment alignment="12850" annotation_id="11503">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11503" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the less dangerous routes are closed to them <Alignment alignment="35396" annotation_id="11556">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11556" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="13245" annotation_id="11560">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11560" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they have not given up hope for life.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4655" annotation_id="12807">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12807" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils fuient des régions dévastées, <Alignment alignment="8411" annotation_id="12850">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12850" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les voies moins dangereuses leur sont fermées <Alignment alignment="11556" annotation_id="12906">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12906" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="7539" annotation_id="12909">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12909" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils n'ont pas renoncé à espérer de la vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11606" docOffset="79">
      <en>Yes, it is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11617" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">indeed</DiscourseConnective> the anti-immigration mechanisms that encourage migrants to take increasingly risky routes to flee the desolation of their countries that are the cause.</en>
      <fr>Oui, ce sont bien les dispositifs de lutte contre l'immigration qui poussent les migrants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13051">à</DiscourseConnective> emprunter des routes toujours plus risquées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13097">pour</DiscourseConnective> fuir la désolation de leurs pays, qui est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13144">en</DiscourseConnective> cause.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11776" docOffset="80">
      <en>Was it not the forthcoming announcement of joint patrols in Italy and Libya that hastened the departure of boats to Europe in recent weeks?</en>
      <fr>N'est-ce pas l'annonce, dans les jours à venir, de patrouilles communes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13226">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Italie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13237">et</DiscourseConnective> à la Libye, qui a précipité ces dernières semaines les embarcations vers l'Europe?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11916" docOffset="81">
      <en>Yes, Europe's obsession with shoring up its borders and its determination to focus the weight of its administration on third countries that destroy freedom, are lethal.</en>
      <fr>Oui, l'obsession de l'Europe, arc-boutée sur ses frontières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13383">et</DiscourseConnective> déterminée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13397">à</DiscourseConnective> faire porter le poids de sa gestion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13435">à</DiscourseConnective> des pays tiers liberticides, est meurtrière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12085" docOffset="82">
      <en>The overemphasis on law and order, the patrols and the barbed wired fences will not overcome their desire to escape.</en>
      <fr>Le "tout sécuritaire", les patrouilles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13521">et</DiscourseConnective> les fils de fer barbelé ne viendront pas à bout de leur volonté de fuir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12202" docOffset="83">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13597" annotation_id="12202">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12202" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the question is this: is Europe ready to take responsibility for the consequences of such a choice?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12202" annotation_id="13597">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13597" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la question est la suivante: l'Europe est-elle prête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13657">à</DiscourseConnective> assumer les conséquences d'un tel choix?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12305" docOffset="84">
      <en>No, it is not, <Alignment alignment="13719" annotation_id="12320">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12320" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is why I am asking the Commission and the Member States:</en>
      <fr>Elle ne l'est pas, <Alignment alignment="9895" annotation_id="13719">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13719" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13722">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> je demande à la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13764">et</DiscourseConnective> aux États membres:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12386" docOffset="85">
      <en>firstly, to do everything in their power to find and, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12440" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> possible, rescue the people who have disappeared at sea, and to investigate the circumstances of this wreck;</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13786">premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, de tout mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13815">en</DiscourseConnective> œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13824">pour</DiscourseConnective> localiser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13839">et</DiscourseConnective>, éventuellement, secourir les personnes disparues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13892">en</DiscourseConnective> mer, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13900">et</DiscourseConnective> d'enquêter sur les circonstances de ce naufrage;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12552" docOffset="86">
      <en>secondly, to reaffirm international maritime law, which makes it mandatory to provide assistance to anyone in distress, <Alignment alignment="15950" annotation_id="12672">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12672" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the seven Tunisian fishermen are still on trial;</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13952">deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, de réaffirmer le droit maritime international qui fait obligation de prêter assistance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14053">à</DiscourseConnective> toute personne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14070">en</DiscourseConnective> détresse, <Alignment alignment="12672" annotation_id="14083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14083" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les sept pêcheurs tunisiens sont toujours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14135">en</DiscourseConnective> procès;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12727" docOffset="87">
      <en>thirdly, to halt all negotiations on migration issues with countries that do not provide any guarantees of respect for human rights;</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14146">troisièmement</DiscourseConnective>, de stopper toute négociation sur les questions migratoires avec les pays qui ne présentent aucune garantie de respect des droits humains;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12860" docOffset="88">
      <en>fourthly, to respect the right of every human being to leave any country and ask for international protection in any country.</en>
      <fr>quatrièmement, de respecter le droit de tout être humain de quitter tout pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14377">et</DiscourseConnective> de demander protection internationale dans tout pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12986" docOffset="89">
      <en>You are right, the people who disappeared at sea are not illegal migrants;</en>
      <fr>Vous avez raison, les personnes disparues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14476">en</DiscourseConnective> mer ne sont pas des migrants illégaux;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13061" docOffset="90">
      <en>fifthly, to put an end to the restrictive visa policy, which is often arbitrary and unfair;</en>
      <fr>cinquièmement, de mettre fin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14547">à</DiscourseConnective> une politique des visas restrictive, souvent arbitraire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14605">et</DiscourseConnective> injuste;</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13153" docOffset="91">
      <en>and lastly, to closely examine, from the point of view of development in third countries, all the European Union's policies, including the predation of mining resources, agricultural dumping, free-trade agreements, trade in weapons and indulgent cooperation with autocrats.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14617">enfin</DiscourseConnective>, de passer au crible du développement humain, dans les pays tiers, toutes les politiques de l'Union, de la prédation des ressources minières au dumping agricole, en passant par les accords de libre-échange, le commerce des armes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14852">ou encore</DiscourseConnective> la coopération complaisante avec les autocrates.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13427" id="223" name="Giusto Catania">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13427" docOffset="92">
      <en>on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group. - (IT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, what happened the other day is just the latest in a long line of shameful tragedies that have assumed mammoth dimensions.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. - (IT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14976">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, ce qu'il s'est passé l'autre jour n'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15030">que</DiscourseConnective> la plus récente d'une série de tragédies honteuses qui a pris des dimensions colossales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13624" docOffset="93">
      <en>The death at sea of emigrants trying to reach our shores is without a shadow of a doubt the greatest violation of life wrought in civilised Europe.</en>
      <fr>La mort <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15131">en</DiscourseConnective> mer d'émigrants essayant d'atteindre nos rivages est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15187">sans</DiscourseConnective> l'ombre d'un doute la plus grande atteinte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15235">à</DiscourseConnective> la vie qui puisse se concevoir dans l'Europe des civilisations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13772" docOffset="94">
      <en>These tragedies demonstrate the terrible face of our fortress.</en>
      <fr>Ces tragédies montrent la face noire de notre forteresse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13835" docOffset="95">
      <en>Perhaps we ought to begin to think about our responsibility for the deaths of men and women whose sole ambition was to find a better life and escape hunger and war.</en>
      <fr>Peut-être devrions-nous commencer par penser à notre responsabilité dans les morts d'hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15451">et</DiscourseConnective> de femmes dont l'unique ambition était de trouver une vie meilleure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15522">et</DiscourseConnective> d'échapper à la faim <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15546">et</DiscourseConnective> à la guerre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14000" docOffset="96">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14000" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>, we should probably analyse the fact that those shipwrecked in the Mediterranean are not an anomaly of a mechanism that creates illegal immigration; <Alignment alignment="1758" annotation_id="14159">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14159" sense="Expansion.Restatement">rather</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are a foreseeable consequence of the immigration policy of the European Union and its Member States.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions sans doute analyser le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15604">que</DiscourseConnective> les naufragés de la Méditerranée ne sont pas l'anomalie d'un mécanisme qui crée de l'immigration clandestine; ils sont <Alignment alignment="14159" annotation_id="15727">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15727" sense="Expansion.Restatement">plutôt</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une conséquence prévisible de la politique d'immigration de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15813">et</DiscourseConnective> de ses États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14272" docOffset="97">
      <en>The slaughter in the Mediterranean is caused by the philosophy of repression, by the policies of turning people back at sea, by the virtual barbed wire along our coasts, by the prohibitionist practices implemented in the immigration policy of the European Union and its Member States, including Italy and Malta.</en>
      <fr>Cette hécatombe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15854">en</DiscourseConnective> Méditerranée est provoquée par une logique répressive, par des politiques visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15938">à</DiscourseConnective> refouler les gens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15958">en</DiscourseConnective> pleine mer, par les fils de fer barbelés virtuels qui longent nos côtes, par les pratiques prohibitionnistes mises en œuvre dans la politique d'immigration de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16139">et</DiscourseConnective> de ses États membres dont l'Italie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16177">et</DiscourseConnective> Malte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14584" docOffset="98">
      <en>There is no other way to enter Europe; there are no legal channels for accessing the European labour market or finding recognition of the sacrosanct right of asylum.</en>
      <fr>Il n'existe pas d'autre manière d'entrer en Europe; il n'existe pas de canaux réguliers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16275">pour</DiscourseConnective> accéder au marché du travail européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16318">ou</DiscourseConnective> obtenir la reconnaissance du sacro-saint droit d'asile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14750" docOffset="99">
      <en>Hope is consigned to the stormy waves of the Mediterranean Sea; rights are delivered into the hands of unscrupulous boatmen, who have become the only means, or at least the most accessible means, to enter the European Union.</en>
      <fr>L'espoir est confié aux tempêtes de la mer Méditerranée; les droits sont remis entre les mains de passeurs sans scrupules devenus les seuls moyens, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16525">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16528">tout au moins</DiscourseConnective> les plus accessibles, d'entrer dans l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14975" docOffset="100">
      <en>That is the real cause of the deaths off the coast of Libya a few days ago.</en>
      <fr>C'est la cause véritable de ces morts au large des côtes libyennes, il y a quelques jours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15051" docOffset="101">
      <en>That is the reason why, in the last 20 years, tens of thousands of migrants have died in an attempt to reach Europe; faceless, nameless men and women reduced to food for the fishes.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle, au cours des vingt dernières années, des milliers de migrants sont morts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16793">en</DiscourseConnective> tentant d'atteindre l'Europe; des hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16837">et</DiscourseConnective> des femmes sans visage et sans nom réduits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16883">à</DiscourseConnective> servir de nourriture aux poissons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15233" docOffset="102">
      <en>I asked President Pöttering to open today's session with a minute's silence, as a sign of mourning in recognition of these victims.</en>
      <fr>J'ai demandé au Président Pöttering d'ouvrir la séance d'aujourd'hui par une minute de silence, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17016">en</DiscourseConnective> signe de deuil et de reconnaissance de ces victimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15365" docOffset="103">
      <en>I thank him for granting my request.</en>
      <fr>Je le remercie d'avoir accédé à ma demande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15402" docOffset="104">
      <en>I think we had a duty to do this, <Alignment alignment="17164" annotation_id="15436">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15436" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> clearly it is not enough.</en>
      <fr>Je pense que nous avions le devoir de le faire, <Alignment alignment="15436" annotation_id="17164">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17164" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est évident que cela ne suffit pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15466" docOffset="105">
      <en>It demonstrates our indignation, <Alignment alignment="34449" annotation_id="15499">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15499" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must try to produce a policy in this House, a concrete policy, that begins to say never again, never again must there be deaths in the Mediterranean.</en>
      <fr>C'est la démonstration de notre indignation, <Alignment alignment="15499" annotation_id="17253">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17253" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons tenter de produire, au sein de cette Assemblée, une politique concrète qui commence par <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17358">dire que</DiscourseConnective> plus jamais, plus jamais il ne doit y avoir de morts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17420">en</DiscourseConnective> Méditerranée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15656" id="224" language="FR" name="Jacques Barrot">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15656" docOffset="106">
      <en>Mr President, I will be brief.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - Monsieur le Président, je serai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17504">bref</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15687" docOffset="107">
      <en>What is important is to take action, <Alignment alignment="17540" annotation_id="15724">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15724" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I echo what Mr Deprez said.</en>
      <fr>Ce qui importe, c'est d'agir, <Alignment alignment="15724" annotation_id="17540">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17540" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je fais écho à ce qu'a dit le président Deprez.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15756" docOffset="108">
      <en>We do need to move towards this global approach, towards partnership agreements, <Alignment alignment="32450" annotation_id="15837">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15837" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will not succeed in solving the problems unilaterally.</en>
      <fr>Il faut, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17600">en effet</DiscourseConnective>, aller vers cette approche globale, vers des accords de partenariat, <Alignment alignment="15837" annotation_id="17678">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17678" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous n'arriverons pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17704">à</DiscourseConnective> résoudre les problèmes de manière unilatérale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15903" docOffset="109">
      <en>I am quite happy to admit, <Alignment alignment="17776" annotation_id="15930">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15930" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you pointed out, that as Europeans we have responsibilities.</en>
      <fr>Je veux bien admettre, <Alignment alignment="15930" annotation_id="17776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17776" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous l'avez souligné, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17801">que</DiscourseConnective> nous, Européens, avons des responsabilités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15994" docOffset="110">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23757" annotation_id="15994">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15994" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, on the issue of legal migration, we need to demonstrate a spirit of openness.</en>
      <fr>Il faut <Alignment alignment="15994" annotation_id="17857">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17857" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, sur la question de la migration légale, nous marquions un esprit d'ouverture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16078" docOffset="111">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="17958" annotation_id="16081">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16081" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> need to fulfil our duty to receive people who are fleeing persecution and war.</en>
      <fr>Il faut <Alignment alignment="16081" annotation_id="17958">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17958" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que nous remplissions notre devoir d'accueil à l'égard des personnes qui fuient la persécution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18059">et</DiscourseConnective> la guerre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16165" docOffset="112">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18073" annotation_id="16165">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16165" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, having said that, allow me to say, and to remind Parliament quite truthfully that the responsibility <Alignment alignment="18214" annotation_id="16275">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16275" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> lies with a number of third countries with which negotiation is very difficult.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14784" annotation_id="18073">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18073" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18078">ceci étant dit</DiscourseConnective>, vous me permettrez de le dire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18124">et</DiscourseConnective> de le rappeler au Parlement européen avec beaucoup de vérité, les responsabilités sont <Alignment alignment="16275" annotation_id="18214">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18214" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> celles d'un certain nombre d'États tiers avec lesquels la négociation est très difficile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16360" docOffset="113">
      <en>Does that mean that we should give up on negotiating?</en>
      <fr>Pour autant, est-ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18330">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut renoncer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18350">à</DiscourseConnective> négocier?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16414" docOffset="114">
      <en>No!</en>
      <fr>Non!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16418" docOffset="115">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="39395" annotation_id="16418">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16418" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">For example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we need to ensure that Libya finally has an asylum system.</en>
      <fr>Il faut, <Alignment alignment="16418" annotation_id="18376">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18376" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, obtenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18397">que</DiscourseConnective> la Libye ait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18414">enfin</DiscourseConnective> un système d'asile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16490" docOffset="116">
      <en>We need to ensure that Libya can help us to stop a number of the smugglers, who force these poor people to take unnecessary risks.</en>
      <fr>Il faut obtenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18456">que</DiscourseConnective> la Libye puisse nous aider <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18487">à</DiscourseConnective> arrêter un certain nombre de passeurs, qui font prendre des risques inconsidérés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18570">à</DiscourseConnective> ces pauvres gens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16621" docOffset="117">
      <en>I have personally heard the Maltese authorities saying that Libya allowed a number of boats to depart in awful conditions <Alignment alignment="16751" annotation_id="16743">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16743" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that subsequently the Maltese navy was forced to go out and find and save the poor people who were being exploited by the smugglers.</en>
      <fr>J'ai moi-même entendu les autorités maltaises déclarer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18645">que</DiscourseConnective> la Libye laissait partir un certain nombre de bateaux dans des conditions déplorables <Alignment alignment="16743" annotation_id="18735">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18735" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18738">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18741">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>, la marine maltaise était obligée d'aller rejoindre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18801">et</DiscourseConnective> sauver ces pauvres gens exploités par les passeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16880" docOffset="118">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10796" annotation_id="16880">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16880" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we do need to take responsibility, <Alignment alignment="18896" annotation_id="16918">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16918" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> at the same time we need to demonstrate a degree of firmness in our negotiations with a number of states that are not fulfilling their international obligations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4114" annotation_id="18856">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18856" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, assumer nos responsabilités, oui, <Alignment alignment="1359" annotation_id="18896">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18896" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18901">en même temps</DiscourseConnective>, il faut que nous fassions preuve d'une certaine fermeté dans les négociations avec un certain nombre d'États qui ne remplissent pas leurs obligations internationales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17084" docOffset="119">
      <en>I think that is enough to get us all working together to prevent such tragic incidents from reoccurring.</en>
      <fr>Voilà, je crois, en tout cas, de quoi nous mobiliser tous ensemble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19150">pour</DiscourseConnective>, en effet, éviter le retour de tels incidents dramatiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17189" id="225" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17189" docOffset="120">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
