<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statement by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclaration de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="27" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I am saddened and dismayed to have to inform you today that, last weekend, more than 300 people were drowned <Alignment alignment="177" annotation_id="158">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="158" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a number of refugee boats went down in the Mediterranean off the coast of Libya.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, c'est avec tristesse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="73">et</DiscourseConnective> consternation que je dois vous informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="116">que</DiscourseConnective>, la semaine dernière, plus de 300 réfugiés se sont noyés <Alignment alignment="197" annotation_id="177">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="177" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leurs embarcations ont sombré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="215">en</DiscourseConnective> mer Méditerranée, au large des côtes libyennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="244" docOffset="2">
      <en>These boats were carrying people from North and sub-Saharan Africa.</en>
      <fr>Ces embarcations transportaient des personnes du Maghreb <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="323">et</DiscourseConnective> d'Afrique subsaharienne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="312" docOffset="3">
      <en>Some of the refugees were rescued by the Egyptian and Libyan authorities, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="386" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> some bodies have been recovered, <Alignment alignment="351022" annotation_id="423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="423" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hundreds of people are still missing.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités égyptiennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="377">et</DiscourseConnective> libyennes ont pu sauver quelques personnes; quelques cadavres ont été repêchés, <Alignment alignment="545" annotation_id="460">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="460" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des centaines de personnes sont toujours portées disparues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="465" docOffset="4">
      <en>I would like, on behalf of the European Parliament, to say how deeply shocked and saddened we are by this event.</en>
      <fr>Au nom du Parlement européen, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="567">dire que</DiscourseConnective> nous sommes profondément choqués <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="609">et</DiscourseConnective> attristés par cet événement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="578" docOffset="5">
      <en>Over the last two years, the European Union has been experiencing an increase in immigration via the Mediterranean, <Alignment alignment="357932" annotation_id="694">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="694" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the economic crisis means that we can expect to see significantly more people fleeing poverty in Africa.</en>
      <fr>Ces deux dernières années, l'Union européenne a vu s'intensifier l'immigration d'une rive à l'autre de la Méditerranée <Alignment alignment="694" annotation_id="760">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="760" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans le contexte de crise économique actuel, nous pouvons nous attendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="836">à</DiscourseConnective> une forte augmentation du nombre de personnes fuyant la pauvreté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="903">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="803" docOffset="6">
      <en>The large numbers of refugees that tragically lose their lives <Alignment alignment="984" annotation_id="866">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="866" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> attempting to reach the European Union threaten to turn the Mediterranean into a huge open-air graveyard; it is up to us to find solutions to put an end to these tragedies.</en>
      <fr>L'augmentation du nombre de réfugiés qui perdent tragiquement la vie <Alignment alignment="644" annotation_id="984">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="984" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tentant d'atteindre l'Union européenne risque de transformer la Méditerranée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1064">en</DiscourseConnective> un immense cimetière à ciel ouvert. Nous devons faire en sorte que de telles tragédies ne se reproduisent plus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1044" docOffset="7">
      <en>I would ask you now to observe a minute's silence in memory of the dead.</en>
      <fr>Je vous propose d'observer une minute de silence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1228">à</DiscourseConnective> la mémoire des victimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1117" docOffset="8">
      <en>(The House rose and observed a minute's silence)</en>
      <fr>(L'Assemblée, debout, observe une minute de silence)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1166" docOffset="9">
      <en>Thank you.</en>
      <fr>Merci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
