<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statement by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclaration de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="27" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, the Kosovo Parliament declared Kosovo's independence yesterday.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, le Parlement du Kosovo a déclaré hier l'indépendance du Kosovo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="113" docOffset="2">
      <en>This decision was expected and reflects the will of the citizens in Kosovo to take their political fate and institutional shaping of independence peacefully into their own hands.</en>
      <fr>Cette décision attendue reflète la volonté des citoyens du Kosovo de prendre pacifiquement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="207">en</DiscourseConnective> main leur destin politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="237">et</DiscourseConnective> la mise en forme institutionnelle de leur indépendance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="292" docOffset="3">
      <en>About a year ago, the European Parliament, as a consequence of the Ahtisaari report, agreed on the supervised sovereignty of Kosovo.</en>
      <fr>Il y a près d'un an, le Parlement européen, dans la foulée du rapport Ahtisaari, est convenu de superviser la souveraineté du Kosovo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="425" docOffset="4">
      <en>The negotiations between Belgrade and Priština were extremely difficult and regrettably did not lead to a solution which was acceptable politically to all participants.</en>
      <fr>Les négociations entre Belgrade <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="462">et</DiscourseConnective> Pristina ont été extrêmement difficiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="505">et</DiscourseConnective> n'ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="514">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> pas abouti <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="541">à</DiscourseConnective> une solution acceptable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="567">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous les participants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="594" docOffset="5">
      <en>As so often in politics, there was no magic formula.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="595">Comme</DiscourseConnective> très souvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="614">en</DiscourseConnective> politique, il n'y avait pas de formule magique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="647" docOffset="6">
      <en>The heavy burden of recent history contributed to this situation.</en>
      <fr>La lourde charge de l'histoire récente a contribué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="716">à</DiscourseConnective> cette situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="713" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="735" annotation_id="713">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="713" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the case of Kosovo is not a precedent.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="735">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="735" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le cas du Kosovo n'est pas un précédent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="761" docOffset="8">
      <en>The situation of Kosovo as a UN protectorate is unique and is a special case which cannot be compared with others.</en>
      <fr>À titre de protectorat des NU, la situation du Kosovo est unique; c'est un cas spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="874">et</DiscourseConnective> incomparable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="876" docOffset="9">
      <en>I would like to call upon all those involved and appeal to them for reason and calm.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais appeler toutes les parties impliquées à la raison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="952">et</DiscourseConnective> au calme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="961" docOffset="10">
      <en>I am sure that everyone in Kosovo - Serbs and Kosovans -wishes to achieve stability and prosperity in their region.</en>
      <fr>Je suis sûr <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="977">que</DiscourseConnective> tout un chacun au Kosovo - Serbes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1015">et</DiscourseConnective> Kosovars - aspire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1036">à</DiscourseConnective> assurer la stabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1059">et</DiscourseConnective> la prospérité de sa région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1077" docOffset="11">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1096" annotation_id="1077">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1077" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Indeed</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, that is the primary objective of the European Union and the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>C'est <Alignment alignment="1077" annotation_id="1096">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1096" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'objectif premier de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1146">et</DiscourseConnective> de son Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1166" docOffset="12">
      <en>It is our task and duty to encourage the political leaders in Kosovo to assume their responsibilities and to create democratic political institutions which respect the rights and freedoms of all citizens in the context of a multiethnic Kosovo which lives in good-neighbourly relations with its neighbours.</en>
      <fr>C'est notre mission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1187">et</DiscourseConnective> notre obligation d'encourager les leaders du Kosovo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1242">à</DiscourseConnective> assumer leurs responsabilités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1274">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1277">à</DiscourseConnective> créer des institutions politiques démocratiques respectant les droits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1349">et</DiscourseConnective> les libertés de tous les citoyens dans le contexte d'un Kosovo multiethnique vivant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1436">en</DiscourseConnective> bonne entente avec ses voisins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1472" docOffset="13">
      <en>In that connection, I <Alignment alignment="1498" annotation_id="1494">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1494" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcome the decision by the Council to send the EULEX Kosovo mission led by Yves de Kermabon.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce cadre, j'applaudis <Alignment alignment="138" annotation_id="1498">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1498" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la décision du Conseil d'envoyer la mission EULEX Kosovo conduite par Yves de Kermabon.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1593" docOffset="14">
      <en>The task of the mission will be to provide assistance to the Kosovans in the field of policing and the rule of law to ensure a smooth transition.</en>
      <fr>Il reviendra à cette mission de prêter assistance aux Kosovars dans le maintien de l'ordre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1687">et</DiscourseConnective> de soutenir le rôle de la loi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1720">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer une transition en douceur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1739" docOffset="15">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="1772" annotation_id="1741">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1741" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcome the appointment of Pieter Feith as EU Special Representative in Kosovo.</en>
      <fr>J'applaudis <Alignment alignment="1741" annotation_id="1772">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1772" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la désignation de Pieter Feith au titre de représentant spécial de l'UE au Kosovo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1826" docOffset="16">
      <en>This demonstrates the European Union's clear and resolute commitment and our will to do something practical for lasting stability in the Balkans.</en>
      <fr>Ce qui traduit l'implication claire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1901">et</DiscourseConnective> résolue de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1934">et</DiscourseConnective> notre volonté de faire quelque chose de concret <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1985">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer la stabilité dans les Balkans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1972" docOffset="17">
      <en>I trust in the wisdom of the decision to be made by the General Affairs Council at its meeting this afternoon.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2038">à</DiscourseConnective> la sagesse de la décision que devra prendre le conseil des affaires générales qui se réunit cet après-midi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2083" docOffset="18">
      <en>The countries of the Western Balkans have European prospects.</en>
      <fr>Les pays des Balkans occidentaux ont des visées européennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2145" docOffset="19">
      <en>Their accession will not be able to take place in the near future, <Alignment alignment="2267" annotation_id="2212">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2212" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> each of these countries has this prospect.</en>
      <fr>Une accession qui ne pourra se faire dans un futur proche <Alignment alignment="381" annotation_id="2267">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2267" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> chacun de ces pays l'a à l'esprit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2259" docOffset="20">
      <en>In light of that, we should help the people in Serbia and in Kosovo to overcome their differences from the point of view of European integration, as has already happened in other parts of Europe.</en>
      <fr>Sous une telle lumière, nous devons aider les populations de Serbie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2378">et</DiscourseConnective> du Kosovo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2391">à</DiscourseConnective> dépasser leurs différences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2420">dans l'espoir d'</DiscourseConnective>une intégration européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2464">comme</DiscourseConnective> cela s'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2481">déjà</DiscourseConnective> fait dans d'autres parties de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2455" docOffset="21">
      <en>The debate scheduled for Wednesday will be an initial opportunity to do this.</en>
      <fr>Le débat annoncé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2543">pour</DiscourseConnective> mercredi sera une première opportunité de le faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
