<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>6.</en>
    <fr>6.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Financial year 2009 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> amended by the Council (vote)</en>
    <fr>Exercice 2009, modifié par le Conseil (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="56" docOffset="2">
    <en>- After the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="50">Après</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="74" id="075" name="Éric Woerth">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="74" docOffset="3">
      <en>President-in-Office of the Council. - (FR) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, your vote on the second reading of the draft budget constitutes the final stage of a procedure marked by a very high standard of cooperation between the two branches of the budgetary authority and with the Commission.</en>
      <fr>président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="74">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil. - Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="132">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs les parlementaires, votre vote sur la seconde lecture du projet de budget constitue la dernière étape d'une procédure marquée par une très grande qualité de coopération entre les deux branches de l'autorité budgétaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="363">et</DiscourseConnective> avec la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="371" docOffset="4">
      <en>I should like to extend my warmest thanks to all those involved, especially the chairman of the Committee on Budgets, Mr Böge, the rapporteurs, Mrs Haug and Mr Lewandowski, and Commissioner Grybauskaitė.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite en remercier très chaleureusement tous les acteurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="450">notamment</DiscourseConnective> le président de la commission des budgets, Reimer Böge, les rapporteurs, Jutta Haug <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="544">et</DiscourseConnective> Janusz Lewandowski, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="567">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la commissaire Dalia Grybauskaitė.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="575" docOffset="5">
      <en>At our consultation meeting of 21 November we worked together to develop a balanced budget for 2009 that will guarantee that the funding of EU policies is properly assessed at the same time <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="765" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> European taxpayers' interests are protected.</en>
      <fr>Ensemble, lors de notre réunion de concertation le 21 novembre dernier, nous avons défini un budget 2009 équilibré, qui assure un financement bien calibré des politiques de l'Union européenne, tout en préservant les intérêts des contribuables européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="813" docOffset="6">
      <en>Together, we have come up with methods of funding the food facility, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="882" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective> fulfilling our duty to support developing countries <Alignment alignment="1032" annotation_id="942">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="942" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, together, we have designed practical measures making it possible to break the deadlock on cohesion policy and to finally launch the programmes for the period 2007-2013.</en>
      <fr>Ensemble, nous avons dégagé les modalités de financement de la facilité alimentaire, répondant ainsi à notre devoir de solidarité à l'égard des pays en développement <Alignment alignment="942" annotation_id="1032">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1032" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ensemble, nous avons dessiné les mesures concrètes permettant de sortir de la situation de blocage sur la politique de cohésion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1164">et</DiscourseConnective> de lancer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1177">enfin</DiscourseConnective> les programmes de la période 2007-2013.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1116" docOffset="7">
      <en>The importance of this initiative was stressed by the Heads of State or Government at the European Council, <Alignment alignment="1338" annotation_id="1224">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1224" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this represents a major strand of the European response to the economic crisis, which we need to continue to work on without delay.</en>
      <fr>L'importance de cette initiative a été soulignée par les chefs d'État <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1293">et</DiscourseConnective> de gouvernement lors du Conseil européen, <Alignment alignment="339" annotation_id="1338">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1338" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela constitue un volet majeur de la réponse européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1397">à</DiscourseConnective> la crise économique sur lequel nous devons rapidement poursuivre nos travaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1360" docOffset="8">
      <en>Your vote will ensure that the results of the consultation are realised in full <Alignment alignment="1553" annotation_id="1440">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1440" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in accordance with the procedure laid down by the treaty, I can <Alignment alignment="1614" annotation_id="1509">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1509" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> confirm that the Council accepts the maximum rate of increase resulting from your second reading.</en>
      <fr>Votre vote assure la pleine concrétisation des résultats de la concertation <Alignment alignment="1440" annotation_id="1553">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1553" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1557">en</DiscourseConnective> accord avec la procédure fixée par le Traité, je peux <Alignment alignment="1509" annotation_id="1614">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1614" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> confirmer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1629">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil accepte le taux maximum d'augmentation qui résulte de votre seconde lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1617" id="076" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1617" docOffset="9">
      <en>Thank you for your statement, Mr Woerth.</en>
      <fr>Merci de votre déclaration, Monsieur Woerth.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1658" docOffset="10">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1766" annotation_id="1658">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1658" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commission does not wish to comment, I note that the budgetary procedure went ahead in accordance with the Treaty and the Interinstitutional Agreement of 17 May 2006, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1832" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that, pursuant to Article 13 of that Agreement, the Council and Parliament have established that they agree on the maximum rate of increase for non-compulsory expenditure resulting from Parliament's second reading.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="642" annotation_id="1766">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1766" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission ne souhaite pas formuler de commentaire, je constate <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1841">que</DiscourseConnective> la procédure budgétaire s'est achevée conformément aux dispositions du Traité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1923">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'accord interinstitutionnel du 17 mai 2006. Je constate en outre que, selon le point 13 dudit accord interinstitutionnel, le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2063">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement conviennent d'accepter le taux maximal d'augmentation des dépenses non obligatoires qui procèderont de la deuxième lecture du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>

<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2052" docOffset="12">
      <en>The budgetary procedure can <Alignment alignment="2344" annotation_id="2080">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2080" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be deemed closed <Alignment alignment="2371" annotation_id="2102">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2102" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the budget is declared definitively adopted.</en>
      <fr>La procédure budgétaire peut <Alignment alignment="2080" annotation_id="2344">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2344" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être déclarée achevée <Alignment alignment="158" annotation_id="2371">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2371" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le budget définitivement adopté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2151" docOffset="13">
      <en>We shall now sign the various statements, <Alignment alignment="2467" annotation_id="2193">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2193" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in a minute we must vote on a further resolution.</en>
      <fr>Nous allons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2419">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> signer les différentes déclarations, <Alignment alignment="2193" annotation_id="2467">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2467" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons voter sur une autre résolution dans un instant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2247" docOffset="14">
      <en>(The President invited Mr Woerth, Commissioner Grybauskaitė, Mr Böge (Chairman of the Committee on Budgets) and rapporteurs Mrs Haug and Mr Lewandowski to join him)</en>
      <fr>(Le président invite M. Woerth, la commissaire Grybauskaitė, M. Böge (président de la commission des budgets) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2642">et</DiscourseConnective> les rapporteurs Mme Haug <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2670">et</DiscourseConnective> M. Lewandowski <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2688">à</DiscourseConnective> se joindre à lui)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2412" docOffset="15">
      <en>(The budget was signed)</en>
      <fr>(Le budget est signé)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2436" docOffset="16">
      <en>I have just learned that it is Mr Böge's birthday today, and wish to offer him my sincere congratulations.</en>
      <fr>Je viens d'apprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2751">que</DiscourseConnective> M. Böge fête aujourd'hui son anniversaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2797">et</DiscourseConnective> je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2809">à</DiscourseConnective> lui présenter mes sincères félicitations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
