<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Development impact of Economic Partnership Agreements (EPAs) (short presentation)</en>
    <fr>L'impact des accords de partenariat économique (APE) sur le développement (brève présentation)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="82" id="176" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="82" docOffset="1">
      <en>- The next item is a short presentation of the report by Mr Schröder, on behalf of the Committee on Development, on the development impact of Economic Partnership Agreements (EPAs).</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle une brève présentation du rapport de Jürgen Schröder, au nom de la commission du développement, sur l'impact des accords de partenariat économique (APE) sur le développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="264" id="177" language="DE" name="Jürgen Schröder">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="264" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, we are talking about the impact of economic partnership agreements on development.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="368">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, nous discutons aujourd'hui de l'impact des accords de partenariat économique sur le développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="397" docOffset="3">
      <en>'Economic partnership agreements' really is quite a mouthful, particularly in German.</en>
      <fr>L'expression même d'"accord de partenariat économique" est difficilement prononçable, et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="570">plus particulièrement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="592">en</DiscourseConnective> allemand.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="483" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is a horrible phrase, <Alignment alignment="643" annotation_id="508">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="508" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> no doubt very few people in Germany will concern themselves with this topic, despite the fact that it will be one of the most important topics in coming years.</en>
      <fr>Ce terme est tout simplement affreux. <Alignment alignment="508" annotation_id="643">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="643" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis persuadé que peu de gens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="679">en</DiscourseConnective> Allemagne s'intéresseront au sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="717">alors qu'</DiscourseConnective>il s'agira à n'en pas douter d'une des plus importantes questions dans les années à venir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="672" docOffset="5">
      <en>What is it all about?</en>
      <fr>Alors, de quoi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="832">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit-il?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="694" docOffset="6">
      <en>The Cotonou Agreement states that economic partnership agreements should be concluded between the European Union and the ACP (African, Caribbean Pacific) States by the end of 2007.</en>
      <fr>L'accord de Cotonou précise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="871">que</DiscourseConnective> les accords de partenariat économique doivent être conclus entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="959">et</DiscourseConnective> les États ACP (Afrique, Caraïbes, Pacifique) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1007">avant</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'année 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="875" docOffset="7">
      <en>The background to this was that developing countries that were not, and are not, in the ACP Group of States complained to the World Trade Organization (WTO) that the European Union was according the ACP States special privileges.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1037">En</DiscourseConnective> toile de fond : la plainte déposée par les pays ne faisant pas partie du groupe des États ACP devant l'Organisation mondiale du commerce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1177">au motif que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union offrait des privilèges spéciaux aux pays ACP.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1105" docOffset="8">
      <en>We have now managed to set up, at least in part of the Caribbean, an economic partnership agreement of this type, which we hope will be a success.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes parvenus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1265">à</DiscourseConnective> établir un accord de ce type, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1297">à</DiscourseConnective> tout le moins dans une partie des Caraïbes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1343">et</DiscourseConnective> nous espérons qu'il portera ses fruits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1252" docOffset="9">
      <en>My report states that this agreement will form a new basis for development cooperation: we are helping them to help themselves.</en>
      <fr>Mon rapport précise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1406">que</DiscourseConnective> cet accord servira de nouvelle base <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1446">pour</DiscourseConnective> la coopération au développement: aider les gens à s'aider eux-mêmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1380" docOffset="10">
      <en>We are trying to link together trade and development, by which I mean trade policy and development policy.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous efforçons d'établir un lien entre commerce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1573">et</DiscourseConnective> développement ou, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1594">si</DiscourseConnective> vous préférez, entre politique commerciale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1640">et</DiscourseConnective> politique de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1487" docOffset="11">
      <en>There has, of course, been a certain amount of friction, in particular here in Parliament between our committee, the Committee on Regional Development, and the Committee on International Trade, relating primarily to the compatibility of this agreement with the rules of the WTO and especially the issue of parliamentary scrutiny.</en>
      <fr>Bien entendu, nous avons enregistré certaines tensions, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1727">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> ici, au Parlement, entre notre commission, la commission du développement régional <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1825">et</DiscourseConnective> la commission du commerce international, principalement dans le cadre de la compatibilité de l'accord avec les règles édictées par l'OMC <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1965">et</DiscourseConnective>, plus spécifiquement, de la question du contrôle parlementaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1817" docOffset="12">
      <en>My report originally included two paragraphs - numbers 5 and 17 - relating to parliamentary scrutiny.</en>
      <fr>Mon rapport comprenait à l'origine deux paragraphes - les numéros 5 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2100">et</DiscourseConnective> 17 - consacrés au contrôle parlementaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1919" docOffset="13">
      <en>At the request and on the advice of the chairman of the Committee on International Trade, I deleted both of those paragraphs completely and submitted an alternative draft report with these paragraphs deleted, on which we will be voting on Thursday.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2145">À</DiscourseConnective> la demande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2158">et</DiscourseConnective> sur les conseils du président de la commission du commerce international, j'ai choisi de supprimer ces deux paragraphes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2281">et</DiscourseConnective> de soumettre une proposition de rapport alternative qui sera mise aux voix ce jeudi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2168" docOffset="14">
      <en>Apart from the two deletions, my draft report is identical to the first draft.</en>
      <fr>Si l'on excepte les deux paragraphes supprimés, le rapport est identique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2442">à</DiscourseConnective> la première version proposée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2247" docOffset="15">
      <en>It sets out both the opportunities and the risks of the economic partnership agreements, <Alignment alignment="2570" annotation_id="2336">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2336" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it particularly emphasises the potential positive effects of these agreements on the people in those countries.</en>
      <fr>Il brosse un tableau des opportunités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2512">et</DiscourseConnective> des risques liés aux accords de partenariat économique <Alignment alignment="2336" annotation_id="2570">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2570" sense="Comparison.Contrast">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> insiste plus spécifiquement sur les effets positifs potentiels de ces accords sur les populations des pays concernés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2452" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2691" annotation_id="2452">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2452" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I finish, Mr President, I would just like to say one more thing: some of our fellow Members have repeatedly claimed that people in the ACP States had too little time to conclude these agreements.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2452" annotation_id="2691">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2691" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> conclure, Monsieur le Président, je souhaiterais ajouter une dernière chose. Certains de mes collègues ont à plusieurs reprises affirmé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2836">que</DiscourseConnective> les responsables des pays ACP ne disposaient pas de suffisamment de temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2914">pour</DiscourseConnective> négocier et conclure ces accords.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2655" docOffset="17">
      <en>That is not true: they had from 2000 to 2007; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2701" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> they had another year until 2008; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2740" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> we still have time.</en>
      <fr>C'est totalement faux: ils ont eu sept ans pour le faire, entre 2000 et 2007, et une année supplémentaire jusqu'en 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2764" docOffset="18">
      <en>We are not, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2776" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>, saying to people in these countries that they can do it whenever they like: time is running out.</en>
      <fr>Et il nous reste encore suffisamment de temps. Loin de nous l'idée d'affirmer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3152">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils peuvent le faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3176">lorsque</DiscourseConnective> bon leur semble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2882" docOffset="19">
      <en>It is in the interests of the people in the ACP States, <Alignment alignment="2391" annotation_id="2938">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2938" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I <Alignment alignment="7361" annotation_id="2944">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2944" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> call on all Members of this House to vote in favour of my report on Thursday, including those who originally intended to vote against it.</en>
      <fr>Non, le temps presse. Il en va de l'intérêt des populations des pays ACP <Alignment alignment="2938" annotation_id="3274">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3274" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="3494" annotation_id="3277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3277" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'invite mes collègues, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3316">même</DiscourseConnective> ceux qui avaient l'intention de s'y opposer, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3366">à</DiscourseConnective> voter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3374">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur de mon rapport ce jeudi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3092" docOffset="20">
      <en>This is not an argument between the left and the right; it is about helping people in the ACP States to become more self-confident and, in the foreseeable future, to become equal partners in international trade.</en>
      <fr>Il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3415">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit pas d'un affrontement entre gauche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3457">et</DiscourseConnective> droite. Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3471">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'aider les populations des États ACP <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3516">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre confiance en leurs capacités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3555">et</DiscourseConnective>, dans un avenir prévisible, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3586">à</DiscourseConnective> lutter à armes égales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3610">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de commerce international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3304" id="178" name="Viviane Reding">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3304" docOffset="21">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the Commission welcomes the report by Mr Schroeder, which represents a balanced overview of the diversity of opinions surrounding the development impact of the Economic Partnership Agreements (EPAs).</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la Commission salue le rapport de M. Schroeder, qui représente une vue d'ensemble équilibrée de la diversité des avis concernant l'impact des accords de partenariat économique (APE) sur le développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3546" docOffset="22">
      <en>The dossier continues to evolve.</en>
      <fr>Le dossier ne cesse d'évoluer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3579" docOffset="23">
      <en>We have signed a full Economic Partnership Agreement with the Caribbean region, whilst we have negotiated interim agreements with countries and regions in Africa and the Pacific.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons signé un accord de partenariat économique complet avec les Caraïbes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4018">de même que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons négocié des accords provisoires avec divers pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4090">et</DiscourseConnective> régions d'Afrique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4111">et</DiscourseConnective> du Pacifique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3758" docOffset="24">
      <en>These interim EPAs provide for a trade regime compatible with WTO rules and preserve important trade preferences for these countries.</en>
      <fr>Ces APE provisoires prévoient la mise en place d'un régime commercial compatible avec les règles de l'OMS tout en maintenant certaines préférences commerciales importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4300">pour</DiscourseConnective> ces pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3892" docOffset="25">
      <en>The interim agreements are only transitory in nature, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3946" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> they will be replaced by full regional EPAs.</en>
      <fr>Les accords provisoires sont uniquement transitoires et seront remplacés par des APE régionaux complets.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3994" docOffset="26">
      <en>The pace of these negotiations will be set by the regions concerned to ensure those objectives and coverage match their own integration processes, capacity, needs and political priorities.</en>
      <fr>Le rythme de ces négociations sera déterminé par les régions concernées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4492">afin de</DiscourseConnective> s'assurer que les objectifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4528">et</DiscourseConnective> la portée correspondent à leurs processus d'intégration, leur capacité, leurs besoins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4617">et</DiscourseConnective> leurs priorités politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4183" docOffset="27">
      <en>In parallel, the programming of the 10th European Development Fund has moved on.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4648">Parallèlement</DiscourseConnective>, la programmation du 10e Fonds européen de développement a progressé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4264" docOffset="28">
      <en>Most of the regional and national programmes are signed.</en>
      <fr>La plupart des programmes régionaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4768">et</DiscourseConnective> nationaux sont signés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4321" docOffset="29">
      <en>In anticipation of the EPAs, these programmes include considerable support to help our African, Caribbean and Pacific (ACP) partners make the most of the agreements: direct support for the implementation of the agreements and indirect support to build up infrastructure and productive capacity.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4794">En</DiscourseConnective> prévision des APE, ces programmes prévoient un soutien considérable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4865">pour</DiscourseConnective> aider nos partenaires d'Afrique, des Caraïbes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4916">et</DiscourseConnective> du Pacifique (ACP) à tirer un maximum de profits de ces accords: soutien direct <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4999">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en œuvre des accords <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5030">et</DiscourseConnective> soutien indirect <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5050">afin de</DiscourseConnective> développer les infrastructures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5089">et</DiscourseConnective> la capacité de production.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4616" docOffset="30">
      <en>The Commission recognises the essential role of development finance.</en>
      <fr>La Commission reconnaît le rôle essentiel des fonds de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4685" docOffset="31">
      <en>At the same time we welcome the fact that the report acknowledges that the development objectives and outcomes of the agreements are a much wider issue than just financial support.</en>
      <fr>Nous saluons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5202">également</DiscourseConnective> le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5220">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapport reconnaisse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5247">que</DiscourseConnective> les objectifs de développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5282">et</DiscourseConnective> les résultats des accords ne se limitent pas à un simple soutien financier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4866" docOffset="32">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="5380" annotation_id="4869">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4869" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> recognise the essential role of reform in the ACP regions in reaching the development objectives, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4972" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> set out in paragraph 14 of the report.</en>
      <fr>Nous reconnaissons <Alignment alignment="4869" annotation_id="5380">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5380" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le rôle essentiel des réformes dans les régions ACP <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5442">en vue d'</DiscourseConnective>atteindre les objectifs de développement, telles que définies au paragraphe 14 du rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5014" docOffset="33">
      <en>This includes fiscal reform and changes to revenue systems.</en>
      <fr>Celles-ci incluent une réforme fiscale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5581">et</DiscourseConnective> des modifications des systèmes de revenu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5074" docOffset="34">
      <en>The reforms offset shifts in the tax base due to liberalisation and are in themselves valuable steps to ensuring sustainable public financing in the ACP.</en>
      <fr>Les réformes visent à pallier les changements de la base fiscale dus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5695">à</DiscourseConnective> la libéralisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5715">et</DiscourseConnective> constituent de précieuses étapes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5751">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> garantir un financement public durable dans les ACP.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5228" docOffset="35">
      <en>Another essential objective is to support regional economic integration in the ACP.</en>
      <fr>Le soutien de l'intégration économique régionale dans les ACP est un autre objectif essentiel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5312" docOffset="36">
      <en>The interim agreements do not yet include all ACP countries.</en>
      <fr>Les accords provisoires n'incluent pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5948">encore</DiscourseConnective> tous les pays ACP.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5373" docOffset="37">
      <en>This is exactly why these agreements are only temporary pending full agreement. The full agreements will be flexible and comprehensive.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5980">précisément</DiscourseConnective> la raison pour laquelle ces accords ne sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6036">que</DiscourseConnective> provisoires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6053">en attendant</DiscourseConnective> des accords complets, qui seront flexibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6109">et</DiscourseConnective> détaillés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5509" docOffset="38">
      <en>Building up supply-side capacity to trade and engage in goods and service sectors underpins the economic value of a trade agreement.</en>
      <fr>Le renforcement de la capacité commerciale du côté de l'offre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6185">et</DiscourseConnective> l'engagement dans les secteurs des biens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6229">et</DiscourseConnective> services sont à la base de tout accord commercial.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5642" docOffset="39">
      <en>The Commission's view is that protectionism is never a valid policy option.</en>
      <fr>La Commission estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6304">que</DiscourseConnective> le protectionnisme n'est jamais une option politique valable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5718" docOffset="40">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6389" annotation_id="5718">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5718" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we do acknowledge that protection - the legitimate use of measures to protect sensitive sectors and emerging industry - is a valid and essential policy tool.</en>
      <fr>Nous reconnaissons <Alignment alignment="5718" annotation_id="6389">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6389" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6399">que</DiscourseConnective> la protection - l'utilisation légitime de mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6453">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger des secteurs sensibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6490">et</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie émergente - est un outil politique valable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6548">et</DiscourseConnective> essentiel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5885" docOffset="41">
      <en>This is why the EPAs contain all sorts of flexibilities, and <Alignment alignment="9191" annotation_id="5946">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5946" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> exclusions and asymmetrical commitments for the ACP side, <Alignment alignment="17795" annotation_id="6018">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6018" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> called for in the report.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle les APE contiennent toutes sortes de mécanismes de flexibilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6655">et</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="5946" annotation_id="6659">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6659" sense="Expansion.Restatement">notamment</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, des exclusions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6685">et</DiscourseConnective> des engagements asymétriques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6717">pour</DiscourseConnective> les ACP, <Alignment alignment="561" annotation_id="6731">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6731" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que demandé dans le rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6047" docOffset="42">
      <en>On the EU side, our markets are completely open for ACP products, with increased cooperation to meet technical and health standards and facilitate trade.</en>
      <fr>Du côté européen, nos marchés sont totalement ouverts aux produits ACP, avec une coopération renforcée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6869">afin de</DiscourseConnective> respecter des normes techniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6909">et</DiscourseConnective> sanitaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6923">et</DiscourseConnective> faciliter le commerce.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6201" docOffset="43">
      <en>ACP countries will only open their markets gradually, with the possibility to maintain exceptions.</en>
      <fr>Les pays ACP n'ouvriront leurs marchés que progressivement, avec la possibilité de maintenir des exceptions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6300" docOffset="44">
      <en>The Commission does not see our commitment to the EPA process ending on signature.</en>
      <fr>La Commission ne voit pas notre engagement vis-à-vis du processus des APE se terminer avec leur signature.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6383" docOffset="45">
      <en>This is the start of a process of enhanced dialogue, careful implementation, monitoring, and evaluation of the effect, especially <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6513" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> regards the development impact.</en>
      <fr>Celle-ci marque au contraire le début d'un processus de dialogue renforcé, de mise en œuvre soigneuse, de surveillance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7284">et</DiscourseConnective> d'évaluation des effets, et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7315">plus particulièrement</DiscourseConnective> de l'impact sur le développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6548" docOffset="46">
      <en>All of this will use the institutions established to implement the agreement to ensure transparency and the participation of parliamentarians and civil society.</en>
      <fr>Tout ceci exigera des institutions créées en vue de mettre en œuvre l'accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7448">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles garantissent la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7486">et</DiscourseConnective> la participation des députés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7518">et</DiscourseConnective> de la société civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6709" docOffset="47">
      <en>The Commission <Alignment alignment="7563" annotation_id="6724">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6724" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcomes the report by Mr Schröder and will provide a detailed reaction to the points raised in due course.</en>
      <fr>La Commission salue <Alignment alignment="6724" annotation_id="7563">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7563" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le rapport de M. Schröder <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7598">et</DiscourseConnective> communiquera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7614">en</DiscourseConnective> temps voulu des réactions détaillées sur les points soulevés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6842" id="179" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6842" docOffset="48">
      <en>- The item is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le point est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6864" docOffset="49">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6899" docOffset="50">
      <en>Written statements (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclarations écrites (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6929" id="180" name="Kader Arif ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6929" docOffset="51">
      <en>in writing. - (FR) On Thursday Parliament will give its verdict on Mr Schröder's report on Economic Partnership Agreements (EPAs).</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - Le Parlement se prononcera jeudi sur le rapport de M. Schröder sur les Accords de partenariat économique (APE).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7060" docOffset="52">
      <en>I would be extremely disappointed <Alignment alignment="7911" annotation_id="7094">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7094" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our institution's first vote on this both very technical and highly political subject (<Alignment alignment="8020" annotation_id="7184">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7184" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the whole future of our relations with the ACP States is at stake) were to result in the adoption of Mr Schröder's report.</en>
      <fr>Je serais extrêmement déçu <Alignment alignment="2163" annotation_id="7911">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7911" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la première expression de notre institution sur ce sujet à la fois très technique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7996">et</DiscourseConnective> hautement politique (<Alignment alignment="7184" annotation_id="8020">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8020" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tout l'avenir de nos relations avec les pays ACP est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8081">en</DiscourseConnective> jeu) devait se solder par l'adoption du rapport de M. Schröder.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7313" docOffset="53">
      <en>The Socialist Group in the European Parliament will not vote in favour of this text, <Alignment alignment="11509" annotation_id="7398">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7398" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it in no way reflects the concerns both of Europeans and of our ACP partners about the EPAs and the way in which they are negotiated.</en>
      <fr>Le PSE ne votera pas ce texte, <Alignment alignment="7398" annotation_id="8179">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8179" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il ne reflète <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8197">en</DiscourseConnective> rien les préoccupations tant européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8241">que</DiscourseConnective> de nos partenaires ACP sur les APE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8280">et</DiscourseConnective> sur la manière dont ils sont négociés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7538" docOffset="54">
      <en>In contrast to the rapporteur's position, the PSE Group has tabled and will vote in favour of a motion for a resolution which puts development back at the heart of the EPAs' priorities, which rejects the liberalisation of public services and any negotiation on the Singapore issues or on services against the ACP States' wishes, which promotes regional integration, which calls for huge financial support to bring the ACP States' economies up to standard, <Alignment alignment="8749" annotation_id="7994">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7994" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which takes account of the specific characteristics and fragilities of these countries, be they least developed countries or <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8123" sense="Expansion.Alternative">otherwise</DiscourseConnective>.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8322">À l'inverse</DiscourseConnective> de la position du rapporteur, le PSE a déposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8380">et</DiscourseConnective> votera une résolution qui replace le développement au cœur des priorités des APE, qui refuse la libéralisation des services publics <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8515">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que toute négociation sur les sujets de Singapour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8571">ou</DiscourseConnective> sur les services contre la volonté des pays ACP, qui favorise l'intégration régionale, qui demande un soutien financier massif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8701">pour</DiscourseConnective> mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8713">à</DiscourseConnective> niveau les économies des pays ACP <Alignment alignment="1540" annotation_id="8749">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8749" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui prenne en compte les spécificités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8790">et</DiscourseConnective> fragilités de ces pays, qu'ils soient PMA ou pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8134" docOffset="55">
      <en>These are the conditions that would make the EPAs acceptable agreements.</en>
      <fr>Voilà les conditions qui feraient des APE des accords acceptables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8207" docOffset="56">
      <en>Unfortunately we are still a long way away from them.</en>
      <fr>On en est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8920">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8936">encore</DiscourseConnective> très loin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
