<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Order of business: see Minutes</en>
    <fr>Ordre des travaux: voir procès-verbal</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="31" id="081" name="Richard Howitt">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="31" docOffset="1">
      <en>Mr President, on a point of order, can I ask for an urgent action by the President of Parliament to call for the protection of a delegation from Colombia which visited our Parliament on 27 and 28 June, <Alignment alignment="273" annotation_id="233">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="233" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whose members this week received a public death threat <Alignment alignment="276351" annotation_id="292">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="292" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they had spoken out here in favour of the proposal for a humanitarian exchange of prisoners in the Colombian conflict?</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, sur une question préalable, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="89">puis</DiscourseConnective>-je demander une action urgente de la part du Président du Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="162">pour</DiscourseConnective> exiger la protection d'une délégation de Colombie qui a rendu visite à notre Parlement les 27 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="261">et</DiscourseConnective> 28 juin, <Alignment alignment="233" annotation_id="273">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="273" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dont les membres ont reçu cette semaine une menace de mort en direct <Alignment alignment="292" annotation_id="345">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="345" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils avaient indiqué qu'ils étaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="389">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur d'une proposition relative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="426">à</DiscourseConnective> un échange humanitaire de prisonniers dans le conflit de la Colombie?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="419" docOffset="2">
      <en>The accusation that the delegation's members, including Yolanda Pulecio de Betancourt, mother of the French former Colombian presidential candidate, Monsignor Luis Augusto Castro, the head of the Catholic Church in Colombia, and Dr Jose Noe Rios, the general secretary of the Colombian Liberal Party, are all supporters of the country's guerrilla movement, is both preposterous and puts the group in grave danger.</en>
      <fr>L'accusation selon laquelle les membres de la délégation, y compris Yolanda Pulecio de Betancourt, la mère de l'ancienne candidate française à la présidence colombienne, Monsignor Luis Augusto Castro, le responsable de l'église catholique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="737">en</DiscourseConnective> Colombie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="749">et</DiscourseConnective> Dr José Noe Rios, le secrétaire général du parti libéral colombien, sont tous des partisans de la guérilla du pays est à la fois absurde <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="889">et</DiscourseConnective> met le groupe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="906">en</DiscourseConnective> grave danger.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="833" docOffset="3">
      <en>On humanitarian grounds alone, I ask the President to do everything possible to make representations for their safety.</en>
      <fr>D'un point de vue purement humanitaire, je demande au Président de tout mettre en œuvre pour assurer leur sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="952" docOffset="4">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
