<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Welcome</en>
    <fr>Souhaits de bienvenue</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, today and yesterday, the EuroMedScola completed its programme here in Strasbourg.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, hier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="50">et</DiscourseConnective> aujourd'hui, l'EuroMedScola a achevé son programme ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="108">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="112" docOffset="2">
      <en>It was a great pleasure for us to welcome more than 250 young people aged between 16 and 18 from all over the Euro-Mediterranean area, <Alignment alignment="261" annotation_id="247">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="247" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Mediterranean Union, including the 27 EU Member States and our partner countries in the region, making a total of 37 countries.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons eu le très grand plaisir d'accueillir plus de 250 jeunes gens âgés de 16 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="206">à</DiscourseConnective> 18 ans venant de toute la zone euro-méditerranéenne, <Alignment alignment="392" annotation_id="261">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="261" sense="Expansion.Restatement">autrement dit</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de l'Union méditerranéenne, y compris des 27 États membres de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="342">et</DiscourseConnective> de nos pays partenaires dans la région, représentant ainsi un <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="407">total</DiscourseConnective> de 37 pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="394" docOffset="3">
      <en>The participants have now taken their seats up in the gallery.</en>
      <fr>Les participants ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="446">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> rejoint leurs places dans la galerie des visiteurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="457" docOffset="4">
      <en>Over the last two days, they have discussed a wide range of topics, including the environment, immigration, equality, the role of citizens, education and many other issues.</en>
      <fr>Pendant ces deux derniers jours, ils ont discuté d'une vaste série de sujets, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="587">notamment</DiscourseConnective> de l'environnement, de l'immigration, de l'égalité, du rôle des citoyens, de l'éducation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="686">et</DiscourseConnective> de nombreuses autres questions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="630" docOffset="5">
      <en>This is an expression of the cooperation between the European Union and the countries on the southern shore of the Mediterranean.</en>
      <fr>C'est une expression de la coopération entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="785">et</DiscourseConnective> les pays de la rive méridionale de la Méditerranée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="760" docOffset="6">
      <en>School pupils from Israel, Palestine, the Arab states and every country of the European Union have <Alignment alignment="799" annotation_id="859">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="859" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> been here, <Alignment alignment="958" annotation_id="875">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="875" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would very much like to welcome our young friends to the gallery.</en>
      <fr>Des élèves d'Israël, de Palestine, des États arabes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="892">et</DiscourseConnective> de tous les pays de l'Union européenne sont <Alignment alignment="1031" annotation_id="939">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="939" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> présents <Alignment alignment="29" annotation_id="958">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="958" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est avec un immense plaisir que j'accueille nos jeunes amis dans la galerie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="947" docOffset="7">
      <en>It has been a fantastic event, <Alignment alignment="1077" annotation_id="978">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="978" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am delighted to have had the opportunity to meet you.</en>
      <fr>Cette manifestation a été magnifique <Alignment alignment="599" annotation_id="1077">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1077" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis ravi d'avoir ainsi eu l'occasion de vous rencontrer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1038" docOffset="8">
      <en>Once again, a very warm welcome to the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1150">encore</DiscourseConnective>, nous vous souhaitons chaleureusement la bienvenue au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
