<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>15.</en>
    <fr>15.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Energy Star (vote)</en>
    <fr>Étiquetage relatif à l'efficacité énergétique des équipements de bureau (refonte) (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23" docOffset="2">
    <en>Report: Nikolaos Vakalis</en>
    <fr>- Rapport Nikolaos Vakalis</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="48" docOffset="3">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="122">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="67" id="131" name="Nikolaos Vakalis ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="67" docOffset="4">
      <en>rapporteur. - (EL) Mr President, I would like to emphasise that a positive vote by the European Parliament today will be a huge leap forward and will break a taboo that has prevailed in Europe for decades.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je voudrais souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="182">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un vote positif du Parlement européen aujourd'hui constituerait un grand pas en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="265">avant</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="271">et</DiscourseConnective> briserait un tabou qui a régné <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="305">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe pendant des décennies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="273" docOffset="5">
      <en>For the first time, public money will have to be used, through public procurement, to increase energy efficiency, which is quite rightly considered to be a basic pillar of sustainable energy policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="338">Pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois, les deniers publics devront être utilisés, par le biais des marchés publics, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="438">pour</DiscourseConnective> augmenter l'efficacité énergétique, qui est très justement considérée comme un pilier fondamental d'une politique de l'énergie durable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="472" docOffset="6">
      <en>I trust that this will mark the start of taxpayers' money being used for high-priority issues.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="588">que</DiscourseConnective> cela marquera le début d'une période où l'argent des contribuables sera utilisé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="672">à</DiscourseConnective> des questions prioritaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="567" docOffset="7">
      <en>Finally, I should like to thank Commissioner Piebalgs and the German Presidency for making approval of the regulation at first reading possible.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="702">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais remercier le commissaire Piebalgs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="755">et</DiscourseConnective> la présidence allemande qui ont rendu possible l'adoption du règlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="829">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
