<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Community civil protection mechanism (debate)</en>
    <fr>Mécanisme communautaire de protection civile (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="46" id="181" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="46" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Mr Papadimoulis, on behalf of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, on the proposal for a Council decision establishing a Community civil protection mechanism (recast) C6-0076/2006.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur le rapport de M. Papadimoulis, au nom de la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="186">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire, sur la proposition de décision du Conseil instituant un mécanisme communautaire de protection civile (refonte) - C6-0076/2006 -.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="286" id="182" name="Stavros Dimas">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="286" docOffset="2">
      <en>Μember of the Commission. (EL) Mr President, first I wish to thank the European Parliament and, in particular, the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety and the rapporteur, Mr Papadimoulis, on drafting an exceptional report.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="381">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> remercier le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="426">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="430">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>, la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="501">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="531">et</DiscourseConnective> le rapporteur M. Papadimoulis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="564">pour</DiscourseConnective> cet excellent rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="533" docOffset="3">
      <en>The Commission proposal to recast the 2001 Council decision establishing a Community civil protection mechanism takes account of the demand by both the European Parliament and the Council for resources and facilities to be strengthened in the field of civil protection in Europe.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de la Commission de refondre la décision de 2001 du Conseil instituant un mécanisme communautaire de protection civile tient compte de la demande, tant du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="781">que</DiscourseConnective> du Conseil, de renforcer les ressources <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="825">et</DiscourseConnective> les installations dans le domaine de la protection civile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="886">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="813" docOffset="4">
      <en>Its objective is to strengthen the mechanism with the experience acquired from previous emergency situations.</en>
      <fr>Son but est de renforcer le mécanisme avec l'expérience acquise dans les situations d'urgence précédentes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="923" docOffset="5">
      <en>It provides a basis for the further development of cooperation in the field of civil protection by improving and strengthening the existing project in this sector and by launching new activities.</en>
      <fr>Elle fournit la base <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1025">pour</DiscourseConnective> le développement de la coopération dans le domaine de la protection civile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1105">en</DiscourseConnective> améliorant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1119">et</DiscourseConnective> en renforçant le projet existant dans le secteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1171">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1174">en</DiscourseConnective> lançant de nouvelles activités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1119" docOffset="6">
      <en>We must highlight two innovations which we are proposing: funding for the cost of hiring equipment and of hiring transport means.</en>
      <fr>Il convient de souligner deux innovations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1251">que</DiscourseConnective> nous proposons: le financement de la location de l'équipement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1317">et</DiscourseConnective> de la location des moyens de transport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1249" docOffset="7">
      <en>We often face situations in which aid is available <Alignment alignment="1406" annotation_id="1300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1300" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are no suitable means for taking it to the scene of the disaster.</en>
      <fr>Il arrive souvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1378">que</DiscourseConnective> l'aide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1389">soit</DiscourseConnective> disponible, <Alignment alignment="1300" annotation_id="1406">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1406" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'il n'existe pas de moyens adéquats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1449">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'acheminer sur les lieux de la catastrophe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1376" docOffset="8">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1376" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">As a result</DiscourseConnective>, this aid either arrives late or does not arrive at all.</en>
      <fr>Cette aide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1510">soit</DiscourseConnective> arrive trop tard, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1533">soit</DiscourseConnective> elle n'arrive pas du tout.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1445" docOffset="9">
      <en>In the case of emergencies which affect several European countries at once, such as, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1530" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>, forest fires in summer, floods in spring and possible simultaneous terrorist threats throughout Europe, the Member States may find it hard to provide help to other Member States, due to their own needs.</en>
      <fr>Dans les situations d'urgence qui touchent plusieurs pays européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1633">en même temps</DiscourseConnective>, telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1655">que</DiscourseConnective> les feux de forêts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1678">en</DiscourseConnective> été, les inondations au printemps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1715">et</DiscourseConnective> des menaces terroristes potentielles dans toute l'Europe, il peut être difficile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1799">pour</DiscourseConnective> les États membres d'envoyer de l'aide, et ce à cause de leurs propres besoins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1746" docOffset="10">
      <en>That is why the Commission proposed that a safety net be created at Community level, <Alignment alignment="2001" annotation_id="1831">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1831" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have the facility to hire the necessary transport means and equipment.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle la Commission a proposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1937">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un dispositif de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1966">soit</DiscourseConnective> créé au niveau communautaire, <Alignment alignment="1831" annotation_id="2001">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2001" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pouvoir mobiliser les moyens de transport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2048">et</DiscourseConnective> les équipements nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1913" docOffset="11">
      <en>The Commission, of course, knows that the European Parliament understands the importance of the benefit which will accrue from the reforms in question and expresses its thanks for the support which it has already given to the proposed new funding mechanism.</en>
      <fr>La Commission sait, bien sûr, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2110">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen comprend l'importance du bénéfice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2170">qu'</DiscourseConnective>entraîneront les réformes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2199">en</DiscourseConnective> question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2211">et</DiscourseConnective> exprime sa gratitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2235">pour</DiscourseConnective> le soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2251">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2270">déjà</DiscourseConnective> apporté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2283">à</DiscourseConnective> la proposition de nouveau mécanisme de financement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2171" docOffset="12">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2337" annotation_id="2171">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2171" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> emphasised in the Barnier report, the result of the enhanced cooperation in the field of civil protection will be better protection, both for the citizens of the European Union and for the inhabitants of third countries.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2171" annotation_id="2337">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2337" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le souligne le rapport Barnier, le renforcement de la coopération dans le domaine de la protection civile entraînera une meilleure protection, tant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2491">pour</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2531">que</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2535">pour</DiscourseConnective> les habitants des pays tiers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2395" docOffset="13">
      <en>It will ensure that the Community as a whole can offer more coordinated and more effective and more prompt aid to any country affected by a major disaster.</en>
      <fr>Il permettra à la Communauté dans son ensemble d'offrir une aide plus coordonnée, plus efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2666">et</DiscourseConnective> plus rapide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2681">à</DiscourseConnective> n'importe quel pays touché par une grande catastrophe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2551" docOffset="14">
      <en>I should remind you here that the proposal to hire transport means and equipment was part of the proposal for the new funding mechanism on which Parliament formulated its opinion earlier this year.</en>
      <fr>Je dois rappeler ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2759">que</DiscourseConnective> la proposition de louer les moyens de transport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2811">et</DiscourseConnective> l'équipement s'inscrivait dans le cadre de la proposition d'un nouveau mécanisme de financement, sur laquelle le Parlement a donné son avis au début de cette année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2749" docOffset="15">
      <en>The negotiations which followed in the Council proved to be very difficult.</en>
      <fr>Les négociations qui ont suivi au Conseil ont été très difficiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2825" docOffset="16">
      <en>That is why we are calling on all the members of the European Parliament who wish to advance this proposal to do what they can at national level to support it; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2985" sense="Expansion.Alternative">otherwise</DiscourseConnective> we shall not be able to achieve the enhanced cooperation in the field of civil protection called for by Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3046">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous demandons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3076">à</DiscourseConnective> tous les députés du Parlement européen qui souhaitent faire progresser cette proposition de faire tout ce qu'ils peuvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3199">pour</DiscourseConnective> la soutenir au niveau national; sans quoi nous ne réussirons pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3269">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la coopération dans le domaine de la protection civile comme le souhaite le Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3111" id="183" language="EL" name="Dimitrios Papadimoulis ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3111" docOffset="17">
      <en>Mr President, over recent years we have experienced a tsunami, hurricane Katrina and earthquakes in Pakistan and Indonesia with high death tolls, <Alignment alignment="3569" annotation_id="3257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3257" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in the European Union the Member States have frequently faced major floods and storms, forest fires, disasters at sea and industrial accidents.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, ces dernières années, nous avons été confrontés à un tsunami, à l'ouragan Katrina <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3473">et</DiscourseConnective> à des tremblements de terre au Pakistan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3516">et</DiscourseConnective> en Indonésie qui ont fait de nombreuses victimes, <Alignment alignment="3257" annotation_id="3569">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3569" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans l'Union européenne, les États membres ont souvent été touchés par d'importantes inondations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3676">et</DiscourseConnective> tempêtes, des feux de forêts, des catastrophes maritimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3736">et</DiscourseConnective> des accidents industriels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3407" docOffset="18">
      <en>The repercussions of these tragic events are huge not only in terms of human lives, but also to the economy.</en>
      <fr>Les répercussions de ces événements tragiques sont considérables, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3832">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3846">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de vies humaines, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3874">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3879">également</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3889">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'économie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3516" docOffset="19">
      <en>That is why the citizens of the European Union are rightly calling for a more effective approach.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3906">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens de l'Union européenne réclament, à juste titre, une approche plus efficace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3614" docOffset="20">
      <en>Improving the European Union's ability to respond to emergency situations is a priority for the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Améliorer la capacité de réaction de l'Union européenne dans les situations d'urgence est une priorité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4113">pour</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3731" docOffset="21">
      <en>That is why we are today debating ways of improving the Community civil protection mechanism.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4141">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous débattons aujourd'hui des différentes façons d'améliorer le mécanisme communautaire de protection civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3825" docOffset="22">
      <en>During the preparation of the committee proposal we are debating, various alternative proposals were examined.</en>
      <fr>Lors de l'élaboration de la proposition de la commission parlementaire à l'examen aujourd'hui, différentes solutions ont été examinées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3936" docOffset="23">
      <en>One of them was recast, which the Commission chose <Alignment alignment="4463" annotation_id="3987">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3987" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which is the least ambitious choice, <Alignment alignment="4503" annotation_id="4028">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4028" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it introduces a limited number of improvements to the Council decision governing the civil protection mechanism.</en>
      <fr>L'une d'elles était la refonte, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4435">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission a choisie <Alignment alignment="3987" annotation_id="4463">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4463" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui est le choix le moins ambitieux, <Alignment alignment="4028" annotation_id="4503">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4503" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle permet un nombre limité d'améliorations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4552">à</DiscourseConnective> la décision du Conseil régissant le mécanisme de protection civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4149" docOffset="24">
      <en>Could the Commission <Alignment alignment="4650" annotation_id="4170">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4170" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tell me how it arrived at this choice, the least ambitious choice, despite the repeated announcements by the European Council and the resolutions by the European Parliament on greater and stronger development of the Community civil protection mechanism?</en>
      <fr>La Commission pourrait-elle <Alignment alignment="4170" annotation_id="4650">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4650" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> me dire ce qui l'a conduite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4683">à</DiscourseConnective> faire ce choix, le moins ambitieux, malgré les nombreuses annonces faites par le Conseil européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4783">et</DiscourseConnective> les résolutions du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4824">pour</DiscourseConnective> un meilleur développement, plus profond, du mécanisme communautaire de protection civile?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4434" docOffset="25">
      <en>The main weaknesses identified in the recast proposal tabled by the Commission relate, firstly, to the transportation of rescue teams and equipment.</en>
      <fr>Les principales faiblesses identifiées dans la proposition de refonte de la Commission concernent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5017">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> le transport des équipes de secours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5066">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'équipement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4583" docOffset="26">
      <en>Today every Member State bears responsibility for organising the transportation of its own civil protection aid.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, chaque État membre est responsable de l'organisation du transport de ses propres services de protection civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4696" docOffset="27">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5211" annotation_id="4696">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4696" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this shortcoming undermines the effectiveness of European aid.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4696" annotation_id="5211">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5211" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ce défaut nuit à l'efficacité de l'aide européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4768" docOffset="28">
      <en>In 2005 alone, in five emergencies, Member States were unable to send experts and equipment, <Alignment alignment="5409" annotation_id="4861">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4861" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they did not have the means to transport aid where it was needed.</en>
      <fr>Dans la seule année 2005, dans cinq situations d'urgence, les États membres ont été incapables d'envoyer des experts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5390">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'équipement <Alignment alignment="4861" annotation_id="5409">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5409" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils n'avaient pas les moyens d'acheminer l'aide là où elle était nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4935" docOffset="29">
      <en>I think that the Commission needs to do more to address this problem.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5504">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission doit agir davantage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5542">pour</DiscourseConnective> régler ce problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5005" docOffset="30">
      <en>The second weakness relates to the development of a European rapid response capability.</en>
      <fr>La seconde faiblesse se rapporte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5600">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place de la capacité de réaction rapide européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5093" docOffset="31">
      <en>Today, Community civil protection aid is provided by the Member States on a voluntary basis.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, l'aide de la protection civile communautaire est fournie par les États membres sur une base volontaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5186" docOffset="32">
      <en>This does not add up to the European rapid response capability demanded by the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Celle-ci ne s'ajoute pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5807">à</DiscourseConnective> la capacité de réaction rapide européenne réclamée par le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5286" docOffset="33">
      <en>In its communication on 25 April, the Commission proposed the creation of special standby modules which would be mobilised on request by the competent European authority.</en>
      <fr>Dans sa communication du 25 avril, la Commission a proposé la création de modules de réserve spéciaux qui seraient mobilisés sur demande de l'autorité compétente européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5457" docOffset="34">
      <en>I ask you, why did the Commission not include its own proposal in the recast?</en>
      <fr>Je vous le demande, pourquoi la Commission n'a-t-elle pas inclus sa propre proposition dans la refonte?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5535" docOffset="35">
      <en>The third problem relates to early warning.</en>
      <fr>Le troisième problème concerne l'alerte précoce.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5579" docOffset="36">
      <en>The ability of the European Commission to respond to natural disasters <Alignment alignment="6299" annotation_id="5650">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5650" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> depends upon the existence of early warning systems.</en>
      <fr>La capacité de la Commission européenne de réagir aux catastrophes naturelles dépend <Alignment alignment="5650" annotation_id="6299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6299" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de l'existence de systèmes d'alerte précoce.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5708" docOffset="37">
      <en>The recast states that the Monitoring and Information Centre in Brussels should be linked to the systems of the Member States and international organisations.</en>
      <fr>La refonte spécifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6374">que</DiscourseConnective> le centre de suivi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6397">et</DiscourseConnective> d'information de Bruxelles doit être relié aux systèmes des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6474">et</DiscourseConnective> des organisations internationales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5867" docOffset="38">
      <en>That is good, <Alignment alignment="6529" annotation_id="5881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5881" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is not enough <Alignment alignment="6557" annotation_id="5902">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5902" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, immediately after the earthquake caused by the tsunami, the governments learned, <Alignment alignment="6674" annotation_id="5992">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5992" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the citizens never learned.</en>
      <fr>C'est très bien, <Alignment alignment="5881" annotation_id="6529">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6529" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce n'est pas suffisant <Alignment alignment="5902" annotation_id="6557">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6557" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>immédiatement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6580">après</DiscourseConnective> le tremblement de terre causé par le tsunami, les gouvernements en ont eu connaissance, <Alignment alignment="5992" annotation_id="6674">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6674" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les citoyens ne l'ont jamais appris.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6024" docOffset="39">
      <en>That is why a suitable legal basis must be set up within the framework of the Council decision, <Alignment alignment="6826" annotation_id="6120">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6120" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> early warning systems can be developed within the framework of the mechanism.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6716">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> une base juridique convenable doit être mise en place dans le cadre de la décision du Conseil, <Alignment alignment="6120" annotation_id="6826">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6826" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> permettre la conception de systèmes d'alerte précoce dans le cadre du mécanisme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6206" docOffset="40">
      <en>The fourth weakness concerns the coordination of interventions in third countries.</en>
      <fr>La quatrième faiblesse concerne la coordination des interventions dans les pays tiers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6289" docOffset="41">
      <en>In this sector also more work needs to be done, <Alignment alignment="7058" annotation_id="6337">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6337" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is a blatant lack of coordination.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce secteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7015">également</DiscourseConnective> il reste du travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7045">à</DiscourseConnective> accomplir, <Alignment alignment="6337" annotation_id="7058">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7058" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il y a un manque flagrant de coordination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6386" docOffset="42">
      <en>Some Member States work constantly through the Community mechanism, some Member States prefer to work with the United Nations, some Member States work with both and some Member States with neither.</en>
      <fr>Certains États membres travaillent à chaque fois dans le cadre du mécanisme communautaire, certains États membres préfèrent travailler avec les Nations unies, certains travaillent avec les deux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7299">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres encore avec ni l'un ni l'autre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6584" docOffset="43">
      <en>This fragmentation and lack of coordination completely contradict the ambitious announcements by the European Council.</en>
      <fr>Cette fragmentation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7363">et</DiscourseConnective> ce manque de coordination contredisent complètement les annonces ambitieuses faites par le Conseil européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6703" docOffset="44">
      <en>As rapporteur, together with the shadow rapporteurs from all the political groups, we tabled amendments which were approved almost unanimously by the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7478">tant que</DiscourseConnective> rapporteur et avec les rapporteurs fictifs de tous les groupes politiques nous avons déposé des amendements qui ont été adoptés presque à l'unanimité par la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7696">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6914" docOffset="45">
      <en>In brief, they relate to information for citizens, to the integration of civil protection measures in education programmes and advertising campaigns, to land management and use, in order to strengthen prevention, to the definitions of terms based on the agreed international terminology, to the inclusion of public health and to the use of military means on an auxiliary and voluntary basis.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7727">En bref</DiscourseConnective>, ils concernent l'information aux citoyens, l'intégration des mesures de protection civile dans les programmes d'éducation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7858">et</DiscourseConnective> les campagnes de publicité, la gestion territoriale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7913">et</DiscourseConnective> l'utilisation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7931">afin de</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la prévention, de définitions des termes basées sur la terminologie internationale, l'inclusion de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8066">et</DiscourseConnective> l'utilisation de moyens militaires sur une base auxiliaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8128">et</DiscourseConnective> volontaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7306" docOffset="46">
      <en>Finally, I should like to mention the Barnier report on the creation of Europe Aid.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8155">enfin</DiscourseConnective> mentionner le rapport Barnier sur la création d'EuropeAid.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7390" docOffset="47">
      <en>In January 2006, the President of the European Commission and the President of the European Council asked Michel Barnier to examine the role of the European Union in dealing with crises.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8220">En</DiscourseConnective> janvier 2006, le président de la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8278">et</DiscourseConnective> le président du Conseil européen ont demandé à Michel Barnier d'examiner le rôle de l'Union européenne dans la gestion des crises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7577" docOffset="48">
      <en>It turned out to be a very detailed report with interesting proposals.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport est très détaillé et contient des propositions intéressantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7648" docOffset="49">
      <en>Unfortunately, <Alignment alignment="8501" annotation_id="7663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7663" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, both the Commission and the Council simply welcomed the report as an important contribution and did nothing about it.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8485">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="7663" annotation_id="8501">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8501" sense="Comparison.Contrast">pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8525">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil se sont contentés de qualifier le rapport de contribution importante, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8609">mais</DiscourseConnective> ne s'en sont pas servis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7790" docOffset="50">
      <en>I should like the Commissioner to tell me how the Commission intends to make use of the Barnier report.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais que le commissaire m'indique de quelle façon la Commission a l'intention d'utiliser le rapport Barnier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7894" docOffset="51">
      <en>The price of the lack of a unified and effective Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7950" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> it comes to crisis management is very high, which is why we need to proceed more effectively and with greater coordination.</en>
      <fr>Le coût du manque d'unité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8781">et</DiscourseConnective> d'efficacité européenne dans la gestion de crise est très élevé, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8849">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous devons agir de façon plus efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8904">et</DiscourseConnective> plus coordonnée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8079" id="184" language="EL" name="Antonios Trakatellis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8079" docOffset="52">
      <en>Mr President, the Council decision being approved, with our adopted amendments, is the product of an exhaustive preparatory procedure and of the experience acquired over recent years from dealing with natural and man-made disasters, disasters which, apart from their huge impact on every aspect of citizens' every day lives, revealed objective shortcomings in the capacity for national intervention and, hence, enhanced expectations for Community assistance.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, le fait que la décision du Conseil ait été approuvée, avec nos amendements adoptés, est le fruit des préparatifs exhaustifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9071">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'expérience acquise ces dernières années dans la gestion des catastrophes naturelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9163">et</DiscourseConnective> anthropiques, catastrophes qui, à part leur impact gigantesque sur tous les aspects de la vie quotidienne des citoyens, ont révélé des défauts objectifs de la capacité d'intervention nationale, suscitant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9370">donc</DiscourseConnective> des attentes d'amélioration de l'assistance communautaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8538" docOffset="53">
      <en>We are <Alignment alignment="9450" annotation_id="8545">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8545" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> being called upon today to strengthen and arm the Union <Alignment alignment="9499" annotation_id="8611">
          <Alignment alignment="9499" annotation_id="8611">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8611" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> it can respond to this demand by the citizens for effective intervention in the fields of the prevention of and rapid response to natural and man-made disasters.</en>
      <fr>On nous demande <Alignment alignment="8545" annotation_id="9450">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9450" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aujourd'hui de renforcer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9480">et</DiscourseConnective> d'armer l'Union <Alignment alignment="8611" annotation_id="9499">
          <Alignment alignment="8611" annotation_id="9499">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9499" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin qu'</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>elle puisse répondre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9528">à</DiscourseConnective> cette demande de la part des citoyens d'une intervention efficace dans les domaines de la prévention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9631">et</DiscourseConnective> de la réaction rapide aux catastrophes naturelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9684">et</DiscourseConnective> anthropiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8781" docOffset="54">
      <en>This is <Alignment alignment="9711" annotation_id="8789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8789" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an expression of the real solidarity sought between the Member States, which will further strengthen the feeling of participation in a community and will <Alignment alignment="9883" annotation_id="8953">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8953" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> further strengthen the European conscience.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9704">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit <Alignment alignment="8789" annotation_id="9711">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9711" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de l'expression de la véritable solidarité recherchée entre les États membres, qui renforcera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9810">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus le sentiment de participation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9852">à</DiscourseConnective> une communauté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9869">et</DiscourseConnective> renforcera <Alignment alignment="8953" annotation_id="9883">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9883" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> davantage la conscience européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9002" docOffset="55">
      <en>As far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9009" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> the amendments to the initial proposal are concerned, I consider it necessary to draw your attention to the following points:</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9928">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les amendements apportés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9972">à</DiscourseConnective> la proposition initiale, je pense qu'il est nécessaire d'attirer votre attention sur les points suivants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9138" docOffset="56">
      <en>An effective early warning and response system is founded on the following four components: identifying and assessing risks, constantly monitoring them, a warning and communication mechanism and, lastly, preparedness - the capacity to react and assist.</en>
      <fr>Un système de réaction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10103">et</DiscourseConnective> d'alerte précoce efficace se fonde sur les quatre volets suivants: identifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10184">et</DiscourseConnective> évaluer les risques, les contrôler en permanence, prévoir un mécanisme d'alerte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10267">et</DiscourseConnective> de communication <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10287">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10291">enfin</DiscourseConnective>, assurer la capacité de réaction - la capacité de réagir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10354">et</DiscourseConnective> d'aider.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9391" docOffset="57">
      <en>I too, like the rapporteur, should like to emphasise that the amendments which we tabled concern matters such as the early warning system, standby modules from the participating states, response and citizen information guidelines, best practices for dealing with situations and, lastly, mutual consular assistance for determining contact points between Member States.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10379">tout comme</DiscourseConnective> le rapporteur, souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10415">que</DiscourseConnective> les amendements déposés portent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10451">notamment</DiscourseConnective> sur le système d'alerte précoce, les modules de réserve des États participants, des lignes directrices sur la réaction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10580">et</DiscourseConnective> l'information des citoyens, des bonnes pratiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10632">pour</DiscourseConnective> gérer les situations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10658">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10662">enfin</DiscourseConnective>, l'assistance consulaire mutuelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10702">pour</DiscourseConnective> déterminer des interlocuteurs entre les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9759" docOffset="58">
      <en>I should <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9768" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> like to say - and I think that this should be accepted - that we must pay special attention to the public health sector, <Alignment alignment="10907" annotation_id="9894">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9894" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> disasters are usually accompanied by dangers to public health, either as a result of a lack of food or water or from epidemics <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10029" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="11095" annotation_id="10034">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10034" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">consequently</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this component should <Alignment alignment="11111" annotation_id="10070">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10070" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be included in the proposal.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais dire - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10781">et</DiscourseConnective> je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10793">que</DiscourseConnective> cela devrait être accepté - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10825">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons faire particulièrement attention au secteur de la santé publique, <Alignment alignment="9894" annotation_id="10907">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10907" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les catastrophes sont généralement accompagnées de dangers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10976">pour</DiscourseConnective> la santé publique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11000">soit</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11005">à</DiscourseConnective> cause d'une pénurie de nourriture <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11041">ou</DiscourseConnective> d'eau, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11051">soit</DiscourseConnective> à cause d'épidémies. Ce volet devrait, <Alignment alignment="10034" annotation_id="11095">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11095" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="10070" annotation_id="11111">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11111" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> faire partie de la proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10104" docOffset="59">
      <en>Finally, I should like to observe, <Alignment alignment="11188" annotation_id="10139">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10139" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our rapporteur said, that the Barnier report is an exceptional report, which should be taken into account because, <Alignment alignment="11307" annotation_id="10257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10257" sense="Expansion.Alternative">otherwise</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, what was the point in doing all this exceptional work?</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11165">enfin</DiscourseConnective> faire remarquer, <Alignment alignment="10139" annotation_id="11188">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11188" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'a dit le rapporteur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11217">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapport Barnier est exceptionnel et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11260">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il devrait être pris en considération, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11302">car</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="10257" annotation_id="11307">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11307" sense="Expansion.Alternative">sinon</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, pourquoi avoir fait tout ce travail remarquable?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10323" docOffset="60">
      <en>I think that, together with your report today, we shall have an effective mechanism.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11372">qu'</DiscourseConnective>avec votre rapport d'aujourd'hui, nous devrions obtenir un mécanisme efficace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10408" docOffset="61">
      <en>To close, I should like to thank our rapporteur for his excellent work.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11454">Pour conclure</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais remercier notre rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11508">pour</DiscourseConnective> son excellent travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10480" docOffset="62">
      <en>Congratulations, Mr Papadimoulis.</en>
      <fr>Félicitations, Monsieur Papadimoulis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10514" id="185" name="Edite Estrela">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10514" docOffset="63">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (PT) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to begin by congratulating Mr Papadimoulis on his report and the Commission on its initiative.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (PT) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11660">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais commencer par féliciter M. Papadimoulis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11726">pour</DiscourseConnective> son rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11743">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11760">pour</DiscourseConnective> son initiative.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10708" docOffset="64">
      <en>The EU has at its disposal various legal mechanisms for preventing, and responding to, natural disasters.</en>
      <fr>L'UE dispose de différents mécanismes juridiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11830">pour</DiscourseConnective> prévenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11844">et</DiscourseConnective> répondre aux catastrophes naturelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10814" docOffset="65">
      <en>There are indeed a number of Parliament resolutions to this effect.</en>
      <fr>Il existe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11895">en effet</DiscourseConnective> un certain nombre de résolutions du Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11950">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10882" docOffset="66">
      <en>I myself drew up a report on the European strategy for responding to natural disasters on behalf of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety in which I advocated the need for the Union to have quicker and more effective resources for responding to serious emergencies.</en>
      <fr>J'ai moi-même écrit un rapport sur la stratégie européenne de réaction aux catastrophes naturelles au nom de la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12127">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire, dans lequel je relevais la nécessité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12195">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Union de mettre en place des ressources plus efficaces <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12257">et</DiscourseConnective> plus rapides <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12273">pour</DiscourseConnective> réagir aux urgences majeures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11174" docOffset="67">
      <en>On the basis of the experience of recent years with the forest fires in southern Europe and the floods in Central Europe, the creation of detection and early warning systems to protect the citizens and their property from natural disasters, including earthquakes and tsunamis, has become a priority.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12308">À</DiscourseConnective> la suite de l'expérience de ces dernières années avec les incendies de forêts dans le sud de l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12412">et</DiscourseConnective> les inondations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12431">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe centrale, la création de systèmes de détection <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12488">et</DiscourseConnective> d'alerte précoce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12508">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger les citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12535">et</DiscourseConnective> leurs propriétés des catastrophes naturelles, y compris les tremblements de terre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12620">et</DiscourseConnective> les tsunamis, est devenue une priorité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11474" docOffset="68">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12663" annotation_id="11474">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11474" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> responsibility for managing the response to natural disasters rests primarily with the country affected, with the Union playing a supporting role, the Community civil protection mechanism set up in 2001 lacked resources and powers.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11474" annotation_id="12663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12663" sense="Comparison.Concession">Bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la responsabilité de gérer la réaction aux catastrophes naturelles incombe principalement aux pays touchés, l'Union jouant un rôle de soutien, le mécanisme communautaire de protection civile mis en place <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12876">en</DiscourseConnective> 2001 manquait de ressources <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12907">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autorité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11715" docOffset="69">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12922" annotation_id="11715">
          <Alignment alignment="12922" annotation_id="11715">
            <Alignment alignment="12922" annotation_id="11715">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11715" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, it fell short of what was needed.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11715" annotation_id="12922">
          <Alignment alignment="11715" annotation_id="12922">
            <Alignment alignment="11715" annotation_id="12922">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12922" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, il lui manquait le nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11765" docOffset="70">
      <en>This recast, improved proposal is worthy of praise.</en>
      <fr>Cette refonte, cette proposition améliorée, est louable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11817" docOffset="71">
      <en>It will lead to better coordination and quicker assistance for the people affected.</en>
      <fr>Elle permettra une meilleure coordination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13072">et</DiscourseConnective> une assistance plus rapide aux personnes touchées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11901" docOffset="72">
      <en>More needs to be done, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11924" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11933" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> the model needs to be perfected, not only on the basis of the Barnier report, but also the amendments tabled by the Committee on the Environment, of which I should like to highlight the following: cooperation in civil protection should be based on a European strategic coordination centre responsible for gathering and disseminating information on emergencies and for providing additional resources for rapid intervention to fight natural disasters; the involvement of communities in prevention and response, for which they will need training and information; and greater investment in training the assistance intervention teams.</en>
      <fr>Il reste pourtant encore beaucoup à faire et il faut perfectionner le modèle, non seulement sur base du rapport Barnier, mais également des amendements proposés par la commission de l'environnement, dont je voudrais souligner les suivants: la coopération dans le domaine de la protection civile devrait être assurée par un centre européen de coordination stratégique chargé de rassembler et de diffuser l'information sur les situations d'urgence et de fournir des moyens supplémentaires pour une intervention rapide pour lutter contre les catastrophes naturelles; la participation des communautés dans la prévention et la réaction, pour lesquelles elles auront besoin de formation et d'information; et un plus grand investissement dans la formation des équipes d'intervention professionnelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12567" id="186" name="Alfonso Andria">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12567" docOffset="73">
      <en>on behalf of the ALDE Group. - (IT) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to congratulate Mr Papadimoulis on his excellent work.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe ALDE. - (IT) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14007">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais féliciter M. Papadimoulis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14059">pour</DiscourseConnective> son excellent travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12722" docOffset="74">
      <en>His report translates in practical terms that which has already been provided for in the report on the Solidarity Fund, which represents the legal and financial basis for intervention in the field of civil protection.</en>
      <fr>Son rapport traduit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14107">en</DiscourseConnective> termes pratiques ce qui a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14136">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été prévu dans le rapport sur le Fonds de solidarité, qui représente la base juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14228">et</DiscourseConnective> financière de l'intervention dans le domaine de la protection civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12940" docOffset="75">
      <en>The European Union currently has financial means and new knowledge based on the experience of the Community Civil Protection Mechanism, created in 2001, which will enable us to improve the instrument's practicality and effectiveness.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne dispose actuellement de moyens financiers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14362">et</DiscourseConnective> de nouvelles connaissances basées sur l'expérience du mécanisme communautaire de protection civile, créé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14470">en</DiscourseConnective> 2001, qui nous permettront d'améliorer l'aspect pratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14530">et</DiscourseConnective> l'efficacité de cet instrument.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13174" docOffset="76">
      <en>It is true that the emergency response to disasters must come first and foremost from the local level, with prevention and reconstruction measures, <Alignment alignment="14712" annotation_id="13322">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13322" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is <Alignment alignment="14724" annotation_id="13332">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13332" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> true that there is a need for crisis management measures, which can and should be coordinated at European level, <Alignment alignment="14842" annotation_id="13450">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13450" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want to achieve significant economies of scale and, above all, greater efficiency.</en>
      <fr>Il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14577">que</DiscourseConnective> la réaction d'urgence aux catastrophes doit venir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14631">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout du niveau local, avec des mesures de prévention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14690">et</DiscourseConnective> de reconstruction, <Alignment alignment="13322" annotation_id="14712">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14712" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est <Alignment alignment="13332" annotation_id="14724">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14724" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14739">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut des mesures de gestion de crise, qui peuvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14795">et</DiscourseConnective> doivent être coordonnées au niveau européen <Alignment alignment="13450" annotation_id="14842">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14842" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons parvenir à d'importantes économies d'échelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14903">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14906">surtout</DiscourseConnective>, garantir une plus grande efficacité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13539" docOffset="77">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14952" annotation_id="13539">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13539" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="14962" annotation_id="13552">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13552" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the scale of a disaster overwhelms the local or even national capacity to react, it would be desirable to be able to provide rapid additional assistance from other countries, using their available skills and resources.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13539" annotation_id="14952">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14952" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="13552" annotation_id="14962">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14962" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que l'ampleur des catastrophes dépasse la capacité de réaction locale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15040">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15043">même</DiscourseConnective> nationale, il serait bon de pouvoir faire intervenir rapidement d'autres pays, en utilisant leurs compétences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15158">et</DiscourseConnective> leurs ressources disponibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13776" docOffset="78">
      <en>We should <Alignment alignment="15203" annotation_id="13786">
          <Alignment alignment="15203" annotation_id="13786">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13786" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> bear in mind that in many cases major disasters have effects that transcend borders, having an impact on the territories of neighbouring countries.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="13786" annotation_id="15203">
          <Alignment alignment="13786" annotation_id="15203">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15203" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> garder <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15218">à</DiscourseConnective> l'esprit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15229">que</DiscourseConnective> dans de nombreux cas les grandes catastrophes ont des effets qui dépassent les frontières et ont impact sur les territoires des pays voisins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13942" docOffset="79">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="15375" annotation_id="13942">
          <Alignment alignment="15375" annotation_id="13942">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13942" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, I agree with the rapporteur on the importance of proper and appropriate planning of land use and of prevention and management of disasters with a view to reducing risks.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13942" annotation_id="15375">
          <Alignment alignment="13942" annotation_id="15375">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15375" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, je suis d'accord avec le rapporteur sur l'importance d'une planification correcte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15466">et</DiscourseConnective> appropriée de l'utilisation du territoire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15511">et</DiscourseConnective> de la prévention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15531">et</DiscourseConnective> la gestion des catastrophes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15562">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> réduire les risques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14125" docOffset="80">
      <en>There is a need to strengthen the European civil protection system, in order to be able to provide coordinated responses to tackle emergencies and contribute to a European Union capable of giving its own citizens confidence and safety.</en>
      <fr>Il nous faut renforcer le système européen de protection civile, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15658">afin de</DiscourseConnective> pouvoir coordonner notre intervention en cas d'urgence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15721">et</DiscourseConnective> contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15735">à</DiscourseConnective> une Union européenne capable de donner confiance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15786">et</DiscourseConnective> sécurité à ses propres citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14361" docOffset="81">
      <en>I believe that we have to learn to live up to these legitimate expectations.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15831">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons apprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15857">à</DiscourseConnective> être à la hauteur de ces attentes légitimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14438" id="187" name="Richard Seeber">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14438" docOffset="82">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, Commissioner, we all learn from the past and from our own experiences, <Alignment alignment="16025" annotation_id="14528">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14528" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I believe that disaster prevention is one area in which we do this.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, nous tirons tous des leçons du passé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15994">et</DiscourseConnective> de nos propres expériences, <Alignment alignment="14528" annotation_id="16025">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16025" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16037">que</DiscourseConnective> la prévention des catastrophes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16072">en</DiscourseConnective> est un bon exemple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14600" docOffset="83">
      <en>The documents you have submitted <Alignment alignment="16133" annotation_id="14633">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14633" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Mr Papadimoulis' outstanding report represent an attempt by us at putting these experiences to good use.</en>
      <fr>Les documents que vous avez présentés <Alignment alignment="14633" annotation_id="16133">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16133" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le remarquable rapport de M. Papadimoulis exprime notre volonté de faire bon usage de ces expériences.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14742" docOffset="84">
      <en>Three aspects need to be considered: firstly, the preventive measures; secondly, interventions in a crisis situation, and, thirdly, how to deal with the aftermath.</en>
      <fr>Il faut tenir compte de trois aspects: les mesures préventives, les interventions dans une situation de crise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16349">et</DiscourseConnective> la gestion des conséquences.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14906" docOffset="85">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="16381" annotation_id="14906">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14906" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Union can afford a great deal in the way of preventive measures, it is an unfortunate fact that disasters strike in a variety of regions and for various reasons, <Alignment alignment="16563" annotation_id="15087">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15087" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is of the utmost importance that we, here in the European Union, should learn from one another.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14906" annotation_id="16381">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16381" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne peut se permettre beaucoup au niveau des mesures de prévention, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16467">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, les catastrophes touchent différentes régions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16530">pour</DiscourseConnective> différentes raisons, il est <Alignment alignment="15087" annotation_id="16563">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16563" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de la plus haute importance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16596">que</DiscourseConnective> nous, ici au sein de l'Union européenne, apprenions l'un <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16657">de l'autre</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15189" docOffset="86">
      <en>It is in this respect that the European Union has a particular task to perform.</en>
      <fr>Voilà <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16675">en</DiscourseConnective> quoi l'Union européenne a un rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16712">à</DiscourseConnective> jouer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15269" docOffset="87">
      <en>During interventions to deal with a crisis situation, the Union must discharge its particular role as a coordinator.</en>
      <fr>Pendant les interventions dans une situation de crise, l'Union doit remplir son rôle de coordinateur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15386" docOffset="88">
      <en>The Member States must not be discharged from their responsibilities; the prevention of disasters is and remains a national responsibility, <Alignment alignment="16966" annotation_id="15526">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15526" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is for that reason that I take an extremely critical view of the EU's current acquisition of equipment, which represents what might be termed an attempt at duplication, and certainly is not beneficial.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres ne doivent pas être privés de leur responsabilité; la prévention des catastrophes est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16927">et</DiscourseConnective> reste une responsabilité nationale, <Alignment alignment="15526" annotation_id="16966">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16966" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16975">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette raison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16993">que</DiscourseConnective> je porte un regard extrêmement critique sur l'acquisition d'équipement par l'Union européenne à l'heure actuelle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17111">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on pourrait qualifier de tentative de double emploi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17170">et</DiscourseConnective> qui n'est certainement pas profitable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15735" docOffset="89">
      <en>It is important that duplication should be avoided, <Alignment alignment="17256" annotation_id="15787">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15787" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we should concentrate on good coordination of the resources present in the Member States in order to do that.</en>
      <fr>Il est important d'éviter le double emploi, <Alignment alignment="15787" annotation_id="17256">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17256" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17260">pour ce faire</DiscourseConnective>, nous devons nous concentrer sur la bonne coordination des ressources disponibles dans les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15901" docOffset="90">
      <en>The next stage is dealing with the fallout, <Alignment alignment="17430" annotation_id="15945">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15945" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a crisis response instrument - in the shape of the Solidarity Fund - has already been put in place by the European Union in order to do this.</en>
      <fr>L'étape suivante est la gestion des conséquences, <Alignment alignment="15945" annotation_id="17430">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17430" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17454">déjà</DiscourseConnective> mis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17463">en</DiscourseConnective> place un instrument d'intervention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17501">pour</DiscourseConnective> cela - le Fonds de solidarité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16091" docOffset="91">
      <en>Here, too, we should consider how more efficient use may be made of it, possibly by changing the basic rates and concentrating on dealing only with crises that affect Europe as a whole.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17553">également</DiscourseConnective> essayer de trouver comment l'utiliser de façon plus efficace, peut-être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17635">en</DiscourseConnective> changeant les taux de base <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17665">et</DiscourseConnective> en nous concentrant uniquement sur les crises qui touchent l'Europe dans son ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16277" id="188" name="Evangelia Tzampazi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16277" docOffset="92">
      <en>(EL) Mr President, the protection of European citizens from accidents and natural disasters is directly connected to their economic and social security.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Monsieur le Président, la protection des citoyens européens contre les accidents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17841">et</DiscourseConnective> les catastrophes naturelles est directement liée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17893">à</DiscourseConnective> leur sécurité économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17920">et</DiscourseConnective> sociale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16430" docOffset="93">
      <en>Over recent years, there has been a huge increase in the number of natural disasters, resulting in an equally huge increase in requests for assistance from the civil protection mechanism on the part of the governments of the Member States.</en>
      <fr>Ces dernières années, le nombre de catastrophes naturelles a considérablement augmenté, donnant lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18033">à</DiscourseConnective> une augmentation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18052">également</DiscourseConnective> importante des demandes d'aide du mécanisme de protection civile de la part des gouvernements des États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16670" docOffset="94">
      <en>Civil protection is a complex system which consists of prevention, intervention and, lastly, restoration.</en>
      <fr>La protection civile est un système complexe qui consiste en la prévention, l'intervention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18266">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18270">finalement</DiscourseConnective>, la reconstruction.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16776" docOffset="95">
      <en>The excellent report by Mr Papadimoulis on the proposed recast does, I think, improve the Council proposal in a way which strengthens the supportive and supplementary actions by the Union <Alignment alignment="18496" annotation_id="16964">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16964" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are needed.</en>
      <fr>L'excellent rapport de M. Papadimoulis sur la proposition de refonte améliore, à mon sens, la proposition du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18418">du fait qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle renforce les actions complémentaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18471">et</DiscourseConnective> de soutien de l'Union <Alignment alignment="16964" annotation_id="18496">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18496" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles sont nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16986" docOffset="96">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18539" annotation_id="16986">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16986" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I stand by the ongoing need for instruction of the parties involved <Alignment alignment="18602" annotation_id="17063">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17063" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I consider that greater information for the public is needed, especially in areas with a high degree of risk, in order to help improve prevention and preparedness in the areas in question.</en>
      <fr>Je soutiens <Alignment alignment="16986" annotation_id="18539">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18539" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le besoin actuel de formation des parties impliquées <Alignment alignment="17063" annotation_id="18602">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18602" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18614">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une meilleure information du public est nécessaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18669">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> dans les domaines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18702">à</DiscourseConnective> haut risque, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18717">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>aider à améliorer la prévention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18756">et</DiscourseConnective> la capacité de réaction dans les domaines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18801">en</DiscourseConnective> question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17256" id="189" name="Stavros Dimas">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17256" docOffset="97">
      <en>Μember of the Commission. (EL) Mr President, I should like to thank all the speakers for their excellent comments.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je voudrais remercier tous les orateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18877">pour</DiscourseConnective> leurs excellents commentaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17371" docOffset="98">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18913" annotation_id="17371">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17371" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I touch on the matter of the amendments, I should like to reply on the question of the Barnier report and to say that the Commission has already started work on many of the issues connected with this report, the most important, of course, being the development of civil protection modules.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17371" annotation_id="18913">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18913" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> me pencher sur les amendements, je voudrais répondre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18975">à</DiscourseConnective> la question du rapport Barnier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19008">et dire que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19036">déjà</DiscourseConnective> commencé à appliquer de nombreux points liés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19086">à</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport, le plus important étant évidemment la mise en place de modules de protection civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17668" docOffset="99">
      <en>Meetings have been held with specialists from the Member States in order to ascertain what types of modules should be available in each case and the specific terms and conditions for each type of module.</en>
      <fr>Des réunions ont eu lieu avec des spécialistes des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19250">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>établir quel genre de modules sont nécessaires dans chaque cas et quelles conditions chaque type de modules doit remplir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17872" docOffset="100">
      <en>A second field of work relates to exercises <Alignment alignment="19432" annotation_id="17916">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17916" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, despite the fact that no provision is made for the creation of a European institute in accordance with the Barnier report, we do nonetheless propose that a network of centres should be developed which will extend the existing exercise programme.</en>
      <fr>Le deuxième domaine de travail est lié aux exercices <Alignment alignment="17916" annotation_id="19432">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19432" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19436">bien qu'</DiscourseConnective>aucune disposition ne prévoie la création d'un institut européen conformément au rapport Barnier, nous proposons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19557">néanmoins</DiscourseConnective> la création d'un réseau de centres, ce qui étendra le programme d'exercices existant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18167" docOffset="101">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="19668" annotation_id="18170">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18170" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> agree that the Monitoring and Information Centre should be reinforced.</en>
      <fr>Nous convenons <Alignment alignment="18170" annotation_id="19668">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19668" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19678">que</DiscourseConnective> le centre de suivi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19701">et</DiscourseConnective> d'information doit être renforcé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18246" docOffset="102">
      <en>We have already requested an increase in the number of employees, of officers, to be employed at the centre.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19749">déjà</DiscourseConnective> demandé une augmentation du personnel de ce centre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18355" docOffset="103">
      <en>We have <Alignment alignment="19817" annotation_id="18363">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18363" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> asked the Member States to give us the opportunity next year to use certain specialists at the MIC.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="18363" annotation_id="19817">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19817" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demandé aux États membres de nous donner la possibilité l'année prochaine d'utiliser certains spécialistes au centre de suivi et d'information.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18468" docOffset="104">
      <en>Finally, the Commission has two legislative proposals, one for the means of financing and one for the recast of the 2001 decision, which will give us the possibility of working in another sector, the transport sector, about which I spoke earlier.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19971">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, la Commission a deux propositions législatives, l'une <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20032">pour</DiscourseConnective> le moyen de financement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20061">et</DiscourseConnective> l'autre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20072">pour</DiscourseConnective> la refonte de la décision de 2001, qui nous donnera la possibilité de travailler dans un autre secteur, le secteur du transport, dont j'ai parlé précédemment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18715" docOffset="105">
      <en>Now, as far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18727" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> the amendments are concerned, the European Parliament has presented a series of important amendments with a view to strengthening civil protection capabilities at European level.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20236">Maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20248">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les amendements, le Parlement européen a présenté une série d'importants amendements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20352">dans le but de</DiscourseConnective> renforcer les capacités de la protection civile au niveau européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18909" docOffset="106">
      <en>The amendments relate to the need to safeguard prompt transportation of civil protection aid, the importance of early warning and alert systems, the interoperability of civil protection modules and the role which the mechanism can play in helping the citizens of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Les amendements concernent le besoin de garantir le transport rapide de l'aide de la protection civile, l'importance des systèmes d'alerte précoce, l'interopérabilité des modules de protection civile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20635">et</DiscourseConnective> le rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20646">que</DiscourseConnective> peut jouer le mécanisme dans l'aide aux citoyens de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19192" docOffset="107">
      <en>The Commission can accept most of the proposed amendments.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est en mesure d'accepter la plupart des amendements proposés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19251" docOffset="108">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20798" annotation_id="19251">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19251" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, there are some which cause problems and cannot be adopted <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19318" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> they stand.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19251" annotation_id="20798">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20798" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, certains posent problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20834">et</DiscourseConnective> ne peuvent être adoptés tels quels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19333" docOffset="109">
      <en>I refer to those relating to the provision of measures relating to prevention, public health and deliberate maritime pollution.</en>
      <fr>Je pense aux amendements liés aux mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20915">pour</DiscourseConnective> la prévention, la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20953">et</DiscourseConnective> la pollution maritime délibérée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19461" docOffset="110">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20989" annotation_id="19461">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19461" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> regards the measures relating to prevention, the Commission wishes to emphasise that the proposal for the means of financing civil protection will cover actions in this sector.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19461" annotation_id="20989">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20989" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">En</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce qui concerne les mesures de prévention, la Commission souhaite souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21068">que</DiscourseConnective> la proposition sur les moyens de financement de la protection civile couvrira les actions dans ce secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19641" docOffset="111">
      <en>The Community civil protection mechanism is designed to cover actions in the sectors of preparedness and intervention only.</en>
      <fr>Le mécanisme communautaire de protection civile est conçu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21237">pour</DiscourseConnective> couvrir uniquement les actions concernant la capacité de réaction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21308">et</DiscourseConnective> l'intervention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19765" docOffset="112">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21327" annotation_id="19765">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19765" sense="Comparison.Concession">Nonetheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Commission agrees with the European Parliament about the importance of actions in the field of prevention and has promised to promote them within an appropriate framework.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19765" annotation_id="21327">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21327" sense="Comparison.Concession">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la Commission est d'accord avec le Parlement européen au sujet de l'importance des actions dans le domaine de la prévention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21462">et</DiscourseConnective> a promis de les faciliter dans un cadre approprié.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19954" docOffset="113">
      <en>As regards the inclusion of public health, the Commission recognises that civil protection actions very often aim to protect public health.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21516">Quant à</DiscourseConnective> l'inclusion de la santé publique, la Commission reconnaît <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21582">que</DiscourseConnective> les actions de la protection civile ont très souvent pour but de protéger la santé publique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20094" docOffset="114">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21679" annotation_id="20094">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20094" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the civil protection mechanism set up at European Union level does not form part of public health policy, which is covered by other existing Community mechanisms, such as the Community action programme in the health sector.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="20094" annotation_id="21679">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21679" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le mécanisme de protection civile mis en place au niveau de l'Union européenne ne fait pas partie de la politique de santé publique, qui est couverte par d'autres mécanismes communautaires existants, tels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21894">que</DiscourseConnective> le programme d'action communautaire dans le secteur de la santé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20327" docOffset="115">
      <en>As far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20334" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> deliberate or intentional maritime pollution is concerned, the Commission fully supports the proposal whereby it must be possible for the civil protection mechanism to intervene in cases of extensive maritime pollution caused either accidentally or deliberately.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21963">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la pollution maritime délibérée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22014">ou</DiscourseConnective> intentionnelle, la Commission soutient pleinement la proposition permettant au mécanisme de protection civile d'intervenir dans les cas de pollution maritime majeure causée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22190">soit</DiscourseConnective> accidentellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22212">soit</DiscourseConnective> délibérément.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20600" docOffset="116">
      <en>The proposal by the European Commission to extend the scope <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20660" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective> it <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20671" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> covers man-made disasters covers this possibility.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de la Commission européenne d'étendre le champ d'application aux catastrophes anthropiques prévoit cette possibilité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20727" docOffset="117">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="22364" annotation_id="20727">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20727" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the term 'intentional, deliberate' maritime pollution usually refers to the jettisoning of small quantities of oil from ships and the Commission wishes to avoid the interpretation that the scope of the regulation covers jettisoning to such a minor degree.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="20727" annotation_id="22364">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22364" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la pollution maritime dite "intentionnelle, délibérée" se rapporte habituellement au largage de petites quantités de carburant des bateaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22514">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission souhaite éviter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22547">que</DiscourseConnective> le champ d'application du règlement couvre le largage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22605">à</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22607">si</DiscourseConnective> petite échelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20992" docOffset="118">
      <en>It would be practically impossible for the Commission to mobilise the mechanism - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21074" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">nor</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="22737" annotation_id="21079">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21079" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I said earlier, does it have the staff - <Alignment alignment="13307" annotation_id="21123">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21123" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this sort of minor jettisoning should be dealt with by the means available to each country.</en>
      <fr>Il serait pratiquement impossible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22660">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Commission de mobiliser le mécanisme - elle ne dispose pas non plus, <Alignment alignment="21079" annotation_id="22737">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22737" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai dit précédemment, du personnel - <Alignment alignment="21123" annotation_id="22784">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22784" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce genre de largage mineur doit être géré par les moyens disponibles dans chaque pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21219" docOffset="119">
      <en>That is why the corresponding amendments were not accepted.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle les amendements correspondants n'ont pas été acceptés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21279" docOffset="120">
      <en>Finally, the Commission would point out that a series of amendments relates to aspects of existing legislation.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22959">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, la Commission voudrait souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22999">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une série d'amendements concerne les aspects de la législation existante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21391" docOffset="121">
      <en>The Commission supports some of these amendments in essence.</en>
      <fr>La Commission soutient certains de ces amendements par essence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21452" docOffset="122">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23140" annotation_id="21452">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21452" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the interinstitutional agreement on the use of the recast technique does not allow the Commission to accept them, <Alignment alignment="23275" annotation_id="21575">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21575" sense="Expansion.Alternative">unless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are of vital importance to the application of the new provisions contained in the proposal or derive directly from the new provisions.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="21452" annotation_id="23140">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23140" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'accord interinstitutionnel sur l'utilisation de la technique de la refonte ne permet pas à la Commission de les accepter, <Alignment alignment="21575" annotation_id="23275">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23275" sense="Expansion.Alternative">à moins d'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>être indispensables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23305">à</DiscourseConnective> l'application des nouvelles dispositions contenues dans la proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23378">ou</DiscourseConnective> de provenir directement des nouvelles dispositions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21722" docOffset="123">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23455" annotation_id="21722">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21722" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Commission will bear the issues in question in mind within the framework of the development of our policy in this sector.</en>
      <fr>La Commission gardera <Alignment alignment="21722" annotation_id="23455">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23455" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les points <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23476">en</DiscourseConnective> question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23488">à</DiscourseConnective> l'esprit lorsqu'elle élaborera notre politique dans ce secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21857" docOffset="124">
      <en>These are the main issues on which the Commission's position differs from that taken in the European Parliament report.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont là les principaux points sur lesquels la position de la Commission diverge par rapport au rapport du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21977" docOffset="125">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23695" annotation_id="21977">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21977" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I wish to stress that these differences of opinion do not overshadow our common objectives.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="21977" annotation_id="23695">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23695" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23715">que</DiscourseConnective> ces divergences d'opinions ne nuisent pas à nos objectifs communs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22078" docOffset="126">
      <en>We agree fully with the ambition of the European Parliament to develop a very strong European intervention capability in the field of civil protection, both inside and outside the European Union, <Alignment alignment="24016" annotation_id="22274">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22274" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we thank you for your support.</en>
      <fr>Nous partageons entièrement l'ambition du Parlement européen de mettre en place une capacité européenne d'intervention très forte dans le domaine de la protection civile, tant à l'intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23976">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à l'extérieur de l'Union européenne, <Alignment alignment="22274" annotation_id="24016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24016" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous vous remercions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24040">pour</DiscourseConnective> votre soutien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22309" docOffset="127">
      <en>I shall send the European Parliament secretariat a full list of the Commission's positions on the amendments.</en>
      <fr>J'enverrai au secrétariat du Parlement européen une liste complète des avis de la Commission sur les amendements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22419" docOffset="128">
      <en>I should like once again to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Papadimoulis, on his excellent work.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais encore une fois féliciter le rapporteur, M. Papadimoulis, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24244">pour</DiscourseConnective> son excellent travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="22516" id="190" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="22516" docOffset="129">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22538" docOffset="130">
      <en>The vote will take place on Tuesday at 12 noon.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu mardi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24315">à</DiscourseConnective> 12 heures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22586" docOffset="131">
      <en>Written statement (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclaration écrite (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="22615" id="191" name="Hélène Goudin">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="22615" docOffset="132">
      <en>(SV) The European Parliament is now dealing with a proposal for revising the Civil Protection Mechanism set up in 2001.</en>
      <fr>(SV) Le Parlement européen se penche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24398">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> sur une proposition de révision du mécanisme de protection civile mis en place <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24488">en</DiscourseConnective> 2001.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22735" docOffset="133">
      <en>There is no doubt that disasters put great strains on the parties affected.</en>
      <fr>Il ne fait aucun doute <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24520">que</DiscourseConnective> les catastrophes mettent les victimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24562">à</DiscourseConnective> rude épreuve.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22811" docOffset="134">
      <en>Coordinated European civil protection is not, <Alignment alignment="9698" annotation_id="22857">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22857" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the solution to the problem, especially in the form in which it appears in this proposal.</en>
      <fr>Une protection civile européenne coordonnée n'est <Alignment alignment="22857" annotation_id="24628">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24628" sense="Comparison.Contrast">pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas la solution au problème, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24666">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> sous la forme proposée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22956" docOffset="135">
      <en>Civil protection in each Member State is funded through taxes.</en>
      <fr>La protection civile dans chaque État membre est financée par les impôts.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23019" docOffset="136">
      <en>It is up to each State to choose how tax revenue collected from its citizens is to be distributed.</en>
      <fr>Il revient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24790">à</DiscourseConnective> chaque État de choisir comment distribuer les recettes fiscales versées par ses citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23118" docOffset="137">
      <en>This proposal may entail a risk of certain Member States choosing to invest a minimum of resources in national civil protection, relying on other EU countries contributing <Alignment alignment="25099" annotation_id="23290">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23290" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a disaster occurs.</en>
      <fr>Cette proposition peut induire le risque de voir certains États membres faire le choix d'investir un minimum de ressources dans la protection civile nationale en comptant sur la contribution des autres pays européens <Alignment alignment="23290" annotation_id="25099">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25099" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> survient une catastrophe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23314" docOffset="138">
      <en>This problem of free-riding is very serious and is unfair towards people in those countries that choose to have strong civil protection.</en>
      <fr>Ce comportement opportuniste est très grave <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25177">et</DiscourseConnective> injuste envers les personnes qui vivent dans des pays qui ont choisi de se doter d'une protection civile solide.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23451" docOffset="139">
      <en>Where international efforts are concerned, these should be coordinated through OCHA and funded by the Member States and not by the EU.</en>
      <fr>En ce qui concerne les efforts internationaux, ils devraient être coordonnés par l'intermédiaire du BCAH <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25398">et</DiscourseConnective> financés par les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25432">et</DiscourseConnective> non par l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23586" docOffset="140">
      <en>The Commission's document <Alignment alignment="25485" annotation_id="23612">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23612" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> talks about rapid reaction forces and about the Member States having to give notice of available resources, including military resources and military capacity, in cases where an affected country requests that type of aid. The June List resolutely objects to these proposals.</en>
      <fr>Le document de la Commission évoque <Alignment alignment="23612" annotation_id="25485">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25485" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les forces de réaction rapide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25525">et</DiscourseConnective> prévoit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25536">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres donnent une liste des ressources disponibles, y compris les ressources militaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25640">et</DiscourseConnective> la capacité militaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25666">dans le cas où</DiscourseConnective> un pays touché réclame ce genre d'aide.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23892" docOffset="141">
      <en>A country's military resources are a matter for that particular nation, <Alignment alignment="25783" annotation_id="23964">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23964" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is up to each Member State to decide whether <Alignment alignment="25846" annotation_id="24016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24016" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not such resources should be mobilised.</en>
      <fr>Les ressources militaires d'un pays ne concernent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25771">que</DiscourseConnective> ce pays <Alignment alignment="23964" annotation_id="25783">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25783" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il revient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25797">à</DiscourseConnective> chaque État membre de décider de les mobiliser <Alignment alignment="24016" annotation_id="25846">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25846" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
