<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>23.</en>
    <fr>23.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Stabilisation of Afghanistan: challenges for the EU and the international community (</en>
    <fr>Stabilisation de l'Afghanistan: défis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="52">et</DiscourseConnective> la communauté internationale (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="90" docOffset="2">
    <en>- After the vote on Amendment 11:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="88">Après</DiscourseConnective> le vote sur l'amendement 11:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="124" id="172" language="DE" name="André Brie">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="124" docOffset="3">
      <en>Mr President, in view of yesterday's appalling terrorist attack in Kabul, and on the basis of today's discussion, I should like to propose as an oral amendment that a new section 3a be inserted as follows: 'condemns in the strongest possible terms the terrorist attack against the Indian Embassy in Kabul on 7 July 2008, which caused more than 40 deaths, including those of four members of Embassy staff; expresses its sincerest sympathy for the relatives, the wounded and the Afghan and Indian Governments'.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, en réponse à l'épouvantable attentat terroriste qui a eu lieu hier à Kaboul, et sur la base de la discussion d'aujourd'hui, je voudrais proposer, sous forme d'amendement oral, qu'un nouveau point 3a soit inséré comme suit: "condamne de manière véhémente l'attentat perpétré le 7 juillet 2008 contre l'ambassade de l'Inde à Kaboul, qui a causé la mort de quarante personnes, dont quatre membres du personnel de l'ambassade; exprime ses plus sincères condoléances et son soutien aux familles des victimes, aux blessés ainsi qu'aux gouvernements afghan et indien".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="633" docOffset="4">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="644" docOffset="5">
      <en>(Parliament agreed to accept the oral amendment)</en>
      <fr>(L'amendement oral est retenu)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="693" docOffset="6">
      <en>President. - Voting is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le Président. - Ceci met fin aux votes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
