<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>One-minute speeches on matters of political importance</en>
    <fr>Interventions d'une minute sur des questions politiques importantes</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="55" id="028" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="55" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle les interventions d'une minute sur des questions politiques importantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="132" id="029" name="Nicodim Bulzesc">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="132" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, on 4 and 5 December 2008 the European Parliament will discuss a set of proposals to modify Directive 2003/87/EC concerning the emissions trading scheme for greenhouse gas emissions for the period 2013-2020.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, les 4 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="199">et</DiscourseConnective> 5 décembre 2008, le Parlement européen discutera une série de propositions visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="284">à</DiscourseConnective> modifier la directive 2003/87/CE établissant un système d'échange de quotas d'émission de gaz à effet de serre dans la Communauté, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="417">pour</DiscourseConnective> la période 2013-2020.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="353" docOffset="3">
      <en>The proposal foresees a huge increase in auctioning as early as 2013.</en>
      <fr>La proposition prévoit une énorme augmentation des mises aux enchères dès 2013.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="423" docOffset="4">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="27222" annotation_id="423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="423" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> today 90% of pollution allowances are handed out to industrial installations for free, the new directive states that full auctioning should be the rule from 2013 onwards.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="423" annotation_id="524">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="524" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Alors qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>aujourd'hui 90 % des droits d'émissions sont attribués gratuitement aux installations industrielles, la nouvelle directive dispose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="664">que</DiscourseConnective> leur mise aux enchères totale doit être la règle à partir de 2013.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="600" docOffset="5">
      <en>In the case of Romania, this will have extremely severe consequences on the whole economy, <Alignment alignment="18859" annotation_id="691">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="691" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the industry will be seriously affected.</en>
      <fr>Dans le cas de la Roumanie, la nouvelle directive aura des conséquences extrêmement graves sur l'ensemble de l'économie <Alignment alignment="691" annotation_id="855">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="855" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> affectera durement l'industrie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="736" docOffset="6">
      <en>Many industrial companies would have to relocate to third countries with less climate protection, which will raise prices and slow down Romania's development project on infrastructure.</en>
      <fr>De nombreuses entreprises industrielles seront contraintes de se délocaliser dans des pays tiers moins soucieux de protéger le climat, ce qui entraînera une hausse des prix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1063">et</DiscourseConnective> ralentira les projets de développement des infrastructures de la Roumanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="921" docOffset="7">
      <en>This is why I ask that industries in Romania should receive all their allowances for CO2 certificates for free for the entire period.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1141">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> je demande à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1172">que</DiscourseConnective> les industries roumaines reçoivent gratuitement tous leurs droits aux certificats de CO2 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1265">pour</DiscourseConnective> la totalité de la période.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1055" id="030" name="Miguel Angel Martínez Martínez">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1055" docOffset="8">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, last night, in a joint and extremely smooth operation on French territory, security forces from France and Spain arrested one of the main and perhaps most bloodthirsty leaders of ETA, Txeroki, whom they have been pursuing for more than six years for various murders and attacks.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, la nuit dernière, dans le cadre d'une opération conjointe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1383">et</DiscourseConnective> parfaitement huilée réalisée sur le territoire français, les forces de sécurité françaises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1477">et</DiscourseConnective> espagnoles ont arrêté en douceur l'un des principaux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1534">et</DiscourseConnective> peut-être des plus dangereux, leaders de l'ETA, Txeroki, qu'elles recherchaient depuis plus de six ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1640">pour</DiscourseConnective> divers meurtres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1661">et</DiscourseConnective> attaques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1353" docOffset="9">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="31151" annotation_id="1353">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1353" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> exercising the caution that is always needed in such cases, I believe that this is very good news <Alignment alignment="8139" annotation_id="1457">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1457" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am sure that the House will share our satisfaction, which makes up for our disgust on other occasions <Alignment alignment="32405" annotation_id="1565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1565" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have had to speak about the crimes of this organisation.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1353" annotation_id="1674">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1674" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> prenant les précautions toujours indispensables dans de telles circonstances, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1769">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est une très bonne nouvelle <Alignment alignment="1457" annotation_id="1803">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1803" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis sûr <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1818">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Assemblée partagera notre satisfaction, qui compense notre dégoût <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1890">en</DiscourseConnective> d'autres occasions <Alignment alignment="1565" annotation_id="1912">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1912" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1929">à</DiscourseConnective> parler des crimes de cette organisation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1630" docOffset="10">
      <en>This is a very severe blow for the terrorist organisation <Alignment alignment="2033" annotation_id="1688">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1688" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we should congratulate the security forces, governments and people of France and Spain on the success of the operation.</en>
      <fr>C'est un coup très sévère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1998">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette organisation terroriste <Alignment alignment="1688" annotation_id="2033">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2033" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons féliciter les forces de sécurité, les gouvernements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2100">et</DiscourseConnective> les populations de France <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2129">et</DiscourseConnective> d'Espagne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2142">pour</DiscourseConnective> le succès de cette opération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1812" docOffset="11">
      <en>We should <Alignment alignment="2191" annotation_id="1822">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1822" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> congratulate ourselves on the example set by international cooperation as an essential instrument of anti-terrorist resistance.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions <Alignment alignment="1822" annotation_id="2191">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2191" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous féliciter nous-mêmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2227">pour</DiscourseConnective> cet exemple où la coopération internationale devient un instrument essentiel de résistance anti-terroriste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1955" docOffset="12">
      <en>Lastly, Mr President, I must say that the terrorists should know that this will be their fate: being arrested and handed over to the courts and paying for their crimes, or at least those which can be proven, with years in jail.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2340">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, Monsieur le Président, je dois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2378">dire que</DiscourseConnective> les terroristes devraient savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2420">que</DiscourseConnective> tel sera leur sort: être arrêtés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2457">et</DiscourseConnective> traduits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2469">en</DiscourseConnective> justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2480">et</DiscourseConnective> payer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2489">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur crimes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2507">du moins</DiscourseConnective> ceux qui peuvent être prouvés, par des années de prison.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2183" id="031" name="Viktória Mohácsi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2183" docOffset="13">
      <en>(HU) Thank you, Mr President.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Merci, Monsieur le Président.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2213" docOffset="14">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, it has been almost 10 months <Alignment alignment="2666" annotation_id="2264">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2264" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Parliament adopted a resolution requesting that the European Commission formulate a strategy on the Roma.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2617">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, il y a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2638">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> près de dix mois <Alignment alignment="2264" annotation_id="2666">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2666" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement européen a adopté une résolution demandant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2726">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne d'élaborer une stratégie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2778">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur des Roms.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2389" docOffset="15">
      <en>Apart from one staff working document, the Commission has not brought out anything new even for the EU-Roma summit, which was referred to as a historic one.</en>
      <fr>À l'exception d'un document de travail des services de la Commission, la Commission n'a rien présenté de nouveau, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2912">même</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2917">pour</DiscourseConnective> le sommet UE-Roms, décrit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2948">comme</DiscourseConnective> un événement historique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2546" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2546" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Meanwhile</DiscourseConnective>, in Kosovo, the Roma are still living in life-threatening settlements tainted by lead pollution, <Alignment alignment="34321" annotation_id="2653">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2653" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in Hungary attacks with Molotov cocktails or firearms have been perpetrated in nine settlements against the houses of Roma families.</en>
      <fr>Pendant ce temps, au Kosovo, les Roms vivent toujours dans des habitations polluées au plomb qui mettent leur vie en danger, <Alignment alignment="2653" annotation_id="3104">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3104" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3107">en</DiscourseConnective> Hongrie des attaques au cocktail Molotov <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3151">ou</DiscourseConnective> à l'arme à feu ont été perpétrées dans neuf quartiers contre les maisons des familles Roms.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2790" docOffset="17">
      <en>The most recent and terribly sad site of such attacks was Nagycsécs, where two Roma trying to flee the burning house were cruelly shot to death with pellet guns.</en>
      <fr>La plus récente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3262">et</DiscourseConnective> la plus tragique de ces attaques a eu lieu à Nagycsécs, où deux Roms qui tentaient de fuir leur maison en flammes ont été abattus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3395">à</DiscourseConnective> coups de fusil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2952" docOffset="18">
      <en>During the same period, according to reports by civil organisations, close to 30 000 Roma fled Italy in recent months because of police brutality and anti-Roma sentiment.</en>
      <fr>Au cours de la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3428">même</DiscourseConnective> période, d'après des rapports d'organisations civiles, près de 30 000 Roms ont fui l'Italie ces derniers mois à cause des brutalités policières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3577">et</DiscourseConnective> du sentiment anti-Roms.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3123" docOffset="19">
      <en>On top of this situation, there is the current economic crisis, which - let there be no doubt - will most harshly affect the excluded and destitute social classes and the Roma.</en>
      <fr>Par-dessus le marché, il y a la crise économique actuelle, qui - cela ne fait aucun doute - affectera le plus durement les classes sociales exclues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3752">et</DiscourseConnective> défavorisées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3768">et</DiscourseConnective> les Roms.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3300" docOffset="20">
      <en>I would like to remind every responsible politician that this is another reason why we need to create a European Roma strategy.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais rappeler à tous les responsables politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3837">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est là une raison supplémentaire d'élaborer une stratégie européenne pour les Roms.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3428" docOffset="21">
      <en>Thank you very much.</en>
      <fr>Merci de votre attention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3449" id="032" name="Bogusław Rogalski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3449" docOffset="22">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, I would like to raise the issue of the by-pass around the town of Augustów in Poland.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais soulever la question du contournement routier de la ville d'Augustów <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4062">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3554" docOffset="23">
      <en>The lengthening wait for a judgment of the European Court of Justice in the matter means further fatal road accidents involving pedestrians.</en>
      <fr>L'attente interminable d'un jugement de la Cour de justice européenne sur cette affaire signifie l'occurrence d'autres accidents mortels de la circulation impliquant des piétons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3695" docOffset="24">
      <en>Each year some two million goods vehicles pass through the centre of the town.</en>
      <fr>Chaque année, quelque deux millions de véhicules utilitaires traversent le centre de la ville.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3774" docOffset="25">
      <en>In view of the many projects for reserves in the Podlasie region, the freezing of all road investments in the region by the European Commission, deprives it of the opportunity of future development.</en>
      <fr>Considérant les nombreux projets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4381">en</DiscourseConnective> réserve dans la région de Podlachie, le gel de tous les investissements routiers dans la région par la Commission européenne prive cette zone de l'opportunité d'un développement futur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3973" docOffset="26">
      <en>The European Commission's decision means the area is turning into a skansen, which on the model of some Western countries will make it a scenic tourist facility.</en>
      <fr>La décision de la Commission européenne signifie que la région va se transformer en un musée en plein air <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4675">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4679">à</DiscourseConnective> l'instar de ce qui se passe dans certains pays occidentaux, deviendra un centre d'attraction touristique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4135" docOffset="27">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8541" annotation_id="4135">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4135" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not having the Augustów by-pass on grounds of protecting the environment at any cost, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4225" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective> ignoring human needs, is depriving the residents of north-eastern Poland of the opportunity of development and a dignified life.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4135" annotation_id="4787">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4787" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ne pas construire le contournement routier d'Augustów <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4846">pour</DiscourseConnective> des motifs de protection de l'environnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4895">à</DiscourseConnective> tout prix, en ignorant les besoins de la population, revient à refuser aux résidents du nord-est de la Pologne l'opportunité du développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5039">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une vie digne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4360" docOffset="28">
      <en>The European Commission must take this into account.</en>
      <fr>La Commission européenne doit prendre ce fait en compte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4413" docOffset="29">
      <en>Nature needs protection, but not at the cost of human life.</en>
      <fr>La nature doit être protégée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5146">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas au prix de la vie humaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4473" id="033" name="László Tőkés">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4473" docOffset="30">
      <en>(HU) Mr President, 'I desire mercy and not sacrifice': the words of Jesus echo in our souls <Alignment alignment="5300" annotation_id="4565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4565" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we encounter rampant violence and cruelty in the world.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Monsieur le Président, "Je désire la miséricorde <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5236">et</DiscourseConnective> non le sacrifice": les mots de Jésus résonnent dans nos âmes <Alignment alignment="4565" annotation_id="5300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5300" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous sommes confrontés à la violence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5343">et</DiscourseConnective> à la cruauté qui sévissent dans ce monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4626" docOffset="31">
      <en>Terror and force are even more painful <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4665" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> committed in the name of fundamentalist religiosity or religious exclusivism.</en>
      <fr>La terreur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5399">et</DiscourseConnective> la force sont d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5418">autant</DiscourseConnective> plus douloureuses dès lors qu'elles s'exercent au nom du fondamentalisme religieux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5508">ou</DiscourseConnective> d'une religion intégriste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4748" docOffset="32">
      <en>That is why we must protest against the brutal execution of the 13-year-old South Somalian girl, who <Alignment alignment="3059" annotation_id="4849">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4849" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> having been raped by three men, was stoned to death upon the verdict of an Islamic court.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5538">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous devons protester contre l'exécution atroce d'une jeune Somalienne du Sud âgée de 13 ans qui, <Alignment alignment="8810" annotation_id="5651">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5651" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avoir été violée par trois hommes, a été lapidée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5706">à</DiscourseConnective> mort en exécution du verdict d'un tribunal islamique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4945" docOffset="33">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5762" annotation_id="4945">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4945" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">And</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must protest against the persecution of Iraq's Christian minority, who have been forced to flee their homes in Mosul and its surrounding region in the thousands by militant Shiites.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12644" annotation_id="5762">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5762" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons protester contre la persécution de la minorité chrétienne irakienne, dont les membres ont été contraints de fuir par milliers leurs maisons de Mosoul <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5927">et</DiscourseConnective> de la région environnante, chassés par des militants chiites.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5134" docOffset="34">
      <en>In the spirit of our European Christian tradition, religious tolerance and ecumenical brotherhood, the European Union should raise its voice and take action to protect the victims of religious violence and persecution.</en>
      <fr>Dans l'esprit de notre tradition européenne chrétienne, faite de tolérance religieuse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6078">et</DiscourseConnective> de fraternité œcuménique, l'Union Européenne devrait élever la voix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6149">et</DiscourseConnective> prendre des mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6172">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger les victimes de la violence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6214">et</DiscourseConnective> de la persécution religieuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5353" id="034" name="Ilda Figueiredo">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5353" docOffset="35">
      <en>(PT) In Portugal, workers are fighting for their rights in a wide range of sectors.</en>
      <fr>(PT) Au Portugal, les travailleurs luttent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6290">pour</DiscourseConnective> leurs droits dans toute une série de secteurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5437" docOffset="36">
      <en>We wish to express our solidarity with all those who are fighting.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons exprimer notre solidarité avec tous ceux qui combattent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5504" docOffset="37">
      <en>We particularly support the courageous fight of teachers and the impressive demonstration that brought together, in Lisbon, on 8 November, 120 000 teachers from all corners of the country.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6415">En particulier</DiscourseConnective>, nous soutenons le combat courageux des enseignants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6482">et</DiscourseConnective> la manifestation impressionnante qui a rassemblé le 8 novembre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6548">à</DiscourseConnective> Lisbonne 120 000 enseignants venus de tout le pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5693" docOffset="38">
      <en>This second large-scale demonstration in six months involved nearly 80% of this professional class.</en>
      <fr>Cette deuxième manifestation à grande échelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6648">en</DiscourseConnective> six mois a impliqué près de 80 % de cette catégorie professionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5793" docOffset="39">
      <en>It has been followed by other events aimed at showing that teachers are determined to continue defending state schooling and fighting for their dignity and respect for their work which is essential for training the young generations and for ensuring development and progress in Portugal which has some of the worst school achievement levels in the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Elle a été suivie par d'autres événements visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6769">à</DiscourseConnective> montrer la détermination des enseignants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6812">à</DiscourseConnective> défendre l'école publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6840">et</DiscourseConnective> à combattre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6855">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur dignité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6873">et</DiscourseConnective> le respect de leur travail, qui est essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6922">pour</DiscourseConnective> la formation des jeunes générations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6963">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6966">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer le développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6996">et</DiscourseConnective> le progrès au Portugal, dont le niveau en matière de résultats scolaires est parmi le plus mauvais de l'Union Européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6157" docOffset="40">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="27450" annotation_id="6160">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6160" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> support the fight of workers from Pirites Alentejanas, in Aljustrel, against the halt in mining activity which the multinational decided to suspend six months <Alignment alignment="15418" annotation_id="6324">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6324" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it was resumed, sending more than 600 people into unemployment.</en>
      <fr>Nous soutenons <Alignment alignment="6160" annotation_id="7136">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7136" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les ouvriers de Pirites Alentejanas, dans l'Aljustrel, contre l'arrêt de l'activité minière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7234">que</DiscourseConnective> cette multinationale à décidé de suspendre six mois <Alignment alignment="6324" annotation_id="7290">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7290" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sa reprise, mettant ainsi plus de 600 personnes au chômage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6394" docOffset="41">
      <en>Measures must be urgently taken to prevent unemployment from worsening in such a deprived area and to prevent the country becoming poorer.</en>
      <fr>Des mesures urgentes doivent être prises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7397">afin de</DiscourseConnective> prévenir une aggravation du chômage dans cette région défavorisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7471">et</DiscourseConnective> d'empêcher le pays de devenir plus pauvre</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6533" id="035" name="Georgios Georgiou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6533" docOffset="42">
      <en>(EL) Mr President, I should like to inform Parliament that over the last three days, from 14 to 16 November, a country which is a candidate for accession to the European Union has had a naval presence occupying the Greek continental shelf.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Monsieur le Président, j'aimerais informer le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7577">que</DiscourseConnective> pendant ces trois derniers jours, du 14 au 16 novembre, un pays candidat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7654">à</DiscourseConnective> l'adhésion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7667">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union Européenne s'est permis de faire croiser sa flotte navale et d'occuper le plateau continental grec.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6773" docOffset="43">
      <en>I do not intend here to advocate in favour of Greece.</en>
      <fr>Je n'entends pas ici me faire l'avocat de la Grèce.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6827" docOffset="44">
      <en>The Greek continental shelf is <Alignment alignment="7615" annotation_id="6858">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6858" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> part of the European continental shelf <Alignment alignment="24245" annotation_id="6902">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6902" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I see no concern on the part of Europe in protecting its sovereign rights in the area.</en>
      <fr>Le plateau continental de la Grèce fait <Alignment alignment="6858" annotation_id="7869">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7869" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> partie du plateau continental européen <Alignment alignment="6902" annotation_id="7914">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7914" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je ne vois pas pourquoi l'Europe ne protègerait pas ses droits souverains dans cette région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6993" docOffset="45">
      <en>I wonder how a country which behaves in such a way, with such a blatant presence and with such intentions, can join Europe <Alignment alignment="8173" annotation_id="7116">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7116" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> how we plan to accept this Asian country into Europe <Alignment alignment="8250" annotation_id="7173">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7173" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it behaves in such a way.</en>
      <fr>Je me demande comment un pays qui se comporte de cette manière, marquant sa présence de façon provocante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8115">et</DiscourseConnective> avec de telles intentions, pourrait rejoindre l'Europe <Alignment alignment="7116" annotation_id="8173">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8173" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> comment nous pouvons envisager d'accepter ce pays asiatique dans l'Europe <Alignment alignment="7173" annotation_id="8250">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8250" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">alors qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il se comporte de cette manière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7204" id="036" name="Irena Belohorská">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7204" docOffset="46">
      <en>- (SK) In October last year I made a written declaration warning about the emergence of an extreme right-wing organisation called the Hungarian Guard.</en>
      <fr>- (SK) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8299">En</DiscourseConnective> octobre de l'année dernière, j'ai fait une déclaration écrite de mise en garde contre l'émergence d'une organisation d'extrême droite dénommée la Garde nationale hongroise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7355" docOffset="47">
      <en>Sadly, the inactivity of the Hungarian authorities, coupled with our indifference at a European level, have borne fruit.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8475">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, le laisser-faire des autorités hongroises, associé à notre indifférence au niveau européen, a porté ses fruits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7476" docOffset="48">
      <en>This fascism has now been exported to Slovakia.</en>
      <fr>Ce mouvement fasciste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8626">s'</DiscourseConnective>exporte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8636">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> en Slovaquie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7524" docOffset="49">
      <en>Let us not stand idly by in the face of the provocations that have taken place over the past two weeks.</en>
      <fr>Ne restons pas inertes face aux provocations qui ont eu lieu au cours des deux dernières semaines.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7628" docOffset="50">
      <en>On 8 November, in the Slovak town of Kráľovsky Chlmec, 28 members of the Hungarian organisation marched in replica fascist uniforms and laid a wreath to the victims of wars with the provocative inscription I believe in a Hungary reborn.</en>
      <fr>Le 8 novembre, dans la ville slovaque de Kráľovsky Chlmec, 28 membres de cette organisation hongroise ont défilé vêtus de répliques d'uniformes du parti fasciste hongrois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8931">et</DiscourseConnective> ont déposé une gerbe aux victimes des guerres portant l'inscription provocatrice "Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9025">à</DiscourseConnective> la renaissance de la Hongrie".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7865" docOffset="51">
      <en>I am appalled that the act of intervention by the Slovak authorities remained unnoticed in Europe.</en>
      <fr>Je suis consternée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9077">que</DiscourseConnective> l'acte d'intervention des autorités slovaques soit passé inaperçu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9147">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7964" docOffset="52">
      <en>How is it possible that just at the time <Alignment alignment="6313" annotation_id="8005">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8005" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europe is commemorating the 70th anniversary of Kristallnacht, a Member State can tolerate on its own territory the existence of organisations such as the 'Nyilas', the Hungarian Guard, Jobbik or Hnutie 64?</en>
      <fr>Comment est-il possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9182">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9187">précisément</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="8005" annotation_id="9199">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9199" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">au moment où</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Europe commémore le 70e anniversaire de la Nuit de cristal, un État membre puisse tolérer sur son territoire l'existence d'organisations telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9358">que</DiscourseConnective> les "Nyilas", la Garde nationale hongroise, Jobbik <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9413">ou</DiscourseConnective> Hnutie 64?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8217" docOffset="53">
      <en>Can we really be indifferent to the fact that this amounts to a display of contempt for the millions of victims of the Second World War or to the fact that fascists are able to march through the towns of one of our Member States?</en>
      <fr>Pouvons-nous réellement rester indifférents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9471">au fait</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9479">que</DiscourseConnective> ceci équivaut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9497">à</DiscourseConnective> une manifestation de mépris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9527">pour</DiscourseConnective> les millions de victimes de la Deuxième Guerre mondiale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9589">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9592">au fait</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9600">que</DiscourseConnective> des fascistes sont capables de défiler dans les villes de l'un de nos États membres?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8447" id="037" name="Ján Hudacký">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8447" docOffset="54">
      <en>- (SK) On the day <Alignment alignment="22723" annotation_id="8465">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8465" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are commemorating the 19th anniversary of the Velvet Revolution in the former Czech-Slovak Republic, allow me to express my unease over the policy of the current Slovak government, particularly in the area of the economy, which has outlines very similar to those from the period prior to November 1989.</en>
      <fr>- (SK) <Alignment alignment="8465" annotation_id="9696">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9696" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Le jour où</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans l'ancienne République de Tchécoslovaquie, nous commémorons le 19e anniversaire de la Révolution de velours, permettez-moi d'exprimer mon malaise devant la politique de l'actuel gouvernement slovaque - particulièrement dans le domaine de l'économie - dont les orientations sont très similaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10006">à</DiscourseConnective> celles de la période antérieure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10040">à</DiscourseConnective> novembre 1989.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8776" docOffset="55">
      <en>The attempts at complete political management of the private sector and the regulatory interference of the state to the extent carried out by this government are unacceptable in a healthy market system.</en>
      <fr>Les tentatives de gestion politique complète du secteur privé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10119">et</DiscourseConnective> l'interférence réglementaire de l'État pratiquées par ce gouvernement atteignent un degré inacceptable dans une saine économie de marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8979" docOffset="56">
      <en>Through amendments to the law on prices and criminal law the way has been opened to a new regulation of prices in connection with the transfer to the Euro, involving punishments of up to three years in prison for small traders and service providers.</en>
      <fr>Par le biais d'amendements à la loi sur les prix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10309">et</DiscourseConnective> au droit pénal, la voie a été ouverte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10350">à</DiscourseConnective> un nouveau règlement sur les prix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10386">en</DiscourseConnective> relation avec le passage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10414">à</DiscourseConnective> l'euro, un règlement qui prévoit des sanctions allant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10470">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> trois ans de prison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10498">pour</DiscourseConnective> les petits commerçants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10526">et</DiscourseConnective> les prestataires de service.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9229" docOffset="57">
      <en>In addition to the measures relating to increases in energy prices the government has come up with a range of populist pronouncements and threats, with an attempt to expropriate a number of private companies in the energy sector and a proposal for hard, open-ended and superficial regulatory measures targeted against private entities in the so-called general economic interest.</en>
      <fr>Outre les mesures relatives aux augmentations des prix de l'énergie, le gouvernement a fait une série de déclarations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10676">et</DiscourseConnective> lancé des menaces populistes, avec une tentative d'exproprier plusieurs entreprises privées du secteur de l'énergie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10796">et</DiscourseConnective> présenté une proposition de mesures réglementaires lourdes, non limitatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10875">et</DiscourseConnective> superficielles visant spécifiquement les entités privées, soi-disant dans l'intérêt économique général.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9608" docOffset="58">
      <en>Under the pretext of solving the financial crisis and the economic recession, the above-mentioned measures will prevent further essential liberalisation, deform the market environment and scare off potential investors.</en>
      <fr>Sous le prétexte de résoudre la crise financière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11031">et</DiscourseConnective> de lutter contre la récession économique, ces mesures vont empêcher la poursuite d'une libéralisation essentielle, fausser les lois du marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11176">et</DiscourseConnective> décourager les investisseurs potentiels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9827" id="038" name="Marek Siwiec">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9827" docOffset="59">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, on 14 November in Poznań, as every year, a march for equality was held.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, le 14 novembre une marche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11274">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'égalité a été organisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11305">à</DiscourseConnective> Poznań, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11315">comme</DiscourseConnective> chaque année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9918" docOffset="60">
      <en>A group of my young colleagues, members of the Federation of Young Social Democrats, took part in the march.</en>
      <fr>Un groupe de mes jeunes collègues, députés de la fédération des jeunes sociaux-démocrates, a pris part <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11438">à</DiscourseConnective> cette marche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10027" docOffset="61">
      <en>Their slogan was diversity yes, intolerance no.</en>
      <fr>Leur slogan était: "oui à la diversité, non à l'intolérance".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10075" docOffset="62">
      <en>This is part of a larger campaign being held by the Socialist Group in the European Parliament throughout Europe on the issue of tolerance, and which has been underway for many months now.</en>
      <fr>Cette action fait partie d'une grande campagne organisée par le groupe socialiste au Parlement européen dans toute l'Europe sur la question de la tolérance, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11673">et</DiscourseConnective> qui dure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11685">depuis</DiscourseConnective> plusieurs mois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11707">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10264" docOffset="63">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10264" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective> the demonstration was over, the group was attacked by about a dozen thugs who beat them up and snatched banners with the logo of the Socialist Group in the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>À la fin de la manifestation, le groupe a été attaqué par une douzaine de casseurs qui les ont tabassés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11823">et</DiscourseConnective> se sont emparés des bannières portant le logo du groupe socialiste au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10446" docOffset="64">
      <en>One of the victims was hospitalised.</en>
      <fr>L'une des victimes a dû être hospitalisée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10483" docOffset="65">
      <en>I expect those responsible for this incident to be tracked down and punished by the authorities in Poland.</en>
      <fr>J'espère que les responsables de cet incident vont être recherchés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12026">et</DiscourseConnective> punis par les autorités polonaises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10590" docOffset="66">
      <en>I expect political thuggery, which aims to replace dialogue, to be universally condemned by those involved in politics.</en>
      <fr>J'espère que la politique des casseurs, qui vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12114">à</DiscourseConnective> remplacer le dialogue, sera universellement condamnée par tous ceux qui sont engagés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12201">en</DiscourseConnective> politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10710" id="039" name="Ryszard Czarnecki">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10710" docOffset="67">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, on Friday the EU-Russia Summit in Nice, hastily called in order to enable attendance at the G20 meeting, ended.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, le sommet UE-Russie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12263">à</DiscourseConnective> Nice, convoqué à la hâte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12290">pour</DiscourseConnective> permettre la participation de la Russie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12335">à</DiscourseConnective> la réunion du G20, s'est terminé vendredi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10841" docOffset="68">
      <en>The European Union in effect decided to renew negotiations with Russia on the partnership system, and in doing so went against its own decision, made on 1 September this year, that there would be no negotiations with Russia <Alignment alignment="12618" annotation_id="11065">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11065" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Russian troops do not withdraw from the occupied territories of Georgia.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12401">en effet</DiscourseConnective> décidé de reprendre ses négociations avec la Russie sur le système de partenariat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12492">et</DiscourseConnective> ce faisant elle va à l'encontre de sa propre décision prise le 1er septembre cette année de ne pas négocier avec la Russie <Alignment alignment="2802" annotation_id="12618">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12618" sense="Contingency.Condition">tant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les troupes russes ne se seraient pas retirées des territoires occupés de Géorgie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11141" docOffset="69">
      <en>The European Union is behaving in this matter like an old man, who remembers exactly what he did 50 years ago, <Alignment alignment="5135" annotation_id="11252">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11252" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Treaties of Rome came into being, and forgets what he did two months ago, <Alignment alignment="12933" annotation_id="11335">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11335" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the EU gave itself and Europe its assurances on this important issue.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne se comporte dans cette affaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12760">comme</DiscourseConnective> un vieil homme qui se souvient exactement de ce qu'il a fait il y a 50 ans <Alignment alignment="11252" annotation_id="12841">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12841" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les traités de Rome sont entrés en vigueur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12890">et</DiscourseConnective> oublie ce qu'il a fait il y a deux mois <Alignment alignment="11335" annotation_id="12933">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12933" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'UE s'est donné, à elle-même <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12969">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'Europe, toutes les assurances sur cette importante question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11410" docOffset="70">
      <en>It is now retreating from its own undertakings, <Alignment alignment="9031" annotation_id="11458">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11458" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> what was jointly agreed on 1 September has now been tossed aside.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, elle revient sur ses propres engagements, <Alignment alignment="11781" annotation_id="13092">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13092" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce qui a été convenu conjointement le 1er septembre a été jeté aux orties.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11528" docOffset="71">
      <en>In this context the question arises as to whether human rights, which we in the European Parliament often champion all over the world, should <Alignment alignment="13344" annotation_id="11670">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11670" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> apply to European countries such as Georgia and Russia, <Alignment alignment="11129" annotation_id="11731">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11731" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Union is simply behaving like Pontius Pilate on this issue.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte, la question se pose de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13218">si</DiscourseConnective> les droits de l'homme dont nous, au Parlement européen, nous faisons souvent les champions dans le monde entier, devraient <Alignment alignment="11670" annotation_id="13344">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13344" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> s'appliquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13366">à</DiscourseConnective> des pays européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13387">comme</DiscourseConnective> la Géorgie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13404">et</DiscourseConnective> la Russie, <Alignment alignment="11731" annotation_id="13418">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13418" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne se comporte tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13457">simplement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13468">comme</DiscourseConnective> Ponce Pilate sur cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11809" id="040" name="Monica Frassoni">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11809" docOffset="72">
      <en>(IT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, perhaps you too have heard that there are no longer refuse crises in Campania.</en>
      <fr>(IT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13544">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, vous avez peut-être entendu dire, vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13597">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13604">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il n'y a plus de crise des déchets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13642">en</DiscourseConnective> Campanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11929" docOffset="73">
      <en>Well, that is not the case: a few days ago in Chiaiano, which was to have been one of the sites for Berlusconi's infamous dumps, 12 000 tonnes of asbestos and toxic waste was discovered.</en>
      <fr>Eh bien, ce n'est pas le cas: il y a quelques jours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13707">à</DiscourseConnective> Chiaiano, lieu qui devait être l'un des sites infamants de décharge de Berlusconi, on a découvert 12 000 tonnes d'amiante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13831">et</DiscourseConnective> de déchets toxiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12116" docOffset="74">
      <en>Where it came from no one really knows.</en>
      <fr>D'où viennent-ils, cela personne ne le sait réellement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12156" docOffset="75">
      <en>At present in Italy there is a decree in force that clearly goes against all European legislation concerning, above all, the protection of health as well as impact assessments.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13911">En</DiscourseConnective> Italie, il y a maintenant un décret <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13950">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur qui contredit clairement toute la législation européenne concernant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14029">surtout</DiscourseConnective> la protection de la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14063">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les évaluations d'impact.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12333" docOffset="76">
      <en>What is more, the situation is being treated as a state secret, <Alignment alignment="14157" annotation_id="12397">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12397" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these areas have been declared out of bounds <Alignment alignment="14210" annotation_id="12448">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12448" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is impossible to gain any access to information on what is happening there.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14099">De plus</DiscourseConnective>, la situation est traitée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14133">comme</DiscourseConnective> un secret d'État, <Alignment alignment="12075" annotation_id="14157">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14157" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces zones ont été déclarées secteur interdit <Alignment alignment="12448" annotation_id="14210">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14210" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'il est impossible d'obtenir un quelconque accès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14264">à</DiscourseConnective> l'information sur ce qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14291">s'</DiscourseConnective>y passe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12531" docOffset="77">
      <en>We have called on the Commission to intervene; we believe it has a duty to do so <Alignment alignment="19351" annotation_id="12612">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12612" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> to have 10 000 tonnes of asbestos and toxic waste out there in the open air is a danger to everyone.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons demandé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14321">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission d'intervenir; nous pensons qu'elle en a le devoir <Alignment alignment="12612" annotation_id="14387">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14387" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la présence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14409">en</DiscourseConnective> ce lieu de ces 10 000 tonnes d'amiante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14451">et</DiscourseConnective> de déchets toxiques à l'air libre est un danger <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14502">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12721" docOffset="78">
      <en>We hope that Commissioner Dimas will take action and will do so publicly.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14527">que</DiscourseConnective> le commissaire Dimas va prendre des mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14575">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'il le fera publiquement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12795" id="041" name="Árpád Duka-Zólyomi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12795" docOffset="79">
      <en>(HU) Mr President, it is unacceptable that Slovak-Hungarian relations should unfold according to the intentions of extremist forces.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Monsieur le Président, il est inacceptable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14654">que</DiscourseConnective> les relations slovaco-hongroises se développent en fonction des intentions de forces extrémistes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12928" docOffset="80">
      <en>We firmly condemn those who would spoil relations between these two peoples, for we know who the culprits are.</en>
      <fr>Nous condamnons fermement ceux qui voudraient saper les relations entre ces deux peuples, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14846">car</DiscourseConnective> nous savons qui sont les coupables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13039" docOffset="81">
      <en>In Slovakia, the government party, the Slovak National Party, is stirring up tensions with its hate speech against minorities, its outbursts that revile the nation and its anti-Hungarian slurs.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14886">En</DiscourseConnective> Slovaquie, le parti au pouvoir, le parti national slovaque, exacerbe les tensions avec son discours de haine contre les minorités, ses emportements qui insultent la nation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15061">et</DiscourseConnective> ses insinuations anti-hongroises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13233" docOffset="82">
      <en>In Hungary, <Alignment alignment="22584" annotation_id="13245">
          <Alignment alignment="18877" annotation_id="13245">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13245" sense="Comparison.Contrast">by contrast</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, it is not the government authorities but extra-parliamentary extremist groups who are keen to over-react against these attacks.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15098">En</DiscourseConnective> Hongrie, <Alignment alignment="4530" annotation_id="15110">
          <Alignment alignment="13245" annotation_id="15110">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15110" sense="Comparison.Contrast">par contre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, ce ne sont pas les autorités gouvernementales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15169">mais</DiscourseConnective> des groupes extrémistes extraparlementaires qui sont prompts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15235">à</DiscourseConnective> réagir de manière outrée à ces attaques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13386" docOffset="83">
      <en>This is a fundamental difference.</en>
      <fr>La différence est fondamentale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13420" docOffset="84">
      <en>Both phenomena are to be condemned.</en>
      <fr>Les deux phénomènes doivent être condamnés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13456" docOffset="85">
      <en>One of the reasons for the poisoning of relations between the two peoples is that the Socialist Group in the European Parliament turned a blind eye to the policies of the Slovak SMER party coalition, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13656" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective> fuelling extreme, explicitly anti-minority policies.</en>
      <fr>L'une des raisons qui empoisonnent les relations entre les deux peuples est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15430">que</DiscourseConnective> le groupe socialiste au Parlement européen ferme les yeux sur les politiques de la coalition de partis slovaques SMER, ce qui encourage le SMER dans ses politiques extrêmes et explicitement anti-minorités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13717" docOffset="86">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="27212" annotation_id="13717">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13717" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Socialist Group's decision to readmit the SMER into its ranks was a bad one, one that gives free rein to extremist anti-Hungarian expressions.</en>
      <fr>La décision du groupe socialiste de réintégrer le SMER dans ses rangs était <Alignment alignment="13717" annotation_id="15716">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15716" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une mauvaise décision, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15744">car</DiscourseConnective> elle laisse la bride sur le cou aux expressions extrémistes anti-hongroises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13874" docOffset="87">
      <en>Unfortunately, the coalition government in Bratislava does not provide an opportunity for the improvement of Slovak-Hungarian relations.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15825">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, la coalition gouvernementale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15871">à</DiscourseConnective> Bratislava ne fait rien pour créer les conditions propices à une amélioration des relations slovaco-hongroises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14011" docOffset="88">
      <en>Thank you.</en>
      <fr>Merci de votre attention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14022" id="042" name="Hannes Swoboda">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14022" docOffset="89">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, I do not want to go into the details now, <Alignment alignment="16090" annotation_id="14083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14083" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I think that Mr Duka-Zólyomi - with whom I am good friends - is well aware that the Socialist Group in the European Parliament is highly critical of the coalition, and <Alignment alignment="2970" annotation_id="14255">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14255" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> of Mr Slota's party.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, je ne vais pas entrer dans les détails <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16078">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="14083" annotation_id="16090">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16090" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16104">que</DiscourseConnective> M. Duka-Zólyomi - avec qui j'entretiens de bonnes relations d'amitié - est parfaitement au courant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16207">que</DiscourseConnective> le groupe socialiste au Parlement européen est très critique à l'égard de la coalition, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16299">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="14255" annotation_id="16302">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16302" sense="Expansion.Restatement">notamment</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> du parti de M. Slota.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14290" docOffset="90">
      <en>It is now time, <Alignment alignment="16334" annotation_id="14306">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14306" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, particularly following the very welcome meeting between the two prime ministers, Mr Fico and Mr Gyurcsány, to arrange matters <Alignment alignment="8890" annotation_id="14441">
          <Alignment alignment="16500" annotation_id="14441">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14441" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the two countries can resolve their problems together in peace, and not give radicals a platform.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14306" annotation_id="16334">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16334" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il est temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16358">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16370">surtout</DiscourseConnective> à la suite de la réunion très opportune entre les deux premiers ministres, M. Fico <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16461">et</DiscourseConnective> M. Gyurcsány, d'arranger les choses <Alignment alignment="14441" annotation_id="16500">
          <Alignment alignment="14441" annotation_id="16500">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16500" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> les deux pays puissent résoudre leurs problèmes ensemble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16566">en</DiscourseConnective> paix, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16575">et</DiscourseConnective> ne pas offrir de plateforme aux radicaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14547" docOffset="91">
      <en>On that we agree: the radicals must not be allowed to continue spreading poison.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16620">Là-dessus</DiscourseConnective> nous sommes d'accord: il ne faut pas laisser les radicaux continuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16698">à</DiscourseConnective> répandre leur poison.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14628" docOffset="92">
      <en>That certainly applies to Mr Slota's verbal radicalism, <Alignment alignment="2434" annotation_id="14684">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14684" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it <Alignment alignment="7996" annotation_id="14691">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14691" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> applies particularly to the Hungarian Guard.</en>
      <fr>Ceci s'applique certainement au radicalisme verbal de M. Slota, <Alignment alignment="3" annotation_id="16786">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16786" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela s'applique <Alignment alignment="14691" annotation_id="16807">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16807" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16820">surtout</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16828">à</DiscourseConnective> la Garde nationale hongroise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14741" docOffset="93">
      <en>I call on both countries and both prime ministers, and all parties in this House, to make every effort to silence the radicals, to stop them blockading borders and to ensure that peacefully minded people who want to protect and assist minorities have their voices heard.</en>
      <fr>J'appelle les deux pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16884">et</DiscourseConnective> les deux premiers ministres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16915">et</DiscourseConnective> tous les partis dans cette Assemblée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16956">à</DiscourseConnective> faire tout leur possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16983">pour</DiscourseConnective> réduire au silence les radicaux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17021">pour</DiscourseConnective> mettre fin à leur blocage des frontières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17067">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17070">pour</DiscourseConnective> garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17084">que</DiscourseConnective> la voix des citoyens pacifiques qui veulent protéger <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17141">et</DiscourseConnective> assister les minorités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17167">soit</DiscourseConnective> entendue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
