<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Agenda</en>
    <fr>Ordre du jour</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="7" id="103" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7" docOffset="1">
      <en>As regards the draft resolution by the Committee on Foreign Affairs on the humanitarian situation in Sri Lanka, I have received a written objection to the inclusion of the said draft resolution from Robert Evans and 40 other signatories.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la proposition de résolution de la commission des affaires étrangères sur la situation humanitaire au Sri Lanka, j'ai reçu de M. Robert Evans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="175">et</DiscourseConnective> quarante autres signataires une opposition par écrit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="231">à</DiscourseConnective> l'inscription de ladite proposition de résolution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="245" docOffset="2">
      <en>In accordance with the provisions of Rule 90(4) of the Rules of Procedure, the draft resolution is included for debate and vote on the agenda of the current session.</en>
      <fr>Conformément aux dispositions de l'article 90, paragraphe 4, du règlement, la proposition de résolution est inscrite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="401">pour</DiscourseConnective> débat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="412">et</DiscourseConnective> vote <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="420">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre du jour de la présente session.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="411" docOffset="3">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="2064" annotation_id="413">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="413" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> propose to you that the debate this evening be included as the last item, <Alignment alignment="532" annotation_id="497">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="497" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the vote will take place tomorrow at 12 noon.</en>
      <fr>Je vous propose <Alignment alignment="460" annotation_id="478">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="478" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'inscrire le débat ce soir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="511">comme</DiscourseConnective> dernier point, <Alignment alignment="497" annotation_id="532">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="532" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le vote aura lieu demain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="560">à</DiscourseConnective> midi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="547" docOffset="4">
      <en>The deadline for tabling amendments is 3 p.m. this afternoon.</en>
      <fr>Le délai de dépôt des amendements est fixé à cet après-midi à 15 heures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="609" id="104" name="Robert Evans">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="609" docOffset="5">
      <en>Madam President, on Monday evening, the Committee on Foreign Affairs adopted a motion regarding the deteriorating humanitarian situation in Sri Lanka, pursuant to Rule 91.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, lundi soir, la commission des affaires étrangères a adopté une motion relative à la détérioration de la situation humanitaire au Sri Lanka conformément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="820">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 91 du règlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="781" docOffset="6">
      <en>The situation in Sri Lanka is clearly very serious, <Alignment alignment="1059" annotation_id="833">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="833" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> exactly what is happening regarding the humanitarian situation is far from clear.</en>
      <fr>La situation au Sri Lanka est manifestement grave, <Alignment alignment="311" annotation_id="900">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="900" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est très difficile de savoir avec précision où en est la situation humanitaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="919" docOffset="7">
      <en>I am conscious that there are many differing views across this House.</en>
      <fr>J'ai conscience des nombreux avis divergents au sein de cette Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="989" docOffset="8">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1072" annotation_id="989">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="989" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I suggest that the most sensible course of action would be to timetable a proper debate, which cannot seriously be fitted in in this part-session but could be in our next part-session, which is just 10 days away.</en>
      <fr>Je suggère <Alignment alignment="989" annotation_id="1072">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1072" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1077">que</DiscourseConnective> l'approche la plus raisonnable serait de programmer un véritable débat. Il n'est plus possible de l'intégrer à la période de session actuelle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1224">mais</DiscourseConnective> nous pourrions le faire lors de la prochaine période de session, qui commence dans 10 jours à peine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1205" docOffset="9">
      <en>I am grateful to Mr Daul of the PPE-DE Group for indicating his group's support for this course of action.</en>
      <fr>Je remercie M. Daul du groupe PPE-DE d'avoir exprimé le soutien de son groupe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1408">à</DiscourseConnective> cette approche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1312" docOffset="10">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1312" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> we are a serious Chamber, I suggest and ask colleagues to support a debate with resolution and full participation at the next part-session, to do justice to the gravity of the situation in Sri Lanka.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes une assemblée sérieuse, c'est pourquoi je demande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1488">et</DiscourseConnective> je recommande à mes collègues de soutenir un débat complet accompagné d'une résolution lors de la prochaine période de session, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1619">afin de</DiscourseConnective> rendre justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1642">à</DiscourseConnective> la gravité de la situation au Sri Lanka.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1515" id="105" name="Daniel Cohn-Bendit">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1515" docOffset="11">
      <en>(FR) Madam President, <Alignment alignment="1766" annotation_id="1537">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1537" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> someone proposes something, someone may always speak against it prior to the vote.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, <Alignment alignment="23" annotation_id="1707">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1707" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> quelqu'un propose quelque chose, quelqu'un peut toujours parler contre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1785">avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1625" docOffset="12">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="2997" annotation_id="1627">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1627" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> wish merely to say that the situation in Sri Lanka is extremely tragic.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1627" annotation_id="1800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1800" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je veux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1814">simplement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1825">dire que</DiscourseConnective> la situation au Sri Lanka est extrêmement dramatique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1709" docOffset="13">
      <en>There are 150 000 people trapped with no way out.</en>
      <fr>Il y a 150 000 personnes enfermées, qui ne peuvent pas sortir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1759" docOffset="14">
      <en>This is exactly the same as in Burma.</en>
      <fr>C'est exactement le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1971">même</DiscourseConnective> cas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1980">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1797" docOffset="15">
      <en>This is why Sri Lanka should be left on the agenda today, to show our determination to support those who are trapped.</en>
      <fr>C'est pour cela qu'il faut laisser le Sri Lanka, aujourd'hui, à l'ordre du jour, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2077">pour</DiscourseConnective> montrer notre détermination d'être solidaires avec ceux qui sont enfermés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
