<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>36.</en>
    <fr>36.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Interim Trade Agreement with Turkmenistan</en>
    <fr>Accord commercial intérimaire avec le Turkménistan</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="46" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="57">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="65" id="140" name="Karel Schwarzenberg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="65" docOffset="3">
      <en>President-in-Office of the Council. - Mr President, let me remind you that the Council has always examined the opinions and resolutions of Parliament with great interest and attention.</en>
      <fr>président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="82">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, permettez-moi de vous rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="167">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil a toujours examiné les avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="210">et</DiscourseConnective> les résolutions du Parlement avec le plus grand intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="269">et</DiscourseConnective> la plus grande attention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="250" docOffset="4">
      <en>At the same time, the Council has taken the issue of human rights very seriously, <Alignment alignment="379" annotation_id="332">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="332" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> evidenced in the contractual relations of the European Union with countries in various parts of the world.</en>
      <fr>Dans le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="306">même</DiscourseConnective> temps, il a pris très au sérieux la question des droits de l'homme, <Alignment alignment="1961" annotation_id="379">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="379" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> en témoignent les relations contractuelles de l'Union européenne avec des pays aux quatre coins du monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="442" docOffset="5">
      <en>Under the Cotonou Agreement, a treaty between the European Union and the group of African, Caribbean and Pacific States, there have been more than 15 cases since 1995 <Alignment alignment="6462" annotation_id="609">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="609" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Community has partially or fully suspended the application of agreements in relation to some of the countries for non-execution of obligations relating to the human rights clause.</en>
      <fr>Sous l'accord de Cotonou, un traité entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="552">et</DiscourseConnective> le groupe des États d'Afrique, des Caraïbes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="599">et</DiscourseConnective> du Pacifique, il est arrivé plus de quinze fois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="651">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 1995, <Alignment alignment="609" annotation_id="664">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="664" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union suspende totalement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="696">ou</DiscourseConnective> partiellement l'application d'accords avec certains pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="756">pour</DiscourseConnective> non-exécution des obligations découlant de la clause relative aux droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="798" docOffset="6">
      <en>You will certainly <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="817" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> know about the sanctions the Council imposed on Uzbekistan following the Andijan events in 2005.</en>
      <fr>Vous avez certainement eu vent des sanctions imposées par le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="915">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Ouzbékistan à la suite des événements d'Andijan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="967">en</DiscourseConnective> 2005.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="919" docOffset="7">
      <en>Of course, much remains to be done in the field of human rights and respect for the rule of law and democracy in Turkmenistan.</en>
      <fr>Bien sûr, beaucoup reste encore <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1008">à</DiscourseConnective> faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1016">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1048">et</DiscourseConnective> de respect de l'État de droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1081">et</DiscourseConnective> de la démocratie au Turkménistan.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1046" docOffset="8">
      <en>We will continue to push, in particular, for the release of all political prisoners, for free access of the International Committee of the Red Cross to prisons, for lifting of the restrictions on foreign travel and for freedom of the media in civil society.</en>
      <fr>Nous continuerons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1136">notamment</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1146">à</DiscourseConnective> faire pression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1163">pour</DiscourseConnective> la libération de tous les prisonniers politiques, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1218">pour</DiscourseConnective> le libre accès du Comité international de la Croix-Rouge aux prisons, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1293">pour</DiscourseConnective> la levée des restrictions aux voyages à l'étranger <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1349">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1352">pour</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse dans la société civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1304" docOffset="9">
      <en>We are committed to taking appropriate measures in conformity with the agreement, including, <Alignment alignment="1508" annotation_id="1397">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1397" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> necessary, the suspension of the agreement with Turkmenistan, in case of a violation of human rights, as stipulated in the agreement.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous engageons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1425">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre les mesures qui s'imposent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1462">en</DiscourseConnective> conformité avec l'accord conclu - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1499">et</DiscourseConnective> donc, <Alignment alignment="1397" annotation_id="1508">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1508" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nécessaire, à suspendre l'accord avec le Turkménistan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1565">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de violation des droits de l'homme, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1608">comme</DiscourseConnective> prévu dans l'accord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1534" id="141" name="Charlie McCreevy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1534" docOffset="10">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the Commission has carefully taken note of Parliament's concerns about the democracy and human rights situation in Turkmenistan.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la Commission a pris bonne note des préoccupations du Parlement concernant la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1779">et</DiscourseConnective> la situation en matière de droits de l'homme au Turkménistan.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1705" docOffset="11">
      <en>We welcome the statement in the joint draft resolution that the conclusion of an interim trade agreement would be a good first step that will allow us to engage more with Turkmenistan in order to promote further positive developments and cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Nous saluons la déclaration du projet conjoint de résolution selon laquelle la conclusion d'un accord intérimaire sur le commerce constituerait une <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1992">première étape</DiscourseConnective> intéressante qui nous permettrait de renforcer nos relations avec le Turkménistan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2089">pour</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir de nouvelles évolutions positives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2139">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'une plus grande collaboration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1956" docOffset="12">
      <en>The Commission is aware of Parliament's concerns regarding the possibility of suspending the agreements.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est consciente des préoccupations du Parlement concernant la possibilité de suspendre les accords.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2061" docOffset="13">
      <en>I recall the statement by my colleague, Ms Ferrero-Waldner, at the debate last month that both the Interim Trade Agreement (Article 1) and the PCA (Article 2) contain human rights clauses which constitute an essential element of those agreements.</en>
      <fr>Je reprends à mon compte la déclaration de ma collègue, Mme Ferrero-Waldner, lors du débat du mois dernier, selon laquelle tant l'accord intérimaire sur le commerce (article 1) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2469">que</DiscourseConnective> l'APC (article 2) contiennent des clauses relatives aux droits de l'homme, qui forment une composante essentielle de ces accords.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2308" docOffset="14">
      <en>As well as these provisions, Article 28 of the ITA and Article 94 of the PCA will enable each side to take appropriate measures in case of grave violations of the agreements.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2603">En plus de</DiscourseConnective> ces dispositions, l'article 28 de l'AIC <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2654">et</DiscourseConnective> l'article 94 de l'APC permettront à chacune des parties de prendre les mesures qui s'imposent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2751">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de violations graves des accords.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2483" docOffset="15">
      <en>In the Commission's view, these measures could <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2530" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> include the suspension of the agreements.</en>
      <fr>Aux yeux de la Commission, ces mesures pourraient aller jusqu'à la suspension des accords.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2577" docOffset="16">
      <en>The Commission undertakes to monitor closely the human rights situation in Turkmenistan, together with Member States, <Alignment alignment="5944" annotation_id="2695">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2695" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> to report on a regular basis to the appropriate bodies of Parliament.</en>
      <fr>La Commission entreprend de surveiller étroitement la situation des droits de l'homme au Turkménistan, en collaboration avec les États membres, <Alignment alignment="2695" annotation_id="3027">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3027" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de faire régulièrement état de la situation aux organes compétents du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2769" docOffset="17">
      <en>Should Parliament recommend taking measures in the light of reported grave violations of essential elements of the Interim Trade Agreement, especially with regard to human rights, the Commission will seriously consider duly reflecting Parliament's recommendations in its proposal to the Council.</en>
      <fr>Si ce dernier devait recommander certaines mesures après constat de graves violations de points essentiels de l'accord intérimaire sur le commerce, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3259">notamment</DiscourseConnective> concernant les droits de l'homme, la Commission envisagera sérieusement de refléter pleinement les recommandations du Parlement dans la proposition qu'elle transmettra au Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3065" id="142" name="Harlem Désir">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3065" docOffset="18">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, the declarations by the President-in-Office of the Council and the Commissioner are very interesting <Alignment alignment="4137" annotation_id="3185">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3185" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they prove the European Parliament right in calling for the signing of a new trade agreement with Turkmenistan to be linked to respect for human rights.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, les déclarations du Président du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3513">et</DiscourseConnective> du représentant de la Commission sont très intéressantes <Alignment alignment="141" annotation_id="3573">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3573" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles donnent raison au Parlement européen d'exiger qu'il y ait un lien entre la signature d'un nouvel accord commercial avec le Turkménistan et le respect des droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3344" docOffset="19">
      <en>The latter is a fundamental principle for trade agreements made by the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont là des principes fondamentaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3797">pour</DiscourseConnective> les accords commerciaux passés par l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3431" docOffset="20">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9814" annotation_id="3431">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3431" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, given the huge number of human rights violations in that country, even now, I believe that the best way to establish this philosophy is to start by postponing this new trade commitment that you are proposing to us, and thus not to give our assent, which we are being asked to give today.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1967" annotation_id="3857">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3857" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3871">que</DiscourseConnective>, compte tenu des violations massives des droits de l'homme dans ce pays, à l'heure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3958">même</DiscourseConnective>, la meilleure façon de mettre en œuvre cet état d'esprit, c'est de commencer par surseoir à l'engagement commercial nouveau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4087">que</DiscourseConnective> vous nous proposez, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4111">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4114">donc</DiscourseConnective> de ne pas voter pour ce qui nous concerne l'avis conforme que l'on nous demande de voter aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3728" id="143" name="Helmuth Markov">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3728" docOffset="21">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, I should like to say that, in its debate and its papers, Parliament has called on both the Commission and the Council to state that, <Alignment alignment="4388" annotation_id="3880">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3880" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Parliament were to call for this agreement to be suspended or revoked, they would do so.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4270">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans son débat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4290">et</DiscourseConnective> dans ses documents, le Parlement a demandé tant à la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4357">qu'</DiscourseConnective>au Conseil de déclarer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4383">que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="70" annotation_id="4388">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4388" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement devait demander la suspension <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4434">ou</DiscourseConnective> l'annulation de cet accord, ils le feraient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3972" docOffset="22">
      <en>The statements were very different.</en>
      <fr>Les déclarations ont été très divergentes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4008" docOffset="23">
      <en>The President-in-Office of the Council expressed no opinion at all as to how the Council would react <Alignment alignment="4625" annotation_id="4109">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4109" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Parliament were to call for this.</en>
      <fr>Le président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4538">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil n'a exprimé aucun avis sur la manière dont le Conseil réagirait <Alignment alignment="1129" annotation_id="4625">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4625" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement devait lui demander cette suspension ou annulation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4146" docOffset="24">
      <en>The Commissioner merely replied that the Commission would give some thought to what it would do <Alignment alignment="4794" annotation_id="4242">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4242" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Parliament made this request.</en>
      <fr>Le commissaire a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4710">simplement</DiscourseConnective> répondu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4729">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission réfléchirait attentivement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4774">à</DiscourseConnective> ce qu'elle ferait <Alignment alignment="4242" annotation_id="4794">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4794" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement lui adressait cette demande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4275" docOffset="25">
      <en>My point is that Parliament's demands have in no way been met by either the Commission or the Council, <Alignment alignment="18" annotation_id="4378">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4378" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="4927" annotation_id="4382">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4382" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I can only recommend that we now withhold our support for this.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4848">que</DiscourseConnective> ni la Commission ni le Conseil n'ont répondu aux exigences du Parlement <Alignment alignment="4153" annotation_id="4924">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4924" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="4382" annotation_id="4927">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4927" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je ne peux que recommander <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4969">que</DiscourseConnective> nous refusions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4988">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> notre soutien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4456" docOffset="26">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4467" id="144" name="Daniel Caspary">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4467" docOffset="27">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, we have now been debating the subject of Turkmenistan for three-and-a-half years in various committees in this House.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, cela fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5088">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> trois ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5109">et</DiscourseConnective> demi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5117">que</DiscourseConnective> nous débattons la question du Turkménistan dans diverses commissions de ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4626" docOffset="28">
      <en>There are European Treaties by which Parliament, too, must abide, even <Alignment alignment="5278" annotation_id="4697">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4697" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we do not always like it.</en>
      <fr>Il existe des Traités européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5239">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5261">aussi</DiscourseConnective> respecter, <Alignment alignment="4697" annotation_id="5278">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5278" sense="Contingency.Condition">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela ne nous plaît pas toujours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4726" docOffset="29">
      <en>Today, we have managed to obtain, in the Council and Commission statements, the assurances that are possible within the framework of the European Treaties.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, nous avons pu obtenir, dans les déclarations du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5388">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission, les promesses qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5427">s'</DiscourseConnective>avèrent possibles dans le cadre des Traités européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4882" docOffset="30">
      <en>The Commission and the Council have agreed to seriously consider following Parliament's lead <Alignment alignment="5582" annotation_id="4975">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4975" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it delivers opinions and possibly even calls for the suspension of the agreement.</en>
      <fr>La Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5498">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil ont accepté d'envisager sérieusement de suivre l'exemple du Parlement <Alignment alignment="4975" annotation_id="5582">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5582" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il exprimera ses avis, voire lorsqu'il demandera éventuellement la suspension de l'accord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5062" docOffset="31">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5680" annotation_id="5062">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5062" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we all know, unfortunately, this is all Parliament can hope for within the scope of the European Treaties.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5062" annotation_id="5680">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5680" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous le savons tous, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5707">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, c'est tout ce que le Parlement peut espérer dans le cadre des Traités européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5172" docOffset="32">
      <en>There is one mistake we should not make, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5213" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that is to hold our relations with a country hostage in order to obtain more power for the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne devons pas commettre l'erreur de mettre en péril nos relations avec un pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5889">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>obtenir plus de pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5920">pour</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5329" docOffset="33">
      <en>I urge you to recognise the statements by the Council and the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Je vous recommande vivement de reconnaître les déclarations du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6019">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5403" docOffset="34">
      <en>That was all that could be hoped for.</en>
      <fr>C'est tout ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6054">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pouvions espérer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5441" docOffset="35">
      <en>Against this background and in these circumstances, I would ask you to support the signing of the agreement.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6098">et</DiscourseConnective> des circonstances, je voudrais vous demander de soutenir la signature de l'accord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5550" id="145" name="Daniel Cohn-Bendit">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5550" docOffset="36">
      <en>on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group. - (DE) Mr President, <Alignment alignment="6246" annotation_id="5605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5605" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that was not on behalf of the group, I move adjournment on behalf of the Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe des Verts/ALE. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="5605" annotation_id="6246">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6246" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce n'était au nom du groupe, je demanderais la suspension au nom du groupe des Verts/Alliance libre européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
