<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Opening of the sitting</en>
    <fr>Ouverture de la séance</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23" docOffset="1">
    <en>(The sitting was opened at 10.05 a.m.)</en>
    <fr>(La séance est ouverte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="46">à</DiscourseConnective> 10h05)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="62" docOffset="2">
    <en>President. In accordance with the Act relating to the election of the Members of the European Parliament by direct universal suffrage, I declare the session open.</en>
    <fr>Le Président. - Conformément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="84">à</DiscourseConnective> l'acte relatif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="101">à</DiscourseConnective> l'élection au suffrage universel direct des députés au Parlement européen, je déclare ouverte la session du Parlement européen.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="225" docOffset="3">
    <en>This is the second time that, quite undeservedly, I have had the honour of presiding over the election of the President of the European Parliament.</en>
    <fr>C'est la deuxième fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="254">que</DiscourseConnective>, sans aucun mérite, j'ai l'honneur de présider l'élection du Président du Parlement européen.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="373" docOffset="4">
    <en>It will, of course, be the President who delivers a keynote speech.</en>
    <fr>C'est bien entendu le Président qui prononcera le discours d'ouverture.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="441" docOffset="5">
    <en>The applause with which we welcomed the new Member States (Bulgaria and Romania) yesterday and the warm tribute paid to Mr Borrell are signs of trust and continuity.</en>
    <fr>Les applaudissements qui ont accueilli les nouveaux États membres (la Bulgarie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="503">et</DiscourseConnective> la Roumanie) hier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="525">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que le chaleureux hommage rendu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="563">à</DiscourseConnective> M. Borrell sont des signes de confiance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="605">et</DiscourseConnective> de continuité.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="607" docOffset="6">
    <en>In a few weeks' time, it will be the 50th anniversary of the Treaty of Rome, which marks the birth of the European family, a newcomer to the international political and economic scene.</en>
    <fr>Dans quelques semaines, ce sera le 50e anniversaire du traité de Rome, qui a marqué la naissance de la famille européenne, nouvelle venue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="761">à</DiscourseConnective> l'époque sur la scène politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="795">et</DiscourseConnective> économique internationale.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="792" docOffset="7">
    <en>We will proudly celebrate it:</en>
    <fr>Nous le célébrerons fièrement:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="822" docOffset="8">
    <en>because of the extraordinary 60 years of practically uninterrupted peace on our continent;</en>
    <fr>en raison des 60 années de paix pratiquement ininterrompue sur notre continent, ce qui est extraordinaire;</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="913" docOffset="9">
    <en>because of our shared values: freedom, democracy and social justice; and</en>
    <fr>en raison de nos valeurs communes: liberté, démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1018">et</DiscourseConnective> justice sociale;</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="986" docOffset="10">
    <en>because of the hopes that political Europe has inspired in many parts of the world.</en>
    <fr>en raison des espoirs inspirés par l'Europe politique dans de nombreuses régions du monde.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1070" docOffset="11">
    <en>It is only by looking ahead that we can respond to these expectations, to the demands and <Alignment alignment="1479" annotation_id="1160">
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1160" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
      </Alignment> to the criticisms of Europeans on institutional and social issues.</en>
    <fr>Ce n'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1138">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> regardant vers l'avenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1168">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pourrons répondre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1195">à</DiscourseConnective> ces attentes, aux exigences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1225">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="1160" annotation_id="1228">
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1228" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
      </Alignment> aux critiques des Européens sur les questions institutionnelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1298">et</DiscourseConnective> sociales.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1232" docOffset="12">
    <en>I am referring to a globalised world, to the progress it has made and to the ever-growing injustice within it.</en>
    <fr>Je fais ici référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1333">à</DiscourseConnective> la mondialisation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1354">à</DiscourseConnective> sa progression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1371">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1374">à</DiscourseConnective> l'injustice croissante qu'elle entraîne.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1343" docOffset="13">
    <en>I am referring to the great responsibility that we have towards the future of energy and the environment, that is to say, towards the survival of the planet and towards future generations.</en>
    <fr>Je fais référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1435">à</DiscourseConnective> la grande responsabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1462">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons envers l'avenir de l'énergie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1506">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'environnement, c'est-à-dire envers la survie de la planète <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1573">et</DiscourseConnective> les générations futures.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1532" docOffset="14">
    <en>I am referring to new opportunities linked to developments in science, to the way in which the applications of these developments are managed, and to the advantages and ethical dilemmas that arise in everyone's minds <Alignment alignment="1833" annotation_id="1749">
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1749" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
      </Alignment> that mean making informed decisions.</en>
    <fr>Je fais référence aux nouvelles possibilités liées aux évolutions scientifiques, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1682">à</DiscourseConnective> la manière dont les applications de ces évolutions sont gérées et aux avantages, mais aussi aux dilemmes éthiques, qui viennent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1812">à</DiscourseConnective> l'esprit de chacun <Alignment alignment="1749" annotation_id="1833">
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1833" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
      </Alignment> qui impliquent de prendre des décisions éclairées.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
</DOCUMENT>
