<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>7.</en>
    <fr>7.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Common organisation of the markets in fisheries and aquaculture (vote)</en>
    <fr>Organisation commune des marchés dans le secteur des produits de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="77">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'aquaculture (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="74" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Report: Pedro Gueirrero</en>
    <fr>- Rapport Pedro Gueirrero</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="100" docOffset="3">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="132">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="119" id="067" name="Pedro Guerreiro">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="119" docOffset="4">
      <en>rapporteur. - (PT) I should like to begin this short statement by welcoming the decision by the European Parliament Committee on Fisheries to produce a report on the Common Organisation of the Markets in fisheries and aquaculture products.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (PT) je voudrais commencer cette brève déclaration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="212">en</DiscourseConnective> saluant la décision de la commission de la pêche du Parlement européen de rédiger un rapport sur l'organisation commune des marchés dans le secteur des produits de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="388">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'aquaculture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="359" docOffset="5">
      <en>It is known and recognised that this COM has still not realised the objectives for which it was created, namely to ensure stable markets for fisheries products and to secure a fair income for producers.</en>
      <fr>Chacun sait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="421">et</DiscourseConnective> reconnaît <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="434">que</DiscourseConnective> cette OCM n'a pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="456">encore</DiscourseConnective> atteint les objectifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="485">pour</DiscourseConnective> lesquels elle a été créée, à savoir garantir des marchés stables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="555">pour</DiscourseConnective> les produits de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="585">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que des revenus justes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="614">pour</DiscourseConnective> les producteurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="562" docOffset="6">
      <en>That being so, we appreciate the European Commission's albeit tardy decision to undertake an in-depth evaluation of the existing COM and call on it to carry out its urgent revision in order to boost its contribution to guaranteeing incomes in the sector, ensuring market stability, improving the marketing of fisheries products and increasing the value-added generated, notably by a significant increase in financial resources.</en>
      <fr>Cela étant dit, nous apprécions la décision, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="681">même</DiscourseConnective> tardive, de la Commission d'entreprendre une évaluation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="742">en</DiscourseConnective> profondeur de l'OCM existante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="775">et</DiscourseConnective> nous l'invitons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="794">à</DiscourseConnective> mener à bien sa révision urgente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="829">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>accroître sa contribution visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="869">à</DiscourseConnective> garantir les revenus dans ce secteur, garantir la stabilité des marchés, améliorer la commercialisation des produits de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1000">et</DiscourseConnective> augmenter la valeur ajoutée générée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1040">notamment</DiscourseConnective> au travers d'une augmentation significative des ressources financières.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="990" docOffset="7">
      <en>Despite the fact that some of our initial proposals did not obtain the necessary consensus in the Committee on Fisheries, we consider that the report now put to the vote contains valuable measures, such as measures to determine whether the existing intervention mechanisms are the most suitable ones <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1290" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> whether they are sufficiently flexible to meet the relevant needs in the various Member States; to introduce a compensatory payment for sardines like the one already existing for tuna; to meet the need for the Structural Funds to contribute to the modernisation and creation of support infrastructures for producers in the context of production/marketing; to provide genuine support for the creation and funding of producers' organisations and above all for small-scale coastal and traditional fisheries; to ensure the application to imported fisheries products sold on the internal market of the same rules and requirements as those applied to Community fisheries products.</en>
      <fr>Malgré le fait que certaines de nos propositions initiales n'aient pas fait l'objet d'un consensus nécessaire au sien de la commission de la pêche, nous estimons que le rapport soumis aujourd'hui au vote contient des mesures précieuses, comme celles visant à déterminer si les mécanismes d'intervention existants sont les plus adéquats et s'ils sont suffisamment souples pour satisfaire aux besoins pertinents dans les différents États membres; à introduire un paiement compensatoire pour les sardines à l'instar de ce qui existe déjà pour le thon; à prendre en considération la nécessité de voir les Fonds structurels contribuer à la modernisation et à la création d'infrastructures de soutien aux producteurs dans le contexte de la production/commercialisation; à fournir un véritable soutien à la création et au financement d'organisations de producteurs, surtout pour les pêches côtières et traditionnelles de petites tailles; à garantir l'application aux produits de la pêche importés et vendus sur le marché intérieur les mêmes règles et exigences que celles appliquées aux produits de la pêche communautaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1969" docOffset="8">
      <en>These are matters which, <Alignment alignment="2266" annotation_id="1994">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1994" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they may not mean much to some Members, are most important for fishermen.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2241">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de questions qui, <Alignment alignment="1994" annotation_id="2266">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2266" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elles ne représentent pas grand chose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2312">pour</DiscourseConnective> certains États membres, sont d'une importance vitale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2370">pour</DiscourseConnective> les pêcheurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
