<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>2.</en>
    <fr>2.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Greenhouse gas emission allowance trading system (</en>
    <fr>Échange de quotas d'émission de gaz à effet de serre (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="54" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="60">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="73" id="077" name="Markus Pieper">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="73" docOffset="3">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, my justification is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="112" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> follows.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, ma justification est la suivante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="124" docOffset="4">
      <en>Unfortunately, no plenary debate, the result of which we could have taken to the trialogue, was held on ETS.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="136">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, aucun débat en plénière, dont nous aurions pu apporter le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="211">résultat</DiscourseConnective> au trialogue, n'a eu lieu sur le SCEQE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="233" docOffset="5">
      <en>Trialogue negotiations merely on the basis of the opinion of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety are not representative of Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Les négociations en trialogue, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="291">simplement</DiscourseConnective> basées sur l'avis de la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="378">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire, ne sont pas représentatives du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="396" docOffset="6">
      <en>Now, we are supposed to endorse the amendments to the Commission's proposal; <Alignment alignment="543" annotation_id="473">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="473" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> what we are supposed to be deciding on today matches the Council paper one-to-one.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="451">Maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, nous sommes supposés adopter les amendements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="508">à</DiscourseConnective> la proposition de la Commission; <Alignment alignment="473" annotation_id="543">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="543" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce qui est censé faire l'objet de notre décision aujourd'hui correspond point <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="626">pour</DiscourseConnective> point au document du Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="560" docOffset="7">
      <en>There is not a single alteration by Parliament, even so much as a comma.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement n'a apporté aucune modification, pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="711">même</DiscourseConnective> une virgule.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="633" docOffset="8">
      <en>What is the reason for this time pressure?</en>
      <fr>Pourquoi sommes-nous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="750">si</DiscourseConnective> pressés par le temps?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="676" docOffset="9">
      <en>After all, we are talking about a period from 2013 onwards.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="775">Après tout</DiscourseConnective>, nous parlons ici d'une période qui débutera en 2013.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="736" docOffset="10">
      <en>With the ETS proposal in its current form, inconsistencies and ballooning costs will catch up with us.</en>
      <fr>Avec la proposition SCEQE sous sa forme actuelle, les incohérences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="907">et</DiscourseConnective> l'explosion des coûts vont nous rattraper.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="839" docOffset="11">
      <en>The subject of emissions trading is the most important industrial policy decision for years, <Alignment alignment="1762" annotation_id="932">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="932" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not decades, to come.</en>
      <fr>Le sujet de l'échange de quotas d'émission est la décision politique industrielle la plus importante des années, <Alignment alignment="62" annotation_id="1066">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1066" sense="Contingency.Condition">sinon</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des décennies, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1087">à</DiscourseConnective> venir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="957" docOffset="12">
      <en>We are not prepared to hand in our democratic right of codecision at the Parliament cloakroom.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne sommes pas prêts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1121">à</DiscourseConnective> laisser notre droit démocratique de codécision au vestiaire du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1052" docOffset="13">
      <en>After all, what is it that many Members have successfully fought for in this House for almost 30 years?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1197">Après tout</DiscourseConnective>, pour quoi de nombreux États membres se battent-ils avec succès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1272">depuis</DiscourseConnective> près de 30 ans au sein de cette Assemblée?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1156" docOffset="14">
      <en>Have they fought to see climate policy left almost entirely to the Council through a simplified procedure?</en>
      <fr>Se battent-ils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1337">pour</DiscourseConnective> voir la politique climatique abandonnée presqu'entièrement au Conseil par une procédure simplifiée?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1263" docOffset="15">
      <en>As an elected parliament, we wish to engage in democratic debate and to do so specifically in view of the consequences of our actions.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1445">tant que</DiscourseConnective> Parlement élu, nous voulons entamer un débat démocratique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1513">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1528">en</DiscourseConnective> vue des conséquences de nos actions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1398" docOffset="16">
      <en>Thank you very much.</en>
      <fr>Merci beaucoup.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
