<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Derogations from internal market rules for defence procurement on the basis of Article 296 TEC (debate)</en>
    <fr>Dérogations aux règles du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43">pour</DiscourseConnective> les marchés publics de la défense sur la base de l'article 296 du traité CE (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="104" id="415" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="104" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the debate on the oral question to the Commission on derogations from internal market rules for defence procurement on the basis of Article 296 TEC, by Arlene McCarthy, on behalf of the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection - B6-0122/2007).</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle la question orale de Mme McCarthy, au nom de la commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="235">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="274">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur les dérogations aux règles du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="341">pour</DiscourseConnective> les marchés publics de la défense sur la base de l'article 296 du traité CE (B6-0122/2007).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="381" id="416" name="Arlene McCarthy ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="381" docOffset="2">
      <en>author. - Mr President, I am sorry Mr Booth has gone <Alignment alignment="17263" annotation_id="434">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="434" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would like to tell him that I am a music lover <Alignment alignment="28790" annotation_id="491">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="491" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> perhaps next time he could perform a Euro-rap <Alignment alignment="23079" annotation_id="541">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="541" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> my report is up!</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je regrette que M. Booth <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="486">soit</DiscourseConnective> parti, <Alignment alignment="434" annotation_id="498">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="498" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'aurais aimé lui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="520">dire que</DiscourseConnective> j'aime beaucoup la musique <Alignment alignment="5175" annotation_id="556">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="556" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, la prochaine fois peut-être, il pourrait chanter un "Euro-rap" <Alignment alignment="7224" annotation_id="627">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="627" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">au moment de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'annonce de mon rapport!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="563" docOffset="3">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="666" annotation_id="563">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="563" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commissioner is aware, the defence procurement market accounts for a large share of EU public procurement, estimated at about EUR 80 billion out of a combined Member State defence budget of EUR 170 billion, <Alignment alignment="46388" annotation_id="777">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="777" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is why we are tabling this question today: defence procurement is still being awarded within mostly fragmented national markets.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="563" annotation_id="666">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="666" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le commissaire le sait, les acquisitions publiques d'équipements de défense représentent une part importante des acquisitions publiques dans l'UE - on estime qu'ils représentent environ 80 milliards d'euros sur un budget de défense combiné des États membres estimé à 170 milliards d'euros - <Alignment alignment="12409" annotation_id="963">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="963" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est la raison pour laquelle nous avons déposé cette question aujourd'hui: les marchés publics de la défense sont toujours attribués dans des marchés nationaux le plus souvent fragmentés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="915" docOffset="4">
      <en>The Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, <Alignment alignment="1233" annotation_id="977">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="977" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, takes note of the Commission's interpretative communication on the application of Article 296 of the Treaty in the field of defence procurement, adopted on 7 December 2006.</en>
      <fr>La commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1189">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs prend <Alignment alignment="977" annotation_id="1233">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1233" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> acte de la communication interprétative adoptée le 7 décembre 2006 par la Commission concernant l'application de l'article 296 du Traité dans le domaine des marchés publics de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1161" docOffset="5">
      <en>This helped clarify the existing legal framework. <Alignment alignment="1499" annotation_id="1211">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1211" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we <Alignment alignment="1517" annotation_id="1223">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1223" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> further note efforts by the Commission to propose new legislation, which should substantially contribute to creating a more competitive environment for the European defence industry and its suppliers.</en>
      <fr>Cette communication a contribué à clarifier le cadre juridique existant, <Alignment alignment="1211" annotation_id="1499">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1499" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous prenons <Alignment alignment="5263" annotation_id="1517">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1517" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> acte des efforts consentis par la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1572">pour</DiscourseConnective> proposer une nouvelle législation qui devrait contribuer sensiblement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1647">à</DiscourseConnective> créer un environnement plus concurrentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1691">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie européenne de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1730">et</DiscourseConnective> ses fournisseurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1429" docOffset="6">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1751" annotation_id="1429">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1429" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we want to ask the Commissioner the following questions.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1429" annotation_id="1751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1751" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous aimerions poser au commissaire les questions suivantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1497" docOffset="7">
      <en>What progress is being made on the draft directive on the procurement of defence equipment not subject to the derogations of Article 296?</en>
      <fr>Quels progrès ont été réalisés concernant la directive, en cours d'élaboration, sur les marchés publics pour les équipements de défense qui ne font pas l'objet des dérogations visées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2010">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 296?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1635" docOffset="8">
      <en>What are the subsequent steps planned by the Commission in this area?</en>
      <fr>Quelles démarches ultérieures la Commission envisage-t-elle dans ce domaine?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1705" docOffset="9">
      <en>How does the Commission evaluate, from the perspective of a fair and efficient working of the internal market, the situation within the European defence industry, where in different Member States a significant number of highly skilled jobs appear to be at risk?</en>
      <fr>Comment la Commission évalue-t-elle, dans la perspective d'un fonctionnement équitable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2191">et</DiscourseConnective> efficace du marché intérieur, la situation de l'industrie européenne de défense, où un nombre important d'emplois hautement qualifiés semble être menacé dans différents États membres?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1967" docOffset="10">
      <en>What impact does it expect the directive to have on the sector, and what is the Commission's strategy to induce Member States to cooperate more closely on defence procurement issues, to improve transparency and gradually open up their national defence procurement markets in order to establish a well-performing and competitive environment for this sensitive sector?</en>
      <fr>Quel impact pense-t-elle que la directive aura sur le secteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2440">et</DiscourseConnective> quelle stratégie envisage-t-elle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2476">pour</DiscourseConnective> amener les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2506">à</DiscourseConnective> coopérer plus étroitement sur les questions des marchés publics de la défense, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2587">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2615">et</DiscourseConnective> à ouvrir progressivement leurs marchés nationaux de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2681">afin de</DiscourseConnective> créer un environnement performant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2723">et</DiscourseConnective> concurrentiel dans ce secteur sensible?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2334" docOffset="11">
      <en>We should <Alignment alignment="30562" annotation_id="2344">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2344" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to know what conclusions can be drawn from the code of conduct that was established in 2006, <Alignment alignment="2880" annotation_id="2447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2447" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> how the Commission understands the future relationship between a potential directive and the code of conduct.</en>
      <fr>Nous aimerions <Alignment alignment="2344" annotation_id="2781">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2781" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> connaître les conclusions qui pourraient être tirées du Code de conduite élaboré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2872">en</DiscourseConnective> 2006 <Alignment alignment="2447" annotation_id="2880">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2880" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous aimerions savoir comment la Commission envisage le lien futur entre une éventuelle directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2981">et</DiscourseConnective> ce Code de conduite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2561" id="417" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2561" docOffset="12">
      <en>Thank you, Mrs McCarthy.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie, Madame McCarthy.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2586" docOffset="13">
      <en>I would like to remind you that rap music and the Greek hendecasyllabic metre have the same rhythm.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3049">à</DiscourseConnective> vous rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3065">que</DiscourseConnective> le rap <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3076">et</DiscourseConnective> le vers hendécasyllabe grec ont le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3114">même</DiscourseConnective> rythme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2686" docOffset="14">
      <en>You and Mr Booth are closer than you think.</en>
      <fr>Vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3132">et</DiscourseConnective> M. Booth êtes plus proches <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3162">que</DiscourseConnective> vous le pensez.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2730" id="418" name="Charlie McCreevy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2730" docOffset="15">
      <en>Mr President, four years ago the Commission announced its intention to develop a European security and defence policy.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, la Commission avait annoncé, il y a quatre ans, son intention de mettre au point une politique européenne de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3323">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2849" docOffset="16">
      <en>Since then, we have been striving to establish a more open and fair European defence market through a number of initiatives.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3338">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> lors, nous nous sommes efforcés d'établir un marché européen de la défense plus ouvert <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3432">et</DiscourseConnective> plus équitable grâce à un certain nombre d'initiatives.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2974" docOffset="17">
      <en>The new procurement directive for defence equipment is a crucial element of this overall strategy and is one of the Commission's strategic priorities for this year.</en>
      <fr>La nouvelle directive sur les marchés publics d'équipements de défense constitue un élément capital de cette stratégie globale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3618">et</DiscourseConnective> représente une des priorités stratégiques de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3680">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3139" docOffset="18">
      <en>At present, the vast majority of defence equipment tenders are conducted outside Community rules.</en>
      <fr>Actuellement, la grande majorité des appels d'offres d'équipements de défense a lieu en dehors des règles communautaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3237" docOffset="19">
      <en>Member States rely upon the derogation from the Treaty under Article 296.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres se prévalent de la dérogation au Traité visée à l'article 296.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3311" docOffset="20">
      <en>In the Commission's view, this derogation should be limited to the exceptional cases.</en>
      <fr>La Commission estime que cette dérogation devrait être limitée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3964">à</DiscourseConnective> des cas exceptionnels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3397" docOffset="21">
      <en>We gave some guidance on the matter last December.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons fourni certaines orientations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4030">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet en décembre dernier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3448" docOffset="22">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3448" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>, the derogation is still the rule more than the exception. Most defence procurement has <Alignment alignment="4133" annotation_id="3549">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3549" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remained outside of the internal market principles.</en>
      <fr>Malgré cela, la dérogation est toujours la règle plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4116">que</DiscourseConnective> l'exception, <Alignment alignment="3549" annotation_id="4133">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4133" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de sorte que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la plupart des acquisitions de défense restent toujours en dehors des principes du marché intérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3611" docOffset="23">
      <en>This means that all 27 Member States procure defence equipment in accordance with their own national regulations, often resulting in non-transparent and sometimes discriminatory practices.</en>
      <fr>Cela signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4261">que</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble des 27 États membres acquièrent des équipements de défense sur la base de leurs propres règlements nationaux, ce qui engendre souvent un manque de transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4436">et</DiscourseConnective> des pratiques parfois discriminatoires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3800" docOffset="24">
      <en>We recognise that current public procurement rules are really suited to the particular needs of the defence procurement. <Alignment alignment="4635" annotation_id="3921">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3921" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we believe we can achieve important economic gains <Alignment alignment="4717" annotation_id="3976">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3976" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we open up national defence markets, which represent 0.8% of the European Union's GDP and one quarter of public procurement at state level.</en>
      <fr>Nous reconnaissons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4498">que</DiscourseConnective> les règles actuelles régissant les marchés publics sont mal adaptées aux besoins spécifiques des acquisitions en matière de défense, <Alignment alignment="3921" annotation_id="4635">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4635" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous pensons qu'il est possible de réaliser des gains économiques importants <Alignment alignment="15745" annotation_id="4717">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4717" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ouvrons les marchés nationaux de défense, qui représentent 0,8% du PIB de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4818">et</DiscourseConnective> un quart des acquisitions publiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4857">à</DiscourseConnective> l'échelon national.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4119" docOffset="25">
      <en>Member States and industry widely acknowledge these advantages.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4897">et</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie reconnaissent ces avantages dans une large mesure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4183" docOffset="26">
      <en>Fair and transparent conditions would allow companies, especially SMEs, to tender more easily in other Member States and <Alignment alignment="5141" annotation_id="4304">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4304" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> widen their access to business opportunities in a much larger home market.</en>
      <fr>Des conditions équitables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4989">et</DiscourseConnective> transparentes permettraient aux entreprises, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5037">surtout</DiscourseConnective> aux PME, de lancer plus facilement des appels d'offres dans d'autres États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5128">et</DiscourseConnective> d'élargir <Alignment alignment="4304" annotation_id="5141">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5141" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leurs possibilités d'accès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5174">à</DiscourseConnective> un marché intérieur beaucoup plus vaste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4384" docOffset="27">
      <en>Longer production runs would allow economies of scale. This <Alignment alignment="5296" annotation_id="4444">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4444" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">in turn</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> would help to reduce costs and lead to lower prices.</en>
      <fr>Des cycles de production plus longs permettraient des économies d'échelle qui, <Alignment alignment="4444" annotation_id="5296">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5296" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">à</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leur tour, contribueraient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5325">à</DiscourseConnective> réduire les coûts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5345">et</DiscourseConnective> donc <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5353">à</DiscourseConnective> faire baisser les prix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4505" docOffset="28">
      <en>The final beneficiary of that would be the taxpayer.</en>
      <fr>Le bénéficiaire final serait le contribuable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4558" docOffset="29">
      <en>Our proposal would adapt certain Community procurement rules to the specific nature of defence and give awarding authorities greater flexibility for sensitive procurement procedures.</en>
      <fr>Notre proposition vise à adapter certaines règles communautaires en matière d'acquisitions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5516">à</DiscourseConnective> la nature spécifique du secteur de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5564">et</DiscourseConnective> à octroyer aux pouvoirs adjudicateurs une plus grande flexibilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5633">pour</DiscourseConnective> des procédures d'acquisitions sensibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4741" docOffset="30">
      <en>This will <Alignment alignment="5696" annotation_id="4751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4751" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> make it easier for Member States to use the derogation under Article 296 of the Treaty only in exceptional cases.</en>
      <fr>Cela permettrait <Alignment alignment="4751" annotation_id="5696">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5696" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aux États membres de ne recourir à la dérogation visée à l'article 296 du Traité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5787">que</DiscourseConnective> dans des cas exceptionnels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4870" docOffset="31">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12518" annotation_id="4870">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4870" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> is the case under the other procurement directives, Member States will continue exchanging views on defence procurement issues via the Advisory Committee on Public Procurement, <Alignment alignment="6071" annotation_id="5050">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5050" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">once</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the directive has been implemented.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4870" annotation_id="5819">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5819" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est le cas avec les autres directives relatives aux marchés publics, les États membres continueront à échanger des avis sur les questions liées aux acquisitions d'équipements de défense au travers du comité consultatif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6046">pour</DiscourseConnective> les marchés publics <Alignment alignment="5050" annotation_id="6071">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6071" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">une fois que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la directive aura été mise en œuvre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5091" docOffset="32">
      <en>I wish to emphasise that the new directive will implement the code of conduct of the European Defence Agency.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6130">à</DiscourseConnective> souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6142">que</DiscourseConnective> la nouvelle directive mettra en œuvre le Code de conduite de l'Agence européenne de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5201" docOffset="33">
      <en>The code of conduct applies only to contracts which are exempted from the Community rules on the basis of Article 296, <Alignment alignment="6356" annotation_id="5320">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5320" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the future directive will apply to contracts which are not exempted from Community rules.</en>
      <fr>Celui-ci s'applique uniquement aux contrats qui sont exemptés des règles communautaires sur la base de l'article 296 <Alignment alignment="5320" annotation_id="6356">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6356" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la future directive s'appliquera aux contrats qui ne sont pas exemptés des règles communautaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5416" docOffset="34">
      <en>Together the code of conduct and the new directive will enhance transparency and fair competition on defence partners in the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Ensemble, le Code de conduite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6494">et</DiscourseConnective> la nouvelle directive accroîtront la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6547">et</DiscourseConnective> la concurrence sur des bases égales pour les partenaires en matière de défense dans l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5557" docOffset="35">
      <en>I am pleased to indicate that work on the proposal for a defence directive is well advanced.</en>
      <fr>J'ai le plaisir de vous signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6687">que</DiscourseConnective> les travaux concernant la proposition d'une directive sur la défense sont bien avancés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5650" docOffset="36">
      <en>My services are currently finalising the impact assessment which will tell us more about the expected impact of the initiative on the market, including social issues.</en>
      <fr>Mes services sont en train de finaliser l'évaluation d'impact qui nous en dira plus sur l'impact probable de l'initiative sur le marché, y compris sur le plan social.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5817" docOffset="37">
      <en>In parallel we are working closely with Member States via the Advisory Committee on Public Procurement and via the European Defence Agency.</en>
      <fr>Nous travaillons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6963">parallèlement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6977">en</DiscourseConnective> étroite collaboration avec les États membres par l'intermédiaire du comité consultatif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7067">pour</DiscourseConnective> les marchés publics <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7092">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que par l'intermédiaire de l'Agence européenne de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5957" docOffset="38">
      <en>Industry is <Alignment alignment="7173" annotation_id="5969">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5969" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> involved in the impact assessment.</en>
      <fr>L'industrie est <Alignment alignment="5969" annotation_id="7173">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7173" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> impliquée dans cette évaluation d'impact.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6009" docOffset="39">
      <en>The Commission is planning to adopt a proposal in the autumn.</en>
      <fr>La Commission entend adopter une proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7270">en</DiscourseConnective> automne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6071" docOffset="40">
      <en>At this stage we aim to present it as part of a package, together with a proposal for a regulation on intra-Community transfers of military equipment and a communication on defence industries.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7282">À</DiscourseConnective> ce stade, notre objectif consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7318">à</DiscourseConnective> présenter cette proposition en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7351">tant que</DiscourseConnective> composante d'un "paquet", conjointement avec une proposition de règlement sur les transferts intracommunautaires d'équipements militaires ainsi qu'avec une communication sur les industries de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6264" docOffset="41">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7564" annotation_id="6264">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6264" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we started the reference in the field of defence procurement, Parliament has always been one of our strongest supporters.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6264" annotation_id="7564">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7564" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Depuis</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le moment où nous nous sommes mis à nous occuper des acquisitions d'équipements de défense, le Parlement a toujours été l'un de nos plus fervents supporters.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6392" docOffset="42">
      <en>This is clearly reflected in Parliament's resolution of 2005.</en>
      <fr>C'est ce qui ressort clairement de la résolution de l'Assemblée de 2005.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6454" docOffset="43">
      <en>I wish to thank you for this and hope that our fruitful cooperation will continue in the future.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7811">à</DiscourseConnective> vous en remercier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7831">et</DiscourseConnective> j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7843">que</DiscourseConnective> notre coopération fructueuse se poursuivra <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7890">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6551" id="419" name="Malcolm Harbour">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6551" docOffset="44">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - Mr President, I wish to begin by welcoming the Commissioner's clear commitment to producing the new directive as soon as possible and by thanking him for outlining a number of important measures on which he and his departments are already working.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, permettez-moi tout d'abord d'exprimer ma satisfaction vis-à-vis de l'engagement clair pris par le commissaire de présenter le plus rapidement possible la nouvelle directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8098">et</DiscourseConnective> de le remercier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8117">pour</DiscourseConnective> avoir souligné un certain nombre de mesures importantes sur lesquelles lui-même <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8202">et</DiscourseConnective> ses services travaillent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8230">déjà</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6832" docOffset="45">
      <en>Clearly, this is a particularly sensitive area because of both its strategic nature and some of the industrial policy issues surrounding the whole defence sector.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agit bien évidemment d'un domaine particulièrement sensible du fait à la fois de sa nature stratégique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8344">et</DiscourseConnective> de certains problèmes liés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8374">à</DiscourseConnective> la politique industrielle qui entourent l'ensemble du secteur de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6995" docOffset="46">
      <en>I should like to raise two particular points, to which the Commissioner could perhaps respond in his winding-up statement.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais formuler deux remarques et j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8501">que</DiscourseConnective> le commissaire pourra éventuellement y répondre dans son intervention finale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7118" docOffset="47">
      <en>Firstly, it is clear that in many areas of defence equipment procurement there are very complex contractual arrangements, in many cases <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7254" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> involving a significant amount of product development.</en>
      <fr>Primo, il est clair <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8603">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il existe dans plusieurs domaines liés aux acquisitions d'équipements de défense des accords contractuels très complexes, qui impliquent souvent une proportion importante de conception de produits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7314" docOffset="48">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8804" annotation_id="7314">
          <Alignment alignment="12477" annotation_id="7314">
            <Alignment alignment="8804" annotation_id="7314">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7314" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the specification of the equipment may involve new technology evolutions.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7314" annotation_id="8804">
          <Alignment alignment="7314" annotation_id="8804">
            <Alignment alignment="7314" annotation_id="8804">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8804" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, les caractéristiques des équipements peuvent impliquer de nouvelles évolutions technologiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7404" docOffset="49">
      <en>These arrangements will be very different in many cases from conventional buying contracts, <Alignment alignment="9012" annotation_id="7496">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7496" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="9033" annotation_id="7506">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7506" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I indicated in my response to Mrs McCarthy's report, there is increasing interest in more transparent conditions for these types of contracts.</en>
      <fr>Dans de nombreux cas, ces accords seront très différents des contrats d'achat traditionnels, <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="9012">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9012" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>on constate, <Alignment alignment="7506" annotation_id="9033">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9033" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai signalé dans ma réponse au rapport de Mme McCarthy, un intérêt croissant en faveur d'une transparence accrue de ces types de contrats.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7652" docOffset="50">
      <en>I wonder whether the Commissioner could indicate or confirm that he will be taking these specific strategic needs into account.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9191">que</DiscourseConnective> le commissaire pourra confirmer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9227">ou</DiscourseConnective> faire état de son intention de prendre ces besoins stratégiques spécifiques en considération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7780" docOffset="51">
      <en>The second point, which is a difficult one, is that in many cases defence procurement agreements <Alignment alignment="9489" annotation_id="7877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7877" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have some form of offset agreement attached to them.</en>
      <fr>La seconde <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9335">remarque</DiscourseConnective> - et c'est un problème difficile - concerne le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9396">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans de nombreux cas, les accords d'acquisition d'équipements de défense s'accompagnent <Alignment alignment="7877" annotation_id="9489">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9489" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'une sorte d'accord de compensation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7935" docOffset="52">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9533" annotation_id="7935">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7935" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">For instance</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the procuring countries may be looking for some form of local investment, involving local firms in assembling the equipment.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14247" annotation_id="9533">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9533" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">Par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, les pays acquéreurs peuvent demander que certains investissements soient réalisés sur place, que des entreprises locales soient chargées du montage des équipements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8074" docOffset="53">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8074" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Or</DiscourseConnective>, in some cases, there is a completely different sort of financial offset in terms of an agreement to buy products from a company in another market.</en>
      <fr>Dans d'autres cas, il peut y avoir un type tout à fait différent de compensation financière, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9804">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir un accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9823">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'achat de produits d'une société sur un autre marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8225" docOffset="54">
      <en>These arrangements seem to raise difficult issues in the context of both competition and procurement law, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8331" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I should be grateful <Alignment alignment="40833" annotation_id="8356">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8356" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commissioner could confirm that he will be looking at these in the review of the directive he has promised.</en>
      <fr>Ces accords semblent poser des difficultés dans le cadre de la législation sur la concurrence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9977">et</DiscourseConnective> dans celle relative aux marchés publics. C'est pourquoi je souhaiterais <Alignment alignment="8356" annotation_id="10052">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10052" sense="Contingency.Condition">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le commissaire confirme son intention d'examiner ces problèmes dans le cadre de la révision promise de la directive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8471" id="420" name="Barbara Weiler">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8471" docOffset="55">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (DE) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, this is not only a tricky subject but, astonishingly, <Alignment alignment="10350" annotation_id="8610">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8610" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an area in which Member States are persistently infringing European law.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10259">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, ce n'est pas seulement un sujet épineux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10314">mais</DiscourseConnective>, de manière surprenante, c'est <Alignment alignment="8610" annotation_id="10350">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10350" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un domaine dans lequel les États membres persistent à enfreindre le droit européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8688" docOffset="56">
      <en>The Green Paper was discussed in 2004, Parliament tabled a motion for a resolution in 2006, <Alignment alignment="10537" annotation_id="8780">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8780" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> now we have a new interpretation - <Alignment alignment="10593" annotation_id="8819">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8819" sense="Comparison.Contrast">yet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in reality, hardly anything has changed.</en>
      <fr>Le livre vert a été discuté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10468">en</DiscourseConnective> 2004, le Parlement a avancé une proposition de résolution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10529">en</DiscourseConnective> 2006 <Alignment alignment="8780" annotation_id="10537">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10537" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, à présent, nous avons une nouvelle interprétation - <Alignment alignment="8819" annotation_id="10593">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10593" sense="Comparison.Contrast">pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10603">en réalité</DiscourseConnective>, rien ou presque n'a été modifié.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8865" docOffset="57">
      <en>Member States are continuing to do <Alignment alignment="10684" annotation_id="8900">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8900" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they please.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres continuent d'agir <Alignment alignment="8900" annotation_id="10684">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10684" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> bon leur semble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8916" docOffset="58">
      <en>Has the CFSP failed in this respect?</en>
      <fr>La PESC a-t-elle échoué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10731">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective> ?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8953" docOffset="59">
      <en>I can see no real improvement since 2004.</en>
      <fr>Je n'observe aucune réelle amélioration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10785">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 2004.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8995" docOffset="60">
      <en>Member States and members of national parliaments seem to be completely unaware of Article 296 of the EC Treaty - as, indeed, it describes an exceptional situation rather than the rule.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10816">et</DiscourseConnective> les députés des parlements nationaux semblent ignorer totalement l'article 296 du traité CE - qui, il est vrai, décrit une situation exceptionnelle et non la règle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9181" docOffset="61">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10984" annotation_id="9181">
          <Alignment alignment="10984" annotation_id="9181">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9181" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the European Court of Justice has found once again that this is not a case of a general automatic derogation.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9181" annotation_id="10984">
          <Alignment alignment="9181" annotation_id="10984">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10984" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, la Cour de justice des Communautés européennes a une fois de plus estimé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11067">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11076">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit pas d'un cas de dérogation automatique générale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9304" docOffset="62">
      <en>Yet there is no improvement to be seen, even <Alignment alignment="36961" annotation_id="9349">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9349" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - and this, too, may still be worth mentioning - the group concerned consists of just six Member States.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11132">Pourtant</DiscourseConnective>, aucune amélioration n'est visible, <Alignment alignment="9349" annotation_id="11177">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11177" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11187">et</DiscourseConnective> il convient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11202">aussi</DiscourseConnective> de le mentionner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11225">encore</DiscourseConnective> - le groupe concerné ne compte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11263">que</DiscourseConnective> six États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9461" docOffset="63">
      <en>There, too, I do not currently see any improvement.</en>
      <fr>Là <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11289">non plus</DiscourseConnective>, je ne vois actuellement aucune amélioration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9513" docOffset="64">
      <en>To put it clearly, I do not want any increase in the defence budget; above all, my group wants to see savings by means of cooperation and the use of synergies.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11344">Pour</DiscourseConnective> être claire, je ne veux aucune augmentation du budget alloué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11410">à</DiscourseConnective> la défense ; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11425">avant</DiscourseConnective> toute chose, mon groupe appelle de ses vœux des économies grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11495">à</DiscourseConnective> la coopération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11512">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'utilisation des synergies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9673" docOffset="65">
      <en>Parliament has made some recommendations in this regard, <Alignment alignment="11605" annotation_id="9730">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9730" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on the components the new Code of Conduct should have.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement a émis certaines recommandations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11592">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="14240" annotation_id="11605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11605" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sur les éléments qui devraient composer le nouveau code de conduite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9797" docOffset="66">
      <en>Perhaps the Commissioner could add something in this regard?</en>
      <fr>Le commissaire pourrait-il peut-être ajouter quelque chose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11745">à ce propos</DiscourseConnective> ?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9858" docOffset="67">
      <en>We have <Alignment alignment="11770" annotation_id="9866">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9866" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> requested better cooperation from the Commission - and not only the Commission, but also the European Defence Agency.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="9866" annotation_id="11770">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11770" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> réclamé une meilleure coopération de la part de la Commission - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11844">et</DiscourseConnective> pas seulement de la Commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11879">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> de l'Agence européenne de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9989" docOffset="68">
      <en>I cannot see much evidence of this in reality.</en>
      <fr>Je n'en vois pas le moindre signe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11959">en réalité</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10036" docOffset="69">
      <en>I should like to reiterate that we have made suggestions on the mechanisms for the competitive award of contracts the Commission still needs to change for us to finally achieve what everyone in this House wants.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais réitérer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11992">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons formulé des suggestions sur les mécanismes d'attribution des contrats sur une base concurrentielle que la Commission doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12129">encore</DiscourseConnective> modifier pour que nous puissions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12169">enfin</DiscourseConnective> parvenir à ce que cette Assemblée souhaite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10248" docOffset="70">
      <en>After all, we agree with the Commission that a genuine European defence market is necessary to reduce military expenditure costs and to make production more efficient in the interests of the taxpayer and the public.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12219">Après tout</DiscourseConnective>, nous sommes d'accord avec la Commission pour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12276">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>un véritable marché européen de la défense est nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12342">pour</DiscourseConnective> réduire les dépenses militaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12379">et</DiscourseConnective> rendre la production plus efficace dans l'intérêt des contribuables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12450">et</DiscourseConnective> des citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10464" id="421" language="DE" name="Alexander Lambsdorff">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10464" docOffset="71">
      <en>Mr President, Commissioner, Chairman, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to start by giving my sincere thanks to the Commissioner for his speech clarifying the current position of the Commission on this subject.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12547">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais commencer par adresser mes sincères remerciements au commissaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12638">pour</DiscourseConnective> son discours, qui est venu clarifier la position actuelle de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12718">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10677" docOffset="72">
      <en>He pointed out that Parliament is a good ally of the Commission's, <Alignment alignment="12796" annotation_id="10744">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10744" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="12800" annotation_id="10748">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10748" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">indeed</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we do support his view that a more transparent, effective and open European defence market is an important objective, with a view both to strengthening the sector in Europe and to further objectives.</en>
      <fr>Il a indiqué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12743">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement était un bon allié de la Commission <Alignment alignment="10744" annotation_id="12796">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12796" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="10748" annotation_id="12800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12800" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous soutenons son point de vue selon lequel une marché européen de la défense qui soit plus transparent, plus efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12930">et</DiscourseConnective> plus ouvert constitue un objectif capital, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12976">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> renforcer ce secteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13007">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13017">et</DiscourseConnective> de réaliser d'autres objectifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10955" docOffset="73">
      <en>I believe that what I have just said goes for all my fellow Members: I would point to the broad consensus we achieved on our resolution on the Green Paper.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13061">que</DiscourseConnective> ce que je viens de dire vaut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13094">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous mes collègues. J'en veux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13129">pour preuve</DiscourseConnective> le large consensus que nous avons pu dégager <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13186">quant à</DiscourseConnective> notre résolution sur le livre vert.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11111" docOffset="74">
      <en>We learn with interest that the work on the Directive on the procurement of defence equipment is well advanced <Alignment alignment="13355" annotation_id="11222">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11222" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the Commission intends to present a proposal in autumn.</en>
      <fr>Nous apprenons avec intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13258">que</DiscourseConnective> les travaux relatifs à la directive sur les marchés d'équipements de défense ont bien avancé <Alignment alignment="11222" annotation_id="13355">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13355" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13358">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission envisage de présenter une proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13414">en</DiscourseConnective> automne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11287" docOffset="75">
      <en>Mrs Weiler has just pointed out that defence markets are still largely national in character.</en>
      <fr>Mme Weiler vient tout juste de préciser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13466">que</DiscourseConnective> les marchés de la défense étaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13504">encore</DiscourseConnective> de nature très nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11381" docOffset="76">
      <en>The State is the only relevant bidder for defence equipment, <Alignment alignment="13609" annotation_id="11442">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11442" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is true that, in the case of many award decisions, recourse is still taken to legal bases that are questionable, to say the least.</en>
      <fr>L'État est le seul vrai soumissionnaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13577">pour</DiscourseConnective> les équipements de défense <Alignment alignment="11442" annotation_id="13609">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13609" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13624">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans le cas de bon nombre de décisions d'attribution, il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13690">encore</DiscourseConnective> fait recours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13710">à</DiscourseConnective> des bases juridiques discutables, c'est le moins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13761">qu'</DiscourseConnective>on puisse dire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11580" docOffset="77">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24610" annotation_id="11580">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11580" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I agree with Mrs Weiler: there is little support for increasing the defence budget.</en>
      <fr>Je rejoins <Alignment alignment="11580" annotation_id="13791">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13791" sense="Comparison.Contrast">néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Mme Weiler: l'augmentation du budget de la défense ne rallie guère les foules.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11673" docOffset="78">
      <en>I believe that this draft Directive takes exactly the right course, namely increasing the efficiency reserve in the European armaments industry, ending the fragmentation of the market, and really improving efficiency and achieving economies of scale.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13889">que</DiscourseConnective> ce projet de directive prend exactement la bonne direction, à savoir qu'il réclame que la réserve d'efficacité dans l'industrie européenne de l'armement soit augmentée, qu'un terme soit mis à la fragmentation du marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14112">et</DiscourseConnective> que l'efficacité soit réellement renforcée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14158">et</DiscourseConnective> que des économies d'échelle soient réalisées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11924" docOffset="79">
      <en>That is why we welcome the Commissioner's remarks on expected growth and on increased competitiveness on the European defence equipment market.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14207">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous nous félicitons des remarques du commissaire sur les perspectives de croissance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14307">et</DiscourseConnective> sur la compétitivité accrue du marché européen des équipements de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12068" docOffset="80">
      <en>I believe that this will <Alignment alignment="14410" annotation_id="12093">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12093" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have a positive effect on the trained labour market.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14394">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles auront <Alignment alignment="12093" annotation_id="14410">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14410" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un effet positif sur le marché du travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12151" docOffset="81">
      <en>We need a clear definition of the equipment covered by the derogation.</en>
      <fr>Il nous faut une définition claire des équipements couverts par la dérogation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12222" docOffset="82">
      <en>The existing regulations are indeed insufficient to meet the particular needs of the defence equipment market.</en>
      <fr>Les réglementations existantes sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14574">en effet</DiscourseConnective> insuffisantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14597">pour</DiscourseConnective> répondre aux besoins spécifiques du marché des équipements de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12333" docOffset="83">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14673" annotation_id="12333">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12333" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we <Alignment alignment="44439" annotation_id="12347">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12347" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcome the Commission's initiative to adapt the rules to the state of affairs on the defence equipment market and to strive for greater flexibility in this regard.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9620" annotation_id="14673">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14673" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous saluons <Alignment alignment="12347" annotation_id="14701">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14701" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'initiative de la Commission, qui consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14755">à</DiscourseConnective> adapter les règles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14776">à</DiscourseConnective> la situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14791">de fait</DiscourseConnective> du marché des équipements de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14836">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14839">à</DiscourseConnective> se démener pour parvenir à une meilleure flexibilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14894">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12517" docOffset="84">
      <en>I would be grateful <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12537" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> the Commissioner could tell us why he decided to adapt general public procurement law instead of presenting a separate directive.</en>
      <fr>Je serais reconnaissant au commissaire de bien vouloir nous expliquer pourquoi il a décidé d'adapter le droit des marchés publics généraux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15046">plutôt que de</DiscourseConnective> présenter une directive séparée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12670" docOffset="85">
      <en>This may well be appropriate, <Alignment alignment="15134" annotation_id="12700">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12700" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I should like him to say a few words about this.</en>
      <fr>Cette décision est peut-être judicieuse, <Alignment alignment="12700" annotation_id="15134">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15134" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je serais ravi qu'il la commente brièvement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12753" docOffset="86">
      <en>The bottom line is that we agree with the Commissioner <Alignment alignment="21236" annotation_id="12808">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12808" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he says that the opening-up of this market will increase transparency and competition and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12903" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> ultimately reduce the burden on taxpayers.</en>
      <fr>Au fond, nous sommes d'accord avec le commissaire <Alignment alignment="12808" annotation_id="15234">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15234" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15248">que</DiscourseConnective> l'ouverture de ce marché augmentera la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15304">et</DiscourseConnective> la concurrence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15322">et</DiscourseConnective>, en dernière analyse, réduira la charge <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15365">pour</DiscourseConnective> les contribuables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12951" docOffset="87">
      <en>Finally, I should like to emphasise that, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12993" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> I see it, this draft Directive is far more important than any considerations of industrial or internal-market policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15389">Pour terminer</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15426">que</DiscourseConnective>, selon moi, ce projet de directive est bien plus important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15489">que</DiscourseConnective> toutes les considérations relatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15529">à</DiscourseConnective> la politique industrielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15557">ou</DiscourseConnective> du marché intérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13114" docOffset="88">
      <en>It will contribute to the development of European security and defence policy, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13193" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> bringing about progress in what is traditionally a core domain of national sovereignty.</en>
      <fr>Il contribuera au développement de la politique européenne de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15652">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense, faisant ainsi progresser un domaine qui a toujours relevé de la souveraineté nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13286" docOffset="89">
      <en>The Directive will bring about progress that may not be revolutionary, but is hopefully measurable, towards a European Security and Defence Policy truly deserving of the name.</en>
      <fr>Les progrès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15767">que</DiscourseConnective> la directive engendrera ne seront peut-être pas révolutionnaires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15837">mais</DiscourseConnective> il est à espérer qu'ils seront mesurables, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15885">en vue d'</DiscourseConnective>une politique étrangère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15918">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité commune véritablement digne de ce nom.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13462" docOffset="90">
      <en>I would like to add that I would be obliged <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13506" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>, in future, such debates were held in Brussels and not in Strasbourg.</en>
      <fr>Autre chose : j'apprécierais qu'à l'avenir, ces débats aient lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16038">à</DiscourseConnective> Bruxelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16050">et</DiscourseConnective> non <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16057">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13579" id="422" name="Leopold Józef Rutowicz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13579" docOffset="91">
      <en>on behalf of the UEN Group. - (PL) Mr President, each year, around EUR 180 billion are spent on defence within the borders of the European Union's common market.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe UEN. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, chaque année, près de 180 milliards d'euros sont consacrés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16182">à</DiscourseConnective> la défense à l'intérieur des frontières du marché commun de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13741" docOffset="92">
      <en>Almost half of this amount is not subject to the public procurement legislation currently in force.</en>
      <fr>Près de la moitié de cette somme n'est pas soumise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16315">à</DiscourseConnective> la législation des marchés publics actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16365">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13841" docOffset="93">
      <en>We need to analyse this situation, which has resulted from the application of Article 296 of the Treaty in relation to public procurement in the field of defence.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons analyser cette situation, qui découle de l'application de l'article 296 du Traité relatif aux marchés publics dans le domaine de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14004" docOffset="94">
      <en>The Communication has partly clarified the issue.</en>
      <fr>La communication à l'examen a partiellement clarifié la situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14054" docOffset="95">
      <en>In view of the specific nature of the arms manufacturing industry and the need to integrate it into the defence policies of specific Member States of the European Union and NATO, we need to ensure the technical compatibility of the equipment and communication systems, as well as the proper compatibility of equipment and appliances.</en>
      <fr>Compte tenu de la nature spécifique du secteur manufacturier des armes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16668">et</DiscourseConnective> de la nécessité de l'intégrer aux politiques de défense de certains États membres de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16775">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'OTAN, nous devons garantir la compatibilité technique des équipements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16853">et</DiscourseConnective> systèmes de communication, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16883">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la bonne comptabilité des équipements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16931">et</DiscourseConnective> appareils.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14388" docOffset="96">
      <en>We need greater cooperation between individual countries, a properly functioning defence industry and well organised supplies.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons besoin d'une meilleure coopération entre les différents pays, d'une industrie de la défense qui fonctionne bien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17068">et</DiscourseConnective> d'approvisionnements bien organisés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14515" docOffset="97">
      <en>The objective of our activities should be to draw up a directive on public procurement in the defence sector.</en>
      <fr>L'objectif de nos activités devrait être de rédiger une directive sur les marchés publics dans le secteur de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14625" docOffset="98">
      <en>A stable arms market and stability with respect to the procurement procedures used will have a positive effect on the sector, in terms of employment and efficiency.</en>
      <fr>Un marché des armes stable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17256">et</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité au niveau des procédures d'attribution des marchés auront un effet positif sur le secteur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17363">en</DiscourseConnective> termes d'emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17382">et</DiscourseConnective> d'efficacité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14790" id="423" name="Andreas Schwab">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14790" docOffset="99">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the basis for today's debate is the report by our former colleague Mr Würmeling.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17436">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, la base du débat d'aujourd'hui est le rapport de notre ancien collègue, M. Würmeling.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14912" docOffset="100">
      <en>It was on this basis that the Commission issued its communication at the end of last year, which was intended to clarify the application of Article 296 but <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15068" sense="Comparison.Contrast">in fact</DiscourseConnective> had little effect.</en>
      <fr>C'est sur cette base <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17557">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission a publié sa communication <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17601">à</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'année dernière, laquelle avait pour objectif de clarifier l'application de l'article 296, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17705">mais</DiscourseConnective> n'a eu guère d'effet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15095" docOffset="101">
      <en>After all, it was initially geared exclusively towards non-military goods, <Alignment alignment="17819" annotation_id="15170">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15170" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="35479" annotation_id="15174">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15174" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the majority of military procurements inevitably fell within the scope of this derogation.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17732">Après tout</DiscourseConnective>, elle était à l'origine uniquement axée sur les marchandises non militaires <Alignment alignment="15170" annotation_id="17819">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17819" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="15174" annotation_id="17823">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17823" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la majeure partie des contrats militaires tombaient inévitablement dans le champ d'application de cette dérogation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15270" docOffset="102">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15270" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>, it is really up to the Commission to ensure that, firstly, the rules on public procurement in the defence sector really support the work of the European Defence Agency <Alignment alignment="18177" annotation_id="15449">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15449" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, secondly, that they take account of the fact that, <Alignment alignment="18233" annotation_id="15505">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15505" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> many of the previous speakers have said, this is a sector that exhibits peculiarities.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle il revient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17996">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission de garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18024">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18029">premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, les règles sur les marchés publics dans le secteur de la défense soutiennent vraiment les activités de l'Agence européenne de défense <Alignment alignment="15449" annotation_id="18177">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18177" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18181">deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18195">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles tiennent compte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18220">du fait que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="16538" annotation_id="18233">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18233" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> quantité d'orateurs précédents l'ont signalé, ce secteur présente des particularités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15595" docOffset="103">
      <en>I have three questions for Commissioner McCreevy, <Alignment alignment="46095" annotation_id="15645">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15645" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</en>
      <fr>J'aurais <Alignment alignment="15645" annotation_id="18334">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18334" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> trois questions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18355">à</DiscourseConnective> poser au commissaire McCreevy.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15656" docOffset="104">
      <en>Firstly, does a directive in this field not have the flaw from the outset that it is based on a communication that was originally intended to cover only non-military goods, and is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15836" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">consequently</DiscourseConnective> unable to achieve what we expect of it <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15888" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> regards the common security policy?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18388">Tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective>, une directive dans ce domaine n'est-elle pas d'emblée bancale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18464">du fait qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle se fonde sur une communication à l'origine destinée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18532">à</DiscourseConnective> couvrir uniquement des marchandises non militaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18585">et</DiscourseConnective>, partant, incapable de satisfaire nos attentes concernant la politique de sécurité commune ?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15927" docOffset="105">
      <en>Secondly, would it not be possible to update the 1958 list, which sets out the derogations relatively clearly but is now out of date?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18681">Ensuite</DiscourseConnective>, n'est-il pas possible de mettre à jour la liste de 1958, qui définit les dérogations avec assez de clarté, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18797">mais</DiscourseConnective> est aujourd'hui dépassée ?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16061" docOffset="106">
      <en>Has the Commission abandoned the task of updating this for good?</en>
      <fr>La Commission a-t-elle renoncé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18860">pour</DiscourseConnective> de bon à la mettre à jour ?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16126" docOffset="107">
      <en>Thirdly, the Commissioner rightly said that normal public procurement law is not suited to the defence sector.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18893">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, le commissaire a dit à juste titre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18935">que</DiscourseConnective> la législation normale des marchés publics n'était pas adaptée au secteur de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16237" docOffset="108">
      <en>Following on from Mr Lambsdorff's question, I would be very interested to hear how the Commissioner intends to take account of the peculiarities of the defence sector in a directive.</en>
      <fr>Pour faire suite à la question de M. Lambsdorff, je serais curieux de savoir comment le commissaire projette de prendre en considération les particularités du secteur de la défense dans une directive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16420" id="424" name="Karl von Wogau">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16420" docOffset="109">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, each year, the 27 Member States of the European Union spend EUR 170 billion on defence.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19291">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, chaque année, les 27 États membres de l'Union européenne dépensent 170 milliards d'euros <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19394">pour</DiscourseConnective> la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16563" docOffset="110">
      <en>These 27 Member States have two million soldiers, 10 000 tanks and 3 000 fighter aircraft.</en>
      <fr>Ces 27 États membres comptent deux millions de soldats, 10 000 tanks <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19480">et</DiscourseConnective> 3 000 avions de chasse, ce qui n'a toutefois pas suffi à mettre un terme au bain de sang dans le cadre du conflit des Balkans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16654" docOffset="111">
      <en>In spite of this, they could not end the bloodshed in the Balkan conflict; we needed our American friends to do it for us.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons eu besoin de nos amis les Américains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19658">pour</DiscourseConnective> le faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19672">à</DiscourseConnective> notre place.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16777" docOffset="112">
      <en>Why was that?</en>
      <fr>Pourquoi ?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16791" docOffset="113">
      <en>At that time there were not yet any common decision-making structures in the EU to enable the implementation of such operations.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19698">À</DiscourseConnective> l'époque, il n'existait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19724">encore</DiscourseConnective> aucune structure commune de prise de décision au sein de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19793">pour</DiscourseConnective> permettre la mise en œuvre de telles opérations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16920" docOffset="114">
      <en>Another of the main reasons for the inefficiency of European defence is the lack of a common defence market.</en>
      <fr>Une autre des raisons majeures de l'inefficacité de la défense européenne est l'absence de marché commun de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17029" docOffset="115">
      <en>One of the reasons for this is Article 296.</en>
      <fr>En cause notamment : l'article 296.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17073" docOffset="116">
      <en>I am convinced that this Article will be retained in future.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20021">que</DiscourseConnective> cet article sera retenu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20049">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17134" docOffset="117">
      <en>The reason that no common European defence market has developed is the excessive application of this Article in the past.</en>
      <fr>Si le marché européen commun de la défense ne s'est pas développé, c'est en raison de l'application excessive de cet article par le passé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17256" docOffset="118">
      <en>First of all, the Commission issued its communication clarifying what is <Alignment alignment="20278" annotation_id="17329">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17329" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> what is not covered by Article 296: I think this communication is helpful.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20200">Tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective>, la Commission a publié sa communication en précisant ce qui est <Alignment alignment="17329" annotation_id="20278">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20278" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce qui n'est pas couvert par l'article 296 : je pense que cette communication est utile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17408" docOffset="119">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20370" annotation_id="17408">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17408" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Defence Agency took action: in my opinion, the Code of Conduct it adopted was an important step in the right direction.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10262" annotation_id="20370">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20370" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'Agence européenne de défense a réagi : selon moi, le code de conduite qu'elle a adopté constituait un pas important dans la bonne direction.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17546" docOffset="120">
      <en>We now <Alignment alignment="44896" annotation_id="17553">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17553" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> need EU legislation in this field, <Alignment alignment="32600" annotation_id="17593">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17593" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - which is why I welcome the fact that this Directive is now envisaged.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, nous avons <Alignment alignment="17553" annotation_id="20546">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20546" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> besoin d'une législation européenne dans ce domaine, <Alignment alignment="17593" annotation_id="20605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20605" sense="Comparison.Contrast">néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20616">et</DiscourseConnective> voilà pourquoi je me félicite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20649">que</DiscourseConnective> cette directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20669">soit</DiscourseConnective> désormais projetée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17673" docOffset="121">
      <en>As MEPs, we keep hearing a great deal of criticism of the EU rules on the award of public contracts, particularly from local authorities.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20697">tant que</DiscourseConnective> députés européens, nous ne cessons d'entendre des critiques au sujet des règles européennes sut l'attribution des contrats publics, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20838">surtout</DiscourseConnective> de la part des autorités locales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17811" docOffset="122">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20880" annotation_id="17811">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17811" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we MEPs shall take very great care that the rules established here are indeed tailored towards the defence field, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17936" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that they improve rather than worsen the situation in that field.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17811" annotation_id="20880">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20880" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20896">en</DiscourseConnective> tant que députés européens, nous devons veiller très attentivement à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20971">que</DiscourseConnective> les règles définies ici soient bel et bien adaptées au secteur de la défense et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21055">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles améliorent la situation dans ce domaine, et non l'inverse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18006" docOffset="123">
      <en>Our assent will be conditional on this.</en>
      <fr>Notre approbation en dépendra.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18046" docOffset="124">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21154" annotation_id="18046">
          <Alignment alignment="21154" annotation_id="18046">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18046" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, we keep hearing that we Europeans are spending too little on defence.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18046" annotation_id="21154">
          <Alignment alignment="18046" annotation_id="21154">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21154" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, nous ne cessons d'entendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21191">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe dépense trop peu d'argent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21230">pour</DiscourseConnective> la dépense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18129" docOffset="125">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21247" annotation_id="18129">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18129" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we continue working on this field and create a common market, we shall at least achieve more security for the same money.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18129" annotation_id="21247">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21247" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous continuons d'y travailler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21281">et</DiscourseConnective> que nous créons un marché commun, nous obtiendrons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21335">au moins</DiscourseConnective> plus de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21361">pour</DiscourseConnective> le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21369">même</DiscourseConnective> montant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18254" id="425" name="Charlie McCreevy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18254" docOffset="126">
      <en>Mr President, in response to comments by Mr Harbour, Mr Lambsdorff and Mr Schwab, I can confirm that the very aim of a dedicated directive on defence procurement is to take account of the specificity of the defence market.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21406">en</DiscourseConnective> réponse aux remarques formulées par MM. Harbour, Lambsdorff <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21469">et</DiscourseConnective> Schwab, je confirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21492">que</DiscourseConnective> le but <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21503">même</DiscourseConnective> d'une directive spécifique sur les acquisitions d'équipements de défense consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21590">à</DiscourseConnective> tenir compte de la spécificité du marché de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18477" docOffset="127">
      <en>We recognise that the existing framework is ill-adapted to the defence market.</en>
      <fr>Nous admettons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21663">que</DiscourseConnective> le cadre actuel est mal adapté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21698">à</DiscourseConnective> ce secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18556" docOffset="128">
      <en>Clearly, the fundamental principles of public procurement rules will have to apply, <Alignment alignment="21820" annotation_id="18640">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18640" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> defence presents specific requirements in terms of security of supply, security of information or the need to have negotiated procedure.</en>
      <fr>Il est évident que les principes fondamentaux des règles relatives aux marchés publics devront s'appliquer, <Alignment alignment="18640" annotation_id="21820">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21820" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le secteur de la défense présente des exigences spécifiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21885">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de sécurité d'approvisionnement, de sécurité des informations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21958">ou</DiscourseConnective> en ce qui concerne la nécessité de recourir à une procédure négociée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18781" docOffset="129">
      <en>Mr Harbour <Alignment alignment="34643" annotation_id="18792">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18792" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> raised the question about offsets, which is a very complex issue.</en>
      <fr>M. Harbour a <Alignment alignment="18792" annotation_id="22044">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22044" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> soulevé la question des compensations, qui est un problème très complexe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18863" docOffset="130">
      <en>Offsets are economic compensations, which most Member States require from non-national suppliers <Alignment alignment="22241" annotation_id="18960">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18960" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they buy military equipment abroad.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22127">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de compensations économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22163">que</DiscourseConnective> la plupart des États membres exigent de la part de fournisseurs étrangers <Alignment alignment="18960" annotation_id="22241">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22241" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils achètent des équipements militaires dans un autre pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19001" docOffset="131">
      <en>They are legally problematic, politically controversial and economically questionable.</en>
      <fr>Ces compensations posent des problèmes sur le plan juridique, elles soulèvent des controverses sur le plan politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22425">et</DiscourseConnective> elles sont contestables sur le plan économique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19088" docOffset="132">
      <en>Direct offsets are directly related to the subject of the procurement contract, they can sometimes be covered by Article 296, <Alignment alignment="22608" annotation_id="19214">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19214" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the procurement contract itself is exempted on the basis of that article.</en>
      <fr>Les compensations directes sont directement liées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22526">à</DiscourseConnective> l'objet du contrat d'achat; elles peuvent parfois être visées par l'article 296 <Alignment alignment="19214" annotation_id="22608">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22608" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le contrat d'achat lui-même fait l'objet d'une dérogation sur la base de cet article.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19291" docOffset="133">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="22697" annotation_id="19291">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19291" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the huge majority of offsets are indirect and non-military in nature.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19291" annotation_id="22697">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22697" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la grande majorité des compensations sont indirectes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22761">et</DiscourseConnective>, par nature, ne sont pas liées au domaine militaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19370" docOffset="134">
      <en>From the Commission's viewpoint, these offsets are not covered by Article 296.</en>
      <fr>De l'avis de la Commission, ces compensations ne sont pas visées par l'article 296.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19449" docOffset="135">
      <en>They must respect Community law, even <Alignment alignment="22954" annotation_id="19487">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19487" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are related to defence contracts exempted on the basis of Article 296.</en>
      <fr>Elles doivent respecter la législation communautaire <Alignment alignment="19487" annotation_id="22954">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22954" sense="Contingency.Condition">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elles ne sont pas liées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22986">à</DiscourseConnective> des contrats de défense faisant l'objet d'une dérogation sur la base de l'article 296.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19566" docOffset="136">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28469" annotation_id="19566">
          <Alignment alignment="23075" annotation_id="19566">
            <Alignment alignment="27917" annotation_id="19566">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19566" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, offsets are a problem in themselves, even in the area covered by Article 296.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19566" annotation_id="23075">
          <Alignment alignment="19566" annotation_id="23075">
            <Alignment alignment="19566" annotation_id="23075">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23075" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, les compensations sont un problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23130">en</DiscourseConnective> soi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23138">même</DiscourseConnective> dans le domaine visé par cet article.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19660" docOffset="137">
      <en>Addressing this problem via the Defence Directive would only cover the Community part of the defence market and would leave indirect offsets for contracts exempted on the basis of Article 296 untouched.</en>
      <fr>S'attaquer à ce problème via la directive sur la défense ne couvrirait que la partie communautaire du marché de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23304">et</DiscourseConnective> cela n'aurait aucune influence sur les compensations indirectes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23371">pour</DiscourseConnective> des contrats faisant l'objet d'une dérogation sur la base de l'article 296.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19863" docOffset="138">
      <en>In conclusion, <Alignment alignment="33587" annotation_id="19878">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19878" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I said earlier, the opening-up of national defence markets will lead to important economic gains and will ultimately benefit all taxpayers.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23452">En</DiscourseConnective> conclusion - <Alignment alignment="19878" annotation_id="23468">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23468" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai dit précédemment -, l'ouverture des marchés nationaux de la défense entraînera des gains économiques importants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23591">et</DiscourseConnective> profitera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23604">en fin de compte</DiscourseConnective> à l'ensemble des contribuables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20021" docOffset="139">
      <en>In order to achieve this we need to create a new legal framework, which adapts certain Community procurement rules to the specificities of defence.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23653">Pour ce faire</DiscourseConnective>, nous devons créer un nouveau cadre juridique qui adaptera certaines règles communautaires en matière d'acquisitions aux spécificités du secteur de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20169" docOffset="140">
      <en>This new directive will give national authorities greater flexibility <Alignment alignment="3252" annotation_id="20239">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20239" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they make sensitive procurements.</en>
      <fr>Cette nouvelle directive donnera une plus grande flexibilité aux autorités nationales <Alignment alignment="20239" annotation_id="23913">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23913" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles feront des achats sensibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20278" id="426" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20278" docOffset="141">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
