<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>8.</en>
    <fr>8.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) (vote)</en>
    <fr>Normes comptables internationales d'information financière (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="61" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Motion for a resolution</en>
    <fr>- Proposition de résolution</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="87" docOffset="3">
    <en>- Before the vote</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="99">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="105" id="146" name="Pervenche Berès">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="105" docOffset="4">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs should like, on the basis of Rule 170(4) of our Rules of Procedure, to have the vote on this resolution postponed until the second part-session in September.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, la commission économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="161">et</DiscourseConnective> monétaire souhaite, sur la base de l'article 170, paragraphe 4, de notre règlement, le report du vote de cette résolution à la seconde session de septembre prochain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="329" docOffset="5">
      <en>The aim of this postponement is to adapt our timetable to the new timetable set at our request by the Commission services for approval of the IFRS 8 accounting standard as a replacement for the IAS 14 standard.</en>
      <fr>Ce report vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="345">à</DiscourseConnective> adapter notre calendrier au nouveau calendrier arrêté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="401">à</DiscourseConnective> notre demande par les services de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="451">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'approbation de la norme comptable IFRS 8 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="499">en</DiscourseConnective> remplacement de la norme IAS 14.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="540" docOffset="6">
      <en>The Commission proposal to adopt IFRS 8 would mean incorporating the equivalent US accounting standard into European law without an impact study on the effect of applying such a standard to European listed companies having been carried out.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de la Commission d'approuver l'IFRS 8 signifierait l'incorporation de la norme comptable américaine équivalente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="662">en</DiscourseConnective> droit européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="680">sans qu'</DiscourseConnective>une étude d'impact <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="707">quant à</DiscourseConnective> l'effet de l'application d'une telle norme aux sociétés cotées européennes n'ait été réalisée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="781" docOffset="7">
      <en>The Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs would like to point out that the convergence of IFRS financial reporting standards and US GAAP - which Commissioner McCreevy is so keen to see happen - must result in standards that make it possible to produce better quality financial information.</en>
      <fr>La commission économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="835">et</DiscourseConnective> monétaire voudrait rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="866">que</DiscourseConnective> la convergence entre les normes comptables IFRS <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="918">et</DiscourseConnective> US GAAP, ardemment voulue par le commissaire McCreevy, doit conduire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="990">à</DiscourseConnective> des normes permettant une information financière de meilleure qualité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1076" docOffset="8">
      <en>Real convergence means much more, for the one party, than simply copying the financial reporting standards of the other party.</en>
      <fr>La convergence réelle signifie bien plus que, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1109">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'une des parties, de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1136">simplement</DiscourseConnective> copier les normes comptables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1176">de l'autre</DiscourseConnective> partie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1203" docOffset="9">
      <en>In this context, the Commission services have agreed to review their timetable, and have <Alignment alignment="1292" annotation_id="1292">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1292" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> consented to an impact study being carried out.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte, les services de la Commission ont accepté de revoir leur calendrier autorisant <Alignment alignment="1292" annotation_id="1292">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1292" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la réalisation d'une étude d'impact.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1345" docOffset="10">
      <en>This information was communicated to us by letter last night.</en>
      <fr>Cette information nous a été communiquée par courrier hier soir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1407" docOffset="11">
      <en>The Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs would <Alignment alignment="1447" annotation_id="1460">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1460" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to point out that the Commission proposals on implementing measures - at the very least in the financial sphere - including financial reporting standards, must be examined within a three-month period.</en>
      <fr>La commission économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1425">et</DiscourseConnective> monétaire voudrait <Alignment alignment="1455" annotation_id="1447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1447" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1462">que</DiscourseConnective> les propositions de la Commission en matière de mesures d'application, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1537">à</DiscourseConnective> tout le moins dans le domaine financier, y compris les normes d'informations financières, doivent être examinées dans un délai de 3 mois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1671" docOffset="12">
      <en>We should like it <Alignment alignment="566455" annotation_id="1689">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1689" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commission could resubmit this implementing measure, accompanied by the results of this impact study <Alignment alignment="1804" annotation_id="1797">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1797" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> requested, before our Committee on 10 September, <Alignment alignment="570193" annotation_id="1851">
          <Alignment alignment="1869" annotation_id="1851">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1851" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> our Parliament might definitively validate or <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1905" sense="Expansion.Alternative">otherwise</DiscourseConnective> the application of this standard in European law.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons <Alignment alignment="1689" annotation_id="1693">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1693" sense="Contingency.Condition">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission puisse représenter cette mesure d'application assortie des résultats de cette étude d'impact <Alignment alignment="1640" annotation_id="1804">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1804" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demandée devant notre commission le 10 septembre prochain, <Alignment alignment="570" annotation_id="1869">
          <Alignment alignment="1851" annotation_id="1869">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1869" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> notre Parlement puisse, lors de sa session de septembre, valider <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1943">ou</DiscourseConnective> non définitivement l'application de cette norme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1994">en</DiscourseConnective> droit européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1965" docOffset="13">
      <en>(Parliament decided to postpone the vote)</en>
      <fr>(Le Parlement décide le report du vote)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
