<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Tribute</en>
    <fr>Éloge funèbre</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I have the sad duty of informing you of the deaths of a fellow Member and a former fellow Member.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, j'ai le triste devoir de vous informer du décès d'un de nos collègues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="107">et</DiscourseConnective> d'un de nos anciens collègues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="128" docOffset="2">
      <en>Our fellow Member Fausto Correia died yesterday morning.</en>
      <fr>Notre collègue, Fausto Correia, est décédé hier matin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="185" docOffset="3">
      <en>He was born on 29 October 1951 in Coimbra and was only 55 years old.</en>
      <fr>Il était né le 29 octobre 1951 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="227">à</DiscourseConnective> Coimbra <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="237">et</DiscourseConnective> était âgé de 55 ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="254" docOffset="4">
      <en>He leaves a wife and three sons.</en>
      <fr>Il laisse derrière lui une épouse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="295">et</DiscourseConnective> trois fils.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="287" docOffset="5">
      <en>An illustrious career as a barrister, journalist and then a politician in Portugal followed <Alignment alignment="310" annotation_id="379">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="379" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he finished law school at university in his home town of Coimbra.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="379" annotation_id="310">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="310" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">Après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des études de droit dans sa ville natale de Coimbra, il avait poursuivi une brillante carrière d'avocat et de journaliste avant d'entrer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="453">en</DiscourseConnective> politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="451" docOffset="6">
      <en>He was for a long time a Member of the Portuguese Parliament as well as Minster of State under Prime Minister António Guterres.</en>
      <fr>Il a longtemps siégé au parlement portugais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="511">et</DiscourseConnective> a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="516">également</DiscourseConnective> assumé la fonction de ministre d'État sous le Premier ministre António Guterres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="579" docOffset="7">
      <en>He had been a Member of the European Parliament since 2004.</en>
      <fr>Il était député européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="632">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 2004.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="639" docOffset="8">
      <en>Fausto Correia was and remains famous and well-loved in Portugal for his unremitting, life-long mission to establish democracy and his dedication to the core values of fraternity and neighbourliness.</en>
      <fr>Fausto Correia était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="666">et</DiscourseConnective> demeure célèbre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="685">et</DiscourseConnective> chéri au Portugal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="706">pour</DiscourseConnective> avoir, tout au long de sa vie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="741">et</DiscourseConnective> sans relâche, tenté d'établir la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="788">et</DiscourseConnective> pour l'attachement qu'il portait aux valeurs fondamentales de fraternité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="864">et</DiscourseConnective> de bon voisinage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="839" docOffset="9">
      <en>Fausto Correia will be sorely missed by his family, his friends and by us, his fellow Members.</en>
      <fr>Fausto Correia manquera cruellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="921">à</DiscourseConnective> sa famille, à ses amis, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="947">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à nous tous, ses collègues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="934" docOffset="10">
      <en>A book of condolences for messages of sympathy from Members and staff of the European Parliament will be open during this week's sitting on Wednesday and Thursday at the front of the Chamber.</en>
      <fr>Un registre de condoléances dans lequel les membres du personnel du Parlement européen peuvent exprimer leurs marques de sympathie sera ouvert durant la séance de cette semaine mercredi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1170">et</DiscourseConnective> jeudi devant l'hémicycle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1126" docOffset="11">
      <en>It is with great sadness that we learnt of the death of our former fellow Member Christian de la Malène, who was a Member of the European Parliament on two occasions - from 1959 to 1961 and from 1962 to 1994.</en>
      <fr>C'est également avec une grande tristesse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1241">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons appris le décès de notre ancien collègue, Christian de la Malène, qui a siégé au Parlement européen de 1959 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1364">à</DiscourseConnective> 1961 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1371">et</DiscourseConnective> de 1962 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1382">à</DiscourseConnective> 1994.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1335" docOffset="12">
      <en>Christian de la Malène, who was <Alignment alignment="574044" annotation_id="1367">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1367" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a former Minister and Senator under President De Gaulle, died on 26 September at the age of 86.</en>
      <fr>Christian de la Malène, <Alignment alignment="1367" annotation_id="1414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1414" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ancien ministre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1440">et</DiscourseConnective> sénateur sous le Président De Gaulle, est décédé le 26 septembre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1508">à</DiscourseConnective> l'âge de 86 ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1468" docOffset="13">
      <en>As a former Chairman of the Group of European Progressive Democrats and the Group of the European Renewal and Democratic Alliance, Christian de la Malène was a convinced European in heart and mind.</en>
      <fr>Ancien président du Groupe des démocrates européens de progrès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1590">et</DiscourseConnective> du Groupe des rénovateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1619">et</DiscourseConnective> du rassemblement des démocrates européens, Christian de la Malène était un Européen convaincu de cœur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1724">et</DiscourseConnective> d'esprit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1666" docOffset="14">
      <en>He dedicated his long life to a strong and democratic Europe, and a political community.</en>
      <fr>Il a consacré toute sa vie à l'édification d'une Europe forte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1799">et</DiscourseConnective> démocratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1815">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une communauté politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1755" docOffset="15">
      <en>Christian de la Malène was a colleague and friend who will be remembered for his humanism and his political commitment.</en>
      <fr>Christian de la Malène était un collègue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1887">et</DiscourseConnective> ami dont l'humanisme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1911">et</DiscourseConnective> l'engagement politique resteront dans les mémoires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1875" docOffset="16">
      <en>On this note we wish to commemorate him in gratitude.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons donc lui rendre hommage et lui exprimer toute notre gratitude.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1929" docOffset="17">
      <en>A moment's silence, please, in remembrance of our deceased colleague.</en>
      <fr>Une minute de silence, je vous prie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2082">en</DiscourseConnective> souvenir de notre collègue disparu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1999" docOffset="18">
      <en>(The assembly rose and observed one minute's silence).</en>
      <fr>(L'assemblée se lève <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2142">et</DiscourseConnective> observe une minute de silence).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
