<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>'IASCF: Review of the constitution - Public Accountability and the Composition of the IASB Proposals for Change' (debate)</en>
    <fr>»IASCF: Révision de la constitution - responsabilité publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="62">et</DiscourseConnective> composition de l'IASB - propositions de changement» (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="122" id="453" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="122" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the oral question by Pervenche Berès on IASCF: 'Review of the constitution - Public Accountability and the Composition of the IASB Proposals for Change' (B6-0463/2008).</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle la question orale de Pervenche Berès sur l'IASCF: Révision de la constitution - responsabilité publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="253">et</DiscourseConnective> composition de l'IASB - propositions de changement' (B6-0463/2008).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="308" id="454" language="FR" name="Pervenche Berès">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="308" docOffset="2">
      <en>Madam President, Commissioner, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="339" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> it comes to financial reporting standards this Parliament now knows that you have a certain capacity for creativity, for setting up 'do nothing' committees.</en>
      <fr>auteure. - Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, dans le domaine des normes comptables, dorénavant le Parlement européen le sait, vous avez une certaine capacité de créativité, de comité Théodule.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="501" docOffset="3">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="530" annotation_id="501">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="501" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> at the start of this legislative term we questioned you about the statutes and role of EFRAG you invented the Roundtable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="627" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> everybody now knows that it has not fulfilled its remit.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2323" annotation_id="530">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="530" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, au début de cette législature, nous vous avons interpellé sur le statut, le rôle de l'EFRAG, vous avez inventé la table ronde, dont chacun reconnaît aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="700">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle n'a pas rempli son rôle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="688" docOffset="4">
      <en>Faced with proposals from the IASCF trustees about establishing a monitoring group, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="772" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="23319" annotation_id="776">
          <Alignment alignment="11924" annotation_id="776">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="776" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">as soon as</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> some of the members failed to agree with your plans, you put forward the idea of setting up an international accounting advisory group.</en>
      <fr>Face aux propositions des trustees de l'IASCF de mettre en place un groupe de supervision, un monitoring group, <Alignment alignment="776" annotation_id="845">
          <Alignment alignment="9710" annotation_id="845">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="845" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">dès lors qu'</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>un certain nombre de membres ne vous agréent pas, vous proposez de créer un groupe consultatif international d'auditeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="923" docOffset="5">
      <en>Parliament has now got used to your practices.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen est dorénavant habitué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1024">à</DiscourseConnective> vos pratiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="970" docOffset="6">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="35639" annotation_id="970">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="970" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we informed you of this, by taking the initiative for a report on questions relating to IASCF governance, you rushed off to officiate, with your Japanese and American colleagues and with IOSCO, by preparing a press release on 7 November 2007 in which you claimed to be arbitrating in all the problems of governance, rather than awaiting the opportunity to be able to act on the legitimacy and authority of a position taken by the democratic representation of the European Union, or to spell it out the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6758" annotation_id="1041">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1041" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous vous avons alerté, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1073">en</DiscourseConnective> prenant l'initiative d'un rapport sur les questions de gouvernance de l'IASCF, vous vous êtes précipité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1180">pour</DiscourseConnective> arbitrer, avec vos collègues japonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1223">et</DiscourseConnective> américains, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1238">et</DiscourseConnective> avec l'OICV, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1254">en</DiscourseConnective> élaborant, le 7 novembre 2007, un communiqué de presse, une déclaration dans laquelle vous prétendiez arbitrer tous les problèmes de gouvernance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1402">plutôt que d'</DiscourseConnective>attendre l'opportunité de pouvoir vous fonder sur la légitimité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1479">et</DiscourseConnective> l'autorité d'une position élaborée par la représentation démocratique de l'Union européenne, en clair, le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1498" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21110" annotation_id="1498">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1498" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Parliament drew up this position on the initiative of our rapporteur, Mr Radwan, you preferred in March to put the debate back to April for reasons that concern you and for which you take sole responsibility.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1498" annotation_id="1608">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1608" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement européen a élaboré cette position <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1663">à</DiscourseConnective> l'instigation de notre rapporteur, Alexander Radwan, vous avez préféré, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1737">en</DiscourseConnective> mars dernier, reporter ce débat au mois d'avril <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1788">pour</DiscourseConnective> des raisons qui vous concernent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1825">et</DiscourseConnective> dont vous prenez seul la responsabilité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1712" docOffset="8">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1712" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>, on the strength of the April proposals, you had the momentum and the opportunity to officiate on what could have been the European Union's position on the international stage, and to do so on the basis of paragraph 9 of this resolution, which I now read: 'notes that in the abovementioned combined statement of 7 November 2007 the Commission seeks - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2068" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> it did <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2078" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> it concluded a roadmap with the US authorities in April 2006 - to preempt solutions where it would be preferable, in the interests of effectiveness and legitimacy, to have an open consultation process and debate, to which this resolution could be a contribution', you preferred, in the secrecy of your private cabinets and departmental offices, to devise a solution without consulting either the Council or this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Lorsque, sur la base de ces propositions en avril, vous aviez la force et la possibilité d'arbitrer ce que pourrait être la position de l'Union européenne sur la scène internationale, sur la base du paragraphe 9 de cette résolution que je lis: "constate que, comme elle l'avait fait en avril 2006 en convenant d'une feuille de route avec les autorités américaines, la Commission, par la déclaration précitée du 7 novembre 2007, a cherché à imposer anticipativement des solutions là où l'efficacité et la légitimité plaident pour un processus ouvert de consultation et de débat, auquel la présente résolution pourrait contribuer", vous avez préféré, dans le secret de votre cabinet ou de vos services, élaborer une solution sans concertation avec le Conseil ni avec ce Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2507" docOffset="9">
      <en>Commissioner, what have you been doing since 24 April, <Alignment alignment="42628" annotation_id="2562">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2562" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we voted on this resolution?</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2682">qu'</DiscourseConnective>avez-vous fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2700">depuis</DiscourseConnective> le 24 avril dernier, <Alignment alignment="8508" annotation_id="2728">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2728" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons voté cette résolution?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2596" docOffset="10">
      <en>Back <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2601" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> we asked you about the role of the IMF and the World Bank.</en>
      <fr>Nous vous avions à l'époque interpellé sur la place du FMI, de la Banque mondiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2665" docOffset="11">
      <en>Other Members since have questioned you about the activities of the Basel Committee, the European supervisors, in the monitoring-group structures for the IASCF.</en>
      <fr>D'autres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2862">depuis</DiscourseConnective> vous ont interpellé sur la place du Comité de Bâle, des superviseurs européens, dans les structures de supervision, de monitoring group, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3006">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'IASCF.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2826" docOffset="12">
      <en>Faced with such a problem you have yet again come up with a 'do nothing' committee, namely the international accounting advisory group.</en>
      <fr>Face à un tel problème, vous avez à nouveau imaginé un comité Théodule, le groupe consultatif international des auditeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2962" docOffset="13">
      <en>You tell us that this monitoring group should not be increased in size <Alignment alignment="3221" annotation_id="3033">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3033" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that would dilute its authority <Alignment alignment="32374" annotation_id="3073">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3073" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we would no longer have the power to guide the trustees.</en>
      <fr>Vous nous dites : "il ne faut pas augmenter le nombre de ce monitoring group, <Alignment alignment="4792" annotation_id="3221">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3221" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>alors l'autorité serait diluée <Alignment alignment="3073" annotation_id="3261">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3261" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous n'aurions plus aucune compétence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3302">pour</DiscourseConnective> piloter les trustees".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3134" docOffset="14">
      <en>The proposal from the trustees rests on a line-up of seven members.</en>
      <fr>La proposition des trustees repose sur une composition de sept membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3202" docOffset="15">
      <en>Your proposal is based on a team of five, plus one observer and two members whom you would put on this consultative body, this international committee of auditors.</en>
      <fr>Votre proposition repose sur une composition de cinq membres, plus un observateur, plus deux membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3503">que</DiscourseConnective> vous mettriez dans ce comité international des auditeurs qui serait consulté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3366" docOffset="16">
      <en>Our proposal is to consolidate the group of seven being suggested by the trustees by including what is necessary.</en>
      <fr>Notre proposition consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3612">à</DiscourseConnective> conforter le groupe de sept proposé par les trustees, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3668">en</DiscourseConnective> incluant ce qui devrait y figurer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3480" docOffset="17">
      <en>The argument as to the number is irrelevant <Alignment alignment="3743" annotation_id="3524">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3524" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, at the same time, there is a further proposal to increase the number of members on the International Accounting Standards Board itself, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3667" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective> taking it from 14 to 16.</en>
      <fr>L'argument du nombre n'en est pas un <Alignment alignment="3524" annotation_id="3743">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3743" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, par ailleurs dans le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3773">même</DiscourseConnective> moment, est proposée l'augmentation du nombre de membres de l'IASB, du board lui-même, pour passer de quatorze <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3889">à</DiscourseConnective> seize.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3700" docOffset="18">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="16596" annotation_id="3703">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3703" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have two things to say to you today, Commissioner.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3703" annotation_id="3898">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3898" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, aujourd'hui, Monsieur le Commissaire, nous vous disons deux choses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3764" docOffset="19">
      <en>Firstly, <Alignment alignment="3985" annotation_id="3773">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3773" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you really want to reform the governance of the IASB then we are in agreement, for we were the ones that asked you to do it, but please consult us, involve us, and do it from the start, not at the last moment.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3973">D'une part</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="3773" annotation_id="3985">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3985" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez vraiment réformer la gouvernance de l'IASB, nous sommes d'accord, c'est nous qui vous l'avons demandé, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4103">mais</DiscourseConnective> consultez-nous, associez-nous, en amont, pas au dernier moment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3986" docOffset="20">
      <en>Do not tell us that you had urgent work to do in August, <Alignment alignment="4253" annotation_id="4043">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4043" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have been asking you for this since last autumn <Alignment alignment="4311" annotation_id="4099">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4099" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you have been aware of Parliament's position since April.</en>
      <fr>Ne nous dites pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4190">que</DiscourseConnective> vous avez dû travailler au mois d'août de manière urgente, <Alignment alignment="13051" annotation_id="4253">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4253" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous vous interpellons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4286">depuis</DiscourseConnective> l'automne dernier <Alignment alignment="4099" annotation_id="4311">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4311" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4319">depuis</DiscourseConnective> avril, vous connaissez la position du Parlement européen!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4161" docOffset="21">
      <en>What is more, we are telling you that the IASB and IASCF work programmes include a second phase in which the entire instrument has to be reviewed, including the conditions under which the IASCF is to be set up, <Alignment alignment="4602" annotation_id="4372">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4372" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we would suggest that you make the most of this moment to lay down clear conditions for the stability and governance of this entire mechanism <Alignment alignment="4754" annotation_id="4518">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4518" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will finally have a system of governance that is equal to the issues that we are faced with today.</en>
      <fr>Et puis nous vous disons que, dans le programme de travail de l'IASB et de l'IASCF, il y a une deuxième phase, dans laquelle l'ensemble du dispositif doit être revu, y compris les conditions de constitution de l'IASCF <Alignment alignment="3115" annotation_id="4602">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4602" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous vous proposons de profiter de ce moment-là <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4653">pour</DiscourseConnective> poser clairement les conditions de l'équilibre, de la gouvernance, de l'ensemble du dispositif, <Alignment alignment="4518" annotation_id="4754">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4754" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">en vue de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> disposer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4773">enfin</DiscourseConnective> d'un système de gouvernance qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4811">soit</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4816">à</DiscourseConnective> la hauteur des enjeux qui sont les nôtres aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4628" docOffset="22">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4628" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Or</DiscourseConnective> to put it in clearer terms, what accounting standards do we need in order to establish a financial market where the interpretation of the financial reporting standards is on the same wavelength as the economic reality of the situation that is facing us here and elsewhere?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4873">En</DiscourseConnective> clair, quelles sont les normes comptables dont nous avons besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4941">pour</DiscourseConnective> disposer d'un marché financier dont la lecture des normes comptables serait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5022">en</DiscourseConnective> phase avec la réalité économique des situations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5073">que</DiscourseConnective> nous connaissons ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5098">ou</DiscourseConnective> ailleurs?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4904" id="455" name="Charlie McCreevy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4904" docOffset="23">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Madam President, the need to improve the governance of the International Accounting Standards Board (IASB) is something that has long been recognised by the Commission, Parliament and the Council of Ministers.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, la Commission, le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5193">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil de ministres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5220">s'</DiscourseConnective>accordent à <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5234">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut améliorer la gouvernance de l'International Accounting Standards Board (IASB) depuis bien longtemps.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5142" docOffset="24">
      <en>I have highlighted the importance of this on numerous occasions. I have been critical of the IASB's lack of adequate consultation and feedback procedures, as well as the lack of impact assessments for new standards.</en>
      <fr>J'ai insisté sur l'importance de cette amélioration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5403">à</DiscourseConnective> plusieurs reprises en dénonçant l'absence de procédures de concertation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5477">et</DiscourseConnective> de rapport adéquates dans cette organisation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5526">tout comme</DiscourseConnective> le manque d'évaluation d'impact des nouvelles normes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5358" docOffset="25">
      <en>Given the IASB's de facto role as a global standards setter, it is imperative its governance procedures are up to the highest standards.</en>
      <fr>L'IASB s'apparente de facto <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5619">à</DiscourseConnective> une instance globale de normalisation. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5660">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>, ses procédures de gestion doivent impérativement respecter les normes les plus exigeantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5495" docOffset="26">
      <en>I want to get to the situation where we can adopt IFRS standards in the EU with full confidence that the process and content of these standards are exemplary.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5779">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans l'UE, nous puissions adopter les normes IFRS en étant sûrs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5848">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles sont exemplaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5654" docOffset="27">
      <en>That is why, <Alignment alignment="5891" annotation_id="5667">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5667" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I learnt that a revision of the constitution of the IASCF was envisaged, I set as a priority the improvement of governance.</en>
      <fr>Voilà pourquoi, <Alignment alignment="5667" annotation_id="5891">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5891" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ai appris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5911">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une révision de la constitution de l'IASCF était envisagée, j'ai considéré, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5990">en</DiscourseConnective> priorité, l'amélioration de sa gestion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5796" docOffset="28">
      <en>You will recall last November, with my counterparts in the US Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), the Financial Services Agency of Japan and the International Organisation for Securities Commissions, I proposed the creation of a monitoring board to ensure the public accountability of the IASCF.</en>
      <fr>Rappelez-vous qu'en novembre dernier, avec des collègues de la Commission boursière (SEC) américaine, de l'Agence des services financiers japonaise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6181">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'Organisation internationale des commissions de valeurs, j'ai proposé la création d'un conseil de supervision chargé de garantir la responsabilité publique de l'IASCF.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6098" docOffset="29">
      <en>We have made some good progress on this.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons fait du chemin depuis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6139" docOffset="30">
      <en>The IASCF has recently proposed modifying its constitution in order to enter into a formal relationship with the proposed monitoring board.</en>
      <fr>L'IASCF a proposé récemment de modifier sa constitution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6446">afin de</DiscourseConnective> formaliser sa relation avec le conseil de supervision.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6279" docOffset="31">
      <en>It accepts that this Board must have the power to participate in the nomination process of the IASCF Trustees and have the ultimate power to approve their appointment.</en>
      <fr>Elle a accepté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6524">que</DiscourseConnective> ce conseil puisse intervenir dans la procédure de nomination de ses administrateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6612">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6615">que</DiscourseConnective> ce soit elle qui décide de leur nomination en dernier ressort.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6447" docOffset="32">
      <en>It <Alignment alignment="10353" annotation_id="6450">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6450" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> accepts that the monitoring board will be able to address any area of work of either the Trustees or the IASB and refer them for consideration by the IASCF Board of Trustees or by the IASB.</en>
      <fr>L'IASCF accepte <Alignment alignment="6450" annotation_id="6698">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6698" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6708">que</DiscourseConnective> le conseil de supervision puisse contrôler le travail de tous les administrateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6794">et</DiscourseConnective> en faire rapport au conseil d'administration de l'IASCF <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6853">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6856">à</DiscourseConnective> l'IASB.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6645" docOffset="33">
      <en>The IASCF intends to reach a conclusion about these matters in early October, with changes to the IASCF constitution entering into force from 1 January 2009.</en>
      <fr>L'IASCF souhaite conclure la procédure début octobre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6803" docOffset="34">
      <en>This will, in particular, allow the monitoring board to become operational early in 2009.</en>
      <fr>La constitution révisée de l'IASCF entrant en vigueur le 1er janvier 2009, le conseil de supervision pourrait prendre ses fonctions début 2009.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6893" docOffset="35">
      <en>That is why I consider the time is now ripe to firm up on these proposals.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7073">donc</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7078">que</DiscourseConnective> l'heure est venue de finaliser nos propositions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6968" docOffset="36">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="43087" annotation_id="6968">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6968" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we leave it too late, we will not be able to reopen the governance issues.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6968" annotation_id="7131">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7131" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous attendons trop, nous ne pourrons plus rouvrir ce dossier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7046" docOffset="37">
      <en>The ongoing financial turmoil emphasises the need to ensure that accounting standards reflect the objectives of prudential supervision and financial stability.</en>
      <fr>L'actuelle crise financière prouve <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7232">que</DiscourseConnective> les normes comptables doivent garantir la supervision prudentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7303">et</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité financière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7206" docOffset="38">
      <en>It has not proven possible to get agreement to have bodies such as the ECB in the monitoring board.</en>
      <fr>Il n'a pas été possible de décrocher un accord sur la participation d'instances telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7418">que</DiscourseConnective> la BCE au conseil de supervision.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7306" docOffset="39">
      <en>As a compromise, we could envisage, in these new arrangements, that there would be an international accounting advisory group to advise the monitoring group on prudential and financial stability matters.</en>
      <fr>Dans la nouvelle configuration, nous pourrions envisager la création d'un groupe consultatif international en comptabilité qui serait chargé de conseiller le groupe de supervision sur les questions de stabilité prudentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7680">et</DiscourseConnective> financière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7510" docOffset="40">
      <en>This group should include both the European Central Bank and the Committee of European Securities Regulators and, no doubt, other relevant international bodies.</en>
      <fr>Y participeraient la Banque centrale européenne, le Comité européen des régulateurs de marchés des valeurs mobilières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7813">et</DiscourseConnective>, bien entendu, les autres instances internationales intéressées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7671" docOffset="41">
      <en>Again, I am grateful to this House for having emphasised the importance of prudential supervision and financial stability in its resolution of 24 April.</en>
      <fr>Une nouvelle fois, je voudrais remercier les députés d'avoir souligné l'importance de la supervision prudentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7995">et</DiscourseConnective> de la stabilité financière dans sa résolution du 24 avril.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7824" docOffset="42">
      <en>In exercising its eventual role in the monitoring board, the Commission must <Alignment alignment="8150" annotation_id="7901">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7901" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> represent the other European institutions, in particular this House.</en>
      <fr>Dans l'exercice de son éventuel mandat au sein du conseil de supervision, la Commission doit <Alignment alignment="17032" annotation_id="8150">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8150" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> représenter les autres institutions européennes et, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8212">surtout</DiscourseConnective>, la présente Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7975" docOffset="43">
      <en>To do so effectively, I would propose to draw up consultation procedures with the European Parliament. These procedures could, <Alignment alignment="21115" annotation_id="8102">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8102" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> necessary, be formalised in an appropriate form.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8244">Pour que</DiscourseConnective> cela <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8258">soit</DiscourseConnective> efficace, je proposerais que des procédures de concertation avec le Parlement européen soient élaborées qui pourraient être formalisées <Alignment alignment="21266" annotation_id="8399">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8399" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8409">en</DiscourseConnective> est.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8154" docOffset="44">
      <en>I have endeavoured to ensure that key MEPs were kept informed by my services about the evolution of this debate. It was, <Alignment alignment="24848" annotation_id="8275">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8275" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, brought to my attention today that there was a lapse in this communication.</en>
      <fr>Je me suis efforcé de faire en sorte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8454">que</DiscourseConnective> les principaux députés européens soient informés par mes services de l'évolution de ce débat <Alignment alignment="8275" annotation_id="8551">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8551" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ai appris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8568">que</DiscourseConnective> la communication n'a pas été optimale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8360" docOffset="45">
      <en>Apparently, in preparing our position, events that took place towards the end of July were not communicated by my services in the usual manner, because of the holiday period.</en>
      <fr>Apparemment, pendant l'élaboration de notre position, mes services n'ont pas, comme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8695">à</DiscourseConnective> l'habitude, communiqué les événements de la fin juillet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8753">parce que</DiscourseConnective> nous étions en période de vacances.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8535" docOffset="46">
      <en>I know that there is widespread dissatisfaction in this House about the fact that you were not properly consulted during the elaboration of our proposals.</en>
      <fr>Je sais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8807">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il règne parmi les députés une grande insatisfaction de n'avoir pas été consultés correctement pendant l'élaboration de nos propositions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8690" docOffset="47">
      <en>I am <Alignment alignment="50576" annotation_id="8695">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8695" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dissatisfied by this fact and have given clear and firm instructions to my services not to repeat such a mistake again.</en>
      <fr>J'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8950">en</DiscourseConnective> suis tout <Alignment alignment="2508" annotation_id="8963">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8963" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> peu satisfait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8983">et</DiscourseConnective> j'ai donné à mes services des consignes claires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9034">et</DiscourseConnective> fermes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9044">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>éviter que cette erreur ne se reproduise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8820" docOffset="48">
      <en>I believe my Director-General has been in contact with Mrs Berès to try and explain this omission.</en>
      <fr>Je pense que mon directeur général a contacté Mme Berès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9149">pour</DiscourseConnective> lui expliquer cette omission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8919" docOffset="49">
      <en>I hope that this oversight will not jeopardise the common goal we have both been striving for, namely, a better governance regime for the IASB.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9193">que</DiscourseConnective> cet oubli ne mettra pas en péril l'objectif commun de nos deux institutions, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9274">soit</DiscourseConnective> l'amélioration du système de gouvernance de l'IASB.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9063" docOffset="50">
      <en>With some further improvements, I am confident that these enhancements to the IASCF's governance will improve the quality of accounting standards and ensure that they meet the needs of all stakeholders - including the European Union, which to this date remains the largest user of IFRS.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9349">que</DiscourseConnective>, moyennant quelques adaptations supplémentaires, une gouvernance plus adéquate de l'IASCF augmentera la qualité des normes comptables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9487">et</DiscourseConnective> garantira la satisfaction des besoins de toutes les parties intéressées, parmi lesquelles l'Union européenne qui est, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9608">à</DiscourseConnective> ce jour, le principal utilisateur des normes IFRS.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9350" docOffset="51">
      <en>The reform of the IASCF governance currently being contemplated represents a step change in the accountability of this body to public authorities, something this House has repeatedly called for.</en>
      <fr>L'actuel projet de réforme de la gouvernance de l'IASCF apportera un changement majeur dans la responsabilité de cette instance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9789">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard des autorités publiques. L'Assemblée l'a demandé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9848">à</DiscourseConnective> maintes reprises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9545" docOffset="52">
      <en>I appeal to the European Parliament to support our proposals as the best way to ensure that this reform achieves real influence.</en>
      <fr>J'invite le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9899">à</DiscourseConnective> soutenir nos propositions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9927">afin que</DiscourseConnective> cette réforme puisse avoir un véritable poids.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9674" id="456" name="Jean-Paul Gauzès">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9674" docOffset="53">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (FR) Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, we have just heard the Chairman of the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs express the real views of those Members who are interested in this issue.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, mes chers collègues, nous venons d'entendre, de la présidente de la commission économique, l'expression de ce qu'en fait pensent les députés qui s'intéressent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10216">à</DiscourseConnective> cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9921" docOffset="54">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9921" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> has been underlined, everyone is aware of the importance of financial accounting standards and of the reforms that have been announced.</en>
      <fr>Vous l'avez souligné, chacun est conscient de l'importance des normes comptables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10315">et</DiscourseConnective> de la réforme qui est annoncée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10060" docOffset="55">
      <en>The time has now come, Commissioner, to clarify and put into action the comments that you have made.</en>
      <fr>L'occasion est venue de clarifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10384">et</DiscourseConnective> de traduire dans les faits les propos <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10425">que</DiscourseConnective> vous tenez, Monsieur le Commissaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10161" docOffset="56">
      <en>I have a suggestion to make: this resolution is a rigorous one <Alignment alignment="10519" annotation_id="10224">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10224" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it needs to be, <Alignment alignment="10539" annotation_id="10244">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10244" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is no need to kill the sinner.</en>
      <fr>Je fais une proposition: cette résolution est sévère <Alignment alignment="10224" annotation_id="10519">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10519" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ceci est mérité, <Alignment alignment="10244" annotation_id="10539">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10539" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il ne faut pas tuer le pécheur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10285" docOffset="57">
      <en>What we could <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10299" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">in fact</DiscourseConnective> do is to take a few days respite in order to establish a protocol between the Commission and Parliament that would clearly define the extent to which Parliament has to be kept informed, its level of involvement in this matter and the positions that it takes up, <Alignment alignment="18895" annotation_id="10569">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10569" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> to this end we need to postpone the vote for a few days.</en>
      <fr>Finalement, ce qui serait possible, ce serait de mettre à profit quelques jours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10656">pour</DiscourseConnective> essayer d'établir, entre la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10700">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement, un protocole qui définirait clairement l'information du Parlement, sa participation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10801">à</DiscourseConnective> cette réflexion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10819">et</DiscourseConnective> ses positions, <Alignment alignment="10569" annotation_id="10837">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10837" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10840">à</DiscourseConnective> cette fin, il faudrait que nous reportions le vote de quelques jours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10630" docOffset="58">
      <en>This is the proposal that the Group of the European People's Party and European Democrats will put forward tomorrow, namely that the vote on the resolution be postponed in order that Parliament and the Commission might be able to cooperate properly on this important subject.</en>
      <fr>C'est la proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10933">que</DiscourseConnective> formulera le PPE demain, de reporter le vote de la résolution pour permettre d'ouvrir véritablement une concertation entre le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11073">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur ce sujet important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10906" docOffset="59">
      <en>Obviously <Alignment alignment="24009" annotation_id="10916">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10916" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nothing is forthcoming during this interval, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10964" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> in order to make up for lost time and the possible lack of information, we shall be obliged to vote on the resolution that is being tabled today, with all the tough decisions that this will entail.</en>
      <fr>Il est bien évident <Alignment alignment="8764" annotation_id="11134">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11134" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> rien n'aboutissait pendant ce laps de temps, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11186">pour</DiscourseConnective> rattraper le temps perdu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11216">et</DiscourseConnective> les éventuels manques d'information, nous serions amenés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11276">à</DiscourseConnective> voter une résolution qui serait celle qui nous est proposée aujourd'hui, avec la sévérité des jugements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11382">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle comporte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11166" docOffset="60">
      <en>In the midst of the difficult circumstances that are now being imposed on us by the current financial crisis, which is not something totally unfamiliar as far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11325" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> accounting standards are concerned, I hope that everyone of us will understand that we have to find a quick and practical solution that will help steer developments in the required direction.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11409">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> des circonstances difficiles amenées par une crise financière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11477">à</DiscourseConnective> laquelle les normes comptables ne sont pas totalement étrangères, chacun comprendra <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11563">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut trouver rapidement une solution pratique qui ouvre la voie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11633">à</DiscourseConnective> une évolution souhaitable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11520" id="457" name="John Purvis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11520" docOffset="61">
      <en>Madam President, I have to admit to the Commissioner that I am really quite confused by what has been going on with this case.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, je dois avouer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11704">à</DiscourseConnective> M. le Commissaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11724">que</DiscourseConnective> je ne comprends pas grand chose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11760">à</DiscourseConnective> ce qu'il se passe ici.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11647" docOffset="62">
      <en>I had heard nothing about it until literally this week <Alignment alignment="11843" annotation_id="11702">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11702" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> suddenly I get deluged with approaches, both from the IASCF and from the Commission, trying to persuade me one way or the other as to whether the IMF should be included in the monitoring group.</en>
      <fr>Je n'étais au courant de rien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11815">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> la semaine dernière <Alignment alignment="11702" annotation_id="11843">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11843" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11847">soudain</DiscourseConnective>, je suis assailli de toutes parts par l'IASCF <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11901">et</DiscourseConnective> par la Commission qui tentent de me convaincre par un moyen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11964">ou</DiscourseConnective> par un autre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11980">que</DiscourseConnective> le FMI doit faire partie du groupe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11900" docOffset="63">
      <en>I think this is a rather unsatisfactory way to proceed with what is essentially almost a piece of legislation, <Alignment alignment="32055" annotation_id="12011">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12011" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would ask the Commissioner <Alignment alignment="22898" annotation_id="12043">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12043" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we could not delay this a little, get it sorted out and come back to it perhaps at the October mini-plenary.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agit là d'une façon de procéder <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12057">pour</DiscourseConnective> le moins déplaisante face à ce qui est, en fin de compte, presque un outil juridique. Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="4943" annotation_id="12160">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12160" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demander au Commissaire <Alignment alignment="12043" annotation_id="12193">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12193" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il est possible de temporiser pour résoudre les problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12253">et</DiscourseConnective> de revenir sur ce dossier éventuellement lors de la mini plénière d'octobre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12155" docOffset="64">
      <en>I would like to suggest that I do not see that adding the IMF and the World Bank to this monitoring group would make it that unwieldy.</en>
      <fr>J'ajouterais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12346">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à mes yeux la participation du FMI <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12384">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Banque mondiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12409">à</DiscourseConnective> ce groupe de supervision ne l'alourdirait en rien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12290" docOffset="65">
      <en>It seems to me they would cover the rest of the world in a rather satisfactory manner.</en>
      <fr>Il me semble qu'elles apporteraient une dimension internationale bienvenue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12377" docOffset="66">
      <en>I do not really see that there is a need <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12418" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> to have yet another accounting advisory group that advises the monitors that monitor things.</en>
      <fr>Je ne vois pas pourquoi un nouveau groupe consultatif en comptabilité serait créé pour conseiller les superviseurs qui supervisent les choses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12516" docOffset="67">
      <en>It is like the house that Jack built.</en>
      <fr>C'est l'histoire du serpent qui se mange la queue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12554" docOffset="68">
      <en>I wonder whether they could not in any case consult quite readily, unofficially, <Alignment alignment="12767" annotation_id="12635">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12635" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they ever need to do so.</en>
      <fr>Ne pourraient-ils pas se concerter <Alignment alignment="18657" annotation_id="12767">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12767" sense="Contingency.Condition">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> besoin en est, sans devoir recourir à une procédure officielle?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12663" docOffset="69">
      <en>I wonder <Alignment alignment="12927" annotation_id="12672">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12672" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we could have some discussions over the next couple of weeks and end up with a vote, possibly in a more satisfactory manner, at the mini-plenary in October.</en>
      <fr>Pourrions-nous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12854">en</DiscourseConnective> rediscuter dans les quinze prochains jours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12900">et</DiscourseConnective> voter dans un contexte, <Alignment alignment="12672" annotation_id="12927">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12927" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> possible, plus harmonieux, lors de la mini plénière d'octobre ?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12832" id="458" name="Zuzana Roithová">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12832" docOffset="70">
      <en>(CS) Commissioner, today's world financial crisis reveals how important fair value, the real value of a company, is for the healthy functioning of financial markets.</en>
      <fr>(CS) Monsieur le Président, la crise financière mondiale nous montre combien l'équité, la valeur équitable de l'entreprise est essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13133">pour que</DiscourseConnective> les marchés financiers soient sains.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12998" docOffset="71">
      <en>This is vital information for shareholders and creditors.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont des informations indispensables aux actionnaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13236">et</DiscourseConnective> créanciers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13056" docOffset="72">
      <en>A monitoring committee could make a contribution to better transparency and comparability of financial reporting and thus to the personal responsibility of shareholders for correct economic decisions.</en>
      <fr>Un groupe de supervision permettrait d'augmenter la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13316">et</DiscourseConnective> d'améliorer la comparabilité des rapports financiers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13372">afin de</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la responsabilité individuelle des actionnaires dans les procédures décisionnelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13257" docOffset="73">
      <en>International standardisation clearly leads to the development of cross-border capital markets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13352" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="25193" annotation_id="13357">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13357" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in the interests of stability, the monitoring group should <Alignment alignment="9858" annotation_id="13427">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13427" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> implement preventive measures against cyclical trends and help to prevent systemic risk.</en>
      <fr>La normalisation internationale mène indubitablement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13527">à</DiscourseConnective> l'émergence de marchés des capitaux transfrontaliers. <Alignment alignment="13357" annotation_id="13583">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13583" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, au nom de la stabilité, le groupe de supervision devrait <Alignment alignment="13427" annotation_id="13656">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13656" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> introduire des mesures de prévention contre les tendances cycliques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13734">et</DiscourseConnective> contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13748">à</DiscourseConnective> prévenir le risque systémique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13521" docOffset="74">
      <en>Of course, the proposal to establish the group has not been subject to questioning.</en>
      <fr>Il va sans dire que la proposition de créer ce groupe n'est pas remise en cause.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13605" docOffset="75">
      <en>Its powers have not been explained, <Alignment alignment="13916" annotation_id="13641">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13641" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whether it will <Alignment alignment="26775" annotation_id="13669">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13669" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have a supervisory function.</en>
      <fr>Ses prérogatives ne sont pas définies et l'on ignore, <Alignment alignment="13641" annotation_id="13916">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13916" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13929">si</DiscourseConnective> ce groupe jouera <Alignment alignment="7392" annotation_id="13949">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13949" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un rôle de supervision.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13703" docOffset="76">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="13979" annotation_id="13705">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13705" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> consider it important that every country should have a delegate in the proposed monitoring group, which must <Alignment alignment="1008" annotation_id="13819">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13819" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> include representatives of important institutions <Alignment alignment="1675" annotation_id="13874">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13874" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13877" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> to reflect the size of the most important world monetary areas, cultural diversity and the interests of the developed and developing economies and international institutions that are answerable to public bodies.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13705" annotation_id="13979">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13979" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il me semble important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14016">que</DiscourseConnective> chaque pays puisse disposer d'un représentant dans ce groupe de suivi dans lequel siègeront <Alignment alignment="13819" annotation_id="14112">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14112" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des représentants des grandes institutions <Alignment alignment="13874" annotation_id="14161">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14161" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> refléter le poids des principaux blocs monétaires au monde, tout comme la diversité culturelle, les intérêts des pays développés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14298">et</DiscourseConnective> en développement, les institutions internationales responsables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14365">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard des instances publiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14092" docOffset="77">
      <en>It is a pity that Parliament was not consulted in advance as a matter of course.</en>
      <fr>Il est dommage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14415">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement n'ait pas été consulté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14455">auparavant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14173" id="459" name="Pervenche Berès">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14173" docOffset="78">
      <en>author. - (FR) Madam President, Commissioner, what have you done since 24 April about taking account of Parliament's position?</en>
      <fr>auteure. - Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14525">qu'</DiscourseConnective>avez-vous fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14543">depuis</DiscourseConnective> le 24 avril <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14562">pour</DiscourseConnective> tenir compte de la position du Parlement européen?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14300" docOffset="79">
      <en>What have you done since 24 April about debating with Parliament on finding effective solutions for handling the governance of the trustees?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14618">Qu'</DiscourseConnective>avez-vous fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14636">depuis</DiscourseConnective> le 24 avril <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14655">pour</DiscourseConnective> débattre avec le Parlement européen des bonnes solutions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14717">pour</DiscourseConnective> piloter la gouvernance des trustees?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14441" docOffset="80">
      <en>We know full well that the IASB is a drunken boat at the hands of auditors who have produced these so-called 'fair values', <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14565" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> no one knows how they have been elected <Alignment alignment="14913" annotation_id="14609">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14609" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is no longer a market to supervise.</en>
      <fr>Nous le savons bien, l'IASB est un bateau ivre entre les mains des auditeurs qui ont produit ces fair values, dont personne ne sait comment on les a élus <Alignment alignment="14609" annotation_id="14913">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14913" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il n'y a plus de marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14656" docOffset="81">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="29439" annotation_id="14656">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14656" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">As a result</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, today we are being asked to discuss the subject of IASCF governance.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14656" annotation_id="14944">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14944" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aujourd'hui, l'enjeu de la gouvernance de l'IASCF est celui dont nous devons débattre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14738" docOffset="82">
      <en>You are proposing to us in haste - and at a time <Alignment alignment="41859" annotation_id="14787">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14787" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are putting to you quite reasonable solutions whereby the governance of these structures might be incorporated into a global and accountable system of governance - that advisory committees should be set up.</en>
      <fr>Vous nous proposez dans la précipitation - <Alignment alignment="1242" annotation_id="15077">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15077" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous vous proposons des solutions raisonnables pour intégrer la gouvernance de ces structures dans une gouvernance mondiale, responsable - de mettre en place des comités de consultation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15002" docOffset="83">
      <en>Is this reasonable?</en>
      <fr>Est ce bien raisonnable?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15022" docOffset="84">
      <en>I do not believe that this question will be solved simply by involving Parliament in this or that stage of the process.</en>
      <fr>Je ne crois pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15313">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une simple association du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15361">à</DiscourseConnective> telle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15369">ou</DiscourseConnective> telle étape du processus suffira à résoudre la question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15142" docOffset="85">
      <en>The proposal that you are putting to us for the governance of the IASCF is not satisfactory.</en>
      <fr>La proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15444">que</DiscourseConnective> vous nous faites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15465">pour</DiscourseConnective> la gouvernance de l'IASCF n'est pas satisfaisante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15235" docOffset="86">
      <en>We look forward to receiving another proposal from you and possibly will have to await the second phase of the consultation exercise and, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15373" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> necessary, the review of this governance process.</en>
      <fr>Nous attendons de votre part une autre proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15572">et</DiscourseConnective>, éventuellement, d'attendre la deuxième phase de la consultation, de la révision de cette gouvernance le cas échéant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15426" id="460" name="Charlie McCreevy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15426" docOffset="87">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Madam President, at my stage in life, I do not get very surprised too often, <Alignment alignment="1644" annotation_id="15531">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15531" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am not the least bit surprised at what goes on here in the European Parliament and the views of some people.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15747">à</DiscourseConnective> mon âge, plus grand chose ne surprend. Je ne suis <Alignment alignment="8085" annotation_id="15799">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15799" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas du tout étonné ni de ce qu'il se passe ici au Parlement européen, ni de l'opinion de certaines personnes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15645" docOffset="88">
      <en>Can I just say in all of this particular debate, let us just remember one small thing. The IASCF and its underlying constituent body, the IASB, is an independent organisation.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi d'ajouter que, dans ce débat-ci nous ne pouvons oublier que l'IASCF <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15996">et</DiscourseConnective>, sous elle, son corps constituant, l'IASB, sont des organisations indépendantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15821" docOffset="89">
      <en>(Inaudible interruption from the floor)</en>
      <fr>(Interruption inaudible dans la salle)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15861" docOffset="90">
      <en>I just want to put the facts on the table.</en>
      <fr>Je me contente d'énoncer les faits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15904" docOffset="91">
      <en>They are totally independent <Alignment alignment="16191" annotation_id="15933">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15933" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they have de facto become the accounts-standard-setting body for the globe <Alignment alignment="51880" annotation_id="16012">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16012" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> IFRS, which came out of the IASB, has now become the de facto worldwide accountancy standard.</en>
      <fr>Elles sont totalement indépendantes <Alignment alignment="11349" annotation_id="16191">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16191" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sont devenues, de fait, des instances internationales de normalisation comptable <Alignment alignment="16012" annotation_id="16277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16277" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la norme IFRS, édictée par l'IASB, est aujourd'hui de facto la norme de comptabilité mondiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16114" docOffset="92">
      <en>I have to point out that this is an independent body; <Alignment alignment="27601" annotation_id="16168">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16168" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we in Europe have adopted IFRS - a decision made before my time by the Commission and to the satisfaction of the European Parliament - we are the largest constituency that has IFRS today.</en>
      <fr>L'organisation est indépendante <Alignment alignment="16168" annotation_id="16414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16414" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>en Europe nous avons adopté la norme IFRS (décision prise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16479">avant que</DiscourseConnective> je n'arrive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16501">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16518">à</DiscourseConnective> la satisfaction du Parlement européen).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16362" docOffset="93">
      <en>This position may change <Alignment alignment="4778" annotation_id="16387">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16387" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the world moves over more to IFRS.</en>
      <fr>À l'heure actuelle, nous sommes la plus vaste entité à appliquer cette norme, mais cela pourrait changer <Alignment alignment="16387" annotation_id="16665">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16665" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le reste du monde s'y rallie petit à petit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16425" docOffset="94">
      <en>We might not <Alignment alignment="16733" annotation_id="16438">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16438" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be the largest any more, <Alignment alignment="15306" annotation_id="16468">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16468" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we certainly are the largest current user of IFRS.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne serons plus <Alignment alignment="16438" annotation_id="16733">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16733" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les plus grands <Alignment alignment="16468" annotation_id="16755">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16755" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pour l'heure, nous sommes le plus gros utilisateur de la norme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16523" docOffset="95">
      <en>For some time, with the support of the European Parliament, we have been endeavouring to improve the governance arrangements of the IASCF trustees, noting that they are an independent organisation.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16824">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> un certain temps, avec le soutien du Parlement européen, nous nous efforçons d'améliorer la gouvernance de l'IASCF par ses administrateurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16971">sans oublier qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle est indépendante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16721" docOffset="96">
      <en>We have made some progress in the past, <Alignment alignment="21406" annotation_id="16761">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16761" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the IAS recently announced that they were going to have a review of their own constitution.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons enregistré quelques progrès dans le passé <Alignment alignment="20175" annotation_id="17063">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17063" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, récemment, l'IAS a annoncé la révision de sa constitution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16857" docOffset="97">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17143" annotation_id="16857">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16857" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are availing ourselves of that opportunity to make our submission.</en>
      <fr>Nous profiterons <Alignment alignment="22733" annotation_id="17143">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17143" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de l'occasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17162">pour</DiscourseConnective> soumettre nos propositions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16930" docOffset="98">
      <en>We have no right to impose our view on the IASCF - this is up to the independent trustees - <Alignment alignment="17317" annotation_id="17022">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17022" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are making it our submission to improve the governance arrangements. I would just point out this basic fact <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17137" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective> everybody, <Alignment alignment="25813" annotation_id="17155">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17155" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we might say in Ireland, 'loses the run of themselves' in this particular area.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'avons pas le droit d'imposer notre point de vue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17250">à</DiscourseConnective> l'IASCF (c'est la prérogative des administrateurs indépendants), <Alignment alignment="3170" annotation_id="17317">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17317" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous soumettons des propositions d'amélioration des mécanismes de gestion pour éviter que, <Alignment alignment="19814" annotation_id="17413">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17413" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le disent les Irlandais, l'organisation 'loses the run of themselves' (perde le contrôle).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17238" docOffset="99">
      <en>That is the de facto and de jure situation.</en>
      <fr>C'est une situation de facto <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17539">et</DiscourseConnective> de jure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17282" docOffset="100">
      <en>The IAS trustees are intending to bring in their new governance arrangements, having considered all the submissions, in early October.</en>
      <fr>Les administrateurs de l'IAS pensent introduire les nouvelles règles de gouvernance début octobre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17650">après</DiscourseConnective> examen de toutes les propositions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17417" docOffset="101">
      <en>The closing date for making our submission has actually passed by a few days.</en>
      <fr>Le délai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17700">pour</DiscourseConnective> le dépôt de nos propositions a expiré il y a quelques jours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17495" docOffset="102">
      <en>It was to be 20 September, <Alignment alignment="17790" annotation_id="17522">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17522" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the date today is 24 September.</en>
      <fr>C'était le 20 septembre <Alignment alignment="17522" annotation_id="17790">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17790" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous sommes aujourd'hui le 24.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17558" docOffset="103">
      <en>We waited to submit our final result.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons attendu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17843">pour</DiscourseConnective> soumettre une proposition finale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17596" docOffset="104">
      <en>We have been in informal consultations with them for some time, so they know, really, what we are going to propose, <Alignment alignment="48060" annotation_id="17712">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17712" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we waited for Parliament's resolution for the courtesy of doing that.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17894">en</DiscourseConnective> concertation informelle avec eux pendant un certain temps. Ils savent donc ce que nous allons proposer <Alignment alignment="23207" annotation_id="18000">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18000" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, par courtoisie, nous avons attendu la résolution du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17786" docOffset="105">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18081" annotation_id="17786">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17786" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will have to submit our formal proposals in the next few days.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="17786" annotation_id="18081">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18081" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> soumettre nos propositions officielles dans les prochains jours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17855" docOffset="106">
      <en>It is entirely a matter for Parliament as to what you want to do with this particular recommendation.</en>
      <fr>Il appartient au Parlement de décider de ce qu'il adviendra de cette recommandation-ci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17957" docOffset="107">
      <en>Mr Gauzès has put forward a reasonable approach about taking a few extra days perhaps to work out a protocol about Parliament's participation in the process which I am endeavouring to set up.</en>
      <fr>M. Gauzès a très raisonnablement suggéré de prendre quelques jours de plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18314">pour</DiscourseConnective> élaborer un protocole régissant la participation de l'Assemblée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18383">à</DiscourseConnective> la procédure, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18399">que</DiscourseConnective> je suis tout à fait disposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18431">à</DiscourseConnective> élaborer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18149" docOffset="108">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18149" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> regards the monitoring board idea, which we announced last November, it is not possible for everybody to be represented on the monitoring board.</en>
      <fr>Quant au conseil de supervision proposé en novembre dernier, tout le monde ne peut y être représenté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18297" docOffset="109">
      <en>It will not be acceptable to the trustees of the IASCF, <Alignment alignment="14407" annotation_id="18353">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18353" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="18601" annotation_id="18358">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18358" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they say absolutely no, then that is that.</en>
      <fr>Les administrateurs de l'IASCF ne l'accepteront pas <Alignment alignment="18353" annotation_id="18597">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18597" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="18358" annotation_id="18601">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18601" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils refusent catégoriquement, c'en est fini.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18404" docOffset="110">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18663" annotation_id="18404">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18404" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we proposed a kind of a way around this by having relevant people, relevant bodies, in this advisory group.</en>
      <fr>Nous proposons <Alignment alignment="18404" annotation_id="18663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18663" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une sorte d'échappatoire en assurant la présence dans ce groupe des personnes et instances concernées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18515" docOffset="111">
      <en>I am not hung up on any particular strong views as to how it should be organised <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18596" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective> who should be on it.</en>
      <fr>Je ne camperai pas sur une position <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18807">quant à</DiscourseConnective> la façon d'organiser ce groupe ni qui doit y participer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18620" docOffset="112">
      <en>I do not have any views about that.</en>
      <fr>Je n'ai aucune opinion en la matière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18656" docOffset="113">
      <en>I only learned today that my services have not been in constant contact with relevant Members here in the European Parliament in the past month or so.</en>
      <fr>J'ai appris aujourd'hui seulement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18944">que</DiscourseConnective>, le mois dernier, mes services n'ont pas été <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18993">en</DiscourseConnective> permanence en contact avec les députés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18807" docOffset="114">
      <en>This was news to me, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18828" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> I thought my officials would have been keeping contact the whole time with the people here who take an interest in this particular subject, <Alignment alignment="33323" annotation_id="18976">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18976" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I find out today that did not occur.</en>
      <fr>Je l'ignorais; je pensais qu'ils maintiendraient un contact suivi avec les personnes intéressées par ce dossier particulier <Alignment alignment="8874" annotation_id="19160">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19160" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je viens de découvrir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19187">que</DiscourseConnective> ça n'a pas été le cas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19017" docOffset="115">
      <en>In my former remarks, I said that I regretted this, <Alignment alignment="19257" annotation_id="19069">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19069" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that I had given directions that it should not happen again; we want to cooperate.</en>
      <fr>J'ai déjà exprimé mes regrets précédemment <Alignment alignment="5573" annotation_id="19257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19257" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ai pris des mesures pour éviter ça se reproduise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19156" docOffset="116">
      <en>No more can I do.</en>
      <fr>Nous voulons coopérer mais je ne peux pas en faire plus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19174" docOffset="117">
      <en>Mr Purvis, it is not as though Parliament can delay until any time it likes - mid-October or beyond - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19276" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="19476" annotation_id="19280">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19280" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I want the European Commission to have a say, I have to submit our formal proposals regarding our ideas about governance to the IASF board forthwith.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur Purvis, le Parlement ne peut reporter la question à sa guise, jusqu'à la mi-octobre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19462">ou</DiscourseConnective> plus tard. <Alignment alignment="19280" annotation_id="19476">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19476" sense="Contingency.Condition">Pour que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission européenne puisse intervenir, je dois soumettre notre proposition formelle sur la gouvernance au conseil de l'IASF sur-le-champ.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19433" docOffset="118">
      <en>They will not agree with some of them.</en>
      <fr>Il n'acceptera pas toutes les suggestions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19472" docOffset="119">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19472" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> Mr John Purvis says, he has been lobbied for the last two days by various actors in this particular scene as to what they want to achieve.</en>
      <fr>M. John Purvis nous a déjà dit que, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19707">depuis</DiscourseConnective> deux jours, il fait l'objet de pressions de la part de plusieurs personnes qui veulent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19801">que</DiscourseConnective> leurs souhaits soient satisfaits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19614" docOffset="120">
      <en>From reading the resolution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19642" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> it is drafted, there is one definite peculiarity about this, which I think should not go unnoticed, particularly by Mrs Berès who has long been an advocate of greater governance and accountability of this particular IASB body.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19839">À</DiscourseConnective> la lecture de la résolution actuelle, une particularité devrait nous sauter aux yeux et particulièrement aux yeux de Madame Berès qui lutte depuis longtemps pour une meilleure gouvernance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20029">et</DiscourseConnective> plus de responsabilité de la part de cette instance de l'IASB.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19872" docOffset="121">
      <en>The peculiarity of the resolution is that it would do exactly what the trustees actually want and reverse what we are trying to do in getting more governance.</en>
      <fr>La résolution a ceci de particulier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20131">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle sert exactement les desseins des administrateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20188">et</DiscourseConnective> va à l'encontre de notre volonté d'améliorer la gestion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20031" docOffset="122">
      <en>That is the peculiarity, <Alignment alignment="48386" annotation_id="20056">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20056" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the matter of the resolution is entirely a matter for the European Parliament, not a matter for me.</en>
      <fr>Cette particularité pose un problème qu'il ne m'incombe pas de résoudre <Alignment alignment="2785" annotation_id="20320">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20320" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui est entièrement du ressort du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20160" docOffset="123">
      <en>I would just make that particular comment in passing, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20214" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> there are people among the IASB trustees who are not too anxious to accommodate some of the more far-reaching governance arrangements that we are proposing for them.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20379">En</DiscourseConnective> passant, j'ajouterais qu'il se trouve parmi les administrateurs de l'IASB des personnes qui ne sont pas trop enclines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20500">à</DiscourseConnective> accepter certaines des règles de gestion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20543">que</DiscourseConnective> nous leur proposons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20388" docOffset="124">
      <en>There will be a fair degree of resistance.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous heurterons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20589">à</DiscourseConnective> une résistance certaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20431" docOffset="125">
      <en>We are reliant on the existing trustees to take account of our concerns and to improve these governance arrangements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20548" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> we think fit.</en>
      <fr>Nous comptons sur les administrateurs actuels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20662">pour qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils examinent nos préoccupations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20703">et</DiscourseConnective> les améliorent dans le sens voulu par nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20565" docOffset="126">
      <en>We are not in the position, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20593" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> we only submit these things, to make demands and say it has to be like this, <Alignment alignment="25512" annotation_id="20678">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20678" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have had contacts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20703" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> they know what we are going to propose.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20763">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un pouvoir de proposition et ne pouvons, dès lors, rien exiger ni imposer <Alignment alignment="17386" annotation_id="20840">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20840" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, par nos contacts, ils savent ce que nous proposerons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20747" docOffset="127">
      <en>They are not happy with some of what we are going to propose. I am aware of that, <Alignment alignment="24318" annotation_id="20829">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20829" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are trying to get this improved governance.</en>
      <fr>Certaines suggestions ne leur plaisent pas, j'en suis bien conscient, <Alignment alignment="19662" annotation_id="20970">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20970" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous tentons de faire en sorte que la gestion soit meilleure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>

<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20881" docOffset="129">
      <en>Not that I am ever surprised by what happens in the political arena, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20950" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> I have been well over 30 years in this field, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20999" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> it will be ironic <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21021" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21025" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective> we have got this far over the years in getting our way on two things - namely that the IFRS has become an international standard <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21160" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that, now, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21175" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> people here know, the United States is proposing that IFRS be available to US companies (something I predicted would happen about two years ago to the relevant members of the relevant Parliament committee and was more or less laughed at that this would ever occur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21443" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it has) - this body that has been demanding with us and pressing us to get increased governance and accountability from this particular body is, at this particular stage and according to some people, actually going to do quite the opposite.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons lutté pendant des années pour faire de la norme IFRS une norme internationale et, comme tout le monde le sait, les États-Unis proposent aujourd'hui que cette norme soit accessible aux sociétés américaines (ce que j'avais prédit il y a deux ans devant la commission parlementaire qui s'est plus ou moins moquée de mois). Il serait, dès lors, assez ironique de la part de cette instance qui a été tellement exigeante et a tant insisté auprès de nous pour que sa gouvernance et sa transparence s'améliore, qu'elle fasse ce que certains disent qu'elle s'apprête à faire, c'est-à-dire, exactement le contraire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21688" docOffset="130">
      <en>I just think it is a little bit ironic, <Alignment alignment="21781" annotation_id="21728">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21728" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I hope I have explained this <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21761" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> best I can.</en>
      <fr>C'est un peu ironique <Alignment alignment="22228" annotation_id="21781">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21781" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'espère m'être fait comprendre. J'ai fait de mon <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21836">mieux</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="21776" id="461" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="21776" docOffset="131">
      <en>I have received one motion for a resolution pursuant to Rule 108(5) of the Rules of Procedure.</en>
      <fr>J'ai reçu une proposition de résolution déposée sur la base de l'Article 108(5) du règlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21871" docOffset="132">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21893" docOffset="133">
      <en>The vote will take place on Thursday, 25 September 2008.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu jeudi 25 septembre 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
