<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Institutional aspects of Regulatory Agencies (short presentation)</en>
    <fr>Stratégie en faveur de la future mise en œuvre des aspects institutionnels des agences de régulation (brève présentation)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="66" id="257" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="66" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is a brief presentation of the report by Mr Papastamkos, on behalf of the Committee on Constitutional Affairs, on a strategy for the future settlement of the institutional aspects of Regulatory Agencies.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle la brève présentation du rapport de M. Papastamkos, au nom de la commission des affaires constitutionnelles, sur une stratégie en faveur de la future mise en œuvre des aspects institutionnels des agences de régulation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="284" id="258" name="Georgios Papastamkos">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="284" docOffset="2">
      <en>rapporteur. - (EL) Mr President, the 29 European regulatory agencies constitute what at first sight appear to be micro-institutions <Alignment alignment="515" annotation_id="416">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="416" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which, in essence, have an obvious macro-impact <Alignment alignment="559" annotation_id="468">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="468" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which have already become an accepted para-institutional component of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (EL) Monsieur le Président, les 29 agences de régulation constituent, au premier abord, des "micro-institutions" qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="497">en</DiscourseConnective> substance, ont <Alignment alignment="120" annotation_id="515">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="515" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des "macro-incidences" manifestes <Alignment alignment="2135" annotation_id="559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="559" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="567">déjà</DiscourseConnective> devenues un paramètre para-institutionnel reconnu de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="562" docOffset="3">
      <en>The excessive increase in the number of regulatory agencies has undoubtedly resulted in inflated European regulatory intervention, the fragmentation of and a lack of transparency in European policies and, by extension, has made operational coordination more difficult.</en>
      <fr>L'augmentation excessive du nombre des agences de régulation a indubitablement eu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="727">pour</DiscourseConnective> effet d'amplifier exagérément l'intervention réglementaire européenne, de disperser les politiques européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="843">et</DiscourseConnective> de les rendre plus opaques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="873">et</DiscourseConnective>, par extension, de rendre plus difficile la coordination fonctionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="831" docOffset="4">
      <en>For all European agencies, the urgent question arises of the need for an interim review of their work and performance.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="948">Pour</DiscourseConnective> toutes les agences européennes, se pose la question urgente de la nécessité d'une évaluation intérimaire de leur travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1074">et</DiscourseConnective> de leurs résultats.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="950" docOffset="5">
      <en>What is required is a minimum total of common principles and rules relating to the structure, operation and control of the regulatory agencies, <Alignment alignment="1268" annotation_id="1094">
          <Alignment alignment="1268" annotation_id="1094">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1094" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> they integrate harmoniously within the framework of fundamental principles which derive from the Treaties.</en>
      <fr>Il est indispensable d'instaurer un ensemble minimal de règles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1160">et</DiscourseConnective> de principes communs concernant la structure, le fonctionnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1227">et</DiscourseConnective> le contrôle des agences de régulation <Alignment alignment="1094" annotation_id="1268">
          <Alignment alignment="1094" annotation_id="1268">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1268" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> ces dernières puissent intégrer de manière harmonieuse les principes fondamentaux qui découlent du système des Traités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1209" docOffset="6">
      <en>Following the Council's refusal to accept a legally binding instrument and the rejection of the proposal to conclude an interinstitutional agreement, the Commission decided to propose the establishment of an interinstitutional working group tasked with drawing up a common framework for the regulatory institutions and defining the competence of each of the European institutions vis-à-vis those agencies.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1397">Après que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil a refusé d'adopter un acte juridiquement contraignant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1472">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'il a rejeté la proposition visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1512">à</DiscourseConnective> conclure un accord interinstitutionnel, la Commission a proposé, à la place, la création d'un groupe de travail interinstitutionnel chargé de définir l'encadrement commun des agences de régulation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1711">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les compétences respectives de chacun des organes de l'Union européenne vis-à-vis de ces agences.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1615" docOffset="7">
      <en>I consider that this proposal falls short of the European Parliament's expectations of achieving an interinstitutional agreement.</en>
      <fr>J'estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1828">que</DiscourseConnective> cette proposition se situe en deçà des attentes du Parlement européen concernant la conclusion d'un accord interinstitutionnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1745" docOffset="8">
      <en>The common approach is <Alignment alignment="1983" annotation_id="1768">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1768" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">indeed</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an interim step towards the adoption of a legally binding text.</en>
      <fr>L'approche commune est <Alignment alignment="1192" annotation_id="1983">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1983" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une étape intermédiaire sur la voie de l'adoption d'un texte juridiquement contraignant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1839" docOffset="9">
      <en>I do, of course, appreciate the Commission's wish to find a way out of a situation of protracted interinstitutional inertia.</en>
      <fr>Je comprends évidemment que la Commission souhaite sortir d'une situation d'inertie interinstitutionnelle prolongée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1964" docOffset="10">
      <en>The setting up of an interinstitutional working group which will carry out a collective policy review of the experience gained from the activities of the regulatory agencies <Alignment alignment="2361" annotation_id="2138">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2138" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whose mandate will be to clarify their position in the multilevel system of European governance is welcome.</en>
      <fr>L'instauration d'un groupe de travail interinstitutionnel, qui dressera un bilan collectif détaillé des expériences tirées des activités des agences de régulation <Alignment alignment="2138" annotation_id="2361">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2361" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui sera chargé de préciser la place qu'elles occupent dans la gouvernance européenne à plusieurs niveaux, est la bienvenue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2250" docOffset="11">
      <en>The proposed approach - a common approach as far as possible - to the structure and workings of the agencies concerned seeks to restrict bureaucratic rigidity <Alignment alignment="2671" annotation_id="2409">
          <Alignment alignment="2913" annotation_id="2409">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2409" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> they can play their regulatory role correctly and effectively and can be supervised and so that the current requirements for auditing and accountability can, at least partially, be satisfied.</en>
      <fr>L'approche - commune, dans la mesure du possible - proposée en ce qui concerne la structure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2581">et</DiscourseConnective> le fonctionnement des agences en question vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2631">à</DiscourseConnective> limiter les lourdeurs bureaucratiques <Alignment alignment="1290" annotation_id="2671">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2671" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leur permettre de jouer correctement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2713">et</DiscourseConnective> efficacement leur rôle réglementaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2753">et</DiscourseConnective> pour qu'il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2767">soit</DiscourseConnective> dès lors possible de les surveiller <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2808">et</DiscourseConnective> de satisfaire, ne serait-ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2839">que</DiscourseConnective> partiellement, le besoin de contrôle (audit) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2888">et</DiscourseConnective> de responsabilisation <Alignment alignment="2409" annotation_id="2913">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2913" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> réclame notre époque.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2609" docOffset="12">
      <en>The priority of seeking a common framework for an interinstitutional understanding and approach lies in maximising the added value of the regulatory agencies in the European structures of governance in general by creating greater transparency, visible democratic control and improved efficiency.</en>
      <fr>La priorité du "cadre commun" recherché en matière d'entente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3000">et</DiscourseConnective> d'approche interinstitutionnelles consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3046">à</DiscourseConnective> optimiser, d'une manière générale, la valeur ajoutée des agences de régulation dans les structures européennes de gouvernance, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3175">en</DiscourseConnective> fixant comme conditions une transparence accrue, un contrôle démocratique visible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3260">et</DiscourseConnective> une efficacité renforcée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2905" docOffset="13">
      <en>Finally, I should like to point out that the establishment of parliamentary control over the structure and the work of the regulatory agencies is consistent with the classic democratic principle requiring political responsibility of any body wielding executive power.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3289">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3318">que</DiscourseConnective> la consécration du contrôle parlementaire exercé sur la structure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3388">et</DiscourseConnective> les travaux des agences de régulation correspond au principe démocratique classique qui impose d'accroître la responsabilité politique de tout organisme détenant un pouvoir exécutif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3173" docOffset="14">
      <en>The possibility of the European Parliament assigning political responsibility to the agencies concerned touches on a core principle of representative democracy, which consists in examining the legality and expediency of the choices made by the executive power.</en>
      <fr>La possibilité qui est donnée au Parlement européen d'attribuer une responsabilité politique aux agences en question est liée au principe central de la démocratie représentative, qui consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3766">à</DiscourseConnective> examiner la légalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3789">et</DiscourseConnective> le bien-fondé des choix opérés par le pouvoir exécutif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3434" id="259" name="Joe Borg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3434" docOffset="15">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the Commission welcomes the positive stance taken by the rapporteur, Mr Papastamkos, and the responsible and associated committees towards the key elements put forward in the March Communication, 'European agencies: The way forward'. These are the moratorium on proposing new agencies, the upcoming evaluation of the agency system and the creation of an interinstitutional working group.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la Commission salue la position positive adoptée par le rapporteur, M. Papastamkos, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3987">et</DiscourseConnective> les commissions au fond <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4014">et</DiscourseConnective> associées à l'égard des principaux éléments présentés dans la communication de mars, "Agences européennes - Orientations pour l'avenir", à savoir le moratoire sur la proposition de nouvelles agences, la prochaine évaluation du système des agences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4264">et</DiscourseConnective> la création d'un groupe de travail interinstitutionnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3864" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4323" annotation_id="3864">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3864" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you know, we attach great importance to the relaunch of the interinstitutional dialogue on the role and place of agencies in European governance, a dialogue aimed at developing a coherent vision and a common approach vis-à-vis regulatory agencies</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3864" annotation_id="4323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4323" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez, nous accordons une grande importance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4381">à</DiscourseConnective> la relance du dialogue interinstitutionnel sur le rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4438">et</DiscourseConnective> la place des agences dans la gouvernance européenne, un dialogue visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4513">à</DiscourseConnective> élaborer une vision cohérente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4545">et</DiscourseConnective> une approche commune à l'égard des agences de régulation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4114" docOffset="17">
      <en>The Commission trusts that Parliament will now be in a position to promptly mandate its representatives to the interinstitutional working group.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est persuadée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4634">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement sera à présent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4666">en</DiscourseConnective> mesure de mandater rapidement ses représentants au sein du groupe de travail interinstitutionnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4259" docOffset="18">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="4781" annotation_id="4262">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4262" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> count on a favourable response from the Council in order to ensure timely progress on the follow-up to the Commission's Communication.</en>
      <fr>Nous comptons <Alignment alignment="759" annotation_id="4781">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4781" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sur une réponse favorable du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4828">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>assurer des progrès opportuns sur le suivi de la communication de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4402" docOffset="19">
      <en>We are confident that the interinstitutional working group will be created before the end of the year.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes convaincus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4939">que</DiscourseConnective> le groupe de travail interinstitutionnel sera sur pied <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4998">avant</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4505" docOffset="20">
      <en>This group will be closely associated in the evaluation process that the Commission is about to launch.</en>
      <fr>Le groupe sera associé étroitement au processus d'évaluation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5084">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5102">s'</DiscourseConnective>apprête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5112">à</DiscourseConnective> lancer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4609" docOffset="21">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6364" annotation_id="4609">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4609" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> concluding, let me say that the Commission has left open the question on the form that will be given to the final outcome of the interinstitutional dialogue in order not to pre-empt the discussions.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4609" annotation_id="5122">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5122" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> conclure, permettez-moi de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5158">dire que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission a laissé ouverte la question de la forme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5222">à</DiscourseConnective> donner au <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5234">résultat</DiscourseConnective> final du dialogue interinstitutionnel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5281">afin de</DiscourseConnective> ne pas préjuger des discussions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4815" docOffset="22">
      <en>It is up to the interinstitutional working group to decide what form it wishes to give to its conclusions.</en>
      <fr>Il appartient au groupe de travail interinstitutionnel de décider quelle forme il souhaite donner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5420">à</DiscourseConnective> ses conclusions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4922" docOffset="23">
      <en>The conclusions, <Alignment alignment="5454" annotation_id="4939">
          <Alignment alignment="5454" annotation_id="4939">
            <Alignment alignment="5454" annotation_id="4939">
              <Alignment alignment="5454" annotation_id="4939">
                <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4939" sense="Comparison.Contrast">on the other hand</DiscourseConnective>
              </Alignment>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, can be implemented in different ways - sometimes spreading best practices could be enough, <Alignment alignment="5589" annotation_id="5049">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5049" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sometimes amendments to the agencies' basic acts might be necessary.</en>
      <fr>Ces dernières, <Alignment alignment="2653" annotation_id="5454">
          <Alignment alignment="1606" annotation_id="5454">
            <Alignment alignment="4939" annotation_id="5454">
              <Alignment alignment="4939" annotation_id="5454">
                <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5454" sense="Comparison.Contrast">d'un autre côté</DiscourseConnective>
              </Alignment>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, peuvent être mises en œuvre de différentes façons - il pourrait parfois suffire de diffuser les meilleures pratiques, <Alignment alignment="5049" annotation_id="5589">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5589" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> parfois des amendements aux règlements de base des agences pourraient être nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5122" docOffset="24">
      <en>The cooperation between Parliament and the Commission in this field is exemplary <Alignment alignment="5762" annotation_id="5203">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5203" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am sure we will continue working on that basis.</en>
      <fr>La coopération entre le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5714">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission dans ce domaine est exemplaire <Alignment alignment="2573" annotation_id="5762">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5762" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis certain que nous continuerons de travailler sur cette base.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5257" id="260" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5257" docOffset="25">
      <en>That concludes the item.</en>
      <fr>Le point est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5282" docOffset="26">
      <en>The vote will take place on Tuesday.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu mardi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
