<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Formal sitting - Hungary</en>
    <fr>Séance solennelle - Hongrie</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="25" id="081" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="25" docOffset="1">
      <en>Mr President of the Republic of Hungary, ladies and gentlemen, it is an honour to welcome you to the plenum of the European Parliament, President Sólyom.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président de la République de Hongrie, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="88">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, nous avons l'honneur de vous accueillir, M. Sólyom, dans l'enceinte du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="179" docOffset="2">
      <en>President Sólyom is a distinguished lawyer who has always demonstrated his determination to protect the law, political freedom and human dignity.</en>
      <fr>Le président Sólyom est un juriste réputé qui s'est toujours montré déterminé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="262">à</DiscourseConnective> protéger le droit, les libertés politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="307">et</DiscourseConnective> la dignité humaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="325" docOffset="3">
      <en>He was one of the first five judges whose appointments were agreed at the national Round Table held in Hungary in 1989, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="445" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> that country and others found their freedom.</en>
      <fr>Il a figuré parmi les cinq juges dont la nomination a été adoptée lors de la Table ronde nationale qui s'est tenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="445">en</DiscourseConnective> Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="456">en</DiscourseConnective> 1989, date à laquelle le pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="489">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres ont recouvré leur liberté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="495" docOffset="4">
      <en>As President of the Constitutional Court, President Sólyom had a huge influence on the decisions that strengthened the young Hungarian democracy and institutions.</en>
      <fr>En sa qualité de président de la Cour constitutionnelle, le président Sólyom a exercé une influence immense sur les décisions qui ont renforcé la jeune démocratie hongroise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="701">et</DiscourseConnective> ses institutions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="658" docOffset="5">
      <en>As the Third President of the Republic of Hungary, Mr Sólyom has increased the weight and prestige of his country.</en>
      <fr>Au cours de son mandat de troisième président de la République de Hongrie, M. Sólyom a accru le poids <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="824">et</DiscourseConnective> le prestige de son pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="773" docOffset="6">
      <en>He is a defender of social and environmental rights.</en>
      <fr>Il est un défenseur des droits sociaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="891">et</DiscourseConnective> environnementaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="826" docOffset="7">
      <en>He commanded respect during the first year of his term in office, carrying out his duties with caution, but acting firmly <Alignment alignment="1056" annotation_id="948">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="948" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> necessary.</en>
      <fr>Il a forcé le respect au cours de la première année de son mandat, exerçant ses responsabilités avec circonspection, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1029">mais</DiscourseConnective> agissant avec fermeté <Alignment alignment="948" annotation_id="1056">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1056" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'était nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="964" docOffset="8">
      <en>He is <Alignment alignment="1091" annotation_id="970">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="970" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a committed environmentalist.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="970" annotation_id="1091">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1091" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un défenseur engagé de l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1005" docOffset="9">
      <en>This has led him to create a European Group of Green Presidents, that is to say, of heads of state concerned about environmental problems, an original and creative initiative.</en>
      <fr>À ce titre, il a créé un groupe européen de présidents écologistes, constitué de chefs d'État préoccupés par les problèmes environnementaux, une initiative originale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1307">et</DiscourseConnective> créative.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1181" docOffset="10">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1192" docOffset="11">
      <en>You can imagine which group the Members applauding you belong to.</en>
      <fr>Vous pouvez imaginer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1360">à</DiscourseConnective> quel groupe appartiennent les députés qui vous applaudissent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1258" docOffset="12">
      <en>Fifty years ago, the uprising of the Hungarian people confirmed the strength of popular support for democratic principles and their will to dictate their own national destiny.</en>
      <fr>Il y a cinquante ans, le soulèvement du peuple hongrois est venu confirmer la vigueur du soutien populaire aux principes démocratiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1559">et</DiscourseConnective> la volonté de la population d'imposer son propre destin national.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1434" docOffset="13">
      <en>We are currently remembering and celebrating a series of milestones.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous rappelons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1648">et</DiscourseConnective> nous célébrons aujourd'hui une série de jalons historiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1503" docOffset="14">
      <en>It all began in 1989, <Alignment alignment="1736" annotation_id="1525">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1525" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> his country proclaimed its independence and in 1990, <Alignment alignment="1792" annotation_id="1583">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1583" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Hungarian Parliament declared 23 October a Hungarian national holiday, demonstrating that the legacy of the 1956 Revolution is still alive amongst us.</en>
      <fr>Tout a commencé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1727">en</DiscourseConnective> 1989, <Alignment alignment="1525" annotation_id="1736">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1736" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le pays a proclamé son indépendance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1780">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1783">en</DiscourseConnective> 1990, <Alignment alignment="1583" annotation_id="1792">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1792" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement hongrois a déclaré le 23 octobre fête nationale du pays, démontrant ainsi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1887">que</DiscourseConnective> l'héritage de la révolution de 1956 est toujours bien présent parmi nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1743" docOffset="15">
      <en>At its plenary sitting yesterday, the European Parliament commemorated the Hungarian Revolution of 1956; this Thursday we shall approve a resolution relating to it.</en>
      <fr>Au cours de sa séance plénière d'hier, le Parlement européen a commémoré la révolution hongroise de 1956; ce jeudi, nous approuverons une résolution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2114">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1908" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2126" annotation_id="1908">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1908" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this afternoon the European Parliament will mark this commemorative day by inaugurating the photographic exhibition 'Hungary - Past and Future - 1956-2006', to which I would like to invite all of the Members of this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1908" annotation_id="2126">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2126" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, cet après-midi, le Parlement européen marquera cette journée de commémoration par l'inauguration de l'exposition de photographies "Hungary - Past and Future - 1956-2006", <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2311">à</DiscourseConnective> laquelle je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2331">à</DiscourseConnective> inviter tous les députés de ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2149" docOffset="17">
      <en>Mr President, thank you for being with us at such an important time for the history of your country and also for the history of the whole of Europe.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je vous remercie d'être parmi nous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2433">en</DiscourseConnective> ce moment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2446">si</DiscourseConnective> important de l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2464">histoire de</DiscourseConnective> votre pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2488">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> de toute l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2298" docOffset="18">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2309" id="082" name="László Sólyom">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2309" docOffset="19">
      <en>President of the Republic of Hungary. Mr President, Members of the European Parliament, Representatives of the Council and the Commission, Ladies and Gentlemen, Hungary and the world celebrate together the 50th anniversary of the 1956 Hungarian Revolution and the fight for freedom.</en>
      <fr>président de la République de Hongrie. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, chers députés du Parlement européen, chers représentants du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2674">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2704">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, la Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2729">et</DiscourseConnective> le monde entier se sont unis pour célébrer le 50e anniversaire de la révolution hongroise de 1956 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2830">et</DiscourseConnective> de la lutte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2845">pour</DiscourseConnective> la liberté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2592" docOffset="20">
      <en>It is encouraging and elevating to feel that there is one commemorative event with which everyone can identify. There are no differences of opinion, no reservations.</en>
      <fr>Il est encourageant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2882">et</DiscourseConnective> gratifiant de sentir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2906">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il existe un événement commémoratif auquel tous peuvent s'identifier, sur lequel il n'existe aucune divergence d'opinion ni réserve.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2758" docOffset="21">
      <en>Everyone pays tribute to the memory of the Hungarian heroes of 1956.</en>
      <fr>Tout le monde rend hommage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3069">à</DiscourseConnective> la mémoire des héros hongrois tombés en 1956.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2827" docOffset="22">
      <en>Now, after 50 years, with a historical perspective, and after the fall of the Soviet communist regime, we can clearly see the historic importance of the 1956 Hungarian Revolution and the fight for freedom.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, cinquante ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3144">après</DiscourseConnective>, avec le recul historique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3176">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3179">après</DiscourseConnective> la chute du régime communiste soviétique, nous nous rendons bien compte de l'importance historique de cette révolution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3304">et</DiscourseConnective> de la lutte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3319">pour</DiscourseConnective> la liberté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3033" docOffset="23">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3336" annotation_id="3033">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3033" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is <Alignment alignment="3365" annotation_id="3045">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3045" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an event <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3059" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> the world celebrates itself - <Alignment alignment="3421" annotation_id="3094">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3094" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it has every reason to do so.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3033" annotation_id="3336">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3336" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, cet événement est <Alignment alignment="3045" annotation_id="3365">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3365" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'occasion pour le monde de s'acclamer lui-même - <Alignment alignment="3094" annotation_id="3421">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3421" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il a toutes les raisons d'agir de la sorte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3128" docOffset="24">
      <en>We can re-experience together the former enthusiasm with which peoples took sides with the Hungarian Revolution.</en>
      <fr>Nous pouvons revivre ensemble l'enthousiasme avec lequel les nations d'alors ont pris position en faveur de la révolution hongroise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3241" docOffset="25">
      <en>The world can now celebrate its generous sacrifice: Austria, which had just been liberated, opening the borders for 160 000 Hungarian refugees; the blood donations in Poland to help to rescue those wounded in the fight for freedom; the tens of thousands of Hungarian refugees who found new homes in various countries around the world.</en>
      <fr>Le monde peut à présent célébrer son généreux sacrifice: l'Autriche à peine libérée et ouvrant ses frontières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3711">à</DiscourseConnective> 160 000 réfugiés hongrois, les dons de sang faits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3763">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3774">afin de</DiscourseConnective> sauver les personnes blessées dans la lutte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3826">pour</DiscourseConnective> la liberté, les dizaines de milliers de réfugiés hongrois trouvant un nouveau foyer dans divers pays du globe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3576" docOffset="26">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3942" annotation_id="3576">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3576" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the real reason for this commemoration and joy is that Hungary today is an independent, sovereign and democratic State, with the rule of law, where the country can become a member of international organisations, such as the European Union, of its own free will.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3576" annotation_id="3942">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3942" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la véritable raison de cette commémoration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3996">et</DiscourseConnective> de cette liesse réside dans le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4035">qu'</DiscourseConnective>aujourd'hui, la Hongrie est un État indépendant, souverain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4097">et</DiscourseConnective> démocratique, dans lequel prédomine l'État de droit, lui permettant ainsi de décider librement d'adhérer à des organisations internationales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4242">par exemple</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3842" docOffset="27">
      <en>It is to the credit of 1956 that the world looks upon Hungary with a positive mind.</en>
      <fr>C'est grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4286">à</DiscourseConnective> cet événement de 1956 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4310">que</DiscourseConnective> la Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4325">s'</DiscourseConnective>est attiré les faveurs du monde entier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3926" docOffset="28">
      <en>The heroic struggle of the Hungarian freedom-fighters against Soviet predominance has earned Hungary recognition and appreciation everywhere up to the present day.</en>
      <fr>Le combat héroïque engagé par les défenseurs de la liberté hongrois contre la prédominance soviétique a depuis valu à la Hongrie la reconnaissance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4514">et</DiscourseConnective> l'estime générales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4090" docOffset="29">
      <en>It has become the custom, since the collapse of the Soviet Union, to present the Hungarian Revolution as a mortal blow to the Soviet world system.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4537">Après</DiscourseConnective> la chute de l'Union soviétique, il est devenu courant de présenter la révolution hongroise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4634">comme</DiscourseConnective> un coup mortel porté au régime soviétique dans le monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4237" docOffset="30">
      <en>That is not how anyone saw it during the early years of the military compulsion and the years of terror dispensed by the Kádár system.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est toutefois pas la perception qu'en avaient les gens de l'époque pendant les premières années de contrainte militaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4822">et</DiscourseConnective> les années de terreur instaurée par le régime de Kádár.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4372" docOffset="31">
      <en>At most, 1956 questioned the communist ideology and presented a dilemma to the left-wing, pro-Soviet section of the intelligentsia in western Europe, by making them face facts.</en>
      <fr>Tout au plus a-t-elle remis en question l'idéologie communiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4944">et</DiscourseConnective> présenté un dilemme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4967">à</DiscourseConnective> la section pro-soviétique de gauche de l'intelligentsia <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5025">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe occidentale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5047">en</DiscourseConnective> plaçant celle-ci face à la réalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4549" docOffset="32">
      <en>These attitudes can still be seen as a measure of intellectual sincerity.</en>
      <fr>Ces attitudes peuvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5108">encore</DiscourseConnective> être considérées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5132">comme</DiscourseConnective> un signe de sincérité intellectuelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4623" docOffset="33">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4623" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective> politically, the Soviet Union had learnt that it could assert itself in the region without hindrance or constraint: the Western powers had no direct security or economic interests there.</en>
      <fr>Il n'empêche que d'un point de vue politique, l'Union soviétique avait réalisé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5255">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle pouvait faire valoir ses droits dans la région <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5310">sans</DiscourseConnective> limites ni contraintes: les pouvoirs occidentaux n'avaient aucun intérêt économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5399">ou</DiscourseConnective> sécuritaire direct dans cette partie du globe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4814" docOffset="34">
      <en>There was an ambivalence between the real political intentions and propaganda of the great Powers, and thereby an ambivalence in the expectations of the Hungarian nation.</en>
      <fr>Il existait une ambivalence entre les véritables intentions politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5520">et</DiscourseConnective> la propagande des grandes puissances, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5561">et</DiscourseConnective>, partant, une ambivalence dans les attentes de la nation hongroise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4985" docOffset="35">
      <en>Neither the American nor the French or British Governments intended to intervene, or even query the integrity of the Soviet sphere of influence - they made this clear to the Soviet Union in October.</en>
      <fr>Aucun des gouvernements américain, français <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5676">ou</DiscourseConnective> britannique n'avait envisagé d'intervenir, ni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5725">même</DiscourseConnective> de vérifier l'intégrité de la sphère d'influence soviétique - ce qu'ils avaient clairement fait comprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5837">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union soviétique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5858">en</DiscourseConnective> octobre de cette année-là.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5184" docOffset="36">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5888" annotation_id="5184">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5184" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they left the Hungarian Government isolated and uninformed <Alignment alignment="5985" annotation_id="5247">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5247" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the freedom-fighters and the population under a misapprehension, for the propaganda of the State-sponsored western radio stations urged them to trust in the arrival of liberating assistance.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5184" annotation_id="5888">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5888" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Au contraire</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ils avaient abandonné le gouvernement hongrois à son isolement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5965">et</DiscourseConnective> à son ignorance, <Alignment alignment="5247" annotation_id="5985">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5985" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les défenseurs de la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6014">et</DiscourseConnective> la population <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6031">à</DiscourseConnective> leur méprise, la propagande diffusée par les stations de radio occidentales publiques encourageant ceux-ci <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6140">à</DiscourseConnective> croire dans l'arrivée d'une aide libératrice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5442" docOffset="37">
      <en>The communists could build the Berlin Wall in 1961 and use military intervention to crush the Prague Spring reform movement in 1968.</en>
      <fr>Les communistes ont pu construire le Mur de Berlin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6239">en</DiscourseConnective> 1961 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6247">et</DiscourseConnective> faire appel à l'armée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6272">pour</DiscourseConnective> réprimer le mouvement de réforme du Printemps de Prague <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6333">en</DiscourseConnective> 1968.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5575" docOffset="38">
      <en>What caused it to relinquish its sphere of influence in the Baltic and central and eastern Europe in 1989, and the collapse itself, was not 1956, but inherent systemic weaknesses and the Soviet Union's inability to compete either economically or in the arms race.</en>
      <fr>La diminution de leur sphère d'influence dans les pays baltes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6405">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'en Europe centrale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6433">et</DiscourseConnective> orientale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6447">en</DiscourseConnective> 1989 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6455">et</DiscourseConnective> la chute proprement dite du communisme ne sont pas dues aux événements de 1956, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6538">mais</DiscourseConnective> à des faiblesses inhérentes au régime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6581">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'incapacité de l'Union soviétique à faire face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6634">à</DiscourseConnective> la concurrence, que ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6659">soit</DiscourseConnective> sur le plan économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6687">ou</DiscourseConnective> dans la course à l'armement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5839" docOffset="39">
      <en>From another point of view, <Alignment alignment="6743" annotation_id="5867">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5867" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Hungarian Revolution and struggle for independence provided the first and weightiest evidence of the instability of the Communist regimes in the central European States, which possessed different historical, political, and cultural traditions from those of the Soviet Union.</en>
      <fr>Vue sous un autre angle <Alignment alignment="5867" annotation_id="6743">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6743" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la révolution hongroise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6778">et</DiscourseConnective> la lutte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6790">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'indépendance ont fourni la première preuve - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6842">et</DiscourseConnective> la plus convaincante - de l'instabilité des régimes communistes dans les États d'Europe centrale, lesquels possédaient des traditions politiques, culturelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7003">et</DiscourseConnective> historiques différentes de celles de l'Union soviétique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6155" docOffset="40">
      <en>These States had traditions of democracy.</en>
      <fr>Ces pays possédaient une tradition démocratique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6197" docOffset="41">
      <en>National independence had become something of almost intrinsic value.</en>
      <fr>L'indépendance nationale avait acquis une valeur quasiment intrinsèque.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6267" docOffset="42">
      <en>The struggles in Poland and Hungary in 1956, in Czechoslovakia in 1968, and in Poland again, headed by the Solidarity trade union, from the 1980s onwards, were concurrently struggles for basic democratic freedoms and for limiting Soviet influence.</en>
      <fr>Les luttes menées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7202">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7213">et</DiscourseConnective> en Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7227">en</DiscourseConnective> 1956, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7236">en</DiscourseConnective> Tchécoslovaquie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7255">en</DiscourseConnective> 1968, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7264">puis</DiscourseConnective> à nouveau en Pologne - entraînée par le syndicat Solidarité - à partir des années 1980 étaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7364">simultanément</DiscourseConnective> des combats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7390">pour</DiscourseConnective> les libertés démocratiques fondamentales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7436">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7439">pour</DiscourseConnective> la limitation de l'influence soviétique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6515" docOffset="43">
      <en>These events and struggles led to the democratic transitions in central Europe in 1989-90.</en>
      <fr>Ces événements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7500">et</DiscourseConnective> ces luttes ont abouti aux transitions démocratiques observées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7565">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe centrale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7584">en</DiscourseConnective> 1989 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7592">et</DiscourseConnective> 1990.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6606" docOffset="44">
      <en>A common feature of the 1956 revolution and the change of regime in 1989 is that both rejected party-state communism.</en>
      <fr>La révolution de 1956 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7623">et</DiscourseConnective> le changement de régime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7650">en</DiscourseConnective> 1989 ont ceci en commun <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7677">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7683">s'</DiscourseConnective>agissait dans les deux cas d'un rejet du communisme de l'État-parti.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6724" docOffset="45">
      <en>Faithfulness to the revolution and the legitimacy of our claims to it depend on whether we allow the line between our free Hungary today and the Hungary we had before 1989 to blur.</en>
      <fr>Notre fidélité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7769">à</DiscourseConnective> la révolution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7785">et</DiscourseConnective> la légitimité de nos prétentions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7821">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard de cette dernière dépendent de notre décision de gommer ou non la ligne de démarcation tracée entre notre Hongrie libre d'aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7965">et</DiscourseConnective> la Hongrie d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7981">avant</DiscourseConnective> 1989.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6905" docOffset="46">
      <en>The parallel lesson of 1956 and 1989 is that in both cases, history surpassed the aspirations that wanted more freedom within a socialist system.</en>
      <fr>Quant aux enseignements à tirer de 1956 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8033">et</DiscourseConnective> 1989, il apparaît dans les deux cas que l'histoire a dépassé les aspirations visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8120">à</DiscourseConnective> une plus grande liberté au sein d'un système socialiste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7051" docOffset="47">
      <en>The greatness of Premier Imre Nagy lies in the fact that he recognised that.</en>
      <fr>Le Premier ministre Imre Nagy doit sa notoriété <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8227">à</DiscourseConnective> la reconnaissance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8247">de ce fait</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7128" docOffset="48">
      <en>He stepped out of his communist past; he stepped out of the Soviet world system.</en>
      <fr>Il a abandonné son passé communiste; il a abandonné le régime soviétique mondial.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7209" docOffset="49">
      <en>He remained a left-wing politician, <Alignment alignment="8384" annotation_id="7245">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7245" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he undertook an historic role, he accepted the fate that the revolutionary Hungarian nation offered to him. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7357" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">And</DiscourseConnective> he would rather die than retreat.</en>
      <fr>Il est resté un homme politique de gauche, <Alignment alignment="7245" annotation_id="8384">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8384" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a endossé un rôle historique en acceptant le destin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8441">que</DiscourseConnective> lui offrait la nation hongroise révolutionnaire, préférant la mort <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8512">à</DiscourseConnective> la retraite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7395" docOffset="50">
      <en>(DE) On 22 October, the eve of the revolution, Heads of State, prime ministers and other distinguished guests took part in a gala event at the Budapest State Opera.</en>
      <fr>Le 22 octobre 1956, à la veille de la révolution, des chefs d'État, des Premiers ministres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8618">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres invités distingués ont pris part <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8663">à</DiscourseConnective> une soirée de gala <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8684">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Opéra national de Budapest.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7560" docOffset="51">
      <en>Some of those invited were from the countries that, at the time, had taken in many Hungarian refugees.</en>
      <fr>Parmi les invités figuraient des personnalités originaires des pays qui allaient accueillir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8808">à</DiscourseConnective> cette époque un grand nombre de réfugiés hongrois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7663" docOffset="52">
      <en>By the end of 1956, more than 153 000 Hungarians had fled to Austria, <Alignment alignment="8935" annotation_id="7733">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7733" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> another 30 000 followed them later.</en>
      <fr>Fin de l'année 1956, plus de 153 000 Hongrois avaient fui vers l'Autriche <Alignment alignment="7733" annotation_id="8935">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8935" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> trente mille autres allaient suivre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7773" docOffset="53">
      <en>Austria selflessly ensured that these refugees were accommodated and cared for, and organised the international aid that had become almost indispensable.</en>
      <fr>Faisant preuve d'altruisme, l'Autriche a veillé à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9028">que</DiscourseConnective> ces réfugiés soit logés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9056">et</DiscourseConnective> nourris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9067">et</DiscourseConnective> a organisé l'aide internationale, devenue plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9117">que</DiscourseConnective> nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7927" docOffset="54">
      <en>This aid extended to advice, legal assistance, help in finding work and even to schooling and religious ministry.</en>
      <fr>Cette aide a permis d'offrir des conseils, une assistance juridique, une aide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9211">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche d'un emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9238">et même</DiscourseConnective> un enseignement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9262">et</DiscourseConnective> un ministère religieux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8041" docOffset="55">
      <en>Austria <Alignment alignment="18246" annotation_id="8049">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8049" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> paved the way for emigration to third countries.</en>
      <fr>L'Autriche a <Alignment alignment="8049" annotation_id="9302">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9302" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> préparé l'émigration vers des pays tiers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8103" docOffset="56">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9383" annotation_id="8103">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8103" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, a tenth of the Hungarians remained in Austria, a country to which Hungarians had always felt close.</en>
      <fr>Un dixième des Hongrois sont <Alignment alignment="8103" annotation_id="9383">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9383" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> restés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9400">en</DiscourseConnective> Autriche, un pays dont ils se sont toujours sentis proches.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8212" docOffset="57">
      <en>Austria's aid was not, <Alignment alignment="9492" annotation_id="8235">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8235" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, restricted to helping the refugees.</en>
      <fr>L'aide autrichienne ne s'est <Alignment alignment="8235" annotation_id="9492">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9492" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas limitée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9514">à</DiscourseConnective> aider les réfugiés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8280" docOffset="58">
      <en>Our neighbour did not just follow the events from close by, but had real empathy for Hungary.</en>
      <fr>Notre voisin a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9551">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> suivi les événements de près, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9595">mais</DiscourseConnective> il a également fait preuve d'empathie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9638">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard de la Hongrie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8374" docOffset="59">
      <en>The occupying forces had only recently left the country; the Red Army had only recently moved out of Vienna.</en>
      <fr>Les forces d'occupation n'ont quitté le pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9708">que</DiscourseConnective> récemment; l'Armée rouge n'a abandonné Vienne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9758">que</DiscourseConnective> dernièrement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8483" docOffset="60">
      <en>People in Austria knew what it meant to live in a country that was not free.</en>
      <fr>Les Autrichiens savaient ce que cela signifiait de vivre dans un pays qui n'est pas libre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8560" docOffset="61">
      <en>They had experienced on a day-to-day basis how a lack of self-determination penetrated and damaged everything.</en>
      <fr>Ils avaient vécu au quotidien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9897">à</DiscourseConnective> quel point l'absence d'autonomie pouvait envahir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9948">et</DiscourseConnective> affecter chaque chose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8671" docOffset="62">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="9985" annotation_id="8674">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8674" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> shared experience of totalitarian regimes.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="8674" annotation_id="9985">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9985" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> partagé l'expérience des régimes totalitaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8722" docOffset="63">
      <en>We are <Alignment alignment="10054" annotation_id="8729">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8729" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> particularly grateful to the Federal Republic of Germany.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <Alignment alignment="8729" annotation_id="10054">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10054" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> particulièrement reconnaissants vis-à-vis de la République fédérale d'Allemagne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8792" docOffset="64">
      <en>The first Hungarian refugees arrived in Germany on 2 November 1956.</en>
      <fr>Les premiers réfugiés hongrois sont arrivés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10185">en</DiscourseConnective> Allemagne le 2 novembre 1956.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8860" docOffset="65">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10218" annotation_id="8860">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8860" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the government realised how many refugees there were, it decided to grant 10% of them asylum, even <Alignment alignment="10343" annotation_id="8964">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8964" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they had initially, on 7 November, only wanted to accept 3 000.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8860" annotation_id="10218">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10218" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le gouvernement a pris la mesure du nombre des réfugiés, il a décidé d'octroyer le droit d'asile à 10 % d'entre eux, <Alignment alignment="8964" annotation_id="10343">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10343" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, initialement, à savoir le 7 novembre, il n'avait accepté que 3 000 réfugiés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9035" docOffset="66">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10429" annotation_id="9035">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9035" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the refugees and exiles from East Germany were already putting a major strain on the German welfare system, the Hungarians were welcomed with great sympathy.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9035" annotation_id="10429">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10429" sense="Comparison.Concession">Alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les réfugiés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10452">et</DiscourseConnective> les exilés d'Allemagne de l'Est mettaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10497">déjà</DiscourseConnective> fortement sous pression le système de protection sociale allemand, les Hongrois ont été accueillis très chaleureusement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9202" docOffset="67">
      <en>The German Red Cross spent a total of DM 30 million on supporting the refugees.</en>
      <fr>La Croix-Rouge allemande a dépensé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10658">en</DiscourseConnective> tout trente millions de marks <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10691">pour</DiscourseConnective> venir en aide aux réfugiés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9282" docOffset="68">
      <en>20 000 Hungarian refugees made a new home for themselves in Germany.</en>
      <fr>Vingt mille réfugiés hongrois ont trouvé un nouveau foyer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10782">en</DiscourseConnective> Allemagne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9351" docOffset="69">
      <en>1 200 students were integrated into German universities, <Alignment alignment="10867" annotation_id="9408">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9408" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a bilingual secondary school was set up in Kastl.</en>
      <fr>Mille deux cents étudiants sont entrés dans les universités allemandes <Alignment alignment="9408" annotation_id="10867">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10867" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une école bilingue a été créée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10901">à</DiscourseConnective> Kastl.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9462" docOffset="70">
      <en>On behalf of the Hungarian people, I would like to thank you for that.</en>
      <fr>Au nom du peuple hongrois, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10946">à</DiscourseConnective> vous remercier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10963">pour</DiscourseConnective> cet accueil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9533" docOffset="71">
      <en>(HU) The commemoration of 1956 has to remember the liberation experienced at the time, with its sense of elemental and pure joy.</en>
      <fr>La commémoration de 1956 doit se souvenir de la libération vécue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11046">à</DiscourseConnective> l'époque <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11057">et</DiscourseConnective> de la joie intense et naturelle qu'elle a entraînée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9662" docOffset="72">
      <en>This is what radiates from the faces of the demonstrators on 23 October 1956 visible on every surviving photograph and film.</en>
      <fr>C'est ce sentiment qui éclairait les visages des manifestants du 23 octobre 1956 et était bien visible sur les photos <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11231">et</DiscourseConnective> les films d'époque qui ont été conservés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9787" docOffset="73">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11276" annotation_id="9787">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9787" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">And</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is what is mentioned by everyone who remembers.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9787" annotation_id="11276">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11276" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est aussi ce que disent tous ceux qui se souviennent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9844" docOffset="74">
      <en>I would like to conclude with the words of a renowned writer. Géza Ottlik wrote: '<Alignment alignment="11405" annotation_id="9926">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9926" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you were not there from the beginning to the end, no poetic imagination, no fervent revolutionary heart, not even the mind of a genius can grasp what it was like.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11344">à</DiscourseConnective> conclure par les propos de Géza Ottlik, écrivain renommé: "<Alignment alignment="9926" annotation_id="11405">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11405" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous n'étiez pas présents du début <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11443">à</DiscourseConnective> la fin, aucune imagination poétique, aucune ferveur révolutionnaire, pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11518">même</DiscourseConnective> l'esprit d'un génie ne pourrait saisir ce dont il s'agissait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10092" docOffset="75">
      <en>I could not have imagined beforehand either the happiness of walking through the streets of Budapest, <Alignment alignment="11673" annotation_id="10194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10194" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I had not known, I simply had no idea that such happiness existed ...</en>
      <fr>Je n'aurais pas pu imaginer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11613">auparavant</DiscourseConnective> le bonheur de marcher dans les rues de Budapest, <Alignment alignment="10194" annotation_id="11673">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11673" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je ne savais pas, je ne savais tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11719">simplement</DiscourseConnective> pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11734">que</DiscourseConnective> ce bonheur existait...</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10272" docOffset="76">
      <en>No one values his wretched life - perhaps made too wretched - more dearly than the abstract honour of the homeland.</en>
      <fr>Personne n'apprécie sa vie misérable, peut-être rendue trop misérable, plus chèrement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11847">que</DiscourseConnective> dans l'honneur abstrait de la patrie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10388" docOffset="77">
      <en>See the faces; notice ... their relieved sense of calm.</en>
      <fr>Scrutez ces visages, remarquez leur sérénité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10444" docOffset="78">
      <en>For the main thing is this: not the brave resolve, not the heroic daring, but what shines in their eyes: a glad relief.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11935">En effet</DiscourseConnective>, le principal ne réside pas tant dans leur bravoure ou leur courage héroïque que dans ce que leurs yeux expriment: une sérénité joyeuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10564" docOffset="79">
      <en>They are marching, together or <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10595" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">separately</DiscourseConnective>, facing tanks, cannons, and machine guns aimed at them, with a profound, happy serenity.</en>
      <fr>Ensemble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12090">ou</DiscourseConnective> séparément, ils marchent face aux tanks, aux canons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12145">et</DiscourseConnective> aux mitrailleuses pointés sur eux, dans un élan de sérénité profonde et joyeuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10695" docOffset="80">
      <en>Nothing is dearer to them than their regained human dignity.'</en>
      <fr>Rien ne leur est plus cher <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12256">que</DiscourseConnective> leur dignité humaine retrouvée".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10757" docOffset="81">
      <en>Thank you.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10768" id="085" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10768" docOffset="82">
      <en>Thank you very much for having shared with us your thoughts about the events that we are commemorating today, Mr President.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je vous remercie beaucoup d'avoir partagé avec nous vos pensées sur les événements dont nous nous souvenons aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10892" docOffset="83">
      <en>We wish your country all the best.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons le meilleur à votre pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10927" docOffset="84">
      <en>Europe has acted as a beacon that has guided many countries, not just in the East, but also in the West and the South of Europe, towards freedom and democracy.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe a officié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12516">comme</DiscourseConnective> un phare qui a guidé bon nombre de pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12563">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12577">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Est, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12586">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12597">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ouest <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12607">et</DiscourseConnective> au sud de l'Europe, vers la liberté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12646">et</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11087" docOffset="85">
      <en>There is no question that the things you have said to us will increase the younger generations' knowledge of those historic events.</en>
      <fr>Il est évident <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12679">que</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12686">que</DiscourseConnective> vous nous avez rappelé permettra aux dernières générations de mieux comprendre ces événements historiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11219" docOffset="86">
      <en>We thank you very much for being here <Alignment alignment="12836" annotation_id="11257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11257" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we hope that you and the Hungarian Government can continue to make progress towards full integration into the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Nous vous remercions de votre présence <Alignment alignment="11257" annotation_id="12836">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12836" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12853">que</DiscourseConnective> le gouvernement hongrois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12882">et</DiscourseConnective> vous-même pourrez avancer sur la voie d'une pleine intégration à l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11387" docOffset="87">
      <en>Thank you very much.</en>
      <fr>Merci beaucoup.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11408" docOffset="88">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11419" docOffset="89">
      <en>(The formal sitting was closed at 12.25 p.m.)</en>
      <fr>(La séance solennelle est levée à 12 h 25)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11465" id="086" name="Gérard Onesta">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11465" docOffset="90">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, regarding the agenda for our sitting, I think, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11531" sense="Expansion.Alternative">unless</DiscourseConnective> I am mistaken, that it had been announced that the voting would begin at 12.30 p.m.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, concernant l'ordre du jour de notre séance, il me semble, sauf erreur de ma part, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13153">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il avait été annoncé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13177">que</DiscourseConnective> le vote commencerait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13202">à</DiscourseConnective> 12 h 30.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11622" docOffset="91">
      <en>I think that probably explains why a number of fellow Members are still not here.</en>
      <fr>J'ai l'impression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13231">que</DiscourseConnective> cela explique que certains collègues ne soient pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13286">encore</DiscourseConnective> là.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11704" docOffset="92">
      <en>Might not voting time quite simply be begun at 12.30 p.m., <Alignment alignment="22369" annotation_id="11763">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11763" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> announced?</en>
      <fr>Est-ce que l'on ne pourrait tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13330">simplement</DiscourseConnective> pas commencer la séance des votes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13375">à</DiscourseConnective> 12 h 30, <Alignment alignment="11763" annotation_id="13386">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13386" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que cela avait été annoncé?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11777" docOffset="93">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11788" id="087" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11788" docOffset="94">
      <en>The vote has been announced <Alignment alignment="13461" annotation_id="11816">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11816" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> everybody is continuing with the House's work.</en>
      <fr>Le vote a été annoncé <Alignment alignment="11816" annotation_id="13461">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13461" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> chacun suit les travaux de l'Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11867" docOffset="95">
      <en>I do not believe that it is appropriate to wait <Alignment alignment="13548" annotation_id="11915">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11915" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">until</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is precisely 12.30 p.m. <Alignment alignment="13571" annotation_id="11948">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11948" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I made it very clear that it would take place <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12000" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> the formal sitting ended.</en>
      <fr>Selon moi, il n'est pas opportun d'attendre <Alignment alignment="11915" annotation_id="13548">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13548" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> 12h30 précises <Alignment alignment="11948" annotation_id="13571">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13571" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">dans la mesure où</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ai dit clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13609">que</DiscourseConnective> le vote aurait lieu dès la fin de la séance solennelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12031" id="088" name="Ignasi Guardans Cambó">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12031" docOffset="96">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, I heard you, not via simultaneous interpreting but directly, in your wonderful Castilian, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12140" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> you stated, at the end of the debate on this issue this morning, that the vote would take place at 12.30 p.m.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, je vous ai écouté, non pas par le biais de d'interprétation simultanée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13769">mais</DiscourseConnective> directement dans votre très bel espagnol. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13816">À</DiscourseConnective> la fin du débat de ce matin sur ce thème, vous avez déclaré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13878">que</DiscourseConnective> le vote aurait lieu à 12 h30.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12254" docOffset="97">
      <en>You did not say anything else: you said that the vote would take place at 12.30 p.m.</en>
      <fr>Vous n'avez rien dit d'autre: vous avez dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13956">que</DiscourseConnective> le vote aurait lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13980">à</DiscourseConnective> 12h30.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12339" docOffset="98">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="14008" annotation_id="12347">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12347" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ask you, out of respect for the honourable Members in relation to an extremely delicate issue, where every vote counts, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12477" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> they always do, to be sensitive enough to take the vote at 12.30 and not at 12.25 or 12.26.</en>
      <fr>Je vous demanderai <Alignment alignment="12347" annotation_id="14008">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14008" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, par respect <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14026">pour</DiscourseConnective> les honorables députés et dans un dossier très sensible dans lequel chaque voix compte, ce qui est toujours le cas, de faire preuve de la délicatesse requise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14189">pour</DiscourseConnective> procéder au vote à 12h30 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14219">et</DiscourseConnective> non <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14226">à</DiscourseConnective> 12h25 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14234">ou</DiscourseConnective> à 12h26.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12572" id="089" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12572" docOffset="99">
      <en>Thank you for complimenting my use of Castilian, Mr Guardans.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur Guardans, je vous remercie de vos éloges sur ma maîtrise de l'espagnol.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12634" docOffset="100">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14327" annotation_id="12634">
          <Alignment alignment="14327" annotation_id="12634">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12634" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, I generally express myself rather well in that language <Alignment alignment="14393" annotation_id="12699">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12699" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="14396" annotation_id="12703">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12703" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I remember rightly, I said 12.30, after the formal sitting.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12634" annotation_id="14327">
          <Alignment alignment="12634" annotation_id="14327">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14327" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En réalité</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, je m'exprime en général <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14363">plutôt</DiscourseConnective> bien dans cette langue <Alignment alignment="12699" annotation_id="14393">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14393" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="12703" annotation_id="14396">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14396" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je me souviens bien, j'ai dit à 12h30 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14437">après</DiscourseConnective> la séance solennelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12766" docOffset="101">
      <en>The Minutes will tell us which of us is right, <Alignment alignment="14518" annotation_id="12813">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12813" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is no need for you to call on me to show sensitivity in taking the decisions that I consider to be appropriate.</en>
      <fr>Le procès-verbal nous dira qui de nous avait raison, <Alignment alignment="12813" annotation_id="14518">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14518" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous n'avez pas à me demander de faire preuve de délicatesse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14584">en</DiscourseConnective> prenant les décisions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14609">que</DiscourseConnective> je juge appropriées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12935" id="090" name="Josu Ortuondo Larrea">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12935" docOffset="102">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, I would like to reiterate what Mr Guardans said to you: that, at the end of the debate on the peace process, you stated that the vote would be at half past twelve, at 12.30, and, <Alignment alignment="14818" annotation_id="13133">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13133" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in the Castilian that you speak so well, what you said - 12.30, after the formal sitting - is in no way inconsistent with voting time taking place at 12.30.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14671">à</DiscourseConnective> reprendre les propos de M. Guardans, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14710">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14719">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à l'issue du débat sur le processus de paix, vous avez affirmé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14785">que</DiscourseConnective> la vote aurait lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14809">à</DiscourseConnective> 12h30. <Alignment alignment="13133" annotation_id="14818">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14818" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans cette langue espagnole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14860">que</DiscourseConnective> vous parlez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14876">si</DiscourseConnective> bien, ce que vous avez dit - à 12h30, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14917">après</DiscourseConnective> la séance solennelle - ne contredit en rien la tenue d'un vote à 12h30.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13303" docOffset="103">
      <en>The second part would simply be a safeguard so that, in the event that the formal sitting does not end at 12.30, the vote could take place after it.</en>
      <fr>La seconde partie de ce que vous avez dit était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15043">simplement</DiscourseConnective> une sorte d'avertissement précisant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15090">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15093">au cas où</DiscourseConnective> la séance solennelle ne serait pas terminée à 12h30, le vote pourrait avoir lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15184">après</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13452" docOffset="104">
      <en>That is what your Castilian words mean.</en>
      <fr>C'est là le sens de vos propos en espagnol.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13492" id="091" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13492" docOffset="105">
      <en>I am not going to take any more points of order.</en>
      <fr>Je n'accepte plus aucune objection.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
