<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statement by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclaration de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="27" id="020" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27" docOffset="1">
      <en>Yesterday another murder was committed by the terrorist organisation ETA.</en>
      <fr>L'organisation terroriste ETA a commis hier un nouveau meurtre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="101" docOffset="2">
      <en>A 46-year-old army sergeant-major, Luis Conde de la Cruz, was killed by a car bomb in northern Spain.</en>
      <fr>Le sergent-major Luis Conde de la Cruz, âgé de 46 ans, a été tué lors d'un attentat à la voiture piégée dans le nord de l'Espagne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="203" docOffset="3">
      <en>This was the third car bomb to explode in Spain within 24 hours.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="227">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de la troisième explosion de ce genre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="272">en</DiscourseConnective> Espagne au cours des 24 dernières heures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="268" docOffset="4">
      <en>Several people were injured in the three blasts, one of them seriously.</en>
      <fr>Plusieurs personnes ont été blessées lors de ces trois déflagrations, dont une sérieusement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="340" docOffset="5">
      <en>The European Parliament strongly condemns this act of terrorism and wishes to express its deep concern.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen condamne fermement cet acte de terrorisme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="474">et</DiscourseConnective> exprime sa profonde préoccupation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="444" docOffset="6">
      <en>On behalf of the European Parliament, may I express my sincere condolences to the family and relatives of Sergeant-Major Conde and our solidarity with Spain, its authorities and especially the Spanish security forces.</en>
      <fr>Au nom du Parlement européen, je voudrais exprimer mes sincères condoléances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="589">à</DiscourseConnective> la famille <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="602">et</DiscourseConnective> aux parents du sergent-major Conde, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="641">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que notre solidarité avec l'Espagne, ses autorités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="698">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="701">surtout</DiscourseConnective> ses forces de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="662" docOffset="7">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="421326" annotation_id="670">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="670" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to express our support and deep sympathy to those who were injured in the bomb blasts and to their families.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="379" annotation_id="745">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="745" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> exprimer notre soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="778">et</DiscourseConnective> notre profonde sympathie aux personnes qui ont été blessées lors des explosions, ainsi qu'à leurs familles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="789" docOffset="8">
      <en>We must reiterate time and again in no uncertain terms that terrorism is a direct attack on freedom, human rights and democracy.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons répéter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="909">sans</DiscourseConnective> cesse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="920">et</DiscourseConnective> clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="934">que</DiscourseConnective> le terrorisme représente une atteinte directe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="984">à</DiscourseConnective> la liberté, aux droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1020">et</DiscourseConnective> à la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="918" docOffset="9">
      <en>We cannot repeat often enough that there is no justification whatsoever for terrorism.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne dirons jamais assez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1068">que</DiscourseConnective> rien ne justifie le terrorisme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1005" docOffset="10">
      <en>For this reason we must act together in our fight against terrorism, always respecting the rule of law and applying the full force of the law.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1104">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous devons agir ensemble dans notre lutte contre le terrorisme, en respectant toujours l'État de droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1223">et</DiscourseConnective> en appliquant pleinement la loi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1148" docOffset="11">
      <en>The European Union is a community based on solidarity.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne est une communauté basée sur la solidarité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1203" docOffset="12">
      <en>An act of terrorism in a member country of the European Union is an attack on the entire European Union, on every single one of us.</en>
      <fr>Tout acte terroriste dans un pays membre de l'Union européenne constitue une attaque contre toute l'Union européenne, contre chacun d'entre nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1335" docOffset="13">
      <en>I now ask you all to rise for a minute's silence.</en>
      <fr>Je vous demande de bien vouloir vous lever <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1511">et</DiscourseConnective> observer une minute de silence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1385" docOffset="14">
      <en>(The House rose and observed a minute's silence.)</en>
      <fr>(L'Assemblée, debout, observe une minute de silence.)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
