<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>3.</en>
    <fr>3.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Burma</en>
    <fr>Birmanie</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="9" id="186" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9" docOffset="2">
      <en>The next item is the debate on six motions for a resolution on Burma.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur six propositions de résolution sur la Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="79" id="187" name="Marios Matsakis ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="79" docOffset="3">
      <en>author. - Madam President, Commissioner, Burma is a regular theme in our sessions on human rights breaches.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, la Birmanie est un thème récurrent de nos débats sur les violations des droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="187" docOffset="4">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="250" annotation_id="187">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="187" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we had a prize for the regime with the worst human rights record, Burma would certainly be a very strong contender.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="187" annotation_id="250">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="250" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avions un Prix du régime ayant le pire des palmarès en matière de droits de l'homme, la Birmanie serait certainement un concurrent très sérieux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="306" docOffset="5">
      <en>Incidentally, Burma is <Alignment alignment="440" annotation_id="329">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="329" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a world star with respect to another evil: drugs.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="403">Soit dit en passant</DiscourseConnective>, la Birmanie bat <Alignment alignment="14634" annotation_id="440">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="440" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des records dans une autre infamie: les drogues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="384" docOffset="6">
      <en>According to the International Narcotics Central Strategy Report for 2006, Burma is the world's second largest producer of illicit opium, accounting for more than 90% of South-East Asian heroin.</en>
      <fr>D'après le rapport 2006 de l'International Narcotics Central Strategy, la Birmanie est le deuxième producteur mondial d'opium illégal, fournissant plus de 90 % de l'héroïne du Sud-Est asiatique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="579" docOffset="7">
      <en>I do not know how well the breaches of human rights are connected to drug production in Burma, <Alignment alignment="812" annotation_id="674">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="674" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I know they should both be dealt with firmly, quickly and effectively.</en>
      <fr>J'ignore comment les violations des droits de l'homme peuvent bien être liées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="768">à</DiscourseConnective> la production de stupéfiants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="799">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie, <Alignment alignment="4775" annotation_id="812">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="812" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je sais que toutes deux devraient être traitées avec fermeté, rapidité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="888">et</DiscourseConnective> efficacité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="749" docOffset="8">
      <en>Unfortunately, it seems that the EU's stance - as well as that of the international community - against the Burmese regime has not been drastic enough to have any good effect.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="903">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, il semble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="930">que</DiscourseConnective> la position de l'UE - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="956">comme</DiscourseConnective> celle de la communauté internationale - contre le régime birman n'ait pas été suffisamment intransigeante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1068">pour</DiscourseConnective> avoir le moindre effet positif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="925" docOffset="9">
      <en>A good example is the recent granting of permission by the Council to the Burmese Foreign Minister to attend the ASEM meeting, only days <Alignment alignment="1266" annotation_id="1062">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1062" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the military junta in Burma had extended the deplorable house arrest of Mrs Aung San Suu Kyi.</en>
      <fr>Le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1113">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil ait récemment autorisé le ministre birman des affaires étrangères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1194">à</DiscourseConnective> assister à la réunion du sommet Asie-Europe, quelques jours seulement <Alignment alignment="1062" annotation_id="1266">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1266" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la prolongation, par la junte militaire birmane, de l'affligeante assignation à résidence de Mme Aung San Suu Kyi, en est un bon exemple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1162" docOffset="10">
      <en>The Council ought to give an explanation for this action.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil a le devoir de donner une explication de son action.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1220" docOffset="11">
      <en>Another example is the fact that an arms embargo on Burma is largely ineffective, <Alignment alignment="1586" annotation_id="1302">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1302" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> countries like China and India are not taking part in it.</en>
      <fr>Un autre exemple est le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1503">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un embargo sur les armes à destination de la Birmanie est largement inefficace, <Alignment alignment="6435" annotation_id="1586">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1586" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1603">comme</DiscourseConnective> la Chine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1618">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Inde n'y adhèrent pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1366" docOffset="12">
      <en>Surely pressure must be put on such countries to join in the arms embargo against Burma?</en>
      <fr>Il est certain qu'il faut faire pression sur ces pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1700">pour qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils se joignent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1724">à</DiscourseConnective> l'embargo sur les armes contre la Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1455" docOffset="13">
      <en>In conclusion, let me reiterate our call for the immediate release from house arrest of Mrs Aung San Suu Kyi.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1770">Pour conclure</DiscourseConnective>, permettez-moi de répéter notre appel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1822">à</DiscourseConnective> la cessation immédiate de l'assignation à résidence de Mme Aung San Suu Kyi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1565" docOffset="14">
      <en>That remarkable lady has contributed enormously to peace and democracy, not only in Burma but internationally, <Alignment alignment="22909" annotation_id="1676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1676" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> she has been awarded both the Nobel Peace Prize and our own Sakharov Prize.</en>
      <fr>Cette femme remarquable a énormément contribué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1948">à</DiscourseConnective> la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1958">et</DiscourseConnective> à la démocratie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1978">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1992">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2005">mais</DiscourseConnective> dans le monde entier, <Alignment alignment="1676" annotation_id="2032">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2032" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle a reçu le Prix Nobel de la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2072">et</DiscourseConnective> notre Prix Sakharov.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1756" docOffset="15">
      <en>It is truly outrageous and shameful that she has spent more than 11 of the last 17 years in detention in her own country.</en>
      <fr>Il est vraiment infâme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2119">et</DiscourseConnective> honteux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2130">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle ait passé plus de 11 des 17 dernières années <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2183">en</DiscourseConnective> détention dans son propre pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1878" docOffset="16">
      <en>International and EU calls for her release have had no effect.</en>
      <fr>Les appels internationaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2244">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'UE en faveur de sa libération n'ont eu aucun effet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1941" docOffset="17">
      <en>Our patience has long run out.</en>
      <fr>Notre patience est à bout.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1972" docOffset="18">
      <en>We recommend that more drastic action, such as expansion of sanctions and enlargement of the list of those targeted, must now take place.</en>
      <fr>Nous recommandons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2349">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> la prise de mesures plus drastiques, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2397">comme</DiscourseConnective> le renforcement des sanctions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2433">et</DiscourseConnective> l'allongement de la liste de ceux qu'elles visent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2110" id="188" name="Zdzisław Zbigniew Podkański ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2110" docOffset="19">
      <en>author. - (PL) Madam President, the European Union has adopted a firm stance regarding the abuses perpetrated by the military regime in Burma/Myanmar.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (PL) Madame la Présidente, l'Union européenne a adopté une attitude ferme contre les abus perpétrés par le régime militaire en place en Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2261" docOffset="20">
      <en>Europe is pressing for Burma/Myanmar to show more respect for human rights and get back on course towards democracy.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe demande instamment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2671">que</DiscourseConnective> la Birmanie améliore son bilan en matière de droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2738">et</DiscourseConnective> se rallie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2751">à</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2378" docOffset="21">
      <en>The authorities in Burma/Myanmar are continuing to imprison and persecute activists working for democracy.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités birmanes continuent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2802">à</DiscourseConnective> emprisonner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2816">et</DiscourseConnective> à persécuter des militants œuvrant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2854">pour</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2485" docOffset="22">
      <en>I believe there are two ways in which the situation in that country could be improved.</en>
      <fr>Il existe selon moi deux solutions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2909">pour</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la situation dans ce pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2572" docOffset="23">
      <en>One is for China and India to stop supplying it with arms and other strategic equipment.</en>
      <fr>La première implique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2972">que</DiscourseConnective> la Chine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2985">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Inde arrêtent de lui fournir des armes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3029">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres équipements stratégiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2661" docOffset="24">
      <en>The other is for foreign enterprises investing in Burma/Myanmar to respect human rights.</en>
      <fr>La seconde requiert <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3087">que</DiscourseConnective> les entreprises étrangères investissant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3131">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie respectent les droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2750" docOffset="25">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="27105" annotation_id="2756">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2756" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> important to develop programmes to assist civil society in Burma/Myanmar, notably organisations for women and ethnic minorities.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <Alignment alignment="2756" annotation_id="3188">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3188" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de développer des programmes de soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3238">à</DiscourseConnective> la société civile birmane, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3267">notamment</DiscourseConnective> aux organisations d'aide aux femmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3313">et</DiscourseConnective> aux minorités ethniques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2890" docOffset="26">
      <en>I represent the Union for Europe of the Nations Group.</en>
      <fr>Je représente le groupe Union <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3371">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe des Nations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2945" docOffset="27">
      <en>We support all actions aimed at protecting human rights and respect for the principles of the rule of law and democratic freedoms including freedom of association and freedom of speech.</en>
      <fr>Nous soutenons toutes les initiatives visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3443">à</DiscourseConnective> la protection des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3481">et</DiscourseConnective> au respect des principes de l'État de droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3528">et</DiscourseConnective> des libertés démocratiques, y compris la liberté d'association <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3594">et</DiscourseConnective> la liberté d'expression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3131" docOffset="28">
      <en>We will continue to do so at all times.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne cesserons de le faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3171" docOffset="29">
      <en>We wish to draw attention to the financial situation of the Burmese people.</en>
      <fr>Nous voudrions attirer l'attention sur la situation financière de la population birmane.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3247" docOffset="30">
      <en>Over 15 million of them are living below the poverty line. This amounts to about 30% of the population.</en>
      <fr>Plus de 15 millions de Birmans vivent sous le seuil de pauvreté, soit environ 30 % de la population.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3351" docOffset="31">
      <en>Immediate assistance is needed to protect the life and health of these individuals.</en>
      <fr>Une assistance immédiate est requise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3880">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger la vie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3901">et</DiscourseConnective> la santé de ces personnes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3435" id="189" name="Marc Tarabella ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3435" docOffset="32">
      <en>author. - (FR) Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I have often spoken in this House about the situation in Burma, making frequent use of the terms 'repression', 'military junta in power' and 'flouted human rights'.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, je me suis souvent exprimé dans cet hémicycle sur la situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4068">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie et les mots répression, junte militaire au pouvoir, droits de l'homme bafoués émaillaient déjà mon discours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3668" docOffset="33">
      <en>The resolution that we are going to vote on today is a call for Burma to bring an end to certain actions.</en>
      <fr>La résolution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4203">que</DiscourseConnective> nous allons voter aujourd'hui est un appel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4250">à</DiscourseConnective> la Birmanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4264">afin qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle mette un terme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4292">à</DiscourseConnective> certains agissements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3774" docOffset="34">
      <en>Along with my colleagues, I particularly and principally deplore the house arrest since 30 May 2003 of Aung San Suu Kyi, the Burmese opposition member who celebrated her 62nd birthday on Tuesday and has spent eleven out of the last seventeen years in detention, mainly under house arrest.</en>
      <fr>Avec mes collègues, je déplore, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4348">notamment</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4358">et</DiscourseConnective> principalement, l'assignation à résidence, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4404">depuis</DiscourseConnective> le 30 mai 2003, d'Aung San Suu Kyi, l'opposante birmane qui a fêté ses 62 ans ce mardi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4498">et</DiscourseConnective> qui a passé onze des dernières dix-sept années <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4548">en</DiscourseConnective> détention, principalement assignée à résidence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4063" docOffset="35">
      <en>She has only been able to leave her home once, for health reasons requiring urgent attention, <Alignment alignment="4705" annotation_id="4157">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4157" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> she has little contact with the outside world.</en>
      <fr>Elle n'a pu quitter sa demeure qu'une seule fois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4649">pour</DiscourseConnective> des raisons de santé impliquant des soins urgents, <Alignment alignment="4157" annotation_id="4705">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4705" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> n'a que peu de contacts avec l'extérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4208" docOffset="36">
      <en>Aung San Suu Kyi is the symbol of the Burmese opposition to the military dictatorship, and <Alignment alignment="4838" annotation_id="4299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4299" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> received the Nobel prize in 1991.</en>
      <fr>Aung San Suu Kyi est l'emblème de l'opposition birmane <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4805">à</DiscourseConnective> la dictature militaire; elle a <Alignment alignment="4299" annotation_id="4838">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4838" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> reçu le prix Nobel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4868">en</DiscourseConnective> 1991.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4338" docOffset="37">
      <en>It is absolutely unacceptable for her to be under house arrest.</en>
      <fr>Il est absolument inadmissible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4908">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4916">soit</DiscourseConnective> assignée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4930">à</DiscourseConnective> résidence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4402" docOffset="38">
      <en>This is why we are calling for her immediate, unconditional release.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4943">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous réclamons sa libération immédiate et inconditionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4471" docOffset="39">
      <en>Burma must entirely stop persecuting and imprisoning pro-democracy activists and must release those who are already in prison.</en>
      <fr>La Birmanie doit absolument cesser de persécuter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5067">et</DiscourseConnective> de mettre derrière les barreaux les activistes pro-démocrates <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5132">et</DiscourseConnective> elle doit relâcher ceux qui sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5168">déjà</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5173">en</DiscourseConnective> prison.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4598" docOffset="40">
      <en>I am thinking <Alignment alignment="5193" annotation_id="4612">
          <Alignment alignment="16263" annotation_id="4612">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4612" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> of U Win Tin, a journalist who, now aged 77, has been in prison for nearly 20 years for writing a letter to the United Nations reporting the poor conditions under which political prisoners were being held.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <Alignment alignment="4196" annotation_id="5193">
          <Alignment alignment="4612" annotation_id="5193">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5193" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5208">à</DiscourseConnective> U Win Tin, un journaliste qui aujourd'hui, à 77 ans, est emprisonné <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5278">depuis</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5285">bientôt</DiscourseConnective> 20 ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5300">pour</DiscourseConnective> avoir écrit aux Nations unies une lettre dénonçant les mauvaises conditions de détention dont étaient victimes les prisonniers politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4832" docOffset="41">
      <en>As Vice-Chairman of the ANASE delegation in Parliament, I see the growing role that this organisation can play in the region.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5447">tant que</DiscourseConnective> vice-président de la délégation ANASE au sein de ce Parlement, je mesure le rôle croissant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5547">que</DiscourseConnective> peut jouer cette organisation dans la région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4958" docOffset="42">
      <en>May it have a positive influence on the Burmese Government in the near future!</en>
      <fr>Puisse-t-elle avoir dans un avenir proche une influence positive sur le gouvernement birman!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5037" id="190" name="Charles Tannock ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5037" docOffset="43">
      <en>author. - Madam President, Burma has one of the world's worst human rights and lack of democracy track records, with people-trafficking for sexual exploitation, domestic service and forced commercial labour.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, la Birmanie affiche le pire palmarès mondial en matière de non-respect des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5820">et</DiscourseConnective> d'absence de démocratie, de trafic d'êtres humains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5874">à</DiscourseConnective> des fins d'exploitation sexuelle, de service domestique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5932">et</DiscourseConnective> autre type de travail forcé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5245" docOffset="44">
      <en>This is compounded by the military junta's severe economic mismanagement.</en>
      <fr>Cette situation est encore aggravée par la calamiteuse gestion économique de la junte militaire au pouvoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5319" docOffset="45">
      <en>Burma <Alignment alignment="6090" annotation_id="5325">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5325" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remains the world's second-largest producer of illicit opium.</en>
      <fr>La Birmanie reste <Alignment alignment="5325" annotation_id="6090">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6090" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le deuxième plus gros producteur d'opium illégal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5392" docOffset="46">
      <en>Despite multi-party elections in 1990, which resulted in the NLD victory, the repressive military junta continues to refuse to hand over power.</en>
      <fr>Malgré les élections multipartites de 1990, qui ont été remportées par le NLD, la junte militaire répressive continue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6268">à</DiscourseConnective> refuser de transmettre le pouvoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5536" docOffset="47">
      <en>NLD leader and Nobel Laureate Aung San Suu Kyi, who marked her 62nd birthday this Tuesday, has been detained for more than 11 of the past 18 years.</en>
      <fr>Le leader du NLD <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6322">et</DiscourseConnective> lauréat du Prix Nobel de la paix, Mme Aung San Suu Kyi, dont c'était le 62e anniversaire mardi, a été maintenue en détention pendant plus de 11 des 18 dernières années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5684" docOffset="48">
      <en>In February 2006, the junta extended her detention for yet another year.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6494">En</DiscourseConnective> février 2006, la junte a prolongé sa détention d'une année supplémentaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5757" docOffset="49">
      <en>Her supporters, as well as those who promote democracy and improved human rights, are routinely harassed or jailed in a country with no independent judiciary and brutal law enforcement agencies.</en>
      <fr>Ses partisans, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6587">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que ceux qui militent pour la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6634">et</DiscourseConnective> les droits de l'homme, sont continuellement harcelés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6690">ou</DiscourseConnective> incarcérés dans ce pays où le pouvoir judiciaire n'est pas indépendant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6764">et</DiscourseConnective> où les forces de police appliquent la loi avec brutalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5952" docOffset="50">
      <en>Following the recent UN Security Council refusal to apply sanctions against Burma, disgracefully, the UN Human Rights Council has focused almost entirely and exclusively on one single country - Israel - totally ignoring Burma.</en>
      <fr>Suite au récent - et scandaleux - refus du Conseil de sécurité des Nations Unies d'appliquer des sanctions contre la Birmanie, le Conseil des Nations Unies pour les droits de l'homme s'est concentré presque entièrement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7044">et</DiscourseConnective> exclusivement sur un seul pays - Israël - en ignorant la Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6179" docOffset="51">
      <en>The EU, along with neighbouring ASEAN countries, and along with India and China as well, must now do much more to apply pressure to secure Aung San Suu Kyi's release.</en>
      <fr>Avec les pays voisins de l'ANASE, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7148">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'avec l'Inde <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7169">et</DiscourseConnective> la Chine, l'UE doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7192">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> exercer davantage de pressions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7234">pour</DiscourseConnective> obtenir la libération de Mme Aung San Suu Kyi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6346" id="191" name="Raül Romeva i Rueda ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6346" docOffset="52">
      <en>author. - (ES) Madam President, <Alignment alignment="7323" annotation_id="6378">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6378" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> other Members have pointed out and as is pointed out time and time again in the reports by the United Nations Special Representative on Human Rights in Myanmar, Mr Paulo Sergio Pinheiro, and in the reports by the United Nations Secretary-General's Special Representative on Human Rights Defenders, Hina Jilani, the situation in Burma continues to be of concern and is deteriorating every day.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (ES) Madame la Présidente, <Alignment alignment="6378" annotation_id="7323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7323" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'autres députés l'ont souligné avant moi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7372">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7375">comme</DiscourseConnective> ne cessent de le répéter les rapports du représentant spécial des Nations unies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7461">pour</DiscourseConnective> la question des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7500">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie, M. Paulo Sergio Pinheiro, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7539">et</DiscourseConnective> les rapports de la représentante spéciale du Secrétaire général des Nations unies pour les défenseurs des droits de l'homme, Hina Jilani, la situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7693">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie reste préoccupante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7724">et</DiscourseConnective> se détériore de jour en jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6774" docOffset="53">
      <en>I would like to begin by recalling the appeals that have been made in this House on previous occasions <Alignment alignment="7872" annotation_id="6877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6877" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which we must make once again.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7769">d'abord</DiscourseConnective> évoquer les nombreux appels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7805">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons lancés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7827">à</DiscourseConnective> diverses occasions au sein de ce Parlement <Alignment alignment="6877" annotation_id="7872">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7872" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7875">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons réitérer aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6912" docOffset="54">
      <en>Extending the confinement of Aung San Suu Kyi by a year is entirely unacceptable, <Alignment alignment="8008" annotation_id="6994">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6994" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7006" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective> call upon the Burmese regime to suspend it as soon as possible.</en>
      <fr>La décision de prolonger d'un an la détention d'Aung San Suu Kyi est tout à fait inacceptable, <Alignment alignment="6994" annotation_id="8008">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8008" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons exiger de la part du régime birman qu'elle soit libérée dans les meilleurs délais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7080" docOffset="55">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="8117" annotation_id="7086">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7086" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> important to call once again for the release of all political prisoners and to guarantee freedom of expression and freedom of demonstration, which are currently being violated in that country.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <Alignment alignment="7086" annotation_id="8117">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8117" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que nous demandions au régime birman de libérer tous les prisonniers politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8207">et</DiscourseConnective> de garantir la liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8246">et</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de manifestation, qui sont actuellement violées dans ce pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7284" docOffset="56">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7284" sense="Comparison.Contrast">On the other hand</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="8322" annotation_id="7303">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7303" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I <Alignment alignment="8356" annotation_id="7314">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7314" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> believe that it is important to point out our responsibility as western countries in relation to that country, in terms of investments, <Alignment alignment="8478" annotation_id="7455">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7455" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I say this <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7470" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> there are at least two crucial factors.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7303" annotation_id="8322">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8322" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, j'estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8342">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il importe <Alignment alignment="7314" annotation_id="8356">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8356" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de rappeler notre responsabilité en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8402">tant que</DiscourseConnective> pays occidentaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8428">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard de ce pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8450">en</DiscourseConnective> termes d'investissement, <Alignment alignment="7455" annotation_id="8478">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8478" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'aborde ce sujet en raison de deux aspects décisifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8534">au moins</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7518" docOffset="57">
      <en>Firstly, let us not forget that Burma currently has, <Alignment alignment="32899" annotation_id="7571">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7571" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not the most significant, then at least one of the most significant reserves of natural gas in South-East Asia.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8544">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, n'oublions pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8573">que</DiscourseConnective> la Birmanie possède l'une des réserves de gaz naturel les plus importantes, <Alignment alignment="7571" annotation_id="8653">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8653" sense="Contingency.Condition">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ne pas dire la plus importante, de l'Asie du Sud-Est.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7686" docOffset="58">
      <en>That is a very attractive thing, naturally.</en>
      <fr>Cela constitue bien sûr un atout pour le moins attrayant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7730" docOffset="59">
      <en>It is therefore essential that, <Alignment alignment="6849" annotation_id="7762">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7762" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is any foreign international investment, we guarantee that there is at least an analysis of the impact of those investments on human rights.</en>
      <fr>Il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8777">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective> essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8802">que</DiscourseConnective> nous puissions garantir, <Alignment alignment="7762" annotation_id="8831">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8831" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'arrivée d'investisseurs étrangers, la réalisation d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8891">au moins</DiscourseConnective> une étude d'impact de ces investissements sur les droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7916" docOffset="60">
      <en>That is something that we forget too often.</en>
      <fr>C'est un aspect <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8985">que</DiscourseConnective> nous oublions trop souvent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7960" docOffset="61">
      <en>Secondly, I believe that it is <Alignment alignment="10304" annotation_id="7991">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7991" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> important to stress that the sanctions currently being imposed by the United States, and the European Union's restrictions, are not proving to be effective.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9017">Deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, il importe <Alignment alignment="7991" annotation_id="9042">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9042" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9064">que</DiscourseConnective> les sanctions actuellement imposées par les États-Unis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9123">et</DiscourseConnective> les restrictions de l'Union européenne ne s'avèrent guère efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8153" docOffset="62">
      <en>The fact that many other Asian countries are clearly increasing their investments in that country obliges us <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8262" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> to take a regional approach to the problem in order to ensure that our actions, and those of our allies, are more effective.</en>
      <fr>La nette hausse des investissements d'autres pays asiatiques dans ce pays nous oblige <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9281">à</DiscourseConnective> adopter une approche régionale du problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9326">afin de</DiscourseConnective> garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9343">que</DiscourseConnective> nos actions, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9360">et</DiscourseConnective> celles de nos alliés, soient plus efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8392" id="192" name="James Nicholson">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8392" docOffset="63">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - Madam President, I reiterate the condemnation of the Burmese regime, which is so clearly and effectively expressed in the resolution.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, je réitère la condamnation du régime birman, qui est exprimée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9524">si</DiscourseConnective> clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9538">et</DiscourseConnective> efficacement dans la résolution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8559" docOffset="64">
      <en>The 17-year-long plight of Aung San Suu Kyi is one which few human beings could withstand.</en>
      <fr>Peu d'êtres humains seraient capables de résister au calvaire que Mme Aung San Suu Kyi subit depuis 17 ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8650" docOffset="65">
      <en>She has selflessly withstood indefinite imprisonment and ongoing separation from her loved ones, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8747" sense="Comparison.Contrast">yet</DiscourseConnective> is still showing unshakeable courage and consistency in her cause, <Alignment alignment="9916" annotation_id="8818">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8818" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> for this she must be applauded.</en>
      <fr>De manière désintéressée, elle a résisté à l'emprisonnement sans fin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9751">et</DiscourseConnective> à la séparation permanente d'avec les êtres qui lui sont chers, en faisant pourtant preuve d'un courage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9858">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une constance imperturbables au service de sa cause, <Alignment alignment="8818" annotation_id="9916">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9916" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hommage doit lui être rendu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9947">pour</DiscourseConnective> cela.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8854" docOffset="66">
      <en>She is, without doubt, a leader of our time, enduring the curtailment of her civil liberties which closely mirrors the suppression of her fellow citizens.</en>
      <fr>Elle est incontestablement un leader de notre temps, supportant la suppression de ses libertés civiles, reflet de l'oppression de ses compatriotes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9009" docOffset="67">
      <en>The human rights abuses in Burma span religious persecution, forced labour and detention without trial and are elements of political violence which the UN has recently justifiably condemned.</en>
      <fr>Les violations des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10143">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie vont jusqu'aux persécutions religieuses, au travail forcé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10213">et</DiscourseConnective> à la détention arbitraire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10242">et</DiscourseConnective> sont des faits de violence politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10282">que</DiscourseConnective> les Nations unies ont condamnés récemment à juste titre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9200" docOffset="68">
      <en>The signatories of this resolution wholeheartedly denounce the economic support given to the regime through investment in the arms trade and the energy industry from other Far Eastern countries, which only shows up this ruthless dictatorship.</en>
      <fr>Les signataires de la présente résolution dénoncent avec vigueur le soutien économique apporté au régime par le biais des investissements d'autres pays d'Extrême-Orient dans le commerce des armes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10539">et</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie énergétique, qui ne font que mettre en lumière cette impitoyable dictature.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9443" docOffset="69">
      <en>All democracies should seriously reconsider financing a country with one of the lowest health expenditures in the world.</en>
      <fr>Toutes les démocraties devraient reconsidérer sérieusement leurs financements en faveur d'un pays dont les dépenses de santé comptent parmi les plus faibles du monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9564" id="193" name="Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9564" docOffset="70">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (PL) Madam President, six months have passed since the last European Parliament resolution that sent out a warning about the serious internal situation in Burma/Myanmar.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (PL) Madame la Présidente, six mois ont passé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10867">depuis</DiscourseConnective> la dernière résolution du Parlement européen qui envoyait un avertissement concernant la gravité de la situation intérieure en Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9764" docOffset="71">
      <en>The military authorities in power in that country have failed to make any progress towards democracy, <Alignment alignment="11066" annotation_id="9866">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9866" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités militaires au pouvoir dans ce pays n'ont <Alignment alignment="9866" annotation_id="11066">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11066" sense="Comparison.Contrast">pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> accompli aucun progrès vers la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9875" docOffset="72">
      <en>Burma/Myanmar's economic situation is causing great concern.</en>
      <fr>La situation économique de la Birmanie est une source importante de préoccupations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9936" docOffset="73">
      <en>Thirty per cent of its people live below the poverty line <Alignment alignment="11271" annotation_id="9994">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9994" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> human rights are openly violated.</en>
      <fr>Trente pour cent de la population y vivent sous le seuil de pauvreté <Alignment alignment="9994" annotation_id="11271">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11271" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les droits de l'homme y sont ouvertement violés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10032" docOffset="74">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11323" annotation_id="10032">
          <Alignment alignment="11323" annotation_id="10032">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10032" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, forced labour and child conscription into the army are part of everyday life.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10032" annotation_id="11323">
          <Alignment alignment="10032" annotation_id="11323">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11323" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, le travail forcé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11350">et</DiscourseConnective> l'enrôlement d'enfants soldats y sont monnaie courante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10123" docOffset="75">
      <en>Opposition activists are persecuted and imprisoned for long periods, as has happened in the case of Aung San Suu Kyi, a Nobel and Sakharov prize winner who has been detained for 17 years.</en>
      <fr>Des militants de l'opposition sont persécutés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11455">et</DiscourseConnective> emprisonnés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11470">pour</DiscourseConnective> de longues périodes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11496">à</DiscourseConnective> l'image de Aung San Suu Kyi, lauréate du prix Nobel de la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11561">et</DiscourseConnective> du prix Sakharov, qui est détenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11598">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 17 ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10311" docOffset="76">
      <en>Against this background, all the political groups in Burma/Myanmar should be urged to take part in the National Convention charged with drafting a new Constitution.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte, tous les groupes politiques de Birmanie devraient être exhortés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11695">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre part <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11710">à</DiscourseConnective> la convention nationale convoquée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11746">pour</DiscourseConnective> rédiger une nouvelle Constitution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10476" docOffset="77">
      <en>Representatives of the National League for Democracy should <Alignment alignment="11855" annotation_id="10536">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10536" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> participate.</en>
      <fr>Les représentants de la Ligue nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11826">pour</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie devraient <Alignment alignment="10536" annotation_id="11855">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11855" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> y participer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10554" docOffset="78">
      <en>Burma/Myanmar's membership of ASEAN is particularly important for its future, <Alignment alignment="11974" annotation_id="10632">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10632" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ASEAN members are required to redouble their efforts towards democracy.</en>
      <fr>L'appartenance de la Birmanie à l'ANASE est particulièrement importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11951">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir du pays, <Alignment alignment="10632" annotation_id="11974">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11974" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les membres de l'ANASE sont invités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12020">à</DiscourseConnective> redoubler d'efforts sur la voie de la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10707" docOffset="79">
      <en>China and India should exert political and economic pressure on the Burmese regime by refusing to support the army of Burma/Myanmar.</en>
      <fr>La Chine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12081">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Inde devraient exercer des pressions politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12134">et</DiscourseConnective> économiques sur le régime birman <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12170">en</DiscourseConnective> refusant de soutenir l'armée de Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10840" docOffset="80">
      <en>For its part, the international community should implement economic sanctions and freeze the assets of members of the Government of Burma/Myanmar and those associated with them.</en>
      <fr>De son côté, la communauté internationale devrait appliquer des sanctions économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12301">et</DiscourseConnective> geler les actifs des membres du gouvernement de Birmanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12361">et</DiscourseConnective> de leurs associés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11018" docOffset="81">
      <en>It is only by taking decisive action of this nature that we can hope to force the Burmese regime to introduce democratic changes.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12392">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> prenant des mesures décisives de cette nature <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12444">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pouvons espérer contraindre le régime birman <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12498">à</DiscourseConnective> introduire des changements démocratiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11148" id="194" name="Urszula Krupa">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11148" docOffset="82">
      <en>on behalf of the IND/DEM Group. - (PL) Madam President, the subject of today's debate on human rights violations is once again the political and social situation in Burma/Myanmar.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe IND/DEM. - (PL) Madame la Présidente, la situation politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12620">et</DiscourseConnective> sociale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12631">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie est à nouveau au cœur du débat d'aujourd'hui sur les violations des droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11328" docOffset="83">
      <en>Ever since 1962, Burma/Myanmar has been ruled by the military, who have kept an iron grip on the country.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12730">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> 1962, la Birmanie est dirigée de main de fer par des forces militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11434" docOffset="84">
      <en>For over 40 years, human rights have been violated in this Asian country, <Alignment alignment="4408" annotation_id="11508">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11508" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> thousands of individuals have been persecuted and punished for opposition activities.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12809">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> plus de 40 ans, les droits de l'homme sont violés dans ce pays asiatique, <Alignment alignment="11508" annotation_id="12890">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12890" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des milliers de personnes ont été persécutées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12939">et</DiscourseConnective> punies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12949">pour</DiscourseConnective> leurs activités dans l'opposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11598" docOffset="85">
      <en>Many have been imprisoned.</en>
      <fr>Nombre d'entre elles sont en prison.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11625" docOffset="86">
      <en>Forced labour is the order of the day, <Alignment alignment="13064" annotation_id="11664">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11664" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> children are conscripted into the army.</en>
      <fr>Le travail forcé est monnaie courante <Alignment alignment="11664" annotation_id="13064">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13064" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des enfants sont enrôlés dans l'armée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11708" docOffset="87">
      <en>Most people in Burma/Myanmar do not have access to medical care.</en>
      <fr>La plupart des citoyens birmans n'ont pas accès aux soins médicaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11773" docOffset="88">
      <en>Many of them die of tuberculosis, malaria, HIV or AIDS <Alignment alignment="13243" annotation_id="11828">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11828" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> almost half the children do not attend school.</en>
      <fr>Beaucoup meurent de la tuberculose, du paludisme, du HIV <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13231">ou</DiscourseConnective> du sida, <Alignment alignment="11828" annotation_id="13243">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13243" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> près de la moitié des enfants ne sont pas scolarisés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11879" docOffset="89">
      <en>Red Cross centres have been shut down <Alignment alignment="13345" annotation_id="11917">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11917" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> those in need deprived of protection and humanitarian aid.</en>
      <fr>Les bureaux de la Croix Rouge ont été fermés <Alignment alignment="11917" annotation_id="13345">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13345" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les plus démunis sont privés de protection <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13391">et</DiscourseConnective> d'aide humanitaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11980" docOffset="90">
      <en>The junta disregards the actions of the UN Human Rights Council and of the ILO.</en>
      <fr>La junte ignore les actions du Conseil des droits de l'homme des Nations unies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13493">et</DiscourseConnective> du BIT.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12060" docOffset="91">
      <en>It <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12063" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> fails to respond to European Parliament resolutions and to documents issued by the Council of the European Community.</en>
      <fr>Elle ne répond pas non plus aux résolutions du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13570">et</DiscourseConnective> aux documents émis par le Conseil de la Communauté européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12186" docOffset="92">
      <en>On 15 May 2007 Aung San Suu Kyi's term of house arrest was extended for a further year.</en>
      <fr>Le 15 mai 2007, l'assignation à résidence d'Aung San Suu Kyi a été prolongée d'un an.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12274" docOffset="93">
      <en>This Nobel Prize winner and opposition activist has spent 11 of the last 17 years either in prison or under house arrest.</en>
      <fr>Cette lauréate du prix Nobel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13751">et</DiscourseConnective> militante de l'opposition a passé 11 des 17 dernières années <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13815">en</DiscourseConnective> prison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13825">ou</DiscourseConnective> assignée à domicile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12396" docOffset="94">
      <en>We appeal for her release and that of other political prisoners.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons sa libération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13878">et</DiscourseConnective> celle d'autres prisonniers politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12461" docOffset="95">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="10440" annotation_id="12464">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12464" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> call for the National League for Democracy to be allowed to resume its activities, <Alignment alignment="14028" annotation_id="12552">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12552" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> for the resumption of humanitarian aid to prevent the extinction of the Burmese nation and ethnic minorities.</en>
      <fr>Nous exigeons <Alignment alignment="8757" annotation_id="13934">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13934" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13944">que</DiscourseConnective> la Ligue nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13967">pour</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13986">soit</DiscourseConnective> autorisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14001">à</DiscourseConnective> reprendre ses activités, <Alignment alignment="12552" annotation_id="14028">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14028" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14034">que</DiscourseConnective> le rétablissement de l'aide humanitaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14078">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>empêcher l'extinction de la nation birmane <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14128">et</DiscourseConnective> des minorités ethniques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12666" docOffset="96">
      <en>A particular problem concerning the continued existence of this regime and others of a totalitarian nature is the ineffective actions taken by international bodies.</en>
      <fr>L'inefficacité des mesures prises par les organismes internationaux est l'une des raisons de la survie de ce régime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14272">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres régimes de nature totalitaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12831" docOffset="97">
      <en>Despite promises to the contrary, the sanctions imposed do not have an impact on the economic structures of the regimes <Alignment alignment="14447" annotation_id="12951">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12951" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the embargoes applied hit ordinary people who are already persecuted and living in extreme poverty.</en>
      <fr>En dépit des promesses affirmant le contraire, les sanctions imposées n'ont pas d'impact sur les structures économiques des régimes <Alignment alignment="12951" annotation_id="14447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14447" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les embargos touchent des citoyens ordinaires qui sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14505">déjà</DiscourseConnective> persécutés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14521">et</DiscourseConnective> vivent dans une pauvreté extrême.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13055" docOffset="98">
      <en>Our European Parliament resolutions and all other actions will remain superficial and ineffective <Alignment alignment="14669" annotation_id="13153">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13153" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">until</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these issues are resolved.</en>
      <fr>Les résolutions du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14596">et</DiscourseConnective> toutes les autres initiatives resteront superficielles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14654">et</DiscourseConnective> inefficaces <Alignment alignment="13153" annotation_id="14669">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14669" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">tant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces problèmes ne seront pas résolus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13186" id="195" name="László Kovács">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13186" docOffset="99">
      <en>Madam President, the Commission remains worried about the situation in Myanmar/Burma.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, la Commission reste préoccupée par la situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14817">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13272" docOffset="100">
      <en>The biggest worries concern the deep social and ethnic fault lines which divide the country <Alignment alignment="14923" annotation_id="13364">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13364" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which result in human insecurity, widespread poverty and lack of progress in economic and social development.</en>
      <fr>Le plus gros souci concerne les profondes failles sociales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14889">et</DiscourseConnective> ethniques qui divisent le pays <Alignment alignment="4939" annotation_id="14923">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14923" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sont à l'origine de l'insécurité, de la pauvreté généralisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14987">et</DiscourseConnective> du blocage du développement économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15029">et</DiscourseConnective> social.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13478" docOffset="101">
      <en>It is obvious, that in a climate of human insecurity and ongoing armed conflict in a few border areas, there is little space for respect for human rights.</en>
      <fr>Dans un tel climat d'insécurité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15073">et</DiscourseConnective> avec les conflits armés permanents dans certaines zones frontalières, il est évident <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15161">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il reste peu de place <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15186">pour</DiscourseConnective> le respect des droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13633" docOffset="102">
      <en>The authorities of Myanmar/Burma are confronted with a number of challenges, like establishing national unity and political stability, <Alignment alignment="433" annotation_id="13768">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13768" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - most importantly - advancing the development level of their country which remains one of the poorest in the world.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités birmanes sont confrontées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15265">à</DiscourseConnective> plusieurs défis: l'établissement de l'unité nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15321">et</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité politique <Alignment alignment="7302" annotation_id="15347">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15347" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15351">surtout</DiscourseConnective>, l'élévation du niveau de développement de leur pays, qui reste l'un des plus pauvres du monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13889" docOffset="103">
      <en>For the international community, helping the transition of Myanmar/Burma towards a more open and more developed society - led by a legitimate and civilian government - should remain the paramount goal.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15455">Pour</DiscourseConnective> la communauté internationale, favoriser la transition de la Birmanie vers une société plus ouverte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15559">et</DiscourseConnective> plus développée - et dirigée par un gouvernement légitime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15620">et</DiscourseConnective> civil - devrait rester l'objectif majeur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14091" docOffset="104">
      <en>The military leadership's erratic governance continues, in economic terms and in the political sphere.</en>
      <fr>La gouvernance erratique de la junte militaire se poursuit, tant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15730">en</DiscourseConnective> termes économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15752">que</DiscourseConnective> politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14194" docOffset="105">
      <en>The military continues to employ practices of forced labour, <Alignment alignment="15837" annotation_id="14255">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14255" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> civil society faces repression, uncertainty and operational difficulties.</en>
      <fr>Les militaires continuent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15794">à</DiscourseConnective> recourir à la pratique du travail forcé, <Alignment alignment="14255" annotation_id="15837">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15837" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la société continue à subir la répression, l'incertitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15905">et</DiscourseConnective> les difficultés opérationnelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14335" docOffset="106">
      <en>The '88 Students' - the then leaders of the 1988 uprising - continue to exploit the minimal space for civil society as much as they can, <Alignment alignment="16118" annotation_id="14472">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14472" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the National League for Democracy is marginalised <Alignment alignment="16184" annotation_id="14528">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14528" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="16187" annotation_id="14532">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14532" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the unjustifiable detention of Mrs Aung San Suu Kyi continues.</en>
      <fr>Ceux que l'on a appelés les "étudiants de 88" - les leaders du soulèvement de 1988 - continuent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16037">à</DiscourseConnective> exploiter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16049">autant</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16056">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils le peuvent l'espace minimal restant de société civile, <Alignment alignment="14472" annotation_id="16118">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16118" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Ligue nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16148">pour</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie est marginalisée <Alignment alignment="14528" annotation_id="16184">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16184" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="14532" annotation_id="16187">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16187" sense="Comparison.Contrast">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la détention injustifiable de Mme Aung San Suu Kyi se poursuit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14601" docOffset="107">
      <en>Transition is hard to imagine with more than one thousand political detainees, among whom Mrs Aung San Suu Kyi sticks out as the icon of peace and reconciliation.</en>
      <fr>La transition est difficilement imaginable, avec plus d'un millier de détenus politiques, parmi lesquels Mme Aung San Suu Kyi, considérée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16393">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'icône de la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16418">et</DiscourseConnective> de la réconciliation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14764" docOffset="108">
      <en>Such transition is equally inconceivable without a genuine dialogue with the various ethnic groups, including those continuing their armed battle.</en>
      <fr>Une telle transition est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16468">également</DiscourseConnective> inconcevable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16491">sans</DiscourseConnective> un véritable dialogue avec les divers groupes ethniques, y compris ceux qui persistent dans la lutte armée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14911" docOffset="109">
      <en>The Commission supports the work of Professor Paolo Sergio Pinheiro, the UN's Special Rapporteur on Human Rights in Myanmar.</en>
      <fr>La Commission soutient le travail du professeur Paolo Sergio Pinheiro, le rapporteur spécial des Nations unies sur les droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16741">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15036" docOffset="110">
      <en>He said, in his last statement, that 'grave human rights violations are indulged not only with impunity but authorised by the sanction of laws'.</en>
      <fr>Dans sa dernière déclaration, il a indiqué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16797">que</DiscourseConnective> "des violations graves des droits de l'homme sont permises, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16861">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> dans l'impunité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16892">mais</DiscourseConnective> autorisées par la loi".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15181" docOffset="111">
      <en>The Commission <Alignment alignment="16941" annotation_id="15196">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15196" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcomes the appointment by the UN Secretary-General of Professor Ibrahim Gambari as Special Envoy for Myanmar, and expects that the Government will extend its full cooperation to him, in order to allow the good offices of the UN Secretary General to continue.</en>
      <fr>La Commission salue <Alignment alignment="15196" annotation_id="16941">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16941" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la nomination par le secrétaire général des Nations unies du professeur Ibrahim Gambari <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17039">comme</DiscourseConnective> envoyé spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17060">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17072">et</DiscourseConnective> espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17082">que</DiscourseConnective> le gouvernement acceptera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17112">également</DiscourseConnective> de coopérer pleinement avec lui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17155">de manière à</DiscourseConnective> permettre la continuation des bons offices du secrétaire général des Nations unies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15462" docOffset="112">
      <en>Regarding the forthcoming session of the National Convention, we call on the Government to listen to the voices of ethnic groups and political stakeholders in opposition.</en>
      <fr>En ce qui concerne la prochaine session de la Convention nationale, nous appelons le gouvernement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17350">à</DiscourseConnective> écouter les voix des groupes ethniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17391">et</DiscourseConnective> des acteurs politiques de l'opposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15633" docOffset="113">
      <en>We note progress in the working conditions of the local International Labour Organisation office, which will hopefully improve the situation of victims of forced labour practices filing a complaint.</en>
      <fr>Nous constatons des progrès dans les conditions de travail de l'agence locale de l'Organisation internationale du travail, ce qui permettra d'améliorer, nous l'espérons, la situation des victimes des pratiques de travail forcé ayant déposé plainte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15832" docOffset="114">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17683" annotation_id="15832">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15832" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we deplore the deteriorating working conditions for the International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) and call on the Government to allow the ICRC to resume its humanitarian mission.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5743" annotation_id="17683">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17683" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous déplorons la détérioration des conditions de travail du comité international de la Croix-Rouge (CICR) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17795">et</DiscourseConnective> nous appelons le gouvernement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17828">à</DiscourseConnective> autoriser le CICR <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17848">à</DiscourseConnective> reprendre sa mission humanitaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16021" docOffset="115">
      <en>Among most observers, there is a growing consensus that more needs to be done about the political and socioeconomic situation.</en>
      <fr>La plupart des observateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17912">s'</DiscourseConnective>accordent généralement pour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17942">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faudrait en faire davantage pour la situation politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18009">et</DiscourseConnective> socio-économique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16148" docOffset="116">
      <en>The European Union, in its common position, has mandated the Commission to engage the Government in a dialogue over its responsibilities to achieve the Millennium Development Goals.</en>
      <fr>Dans sa position commune, l'Union européenne a mandaté la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18099">pour</DiscourseConnective> engager le gouvernement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18128">à</DiscourseConnective> ouvrir le dialogue sur ses responsabilités en matière de réalisation des objectifs de développement du millénaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16330" docOffset="117">
      <en>The EU has, <Alignment alignment="18245" annotation_id="16342">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16342" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, been looking for effective policies which may help the people of Myanmar/Burma <Alignment alignment="18355" annotation_id="16432">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16432" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which may help to bring them back into the international community.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="16342" annotation_id="18245">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18245" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">En conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'UE a cherché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18276">à</DiscourseConnective> élaborer des politiques efficaces susceptibles d'aider la population birmane <Alignment alignment="16432" annotation_id="18355">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18355" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de favoriser son retour au sein de la communauté internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16504" docOffset="118">
      <en>The Three Diseases Fund, supported by the EU and its partners, is an example of this policy.</en>
      <fr>Le fonds pour les trois maladies, soutenu par l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18474">et</DiscourseConnective> ses partenaires, est un exemple de cette politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16597" docOffset="119">
      <en>Our approach focuses on the most basic and immediate human security needs of the population, <Alignment alignment="13671" annotation_id="16690">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16690" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it clearly recognises the limits which exist for all external actors.</en>
      <fr>Notre approche est axée sur les besoins les plus élémentaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18591">et</DiscourseConnective> les plus urgents de la population en matière de sécurité, <Alignment alignment="16690" annotation_id="18652">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18652" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous reconnaissons clairement les limites qui freinent tous les acteurs extérieurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16764" docOffset="120">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18739" annotation_id="16764">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16764" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, withholding aid and contributing to more isolation would only make the population pay the price, that is, the people of Myanmar/Burma who are already suffering.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="16764" annotation_id="18739">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18739" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, retenir l'aide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18765">et</DiscourseConnective> contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18779">à</DiscourseConnective> augmenter l'isolement revient tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18816">simplement</DiscourseConnective> à faire payer le prix de la situation à la population, c'est-à-dire au peuple de Birmanie qui souffre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18929">déjà</DiscourseConnective> tant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16934" docOffset="121">
      <en>We simply do not believe that through increased sanctions the suffering of the people can be relieved.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pensons vraiment pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18969">que</DiscourseConnective> des sanctions supplémentaires puissent soulager la souffrance de la population.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17037" docOffset="122">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1393" annotation_id="17037">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17037" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, such an approach would not help influence the military leaders.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17037" annotation_id="19053">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19053" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, une telle approche ne nous aiderait pas à influencer les chefs militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17111" docOffset="123">
      <en>The Commission is fully committed to stepping up its programmes in Myanmar/Burma, in quantitative and qualitative terms, with a view to contributing effectively to development and reconciliation.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est pleinement engagée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19174">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer ses programmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19201">en</DiscourseConnective> Birmanie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19214">en</DiscourseConnective> termes quantitatifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19237">et</DiscourseConnective> qualitatifs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19253">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> contribuer efficacement au développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19304">et</DiscourseConnective> à la réconciliation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17307" id="196" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17307" docOffset="124">
      <en>That concludes the debate.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17334" docOffset="125">
      <en>The vote will take place shortly.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu dans quelques instants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
