<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Status of elected MEPs in Poland (debate)</en>
    <fr>Statut des députés au Parlement européen élus en Pologne (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="42" id="364" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="42" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the debate concerning an oral question to the Commission from Giuseppe Gargani, on behalf of the Committee on Legal Affairs - B6-0002/2008) concerning the status of MEPs elected in Poland.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur une question orale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="121">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission de Giuseppe Gargani, au nom de la commission des affaires juridiques - B6-0002/2008) concernant le statut des députés au Parlement européen élus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="282">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="248" id="365" name="Giuseppe Gargani">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="248" docOffset="2">
      <en>author. - (IT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the issue that we are discussing tonight has been examined in detail, on more than one occasion I may say, by the Committee on Legal Affairs, which I have the honour to chair, and that Committee has asked me, through this question, to open a discussion and to exchange views with the Commission.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (IT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="341">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, la question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="367">que</DiscourseConnective> nous discutons aujourd'hui a été examinée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="413">en</DiscourseConnective> détail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="423">à</DiscourseConnective> plus d'une reprise, si je <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="451">puis</DiscourseConnective> dire, par la commission des affaires juridiques, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="505">que</DiscourseConnective> j'ai l'honneur de présider. Cette commission m'a demandé, par le biais de cette question, d'ouvrir un débat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="617">et</DiscourseConnective> d'échanger les avis avec la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="595" docOffset="3">
      <en>The question relates to the status of MEPs elected in Poland, who are not in the same position from the point of view of elections and all the provisions that govern the elections of other parliamentarians in other Member States.</en>
      <fr>La question est liée au statut des députés au Parlement européen élus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="730">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne, qui ne bénéficient pas des mêmes conditions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="786">en</DiscourseConnective> matière électorale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="808">et</DiscourseConnective> eu égard à toutes les dispositions qui régissent les élections dans les parlements des autres États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="825" docOffset="4">
      <en>Elections to the European Parliament in Poland are in practice governed by the Act of 23 January 2004, Article 9 of which sets out eligibility requirements: candidates must be aged 21 on the day of the poll, must not have been convicted of criminal offences, must be resident in Poland and must satisfy various other criteria.</en>
      <fr>Les élections du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="956">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="972">en</DiscourseConnective> pratique régies par la loi du 23 janvier 2004, dont l'article 9 fixe les exigences en matière d'éligibilité: les candidats doivent avoir minimum 21 ans le jour du vote, ne peuvent pas avoir été condamnés au pénal, doivent résider <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1205">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1216">et</DiscourseConnective> doivent respecter différents autres critères.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1152" docOffset="5">
      <en>Chapter 17 of that Act sets out the circumstances in which Polish MEPs may lose their seats: their eligibility, that is the eligibility requirements on the day of the poll, may be invalidated, giving rise to the possibility of forfeiture <Alignment alignment="50605" annotation_id="1390">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1390" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these requirements were not met, and various other matters, which I shall not cite in order to get to the crux of the matter that I should like to discuss here.</en>
      <fr>Le chapitre 17 de cette loi établit les circonstances dans lesquelles les députés européens polonais peuvent perdre leur siège: leur élection, vu les exigences en matière d'éligibilité au jour du vote, peut être invalidée, pouvant entraîner la révocation <Alignment alignment="1390" annotation_id="1520">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1520" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces exigences ne sont pas satisfaites, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1562">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres sanctions, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1585">que</DiscourseConnective> je ne citerai pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1607">pour</DiscourseConnective> me concentrer sur le point principal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1649">que</DiscourseConnective> je souhaite aborder ici.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1554" docOffset="6">
      <en>On the basis of a number of combined provisions, <Alignment alignment="47017" annotation_id="1603">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1603" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we lawyers say, an MEP automatically loses his seat - that is, an MEP automatically forfeits that seat - <Alignment alignment="1861" annotation_id="1711">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1711" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he or she has received a criminal conviction; in the case of members of the Polish Parliament, the law of 12 April 2001 - both as regards elections to the Sejm and to the Senate of the Republic - contains no provision of this type, with the result that these provisions relate to Polish MEPs but not to Polish MPs.</en>
      <fr>Sur la base de plusieurs dispositions combinées, <Alignment alignment="10850" annotation_id="1727">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1727" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nos termes de juristes, tout député européen perd automatiquement son siège - le député voit son siège automatiquement confisqué - <Alignment alignment="1711" annotation_id="1861">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1861" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1867">ou</DiscourseConnective> elle est condamné(e) au pénal. Concernant les membres du Parlement polonais, la loi du 12 avril 2001 - pour les élections au Sejm <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2000">et</DiscourseConnective> au Sénat de la République - ne contient aucune disposition de ce type, ce qui entraîne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2090">que</DiscourseConnective> ces dispositions s'appliquent aux députés polonais au Parlement européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2168">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas aux députés polonais au Parlement polonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2029" docOffset="7">
      <en>For that reason, we discussed the question and asked ourselves a question, a question which among other things has repercussions as regards requests for immunity; <Alignment alignment="40312" annotation_id="2192">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2192" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you know, we have - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2215" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> Commissioner Frattini is very well aware - the power to decide on this question.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2227">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette raison que nous avons soulevé ce problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2280">et</DiscourseConnective> nous nous sommes posé une question, une question qui a entre autres des répercussions sur les demandes de levée de l'immunité. <Alignment alignment="2192" annotation_id="2410">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2410" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez - M. Frattini en est bien conscient -, nous avons le pouvoir de décision <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2503">en</DiscourseConnective> la matière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2299" docOffset="8">
      <en>Clearly, <Alignment alignment="2530" annotation_id="2308">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2308" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a member automatically forfeits his or her seat as a result of an event for which immunity cannot be upheld, there is obviously a further problem, a further uncertainty.</en>
      <fr>Clairement, <Alignment alignment="2308" annotation_id="2530">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2530" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un membre perd automatiquement son siège <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2574">à</DiscourseConnective> la suite d'une circonstance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2604">pour</DiscourseConnective> laquelle l'immunité ne peut être levée, un nouveau problème surgit, une nouvelle incertitude.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2481" docOffset="9">
      <en>For that reason, we ask, <Alignment alignment="2764" annotation_id="2506">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2506" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I ask on behalf of the Committee, the Commissioner whether <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2569" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective> not he considers that the Polish legislation on elections to the national parliament breaches Article 10 of the Protocol on Privileges and Immunities, which states that during the sessions of the European Parliament, its members shall enjoy the immunities accorded to members of their Parliament in the territory of their own State.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle nous demandons au commissaire, <Alignment alignment="21398" annotation_id="2764">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2764" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je le demande au nom de la commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2806">s'</DiscourseConnective>il estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2818">que</DiscourseConnective> la législation polonaise en matière d'élections au Parlement national viole l'article 10 du protocole sur les privilèges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2943">et</DiscourseConnective> immunités, qui affirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2969">que</DiscourseConnective> pendant la durée des sessions du Parlement européen, les membres de celui-ci bénéficient, sur leur territoire national, des immunités reconnues aux membres du parlement de leur État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2905" docOffset="10">
      <en>There is <Alignment alignment="3166" annotation_id="2914">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2914" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a clear inconsistency <Alignment alignment="3203" annotation_id="2946">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2946" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> provision is made for a Polish member to lose his or her seat, <Alignment alignment="3240" annotation_id="3012">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3012" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> members of the national parliament are not treated in the same way.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3159">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit <Alignment alignment="2914" annotation_id="3166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3166" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'une incohérence manifeste <Alignment alignment="2946" annotation_id="3203">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3203" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un député polonais perd son siège <Alignment alignment="3012" annotation_id="3240">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3240" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les députés au Parlement national ne sont pas traités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3304">de la même manière</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3085" docOffset="11">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="29164" annotation_id="3093">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3093" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ask the Commission <Alignment alignment="3370" annotation_id="3117">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3117" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it intends to bring proceedings before the Court of Justice with a view to Poland amending this legislation and correctly applying the treaty, <Alignment alignment="3524" annotation_id="3263">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3263" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it would seem that the treaty is not being applied <Alignment alignment="3574" annotation_id="3317">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3317" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it should be.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais <Alignment alignment="3093" annotation_id="3335">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3335" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demander à la Commission <Alignment alignment="3117" annotation_id="3370">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3370" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle a l'intention de déposer plainte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3411">à</DiscourseConnective> la Cour de justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3432">afin de</DiscourseConnective> pousser la Pologne à modifier sa législation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3485">et</DiscourseConnective> à appliquer correctement le traité, <Alignment alignment="3263" annotation_id="3524">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3524" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il semble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3541">que</DiscourseConnective> le traité n'est pas appliqué <Alignment alignment="7130" annotation_id="3574">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3574" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il se doit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3334" docOffset="12">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="26951" annotation_id="3334">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3334" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an exception is involved, <Alignment alignment="3621" annotation_id="3363">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3363" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="3624" annotation_id="3367">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3367" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the comparable and equal treatment of members from all the Member States means that this exception for members from the Polish state runs completely counter to what may be provided and is provided for all other members from the Member States, I would ask the Commission these two things and put this information before Parliament and ask whether the Commissioner can reply to these two questions <Alignment alignment="4041" annotation_id="3766">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3766" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whether it is possible to find a remedy to the questions I have put.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3334" annotation_id="3592">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3592" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">S'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il s'agit d'une exception, <Alignment alignment="3363" annotation_id="3621">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3621" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="3367" annotation_id="3624">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3624" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">vu que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le traitement comparable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3656">et</DiscourseConnective> équitable des membres de tous les États membres signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3716">que</DiscourseConnective> cette exception <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3736">pour</DiscourseConnective> les membres va totalement à l'encontre de ce qui est prévu ou pourrait être prévu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3823">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous les États membres de l'Union, je demande à la Commission d'examiner ces deux éléments <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3919">et</DiscourseConnective> de soumettre ces informations au Parlement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3966">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que de demander <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3988">si</DiscourseConnective> le commissaire peut répondre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4020">à</DiscourseConnective> ces deux questions <Alignment alignment="3766" annotation_id="4041">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4041" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4044">s'</DiscourseConnective>il est possible de trouver une solution aux questions que j'ai posées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3839" id="366" name="Franco Frattini">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3839" docOffset="13">
      <en>Vice-President of the Commission. - (IT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the issue which Mr Gargani has brought up is undoubtedly an important one: it is important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4007" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> two principles, both of which are relevant and important in my view, are at stake.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - (IT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4189">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, la question soulevée par M. Gargani est indubitablement importante, car elle touche à deux principes pertinents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4315">et</DiscourseConnective> importants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4329">à</DiscourseConnective> mes yeux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4098" docOffset="14">
      <en>The first principle is undoubtedly that referred to in Article 10 of the Protocol on Privileges and Immunities and on the status of the members of the European Parliament, which specifies that in the States to which the members of the European Parliament belong, they must be accorded the same prerogatives as members of the national parliament of that country.</en>
      <fr>Le premier principe est sans doute celui mentionné <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4392">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 10 du protocole sur les privilèges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4439">et</DiscourseConnective> immunités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4452">et</DiscourseConnective> dans le statut des députés au Parlement européen, qui stipule <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4517">que</DiscourseConnective> les députés au Parlement européen, dans les États dont ils sont issus, doivent recevoir les mêmes prérogatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4632">que</DiscourseConnective> les membres du Parlement national de ce pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4460" docOffset="15">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="36884" annotation_id="4460">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4460" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, another provision is <Alignment alignment="4719" annotation_id="4490">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4490" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> involved - a provision which is <Alignment alignment="4778" annotation_id="4527">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4527" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> important in my view - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4555" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that is Article 13 of the European Act of 1976 relating to the election of members of Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11201" annotation_id="4682">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4682" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, une autre disposition est <Alignment alignment="12341" annotation_id="4719">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4719" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> impliquée - une disposition qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4762">à</DiscourseConnective> mes yeux, est <Alignment alignment="8402" annotation_id="4778">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4778" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> importante. Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4803">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de l'article 13 de l'acte européen de 1976 relatif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4861">à</DiscourseConnective> l'élection des députés au Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4657" docOffset="16">
      <en>That article very clearly states that <Alignment alignment="4940" annotation_id="4695">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4695" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a Member State introduces national legislation covering the case in question here, that is the loss of the status, the loss of the position of member of the European Parliament, termination of the European parliamentary mandate in that country is subject to national law.</en>
      <fr>Cet article stipule très clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4936">que</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="4695" annotation_id="4940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4940" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>un État membre introduit une législation nationale couvrant le cas qui nous occupe ici, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5035">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir la perte de statut, la perte de la position d'un député au Parlement européen, la cessation du mandat de député européen dans ce pays est soumise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5190">à</DiscourseConnective> la législation nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4972" docOffset="17">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5218" annotation_id="4972">
          <Alignment alignment="5218" annotation_id="4972">
            <Alignment alignment="5218" annotation_id="4972">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4972" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, there is an apparent conflict, <Alignment alignment="5267" annotation_id="5019">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5019" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the rules set out in the Protocol on Privileges, <Alignment alignment="5329" annotation_id="5076">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5076" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cited by Mr Gargani, speak of equal prerogatives for members of the Polish Parliament <Alignment alignment="5426" annotation_id="5165">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5165" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> members of the European Parliament elected in Poland, but at the same time the European Act of 1976 on the election of members of the European Parliament, <Alignment alignment="5697" annotation_id="5324">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5324" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> regards the loss of the status of member of the European Parliament, apparently - or explicitly, I would say - governs the loss of the status of MEP and establishes that the loss of that status is governed by national law.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4972" annotation_id="5218">
          <Alignment alignment="21228" annotation_id="5218">
            <Alignment alignment="4972" annotation_id="5218">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5218" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, il y a un conflit manifeste, <Alignment alignment="306" annotation_id="5267">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5267" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les règles décrites dans le protocole sur les privilèges, <Alignment alignment="2792" annotation_id="5329">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5329" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'a dit M. Gargani, parlent de prérogatives égales entre les membres du Parlement polonais <Alignment alignment="5165" annotation_id="5426">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5426" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les membres du Parlement européen élus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5468">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5480">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>, dans le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5499">même</DiscourseConnective> temps, l'acte européen de 1976 relatif à l'élection des députés au Parlement européen régit manifestement - je dirais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5622">plutôt</DiscourseConnective> explicitement - la perte du statut des députés européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5686">et</DiscourseConnective> établit <Alignment alignment="5324" annotation_id="5697">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5697" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la perte de ce statut est régie par le droit national.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5550" docOffset="18">
      <en>In my opinion, the problem here is more one of the infringement of a third guiding principle for the European Union: whether <Alignment alignment="5909" annotation_id="5675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5675" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not the principle of equal treatment is enshrined in Polish domestic legislation.</en>
      <fr>Selon moi, le problème est ici plus une infraction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5807">à</DiscourseConnective> un troisième principe directeur de l'Union européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5864">que</DiscourseConnective> le principe de traitement équitable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5904">soit</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="5675" annotation_id="5909">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5909" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> non consacré dans la législation nationale polonaise. Ce principe, présent dans la législation constitutionnelle de tous les pays européens, établit que des situations similaires doivent être traitées de manière similaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5760" docOffset="19">
      <en>The principle, enshrined in the constitutional legislation of all the European countries, that establishes that similar situations must be treated in similar ways.</en>
      <fr>Le problème touche plutôt ce principe général. Toutefois, ce principe général ne permet pas à la Commission européenne de définir la manière dont l'ordre juridique polonais devrait modifier sa législation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5924" docOffset="20">
      <en>It is rather that general principle that is at issue; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5978" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> that general principle does not, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6015" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>, allow the European Commission to establish the way in which the Polish legal order should change its legislation, because, <Alignment alignment="6351" annotation_id="6147">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6147" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the issue is subject to national law, <Alignment alignment="6411" annotation_id="6188">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6188" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it were wished in national law to govern the loss of the status of national MP rather than the loss of the status of MEP in a different way, that would be possible, the important factor being that the provisions on one are brought into line with the provisions on the other.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6341">En effet</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="6147" annotation_id="6351">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6351" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il s'agit d'une question régie par le droit national, <Alignment alignment="6188" annotation_id="6411">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6411" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Pologne souhaite régir la perte du statut des députés nationaux de manière différente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6503">que</DiscourseConnective> la perte du statut des députés européens, c'est possible. Il faut simplement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6584">que</DiscourseConnective> les dispositions régissant une matière soient conformes aux dispositions régissant l'autre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6466" docOffset="21">
      <en>This is my personal opinion in that the Commission cannot now say 'we are turning to the Court for a ruling that Polish national law has to be amended in a particular way', <Alignment alignment="6866" annotation_id="6639">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6639" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am of the view that a general principle can be drawn.</en>
      <fr>Selon moi, la Commission ne peut pas dire "nous allons nous adresser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6749">à</DiscourseConnective> la Cour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6759">pour qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle prenne une décision obligeant la Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6813">à</DiscourseConnective> modifier sa loi nationale d'une certaine manière", <Alignment alignment="6639" annotation_id="6866">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6866" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6880">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un principe général peut être dégagé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6699" docOffset="22">
      <en>The general principle is that the Polish legal order must act to amend this difference in treatment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6799" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that, I believe, is a matter for the Polish legislator.</en>
      <fr>Le principe général est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6945">que</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre juridique polonais doit agir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6986">pour</DiscourseConnective> remédier à la différence de traitement. Cette tâche incombe, à mes yeux, au législateur polonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6859" docOffset="23">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7089" annotation_id="6859">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6859" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is a question that has never arisen and is too delicate to be dealt with in any summary way, I believe that the first step is to reach an understanding: <Alignment alignment="7289" annotation_id="7020">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7020" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Polish legislator, <Alignment alignment="7293" annotation_id="7046">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7046" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I believe, should remove this difference in treatment, that is a matter for the Polish Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6859" annotation_id="7089">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7089" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est la première fois que cette question se pose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7145">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'elle est trop délicate <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7174">pour</DiscourseConnective> être traitée selon la procédure sommaire, je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7230">que</DiscourseConnective> la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7237">première étape</DiscourseConnective> consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7261">à</DiscourseConnective> arriver à un arrangement: <Alignment alignment="7020" annotation_id="7289">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7289" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="7046" annotation_id="7293">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7293" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je le pense, le législateur polonais devait supprimer cette différence de traitement, cette tâche relèverait du Parlement polonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7148" docOffset="24">
      <en>Second: does Polish legislation comply with the provisions of the European Act of 1976 which I cited earlier?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7431">Deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, la législation polonaise respecte-t-elle les dispositions de l'acte européen de 1976 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7530">que</DiscourseConnective> j'ai mentionné plus haut?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7258" docOffset="25">
      <en>I can tell you, Mr Gargani, that I have commissioned a comparative study for the 12 new Member States to ascertain whether the legislation, not just Polish legislation, but the legislation of the 11 Member States which acceded to the European Union between 2004 and 2007, whether the national legislation in those Member States complies with the provisions of the European Act of 1976.</en>
      <fr>Je peux vous dire, Monsieur Gargani, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7597">que</DiscourseConnective> j'ai demandé une étude comparative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7636">pour</DiscourseConnective> les 12 nouveaux États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7671">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>évaluer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7686">si</DiscourseConnective> leur législation, pas uniquement la législation polonaise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7748">mais</DiscourseConnective> la législation des 11 États membres qui ont adhéré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7804">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union entre 2004 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7825">et</DiscourseConnective> 2007, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7834">si</DiscourseConnective> leur législation respecte les dispositions de l'acte européen de 1976.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7644" docOffset="26">
      <en>In conclusion, two tasks need to be undertaken.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7908">Pour conclure</DiscourseConnective>, il faut effectuer deux tâches.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7692" docOffset="27">
      <en>First: a review, which I am undertaking, of the conformity of Polish national legislation, and not just Polish legislation, <Alignment alignment="3475" annotation_id="7816">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7816" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the fact that Mr Gargani has brought up the case of Poland does not mean that there are not comparable situations in other Member States.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7954">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, un examen, auquel je procède, de la conformité de la législation nationale polonaise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8054">et</DiscourseConnective> pas uniquement de la législation polonaise, <Alignment alignment="7816" annotation_id="8101">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8101" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> si M. Gargani a soulevé le cas de la Pologne, cela ne signifie pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8172">que</DiscourseConnective> des situations comparables n'existent pas dans d'autres États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7962" docOffset="28">
      <en>My view is that this review is needed for all of them.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8256">que</DiscourseConnective> cet examen est nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8286">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8017" docOffset="29">
      <en>The second task is to assess whether the Polish Parliament can, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8081" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective> legislation, remove what is objectively an apparent conflict, <Alignment alignment="8443" annotation_id="8150">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8150" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is an apparent discrimination between the status, regulated by law, of MEPs elected in Poland and Polish MPs.</en>
      <fr>La deuxième tâche consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8324">à</DiscourseConnective> évaluer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8334">si</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen peut, par le biais de la législation, supprimer ce conflit objectivement manifeste, <Alignment alignment="8150" annotation_id="8443">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8443" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>on constate une discrimination manifeste entre le statut, réglementé par la loi, des députés européens élus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8558">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8569">et</DiscourseConnective> celui des députés au Parlement polonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8272" docOffset="30">
      <en>There is an apparent conflict, <Alignment alignment="8642" annotation_id="8303">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8303" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the only aspect that I believe would be difficult to accept is that it is up to the European Commission to ask the Court of Justice what action the Polish legislator should take.</en>
      <fr>Il y a un conflit manifeste, <Alignment alignment="8303" annotation_id="8642">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8642" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le seul aspect qui, je crois, sera difficile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8690">à</DiscourseConnective> accepter, c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8708">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne demande à la Cour de justice de définir les actions à prendre par le législateur polonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8486" docOffset="31">
      <en>Were Parliament to agree with this stance, we could simply point out that there is apparent discrimination in Poland between the status of two types of parliamentarian.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8828">Si</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement adopte cette position, nous pouvons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8880">simplement</DiscourseConnective> souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8901">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il existe une discrimination manifeste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8943">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne entre le statut des deux types de parlementaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8655" docOffset="32">
      <en>This is a very new exercise <Alignment alignment="9035" annotation_id="8683">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8683" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we should try to make progress with it in a spirit of cooperation.</en>
      <fr>C'est un exercice très nouveau <Alignment alignment="10282" annotation_id="9035">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9035" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons essayer d'y procéder dans un esprit de coopération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8754" id="367" name="Tadeusz Zwiefka">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8754" docOffset="33">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (PL) Mr President, Chairman Gargani presented the situation of Members of the European Parliament in the context of Polish law very clearly, as <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8931" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> their unequal treatment in this same context as regards Members of Parliament in Poland, and also with regard to senators.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, le président Gargani a exposé très clairement la situation des députés au Parlement européen dans le cadre de la loi polonaise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9285">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que leur traitement inéquitable dans ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9331">même</DiscourseConnective> contexte par rapport aux députés au Parlement polonais, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9392">et</DiscourseConnective> par rapport aux sénateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9059" docOffset="34">
      <en>I would agree with the argument put forward by Commissioner Frattini that this violates the principle of equal treatment of Members of Parliament before the law.</en>
      <fr>Je suis d'accord avec l'argument du commissaire Frattini, qui affirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9492">que</DiscourseConnective> cela viole le principe de l'égalité de traitement des députés devant la loi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9221" docOffset="35">
      <en>I would like to inform you that the present ruling coalition in Poland, the Platforma Obywatelska and the Polskie Stronnictwo Ludowe, has already begun work on changing this law <Alignment alignment="9758" annotation_id="9399">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9399" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9402" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> to make it the same for Members of the European Parliament, Members of Parliament in Poland and for Senators.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais vous informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9598">que</DiscourseConnective> la coalition au pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9626">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne, composée de la Platforma Obywatelska <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9675">et</DiscourseConnective> la Polskie Stronnictwo Ludowe, a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9711">déjà</DiscourseConnective> commencé à œuvrer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9734">pour</DiscourseConnective> modifier cette loi <Alignment alignment="949" annotation_id="9758">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9758" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>assurer des conditions égales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9795">pour</DiscourseConnective> les députés au Parlement européen, les députés au Parlement polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9869">et</DiscourseConnective> les sénateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9515" docOffset="36">
      <en>This change will follow the same direction as the provision that is contained in the European Parliament's electoral law, <Alignment alignment="9996" annotation_id="9637">
          <Alignment alignment="42964" annotation_id="9637">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9637" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the same principle <Alignment alignment="16331" annotation_id="9664">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9664" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> applies to Polish Members of Parliament and Polish Senators.</en>
      <fr>Cette modification ira dans le sens de la disposition contenue dans la loi électorale du Parlement européen, <Alignment alignment="9637" annotation_id="9996">
          <Alignment alignment="2326" annotation_id="9996">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9996" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10008">même</DiscourseConnective> principe s'applique <Alignment alignment="9664" annotation_id="10033">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10033" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aux députés au Parlement polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10077">et</DiscourseConnective> aux sénateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9730" docOffset="37">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="35399" annotation_id="9730">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9730" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in this context, <Alignment alignment="35421" annotation_id="9756">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9756" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Mr Gargani said that we are opening a discussion concerning a problem that may be a wider issue, I wonder whether it may be worth thinking about a common electoral law, at least in terms of general principles, a common electoral law for the European Parliament for all Member States of the European Union, <Alignment alignment="19952" annotation_id="10065">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10065" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> today there are very different circumstances in the 27 Member countries.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6932" annotation_id="10095">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10095" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans ce contexte, <Alignment alignment="9756" annotation_id="10124">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10124" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> M. Gargani a affirmé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10151">que</DiscourseConnective> nous allions ouvrir une discussion sur un problème qui pourrait être plus large, je me demande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10250">s'</DiscourseConnective>il vaut la peine de réfléchir à une loi électorale commune, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10312">au moins</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10321">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de principes généraux, une loi électorale commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10381">pour</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen dans tous les États membres de l'Union européenne, <Alignment alignment="5440" annotation_id="10459">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10459" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les contextes sont aujourd'hui très différents dans les 27 États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10141" docOffset="38">
      <en>It is difficult to disagree, <Alignment alignment="28547" annotation_id="10170">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10170" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> of course I accept all legal restrictions as regards MEPs, <Alignment alignment="10673" annotation_id="10233">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10233" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is difficult for me to agree with a situation where, on being sentenced to a fine in a case brought by the public prosecution service for a deliberate crime, or for being charged with such a crime, a person automatically loses their mandate to the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Il est difficile de ne pas être d'accord <Alignment alignment="10170" annotation_id="10582">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10582" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, bien sûr, j'accepte toutes les restrictions juridiques imposées aux députés européens, <Alignment alignment="10233" annotation_id="10673">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10673" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est difficile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10695">pour</DiscourseConnective> moi d'accepter une situation où une personne perd automatiquement son mandat de député européen lorsqu'elle est condamnée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10822">à</DiscourseConnective> une amende par le ministère public <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10859">pour</DiscourseConnective> une infraction volontaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10891">ou</DiscourseConnective> lorsqu'elle est accusée de ce type d'infraction.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10509" id="368" name="Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10509" docOffset="39">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (PL) Mr President, today's debate raises the issue of unequal treatment of Polish Members of the European Parliament and Members of the Sejm <Alignment alignment="19145" annotation_id="10680">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10680" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> regards election criteria, as well as that of loss of mandate.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, le débat d'aujourd'hui soulève la question du traitement inéquitable des députés polonais au Parlement européen par rapport aux députés au Sejm <Alignment alignment="5370" annotation_id="11139">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11139" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> matière de critères d'éligibilité et de perte du mandat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10746" docOffset="40">
      <en>In Article 9 of the Act of 23 January 2004 concerning the electoral ordinance for the European Parliament, we see that the right to stand for election to this institution is given to persons who, among other criteria, have not been convicted of a deliberate crime or charged by the public prosecution service, and Article 142 states that one's mandate can be withdrawn <Alignment alignment="56514" annotation_id="11115">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11115" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">as a result</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="11593" annotation_id="11128">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11128" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, of the member's election to the European Parliament being invalidated.</en>
      <fr>Dans l'article 9 de la loi du 23 janvier 2004 concernant l'ordonnance électorale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11280">pour</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen, nous constatons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11324">que</DiscourseConnective> le droit de se présenter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11353">à</DiscourseConnective> l'élection <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11366">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette institution est accordé aux personnes qui, entre autres, n'ont pas été condamnées pour une infraction volontaire ni inculpées par le ministère public. L'article 142 stipule <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11550">que</DiscourseConnective> le mandat peut être retiré <Alignment alignment="11115" annotation_id="11581">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11581" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">à</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la suite, <Alignment alignment="11128" annotation_id="11593">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11593" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, de l'invalidation de l'élection du député au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11212" docOffset="41">
      <en>This means that the conviction of a Member (this refers to a Member of the European Parliament, as has been mentioned earlier) for a crime committed deliberately is equivalent to their automatically losing their mandate, <Alignment alignment="35082" annotation_id="11433">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11433" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> for members to the national parliament this does not act as an obstacle to them standing for election, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11542" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">nor</DiscourseConnective> does it result in the loss of their mandate.</en>
      <fr>Cela signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11685">que</DiscourseConnective> la condamnation d'un député (ici, un député du Parlement européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11756">comme</DiscourseConnective> mentionné plus haut) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11783">pour</DiscourseConnective> une infraction volontaire équivaut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11823">à</DiscourseConnective> la perte automatique de son mandat, <Alignment alignment="11433" annotation_id="11861">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11861" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11872">pour</DiscourseConnective> un député national, cela ne l'empêche pas de se présenter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11935">à</DiscourseConnective> une élection et n'entraîne pas la fin de son mandat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11591" docOffset="42">
      <en>As regards the privileges of Members of the European Parliament, Rule 5(1) of the Rules of Procedure of the European Parliament states that 'Members shall enjoy privileges and immunities in accordance with the Protocol on the Privileges and Immunities of the European Communities'.</en>
      <fr>Concernant les privilèges des députés au Parlement européen, l'article 5, paragraphe 1, du règlement du Parlement européen dispose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12121">que</DiscourseConnective> "Les députés jouissent des privilèges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12163">et</DiscourseConnective> immunités prévus par le protocole sur les privilèges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12219">et</DiscourseConnective> immunités des Communautés européennes".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11873" docOffset="43">
      <en>In the Preamble, the Protocol states that it regulates the issue of privileges and immunities that are necessary to carry out responsibilities for the European Communities, and, in Article 10(a), states that, during the sessions of the Assembly, 'in the territory of their own State, its members shall enjoy the immunities accorded to members of their Parliament'.</en>
      <fr>Dans son préambule, le protocole stipule <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12303">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il réglemente la question des privilèges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12347">et</DiscourseConnective> immunités nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12372">à</DiscourseConnective> l'accomplissement de la mission de la Communauté européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12435">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12438">à</DiscourseConnective> son article 10, point (a), <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12467">que</DiscourseConnective> ses membres "bénéficient, sur leur territoire national, des immunités reconnues aux membres du Parlement de leur État".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12238" docOffset="44">
      <en>Members of the Polish Parliament and the European Parliament are protected by the same immunity.</en>
      <fr>Les membres du Parlement polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12625">et</DiscourseConnective> du Parlement européen jouissent de la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12666">même</DiscourseConnective> immunité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12335" docOffset="45">
      <en>According to Article 11, 'Representatives of Member States taking part in the work of the institutions of the Communities, their advisers and technical experts shall, in the performance of their duties and during their travel to and from the place of meeting, enjoy the customary privileges, immunities and facilities'.</en>
      <fr>Conformément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12694">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 11, "Les représentants des États membres participant aux travaux des institutions de l'Union, ainsi que leurs conseillers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12828">et</DiscourseConnective> experts techniques jouissent, pendant l'exercice de leurs fonctions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12899">et</DiscourseConnective> au cours de leurs voyages <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12928">à</DiscourseConnective> destination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12942">ou</DiscourseConnective> en provenance du lieu de la réunion, des privilèges, immunités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13008">ou</DiscourseConnective> facilités d'usage".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12655" docOffset="46">
      <en>There is no doubt that a Member of the European Parliament is a representative of a Member State who is taking part in the work of the institutions of the Union.</en>
      <fr>Il ne fait aucun doute <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13054">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un membre du Parlement européen est un représentant d'un État membre qui participe aux travaux des institutions de l'Union.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12817" docOffset="47">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13181" annotation_id="12817">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12817" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Members of the European Parliament and of the Polish Parliament should benefit from the same immunities and privileges, then the rules <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12958" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> regards their eligibility to stand for election as well as for loss of mandate should <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13047" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> be the same.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12817" annotation_id="13181">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13181" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les membres du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13223">et</DiscourseConnective> du Parlement polonais devraient jouir des mêmes immunités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13284">et</DiscourseConnective> privilèges, les règles concernant leur éligibilité pour participer aux élections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13368">et</DiscourseConnective> la perte de leur mandat doivent être les mêmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13065" docOffset="48">
      <en>In acceding to the European Union Poland assumed a responsibility to respect laws in force in the EU, especially those laws having a direct impact on the internal legal system in Member States.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13419">En</DiscourseConnective> adhérant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13431">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne, la Pologne s'est engagée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13478">à</DiscourseConnective> respecter les lois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13499">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur dans l'UE, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13521">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> les lois ayant un impact direct sur le système juridique interne des États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13259" docOffset="49">
      <en>I would encourage the fastest possible standardisation in legislation relating to the status of Members of the Polish Parliament and Members of the European Parliament in Poland, <Alignment alignment="13776" annotation_id="13438">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13438" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I fully agree with the view taken by Commissioner Frattini in this regard.</en>
      <fr>Je préconise la normalisation, le plus rapidement possible, de la législation relative au statut des députés au Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13751">et</DiscourseConnective> au Parlement polonais <Alignment alignment="696" annotation_id="13776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13776" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis entièrement d'accord avec l'avis adopté par le commissaire Frattini <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13855">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13517" id="369" name="Jens-Peter Bonde">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13517" docOffset="50">
      <en>on behalf of the IND/DEM Group. - Mr President, the Polish electoral law on elections to the European Parliament is truly unfair and undemocratic compared to the law on elections to the national parliament.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe IND/DEM. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la loi électorale polonaise sur les élections au Parlement européen est vraiment injuste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14013">et</DiscourseConnective> non démocratique par rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14045">à</DiscourseConnective> la loi sur les élections au parlement national.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13724" docOffset="51">
      <en>The forfeiture of a seat of a deputy to the European Parliament by laws of eligibility is an easy way to put pressure on political opponents and gives the opportunity to settle an account politically with those who have more authority.</en>
      <fr>La perte d'un siège de député au Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14147">en</DiscourseConnective> vertu des lois de l'éligibilité est un moyen facile d'exercer une pression sur les opposants politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14254">et</DiscourseConnective> constitue une occasion de régler ses comptes de manière politique avec ceux qui ont davantage d'autorité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13960" docOffset="52">
      <en>Unfortunately, <Alignment alignment="8292" annotation_id="13975">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13975" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> being in the European Union, the law is still abused in many former Communist countries.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14363">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="13975" annotation_id="14380">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14380" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils fassent partie de l'Union européenne, la loi est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14441">encore</DiscourseConnective> enfreinte dans de nombreux anciens pays communistes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14073" docOffset="53">
      <en>This is the case for Mr Tomczak as well.</en>
      <fr>C'est également le cas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14524">pour</DiscourseConnective> M. Tomczak.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14114" docOffset="54">
      <en>As Members of the European Parliament, Polish MEPs represent not only the Poles but also all Europeans.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14544">tant que</DiscourseConnective> députés du Parlement européens, les députés européens polonais représentent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14629">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> les Polonais, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14657">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> tous les Européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14218" docOffset="55">
      <en>It is unacceptable that these people's representatives are discriminated against by maintaining different legislation with regard to Members of the Polish Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Il est inacceptable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14708">que</DiscourseConnective> les représentants de ces personnes fassent l'objet d'une discrimination grâce au maintien d'une législation différente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14831">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard des députés du Parlement polonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14385" docOffset="56">
      <en>A Polish MEP, <Alignment alignment="17545" annotation_id="14399">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14399" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> convicted, will be punished not only by Polish law but will <Alignment alignment="22043" annotation_id="14462">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14462" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> lose his seat as a Member of the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Un député polonais, <Alignment alignment="14399" annotation_id="14896">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14896" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il est reconnu coupable, sera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14928">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> puni par la loi polonaise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14969">mais</DiscourseConnective> perdra <Alignment alignment="14462" annotation_id="14981">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14981" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> son siège de député au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14521" docOffset="57">
      <en>That fact clearly shows the discrimination of Polish Members of the European Parliament in comparison to members of national parliaments.</en>
      <fr>Ce fait montre clairement la discrimination dont font l'objet les députés polonais du Parlement européen par rapport aux députés du parlement national.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14659" docOffset="58">
      <en>That situation is unacceptable and shows clearly how unjust and unfair the Polish electoral law is.</en>
      <fr>Cette situation est inacceptable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15219">et</DiscourseConnective> montre clairement à quel point la loi électorale polonaise est injuste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15293">et</DiscourseConnective> partiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14759" docOffset="59">
      <en>May I urge Poland to change its electoral law?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15306">Puis</DiscourseConnective>-je encourager vivement la Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15345">à</DiscourseConnective> modifier sa loi électorale?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14806" id="370" name="Aloyzas Sakalas">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14806" docOffset="60">
      <en>Mr President, this oral question is a consequence of the debates in the Committee on Legal Affairs on the immunity of Mr Tomczak.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, cette question orale est une conséquence des débats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15455">en</DiscourseConnective> commission des affaires juridiques concernant l'immunité de M. Tomczak.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14936" docOffset="61">
      <en>The immunity of Mr Tomczak was raised by Parliament a few years ago.</en>
      <fr>L'immunité de M. Tomczak a été levée par le Parlement il y a quelques années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15005" docOffset="62">
      <en>Recently the Committee on Legal Affairs received a request from Mr Tomczak to defend his immunity.</en>
      <fr>Récemment, la commission des affaires juridiques a reçu une demande de M. Tomczak <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15690">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> défendre son immunité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15104" docOffset="63">
      <en>The committee discussed this request <Alignment alignment="40263" annotation_id="15141">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15141" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a draft decision has been prepared.</en>
      <fr>La commission a discuté de cette demande <Alignment alignment="15141" annotation_id="15764">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15764" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un projet de décision a été préparé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15181" docOffset="64">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="15839" annotation_id="15181">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15181" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the adoption of the final decision was postponed <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15244" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> the committee received information that, in the event of his immunity being waived, the legal consequences for Members of the European Parliament from Poland and Members of the Polish Parliament would be different.</en>
      <fr>L'adoption de la décision finale a <Alignment alignment="15181" annotation_id="15839">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15839" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> été reportée, la commission ayant reçu des informations selon lesquelles, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15923">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de levée de son immunité, les conséquences juridiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15984">pour</DiscourseConnective> les députés polonais du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16032">et</DiscourseConnective> les députés du Parlement polonais seraient différentes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15462" docOffset="65">
      <en>According to the Polish Act of 23 January 2004, a Member of the European Parliament from Poland will lose his or her seat automatically in the event of criminal conviction.</en>
      <fr>En vertu de la loi polonaise du 23 janvier 2004, un député polonais du Parlement européen perdra automatiquement son siège <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16214">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de condamnation pénale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15635" docOffset="66">
      <en>For Members of the Polish Parliament this provision is not applicable.</en>
      <fr>Cette disposition ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16266">s'</DiscourseConnective>applique pas aux députés du parlement polonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15706" docOffset="67">
      <en>Such a difference is in breach of European Community law, by maintaining different legislation with regard to members of the national parliament and Polish Members of the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Cette différence est contraire au droit communautaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16371">en</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16374">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> une législation différente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16412">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard des députés du parlement national <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16456">et</DiscourseConnective> des députés polonais du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15898" docOffset="68">
      <en>This discrepancy between Polish and European Community laws needs to be clarified.</en>
      <fr>Cette différence entre le droit polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16544">et</DiscourseConnective> le droit communautaire doit être clarifiée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15981" docOffset="69">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="30234" annotation_id="15981">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15981" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I fully support the formulation of an oral question to the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Je soutiens <Alignment alignment="9870" annotation_id="16603">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16603" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> totalement la formulation d'une question orale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16659">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16063" docOffset="70">
      <en>I hope Mr Frattini will use all his influence to aim to eliminate this discrepancy between Polish and European Community laws.</en>
      <fr>J'espère que M. Frattini usera de toute son influence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16730">en vue d'</DiscourseConnective>éliminer cette différence entre le droit polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16789">et</DiscourseConnective> le droit communautaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16190" id="371" name="Paul Rübig">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16190" docOffset="71">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, Commissioner Frattini, ladies and gentlemen, I believe that democracy in Europe needs to be constantly developed, <Alignment alignment="40465" annotation_id="16323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16323" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are seeing many attacks on our democratic system from outside Europe.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16878">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16901">que</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16919">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe doit être constamment développée, <Alignment alignment="16323" annotation_id="16963">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16963" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous constatons de nombreuses attaques contre notre système démocratique venant de l'extérieur de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16400" docOffset="72">
      <en>The Members of the European Parliament take decisions, of course, on very many issues that have a direct and immediate effect on the European public.</en>
      <fr>Les députés au Parlement européen prennent les décisions, bien entendu, sur de nombreuses questions ayant un effet direct <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17196">et</DiscourseConnective> immédiat sur la population européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16550" docOffset="73">
      <en>Members of parliaments do not take decisions for themselves but represent their voters.</en>
      <fr>Les membres des parlements ne prennent pas de décisions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17294">pour</DiscourseConnective> eux-mêmes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17310">mais</DiscourseConnective> représentent leurs électeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16638" docOffset="74">
      <en>For this reason the Members of the European Parliament must not be inferior in status to members of national parliaments nor, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16764" sense="Comparison.Contrast">conversely</DiscourseConnective>, should national deputies have a lesser status than MEPs.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17345">Pour</DiscourseConnective> cette raison, les députés européens ne doivent pas jouir d'un statut inférieur ni supérieur à celui des députés aux parlements nationaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16833" docOffset="75">
      <en>For this reason I believe that the Commission should examine the impact on Poland's MEPs of the new statute that will apply from 2009 onwards and investigate what changes the statute will make <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17026" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> whether there is not some scope for its principles to be applied in order to remove these disparities.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17488">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17512">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission devrait examiner l'impact des députés européens polonais sur le nouveau statut qui s'appliquera à partir de 2009 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17643">et</DiscourseConnective> se pencher sur les changements apportés par le statut. Elle devrait aussi examiner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17729">si</DiscourseConnective> ses principes ne pourraient pas, dans une certaine mesure, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17791">s'</DiscourseConnective>appliquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17803">pour</DiscourseConnective> supprimer ces disparités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17133" id="372" name="Manuel Medina Ortega">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17133" docOffset="76">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, <Alignment alignment="32974" annotation_id="17152">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17152" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ever, Commissioner Frattini has performed an intricate legal analysis.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="21865" annotation_id="17862">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17862" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> toujours, le commissaire Frattini a procédé à une analyse juridique complexe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17226" docOffset="77">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17946" annotation_id="17226">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17226" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he said, in the current circumstances there would appear to be no grounds for bringing proceedings before the Court of Justice directly.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17226" annotation_id="17946">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17946" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il l'a affirmé, dans les circonstances actuelles, il apparaît que rien ne justifie une action directe devant la Cour de justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17366" docOffset="78">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18081" annotation_id="17366">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17366" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="26230" annotation_id="17375">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17375" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> listening to Mr Zwiefka, who has been telling us about a proposal from the current Polish Government to amend the law, I would ask the Commissioner whether he believes that the Commission could <Alignment alignment="43672" annotation_id="17575">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17575" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> approach the Polish Government on the basis of the debate we are having in Parliament at present to see whether the Polish Government is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17720" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">indeed</DiscourseConnective> proposing to amend the law to harmonise the status of MEPs with that of members of the national parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17366" annotation_id="18081">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18081" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="18266" annotation_id="18092">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18092" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avoir écouté M. Zwiefka, qui nous a parlé d'une proposition d'amendement de la loi par le gouvernement polonais actuel, je demande au commissaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18244">s'</DiscourseConnective>il estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18256">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission pourrait <Alignment alignment="17575" annotation_id="18283">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18283" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>adresser au gouvernement polonais sur la base du débat que nous avons actuellement au Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18381">pour</DiscourseConnective> voir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18391">s'</DiscourseConnective>il propose bien de modifier la loi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18428">en vue d'</DiscourseConnective>harmoniser le statut des députés européens avec celui des députés nationaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17835" id="373" name="Marek Aleksander Czarnecki">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17835" docOffset="79">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, the proposal put forward by Mr Zwiefka to make the situation of Members of the European Parliament the same as Members of the Parliament in Poland does not provide a solution to the problem.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, la proposition avancée par M. Zwiefka d'harmoniser le statut des membres du Parlement européen et du Parlement polonais n'est pas une solution au problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18045" docOffset="80">
      <en>I believe that the best solution, which is <Alignment alignment="13451" annotation_id="18088">
          <Alignment alignment="18738" annotation_id="18088">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18088" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> already part of Polish law, would be that in circumstances where a person is convicted of a deliberate crime, the court should <Alignment alignment="18875" annotation_id="18223">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18223" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> decide to deprive them of public rights, meaning that the person in question cannot stand for election.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18707">que</DiscourseConnective> la meilleure solution qui, <Alignment alignment="18088" annotation_id="18738">
          <Alignment alignment="15758" annotation_id="18738">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18738" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en réalité</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, existe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18757">déjà</DiscourseConnective> dans le droit polonais, serait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18793">que</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18797">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>une personne est accusée d'une infraction volontaire, le tribunal doit <Alignment alignment="20098" annotation_id="18875">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18875" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> décider de la déchoir de ses droits publics, l'empêchant ainsi de se présenter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18964">à</DiscourseConnective> une élection.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18332" docOffset="81">
      <en>This solution exists, <Alignment alignment="19003" annotation_id="18354">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18354" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in France.</en>
      <fr>Cette solution existe, <Alignment alignment="18354" annotation_id="19003">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19003" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19016">en</DiscourseConnective> France.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18378" docOffset="82">
      <en>I would like to give you a specific example: our colleague, Mr Onesta, the Vice-President of the European Parliament, was sentenced a few months ago by a court in France to a suspended sentence of several months for an act that, under Polish law, would automatically mean the loss of one's mandate to the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais vous faire part d'un exemple concret: notre collègue, M. Onesta, vice-Président du Parlement européen, a été condamné il y a quelques mois par un tribunal français <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19202">à</DiscourseConnective> une peine de plusieurs mois avec sursis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19244">pour</DiscourseConnective> un acte qui, dans le droit polonais, entraînerait automatiquement la perte de son mandat au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18704" docOffset="83">
      <en>I see the present situation as being completely wrong.</en>
      <fr>J'estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19370">que</DiscourseConnective> la situation actuelle est totalement mal comprise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18759" docOffset="84">
      <en>I think we should go in the direction of the solution proposed by Mr Frattini.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions aller dans le sens de la solution proposée par M. Frattini.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18838" id="374" name="Giuseppe Gargani">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18838" docOffset="85">
      <en>(IT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, some further brief comments: I am pleased that the debate overall has recognised that there is a significant and thorny problem.</en>
      <fr>(IT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19536">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, j'aimerais faire quelques brèves remarques supplémentaires. Je suis ravi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19623">que</DiscourseConnective> le débat global ait reconnu l'existence d'un problème important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19691">et</DiscourseConnective> épineux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19008" docOffset="86">
      <en>I should like, in particular, to thank Commissioner Frattini who, as the good lawyer that he is, has looked in more detail at the matter, which, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19153" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> he rightly says, does not just relate to Poland.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19714">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> remercier le commissaire Frattini qui, bon juriste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19780">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est, s'est penché plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19809">avant</DiscourseConnective> sur la question qui, il l'a dit justement, ne touche pas que la Pologne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19205" docOffset="87">
      <en>There is a general principle at stake <Alignment alignment="19929" annotation_id="19243">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19243" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am <Alignment alignment="19940" annotation_id="19252">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19252" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> very content, as is the Committee, that you are undertaking an overall review to monitor compliance and to check whether laws are consistent as regards the national and the European question.</en>
      <fr>C'est un principe général qui est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19922">en</DiscourseConnective> jeu <Alignment alignment="19243" annotation_id="19929">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19929" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis <Alignment alignment="19252" annotation_id="19940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19940" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> très content, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19963">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19988">que</DiscourseConnective> vous procédiez à un examen global <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20026">pour</DiscourseConnective> contrôler le respect des lois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20061">et</DiscourseConnective> vérifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20073">si</DiscourseConnective> les lois sont cohérentes concernant la question nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20134">et</DiscourseConnective> européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>

<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19455" docOffset="89">
      <en>One fact is certain, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19476" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>, there is not an apparent conflict <Alignment alignment="20217" annotation_id="19519">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19519" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, as regards guarantees, the Polish law is contrary to the Treaty; <Alignment alignment="20295" annotation_id="19591">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19591" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a Polish MEP were to lose his seat, obviously the article of the treaty which provides for the possibility of taking part in the sessions would fall.</en>
      <fr>Il ne s'agit pas d'un conflit manifeste <Alignment alignment="19519" annotation_id="20217">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20217" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, concernant les garanties, le droit polonais est contraire au traité. <Alignment alignment="19591" annotation_id="20295">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20295" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un député européen polonais perd son siège, il est évident que l'article du traité relatif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20389">à</DiscourseConnective> la participation aux sessions deviendra caduc.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19744" docOffset="90">
      <en>From the Committee's own point of view, <Alignment alignment="20472" annotation_id="19784">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19784" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you have heard in the debate just now from Mr Medina, and from me personally, the issue is not one of bringing proceedings, but of following up the question in order to resolve it.</en>
      <fr>Du point de vue de la commission, <Alignment alignment="19784" annotation_id="20472">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20472" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous l'avez entendu dans la discussion qui a précédé avec M. Medina <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20546">et</DiscourseConnective> avec moi-même, la question n'est pas d'entamer des poursuites, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20612">mais</DiscourseConnective> de suivre la question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20639">pour</DiscourseConnective> la résoudre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19968" docOffset="91">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20657" annotation_id="19968">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19968" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our Polish colleague, Mr Zwiefka, says that this matter has already been brought to the fore in Poland, some progress has already been made.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19968" annotation_id="20657">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20657" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> notre collègue polonais, M. Zwiefka, affirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20705">que</DiscourseConnective> cette question a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20726">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été soulevée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20744">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne, c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20762">déjà</DiscourseConnective> un progrès.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20112" docOffset="92">
      <en>Comparability is what is needed, <Alignment alignment="20826" annotation_id="20145">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20145" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that comparability makes Europe the guarantor of the unity of States that are working together, of citizenship and of equal rights from the point of view of freedom and everyone's status.</en>
      <fr>Ce qui est nécessaire, c'est la comparabilité, <Alignment alignment="20145" annotation_id="20826">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20826" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette comparabilité fait de l'Europe le garant de l'unité d'États qui travaillent ensemble, de la citoyenneté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20939">et</DiscourseConnective> de droits égaux du point de vue de la liberté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20988">et</DiscourseConnective> du statut de chacun.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20336" id="375" name="Sylwester Chruszcz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20336" docOffset="93">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, just to add my support to the speeches, most of which I support, I believe that of course we should harmonise our regulations as soon as possible.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21052">simplement</DiscourseConnective> apporter mon soutien aux discours, avec lesquels je suis en grande partie d'accord. Je crois bien sûr <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21165">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devrions harmoniser nos réglementations le plus vite possible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20502" docOffset="94">
      <en>To illustrate how necessary this, is I would like to draw attention to the story of our colleague, an MEP, who is present here with us: Mr Tomczak, who has been involved in a criminal case in Poland for many years, which is now approaching a conclusion and could impact on his future as a Member of the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21237">Pour</DiscourseConnective> illustrer combien cela est nécessaire, j'aimerais attirer l'attention sur l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21318">histoire de</DiscourseConnective> notre collègue, un député européen, qui est présent aujourd'hui avec nous, M. Tomczak, qui a été impliqué dans une affaire pénale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21460">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne pendant des années, affaire qui arrive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21510">bientôt</DiscourseConnective> à son terme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21530">et</DiscourseConnective> pourrait affecter son avenir en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21565">tant que</DiscourseConnective> député au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20826" docOffset="95">
      <en>A case which does not involve much harm, <Alignment alignment="21642" annotation_id="20867">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20867" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in which witnesses deny that the event took place.</en>
      <fr>Une affaire qui n'est pas très grave, <Alignment alignment="20867" annotation_id="21642">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21642" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans laquelle les témoins disent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21678">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21687">s'</DiscourseConnective>est rien passé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20922" docOffset="96">
      <en>A case that at one time was closed, which perhaps under the influence of some political turbulence has been reopened; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21040" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> now, Mr Tomczak, who has twice been elected (our colleague became an MP in 2005, and an MEP in 2004), now, his immunity as well as his mandate may be removed.</en>
      <fr>Une affaire qui a été close, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21734">puis</DiscourseConnective> rouverte, peut-être en raison de quelques remous politiques. M. Tomczak, qui a été élu à deux reprises (notre collègue est devenu député national <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21885">en</DiscourseConnective> 2005 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21893">et</DiscourseConnective> député européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21912">en</DiscourseConnective> 2004).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21203" docOffset="97">
      <en>This is something that is unbelievable, harmful <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21251" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> which should, as quickly as possible, be cut short and removed from this forum.</en>
      <fr>Son immunité et son mandat pourraient lui être retirés. C'est quelque chose d'inconcevable, de nuisible, à laquelle il faut couper court le plus rapidement possible et qu'il faut bannir de cette Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="21335" id="376" name="Franco Frattini">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="21335" docOffset="98">
      <en>Vice-President of the Commission. - (IT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I feel that tonight's debate has shown two things: the first is that there is a widespread view, which is shared, I would say, by all those who have spoken - and a view which I believe to be right - that the disparity of treatment between MEPs elected in Poland and Polish national MPs should be removed <Alignment alignment="21021" annotation_id="21716">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21716" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that this analysis should be extended to all the other new Member States of the European Union whose compliance with the European Act of 1976 has not as yet been checked.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - (IT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22200">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, selon moi, le débat de ce soir a montré deux choses. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22267">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, il existe un large consensus partagé, je dirais, par tous les intervenants - consensus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22368">que</DiscourseConnective> je pense juste - selon lequel la disparité de traitement entre les députés européens élus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22462">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22473">et</DiscourseConnective> les députés au Parlement polonais doivent être supprimées <Alignment alignment="21716" annotation_id="22534">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22534" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22537">que</DiscourseConnective> cette analyse doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22560">s'</DiscourseConnective>étendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22570">à</DiscourseConnective> tous les autres nouveaux États membres de l'Union européenne pour lesquels il n'a pas encore été vérifié s'ils respectaient l'acte européen de 1976.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21891" docOffset="99">
      <en>The second conclusion, and I refer to the proposal by Mr Medina Ortega, with which I agree, is to pass on the outcome of this debate to the competent authorities of the Polish Government, informing them that this disparity of treatment needs to be removed through national legislation.</en>
      <fr>La deuxième conclusion, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22745">et</DiscourseConnective> je vise ici la proposition de M. Medina Ortega, avec laquelle je suis d'accord, est qu'il faut faire part du <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22857">résultat</DiscourseConnective> de ce débat aux autorités compétentes du gouvernement polonais, pour les informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22948">que</DiscourseConnective> cette disparité de traitement doit être supprimée par la législation nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22177" docOffset="100">
      <en>I shall do that.</en>
      <fr>Je le ferai.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22194" docOffset="101">
      <en>I can tell you that I shall certainly make formal contact with the Minister of Justice of the Polish Government in order to pass on the widespread opinion of this House - which I share - that <Alignment alignment="23254" annotation_id="22386">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22386" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Polish national legislator has sovereign powers over the way in which the elimination of this disparity of treatment is to be achieved, the objective of removing that disparity of treatment must be pursued.</en>
      <fr>Je peux vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23058">dire que</DiscourseConnective> je prendrai formellement contact avec le ministre de la justice du gouvernement polonais pour lui faire part de l'avis prédominant de cette Assemblée - avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23224">que</DiscourseConnective> je partage - selon lequel <Alignment alignment="22386" annotation_id="23254">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23254" sense="Comparison.Contrast">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le législateur national polonais a des pouvoirs souverains sur la manière de supprimer cette disparité de traitement, l'objectif de suppression de cette disparité doit être poursuivi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22603" docOffset="102">
      <en>That is the opinion that I put forward at the beginning: I do not consider that I can tell the Polish legislator how to proceed, <Alignment alignment="23559" annotation_id="22732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22732" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I do consider that I can spell out the objective, <Alignment alignment="23605" annotation_id="22786">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22786" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that objective is to remove the disparity of treatment between the status of Polish national MPs and the status of MEPs elected in Poland.</en>
      <fr>C'est l'avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23454">que</DiscourseConnective> je préconise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23471">depuis</DiscourseConnective> le début. Je ne pense pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23504">que</DiscourseConnective> je peux dire au législateur polonais comment agir, <Alignment alignment="22732" annotation_id="23559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23559" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23573">que</DiscourseConnective> je peux définir l'objectif, <Alignment alignment="16939" annotation_id="23605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23605" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cet objectif est de supprimer la disparité de traitement entre le statut des députés au Parlement national polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23724">et</DiscourseConnective> au Parlement européen élus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23754">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22929" docOffset="103">
      <en>I shall certainly pass on that information <Alignment alignment="7727" annotation_id="22972">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22972" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would add that I shall report back to this House, in view of the interest of Mr Gargani and the Committee on Legal Affairs, on the review of the other 11 new Member States <Alignment alignment="24001" annotation_id="23150">
          <Alignment alignment="24001" annotation_id="23150">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23150" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the governments of other Member States that might be affected can <Alignment alignment="24083" annotation_id="23224">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23224" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be notified <Alignment alignment="55963" annotation_id="23241">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23241" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">accordingly</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</en>
      <fr>Je transmettrai certainement ces informations <Alignment alignment="24202" annotation_id="23812">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23812" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'aimerais ajouter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23834">que</DiscourseConnective> je communiquerai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23855">à</DiscourseConnective> cette Assemblée, vu l'intérêt de M. Gargani <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23901">et</DiscourseConnective> de la commission des affaires juridiques, les résultats de l'examen des 11 autres États membres, <Alignment alignment="23150" annotation_id="24001">
          <Alignment alignment="5344" annotation_id="24001">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24001" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> les gouvernements des autres États membres pouvant être touchés puissent <Alignment alignment="7787" annotation_id="24083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24083" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être notifiés <Alignment alignment="11494" annotation_id="24100">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24100" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">en conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="23254" id="377" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="23254" docOffset="104">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
