<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>1.</en>
    <fr>1.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Draft general budget for the European Union - Financial year 2007 (vote)</en>
    <fr>Projet de budget général de l'Union européenne - Exercice 2007 (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="76" id="060" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="76" docOffset="2">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I would point out that, according to the Treaties, in order to be approved, draft amendments relating to what we call non-obligatory spending must be voted for by a majority of the members of the European Parliament, that is to say, 367 votes.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="82">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="118">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> vertu des Traités, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="143">pour</DiscourseConnective> être approuvés, les projets d'amendements relatifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="199">à</DiscourseConnective> ce que l'on appelle les dépenses non obligatoires doivent obtenir les voix de la majorité des députés européens, c'est-à-dire 367 voix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="342" docOffset="3">
      <en>In the case of proposed amendments relating to obligatory spending, a majority of the votes cast is sufficient.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="337">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les propositions d'amendements relatives aux dépenses obligatoires, la majorité des votes exprimés suffit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="454" docOffset="4">
      <en>Before the vote, Mr Elles wishes to propose certain technical amendments.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="463">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote, M. Elles souhaite proposer certains amendements techniques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="528" id="061" name="James Elles ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="528" docOffset="5">
      <en>rapporteur. - Mr President, it is good to get the vote on the 2007 budget under way.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je me réjouis de la tenue du vote sur le budget 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="613" docOffset="6">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="634" annotation_id="613">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="613" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we start on the vote on Parliament's first reading, I should like to announce that a small number of technical adjustments need to be made.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="613" annotation_id="634">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="634" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> commencer le vote <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="661">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture du Parlement, je voudrais vous signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="721">que</DiscourseConnective> certains ajustements d'ordre technique sont nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="760" docOffset="7">
      <en>Rather than read out a very long list of numbers, the list of technical adjustments has been annexed to our voting lists.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="782">Afin d'</DiscourseConnective>éviter la lecture d'une longue liste de chiffres, la liste des ajustements d'ordre technique a été annexée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="896">à</DiscourseConnective> nos listes de vote.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="882" docOffset="8">
      <en>Following the vote those adjustments will be made by the relevant departments and included in the Minutes of the sitting.</en>
      <fr>Ces ajustements seront effectués <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="951">après</DiscourseConnective> le vote par les départements concernés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="996">et</DiscourseConnective> figureront dans le procès-verbal de la séance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1004" docOffset="9">
      <en>(Parliament accepted the technical amendments proposed by Mr Elles)</en>
      <fr>(Le Parlement adopte les amendements techniques proposés par M. Elles)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1072" docOffset="10">
      <en>(Before the vote on Section I)</en>
      <fr>(<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1118">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote sur la section I)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1103" id="063" name="Louis Grech ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1103" docOffset="11">
      <en>rapporteur. - Mr President, I should like to inform you that the resolution will be adapted according to the result of the vote on the budgetary amendments.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais vous signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1218">que</DiscourseConnective> la résolution sera adaptée en fonction du <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1264">résultat</DiscourseConnective> du vote sur les amendements budgétaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1260" docOffset="12">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1260" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>, any technical corrections needed will be made by the session services.</en>
      <fr>Pour cette raison, tous les ajustements d'ordre technique nécessaires seront apportés par les services de la séance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1342" docOffset="13">
      <en>(Parliament agreed)</en>
      <fr>(Le Parlement marque son accord)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
