<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Welcome</en>
    <fr>Souhaits de bienvenue</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="253" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I wish to welcome the members of a delegation from the Parliament of Kyrgyzstan, under the leadership of Mr Matubraimov, who have taken their seats in the VIP gallery.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais souhaiter la bienvenue aux membres d'une délégation du parlement du Kirghizstan, dirigée par M. Matubraimov, qui ont pris place dans la tribune d'honneur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="198" docOffset="2">
      <en>The delegation is here to take part in the fifth session of the EU-Kyrgyzstan Parliamentary Cooperation Committee here in Strasbourg.</en>
      <fr>La délégation est ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="234">pour</DiscourseConnective> participer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="250">à</DiscourseConnective> la cinquième session de la commission de coopération parlementaire UE-Kirghizstan, ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="339">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="332" docOffset="3">
      <en>A very warm welcome to you all!</en>
      <fr>Soyez tous les bienvenus!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="364" docOffset="4">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="375" docOffset="5">
      <en>We rejoice in the further progress made in relations between our two Parliaments since the entry into force, in 1999, of the Cooperation Agreement between the European Union and the Republic of Kyrgyzstan.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous réjouissons des nouveaux progrès réalisés dans les relations entre nos deux parlements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="495">depuis</DiscourseConnective> l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="511">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="523">en</DiscourseConnective> 1999, de l'accord de coopération entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="584">et</DiscourseConnective> la République kirghize.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="581" docOffset="6">
      <en>I wish you an agreeable sojourn in Strasbourg.</en>
      <fr>Je vous souhaite un agréable séjour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="647">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
