<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>2.</en>
    <fr>2.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Challenges to collective agreements in the EU (</en>
    <fr>Défis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9">pour</DiscourseConnective> les conventions collectives dans l'UE (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="51" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>
      <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="54">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="70" id="124" language="PL" name="Jacek Protasiewicz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="70" docOffset="3">
      <en>Mr President, I would like to inform you that after a debate yesterday during our PPE-DE Group meeting, we as a group are withdrawing three amendments: Amendment 6 to paragraph 9; Amendment 8 to paragraph 15 and Amendment 10 to paragraph 24.</en>
      <fr>au nom du Groupe PPE-DE. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais vous informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="150">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à l'issue d'un débat qui s'est tenu hier durant la réunion du groupe PPE-DE, notre groupe souhaite retirer trois amendements: l'amendement 6 au paragraphe 9, l'amendement 8 au paragraphe 15 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="343">et</DiscourseConnective> l'amendement 10 au paragraphe 24.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="312" docOffset="4">
      <en>I inform you with pleasure, on behalf of the PPE-DE Group, that those three amendments are withdrawn.</en>
      <fr>J'ai le plaisir de vous informer, au nom du groupe PPE-DE, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="439">que</DiscourseConnective> ces trois amendements sont retirés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="414" docOffset="5">
      <en>- After the vote:</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="479">Après</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="432" id="126" name="Emilio Menéndez del Valle">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="432" docOffset="6">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, with all due respect, I must make the following comment.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, avec tout le respect que je vous dois, je me dois de faire cette <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="587">remarque</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="508" docOffset="7">
      <en>Following the very proper and sensible address made on the Alliance of Civilisations by the UN High Representative, you resumed the sitting with these words - perhaps you have them handy - which were more or less <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="721" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> follows:</en>
      <fr>Au terme du discours correct <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="626">et</DiscourseConnective> raisonnable prononcé par le haut-représentant de l'ONU sur le thème de l'Alliance des civilisations, vous avez repris la séance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="757">en</DiscourseConnective> prononçant les paroles suivantes - peut-être les avez-vous sous la main:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="733" docOffset="8">
      <en>'Well, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="740" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> now, following the Alliance of Civilisations, we must return to earth'.</en>
      <fr>"Eh bien, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="843">après</DiscourseConnective> l'Alliance des civilisations, nous devons revenir sur terre".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="816" docOffset="9">
      <en>Mr President, I regret to say that your comment was not in line with parliamentary courtesy and was inappropriate in your position as President.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président je suis au regret de vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="959">dire que</DiscourseConnective> ce commentaire n'était pas conforme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1004">à</DiscourseConnective> la courtoisie parlementaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1034">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'il était inapproprié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1061">en</DiscourseConnective> votre qualité de Président.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="961" id="127" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="961" docOffset="10">
      <en>You must be aware that one of the President's powers - and my Vice-President colleagues frequently do this - is to make innocuous comments about incidents in the House.</en>
      <fr>Vous devez savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1110">que</DiscourseConnective> l'une des prérogatives du président - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1152">et</DiscourseConnective> mes collègues vice-présidents le font souvent - est de faire des commentaires innocents sur les événements qui se déroulent au sein du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1130" docOffset="11">
      <en>These comments must be taken in the context of their content and intention.</en>
      <fr>Ces commentaires doivent être interprétés dans le contexte de leur contenu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1376">et</DiscourseConnective> de leur intention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1206" docOffset="12">
      <en>I can assure you, dear Member, that my intention was absolutely positive.</en>
      <fr>Je <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1401">puis</DiscourseConnective> vous assurer, cher député, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1433">que</DiscourseConnective> mon intention était tout à fait honorable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1280" docOffset="13">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1564" annotation_id="1280">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1280" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="1491" annotation_id="1289">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1289" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you or any other Member has found something disturbing in this innocent and benevolent comment, you must regard it as having been withdrawn.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="275" annotation_id="1480">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1480" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="1289" annotation_id="1491">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1491" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous-même <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1504">ou</DiscourseConnective> tout autre député trouvez que ce commentaire innocent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1561">et</DiscourseConnective> bienveillant est dérangeant, je le retire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
