<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>7.</en>
    <fr>7.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Establishment, operation and use of SIS II (regulation) (vote)</en>
    <fr>Établissement, fonctionnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33">et</DiscourseConnective> utilisation de SIS II (règlement) (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="66" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="79">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="85" id="126" name="Paula Lehtomäki">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="85" docOffset="3">
      <en>President-in-Office of the Council. Mr President, there is hardly any need to underline the importance of the legislative proposals for the second generation Schengen information system.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, inutile de souligner l'importance des propositions législatives relatives au système d'information Schengen de deuxième génération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="272" docOffset="4">
      <en>The SIS II system is a central tool for law enforcement authorities <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="340" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> at the same time makes it possible to expand the Schengen area and abolish controls at internal borders.</en>
      <fr>Le système SIS II représente un instrument primordial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="303">pour</DiscourseConnective> les autorités répressives, qui permet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="346">parallèlement</DiscourseConnective> d'élargir l'espace Schengen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="388">et</DiscourseConnective> de supprimer les contrôles aux frontières intérieures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="449" docOffset="5">
      <en>For the first time in the history of the European Union, we are creating a legislative basis for a massive information system in codecision with the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="446">Pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois dans l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="475">histoire de</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne, un immense système d'information est doté d'une base législative, et ceci <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="581">en</DiscourseConnective> codécision avec le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="619" docOffset="6">
      <en>The Presidency has, together with the European Parliament's rapporteur, Mr Coelho, prepared a compromise that it is hoped will be acceptable to all parties at first reading.</en>
      <fr>La présidence a préparé, en collaboration avec M. Coelho, le rapporteur du Parlement européen, un compromis qui - nous l'espérons - sera adopté par tous les partis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="787">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="793" docOffset="7">
      <en>We thank Mr Coelho and his team for their cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Nous tenons à remercier M. Coehlo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="842">et</DiscourseConnective> son équipe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="856">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur collaboration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="848" docOffset="8">
      <en>The Council's position on the legislative package on SIS II was submitted to the President of Parliament in early October. The Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs voted on its position on 5 October.</en>
      <fr>La position du Conseil sur le paquet de mesures législatives relatives au SIS II a été soumise au président du Parlement début octobre, pour ensuite être mise aux voix le 5 octobre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1062">en</DiscourseConnective> commission des libertés civiles, de la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1112">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires intérieures, qui a rejeté l'amendement proposé par le Conseil concernant l'accès des autorités au système.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1066" docOffset="9">It did not approve the addition proposed by the Council concerning authorities' access to the system.</ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1168" docOffset="10">
      <en>According to the Council's position, all authorities that enter data in the SIS II system should <Alignment alignment="585680" annotation_id="1265">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1265" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have access to that system. This would ensure full and indispensable cooperation between all authorities involved in the protection of the area of freedom, security and justice.</en>
      <fr>Suivant la position du Conseil, toutes les autorités qui introduisent des données dans le système SIS II devraient <Alignment alignment="1265" annotation_id="1351">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1351" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> y avoir accès, ce qui garantirait une coopération totale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1418">et</DiscourseConnective> indispensable entre toutes les autorités impliquées dans la protection de l'espace de liberté, de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1528">et</DiscourseConnective> de justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1448" docOffset="11">
      <en>The addition concerning access by authorities was proposed at a very late stage in the negotiations.</en>
      <fr>L'ajout relatif à l'accès des autorités a été proposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1597">à</DiscourseConnective> un stade très avancé des négociations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1549" docOffset="12">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1645" annotation_id="1549">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1549" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is fully understandable that the Committee on Civil Liberties felt that it could not approve the addition without an opportunity to examine the issue in more detail.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="1549" annotation_id="1645">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1645" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> parfaitement compréhensible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1682">que</DiscourseConnective> la commission des libertés civiles ait estimé ne pas être en mesure de l'approuver <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1769">avant d'</DiscourseConnective>avoir pu examiner la question plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1812">en</DiscourseConnective> détail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1729" docOffset="13">
      <en>The Presidency followed the plenary discussion on this issue on Monday with great interest.</en>
      <fr>La présidence a suivi avec beaucoup d'intérêt le débat de la plénière sur ce point lundi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1821" docOffset="14">
      <en>I hope that the European Parliament can approve the proposed text today.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1922">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen sera disposé à adopter le projet de texte aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1894" docOffset="15">
      <en>In the next few weeks the Council will discuss the outcome of the plenary vote by Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Dans les semaines à venir, le Conseil discutera des résultats du vote en séance plénière du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1988" docOffset="16">
      <en>I believe that we can reach a solution with Parliament at first reading.</en>
      <fr>Selon moi, il est possible de nous mettre d'accord avec le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2184">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2061" docOffset="17">
      <en>I want to emphasise that we are now very close to a solution for this important legislative matter.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2214">à</DiscourseConnective> souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2226">que</DiscourseConnective> nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2242">à</DiscourseConnective> deux doigts de trouver une solution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2280">à</DiscourseConnective> cette question législative capitale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
