<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statement by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclaration de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="27" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, last Thursday and Friday we had a very successful summit meeting of the Heads of State or Government of the countries of the European Union with the President of the Commission, the President of the European Parliament and our three Intergovernmental Conference representatives.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43">et</DiscourseConnective> messieurs, nous avons connu, jeudi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="81">et</DiscourseConnective> vendredi derniers, une réunion très productive des chefs d'État <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="148">et</DiscourseConnective> de gouvernement des pays de l'Union européenne avec le président de la Commission, le Président du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="269">et</DiscourseConnective> nos trois représentants de la conférence intergouvernementale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="328" docOffset="2">
      <en>Whilst I have no wish to anticipate the content of tomorrow's debate with the President-in-Office of the European Council, José Socrates, I would like to stress that, in the eyes of the European Parliament, the summit was a truly resounding success <Alignment alignment="565" annotation_id="577">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="577" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the entry into force of the Treaty, which is scheduled for the start of 2009, will give our Parliament equal rights in almost all areas of legislation.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="335">Bien que</DiscourseConnective> je ne souhaite nullement anticiper le contenu du débat de demain avec le président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="427">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil européen, José Socrates, je voudrais indiquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="496">que</DiscourseConnective>, aux yeux du Parlement européen, le sommet a été un franc succès <Alignment alignment="577" annotation_id="565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="565" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="578">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur du traité, qui est prévue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="615">pour</DiscourseConnective> le début de l'année 2009, donnera à notre Parlement les mêmes droits dans pratiquement tous les domaines de la législation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="737" docOffset="3">
      <en>We in the European Parliament have not wavered from the course we adopted for the Convention and followed in spite of the setbacks in the referendums in France and the Netherlands, <Alignment alignment="952" annotation_id="918">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="918" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="956" annotation_id="922">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="922" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this Treaty now materialises we shall have played a key part in its creation.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'avons pas, au sein du Parlement européen, dévié de la ligne que nous avons adoptée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="834">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Convention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="853">et</DiscourseConnective> nous avons poursuivi sur notre lancée malgré les revers des référendums français <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="937">et</DiscourseConnective> néerlandais <Alignment alignment="414" annotation_id="952">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="952" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="922" annotation_id="956">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="956" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce traité devient réalité, nous aurons joué un rôle majeur dans sa création.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1003" docOffset="4">
      <en>We hope that the ratification process will be successfully concluded in all 27 countries of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1050">que</DiscourseConnective> le processus de ratification se déroulera sans encombre dans les 27 pays de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1115" docOffset="5">
      <en>The signing of the Treaty will take place in Lisbon on 13 December, <Alignment alignment="1209" annotation_id="1183">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1183" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on the previous day - the twelfth of December, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1234" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> agreed with the Presidents of the European Council and the Commission - we shall proclaim the Charter of Fundamental Rights at a formal sitting here in Strasbourg.</en>
      <fr>La signature du traité aura lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1183">à</DiscourseConnective> Lisbonne le 13 décembre <Alignment alignment="1183" annotation_id="1209">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1209" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la veille (le 12 décembre, date décidée avec les présidents du Conseil européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1293">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission), nous proclamerons la Charte des droits fondamentaux lors d'une audience solennelle ici, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1403">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1401" docOffset="6">
      <en>That will be a significant event.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agira d'un événement important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1435" docOffset="7">
      <en>I would like to express my sincere gratitude for the work of our three representatives at the Intergovernmental Conference - Elmar Brok, Enrique Barón Crespo and Andrew Duff.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais exprimer toute ma gratitude à nos trois représentants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1520">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur travail lors de la conférence intergouvernementale - Elmar Brok, Enrique Barón Crespo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1616">et</DiscourseConnective> Andrew Duff.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1610" docOffset="8">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1621" docOffset="9">
      <en>I am pleased to see that Enrique Barón Crespo is with us, <Alignment alignment="1702" annotation_id="1679">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1679" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I cannot see the other representatives.</en>
      <fr>Je suis heureux de voir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1675">qu'</DiscourseConnective>Enrique est parmi nous, <Alignment alignment="1016" annotation_id="1702">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1702" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je ne vois pas les autres représentants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1723" docOffset="10">
      <en>In that case we shall defer the approval of the Minutes.</en>
      <fr>Nous allons donc différer l'approbation du procès-verbal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1780" id="007" name="Daniel Cohn-Bendit">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1780" docOffset="11">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, I have a question for Mr Pöttering: will you still have the right to vote in this Parliament?</en>
      <fr>(DE) M. le président, j'ai une question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1846">pour</DiscourseConnective> M. Pöttering: aurez-vous toujours le droit de vote au sein de ce parlement?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1893" id="008" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1893" docOffset="12">
      <en>I am well aware that Mr Cohn-Bendit's thirst for knowledge knows no bounds.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Je suis conscient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1950">du fait que</DiscourseConnective> la soif de connaissances de M. Cohn-Bendit est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2009">sans</DiscourseConnective> limite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1969" docOffset="13">
      <en>Let me say to you that there was not one second in the entire process <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2039" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> this was in any doubt.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2044">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>au cours de ce processus, le point que vous abordez n'a jamais été mis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2123">en</DiscourseConnective> doute.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2067" docOffset="14">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2133" annotation_id="2067">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2067" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Nor</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> was the matter raised at all during the open session at the summit meeting.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2067" annotation_id="2133">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2133" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De la même manière</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, cette question n'a pas été abordée au cours de la session ouverte de la réunion du sommet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2147" docOffset="15">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2244" annotation_id="2147">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2147" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this rumour was being spread in other circles.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2147" annotation_id="2244">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2244" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette rumeur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2262">s'</DiscourseConnective>est répandue dans d'autres cercles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2198" docOffset="16">
      <en>Wherever I could, I acted immediately to quash it.</en>
      <fr>J'ai tenté d'y mettre fin chaque fois que j'en ai eu l'occasion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2249" docOffset="17">
      <en>There can never be a situation where the European Council or any other body could withdraw the voting rights of the President of the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2385">ou</DiscourseConnective> tout autre organe ne peut en aucun cas priver le Président du Parlement européen du droit de vote.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2403" docOffset="18">
      <en>This is not about me personally but about the office of the President of Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2493">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit pas d'une remise en cause de ma personne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2542">mais</DiscourseConnective> de la fonction de Président du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2488" docOffset="19">
      <en>I would vigorously oppose any such move, <Alignment alignment="2616" annotation_id="2529">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2529" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the House is united on that stance.</en>
      <fr>Je m'y opposerai fermement <Alignment alignment="2529" annotation_id="2616">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2616" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette assemblée est unanime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2647">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2569" docOffset="20">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2580" id="009" name="Hannes Swoboda">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2580" docOffset="21">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, I just wanted to say, on behalf of my group, that we fully endorse your position.</en>
      <fr>(DE) M. le président, je souhaite juste indiquer, au nom de mon groupe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2750">que</DiscourseConnective> nous soutenons pleinement votre position.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2681" docOffset="22">
      <en>It goes without saying that every Member of Parliament elected by the people has full voting rights, including the President.</en>
      <fr>Il va <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2802">sans</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2807">dire que</DiscourseConnective> chaque membre du Parlement élu par le peuple bénéficie du droit de vote, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2889">notamment</DiscourseConnective> le Président.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2807" docOffset="23">
      <en>We entirely agree with that.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes entièrement d'accord sur ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2836" id="010" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2836" docOffset="24">
      <en>Excellent!</en>
      <fr>(DE) Excellent!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2847" docOffset="25">
      <en>I am deeply grateful that we are in complete agreement on that point too.</en>
      <fr>Je suis moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2988">aussi</DiscourseConnective> très heureux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3007">que</DiscourseConnective> nous nous accordions sur ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
