<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Formal sitting - Georgia</en>
    <fr>Séance solennelle - Géorgie</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="25" id="109" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="25" docOffset="1">
      <en>Mr President of the Republic of Georgia, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to welcome you most warmly on behalf of the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président de la République de Géorgie, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="88">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, au nom du Parlement européen, je vous souhaite la bienvenue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="166" docOffset="2">
      <en>Three years ago, following parliamentary elections annulled by the regime of the time, the Rose Revolution took place in your country <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="300" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> history will associate your name with that revolution, Mr Saakashvili.</en>
      <fr>Il y a trois ans, à la suite d'élections parlementaires annulées par le régime de l'époque, éclatait dans votre pays la Révolution des roses, à laquelle l'histoire a depuis associé votre nom, Monsieur Saakachvili.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="375" docOffset="3">
      <en>Led by yourself, your compatriots demanded fair elections and an end to the corruption and bad governance that was ruining your country.</en>
      <fr>Encouragés par votre exemple, vos compatriotes ont exigé des élections équitables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="459">et</DiscourseConnective> la fin de la corruption <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="486">et</DiscourseConnective> de la mauvaise gouvernance qui ruinaient votre pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="512" docOffset="4">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="523" docOffset="5">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="561" annotation_id="523">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="523" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the previous regime refused to accept your demands, it was brought down without a single drop of blood being shed.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="523" annotation_id="561">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="561" sense="Comparison.Concession">Bien qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ayant refusé de se plier à vos exigences, le régime précédent a été renversé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="646">sans que</DiscourseConnective> la moindre goutte de sang n'ait été versée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="647" docOffset="6">
      <en>'People power' prevailed <Alignment alignment="739" annotation_id="672">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="672" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Georgian people were able to elect you en masse as the new President.</en>
      <fr>Le "pouvoir du peuple" a pris le dessus <Alignment alignment="672" annotation_id="739">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="739" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les Géorgiens ont pu vous élire en masse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="783">comme</DiscourseConnective> nouveau président.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="750" docOffset="7">
      <en>Mr President, the European Parliament has supported democratic change in your country.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, le Parlement européen a soutenu le processus démocratique dans votre pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="837" docOffset="8">
      <en>We sent a mission of observers to the elections <Alignment alignment="965" annotation_id="885">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="885" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our Committee on Foreign Affairs had the pleasure of receiving you soon after your inauguration as President, not here in Strasbourg but at our site in Brussels.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons envoyé une mission d'observateurs aux élections <Alignment alignment="885" annotation_id="965">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="965" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> notre commission des affaires étrangères a eu l'honneur de vous recevoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1041">peu après</DiscourseConnective> votre investiture, non pas ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1082">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1096">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1101">à</DiscourseConnective> notre siège situé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1121">à</DiscourseConnective> Bruxelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1051" docOffset="9">
      <en>The Rose Revolution reawakened hopes for real and free democracy in areas even further east of the Baltic, of Central and of Eastern Europe.</en>
      <fr>La Révolution des roses a ravivé l'espoir d'une démocratie libre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1199">et</DiscourseConnective> authentique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1214">également</DiscourseConnective> dans des régions baltes plus à l'est, dans des régions d'Europe centrale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1297">et</DiscourseConnective> orientale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1192" docOffset="10">
      <en>A year later, the Orange Revolution took place in Ukraine.</en>
      <fr>Un an <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1317">plus tard</DiscourseConnective> se produisait la Révolution orange <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1362">en</DiscourseConnective> Ukraine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1251" docOffset="11">
      <en>At that time the future seemed full of promise, <Alignment alignment="1413" annotation_id="1299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1299" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are now seeing that many problems and obstacles have arisen on a journey that is certainly no easy ride.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1374">À</DiscourseConnective> l'époque, l'avenir semblait radieux, <Alignment alignment="1299" annotation_id="1413">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1413" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous assistons aujourd'hui à l'apparition de nombreux problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1482">et</DiscourseConnective> obstacles sur un chemin qui n'est certainement pas de tout repos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1411" docOffset="12">
      <en>You have achieved a great deal over the years that have passed since then, <Alignment alignment="1596" annotation_id="1486">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1486" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the conflicts in the break-away regions of South Ossetia and Abkhazia have become worse.</en>
      <fr>Vous avez considérablement progressé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1588">depuis</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="1486" annotation_id="1596">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1596" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les conflits qui sévissent dans les régions séparatistes de l'Ossétie du Sud <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1678">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'Abkhazie se sont aggravés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1579" docOffset="13">
      <en>It is clear that Russia is now putting great pressure on your country - I can tell you that your country was discussed at great length at the dinner with President Putin - <Alignment alignment="1913" annotation_id="1751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1751" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you now have a great opportunity, on addressing the European Parliament, to explain the situation <Alignment alignment="2012" annotation_id="1853">
          <Alignment alignment="2012" annotation_id="1853">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1853" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the representatives of the peoples of Europe can hear directly from you about the difficult circumstances being experienced by your country and the problems relating to energy dependency on your great neighbour.</en>
      <fr>Il est évident <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1728">que</DiscourseConnective> la Russie exerce à présent des pressions intenses sur votre pays - je peux vous assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1820">que</DiscourseConnective> la Géorgie a fait l'objet de longs débats au cours du dîner avec le président Poutine -, <Alignment alignment="1751" annotation_id="1913">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1913" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous disposez aujourd'hui d'une excellente occasion d'expliquer votre situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1996">à</DiscourseConnective> ce Parlement, <Alignment alignment="1853" annotation_id="2012">
          <Alignment alignment="1853" annotation_id="2012">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2012" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> les représentants des peuples d'Europe puissent entendre de votre bouche même les conditions difficiles auxquelles votre pays doit faire face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2163">et</DiscourseConnective> les problèmes de dépendance énergétique à l'égard de votre puissant voisin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2073" docOffset="14">
      <en>The European Parliament and the European Union as a whole fully support the sovereignty and territorial integrity of your country; there is absolutely no doubt about that.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2264">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne dans son ensemble soutiennent pleinement la souveraineté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2343">et</DiscourseConnective> l'intégrité territoriale de votre nation. Soyez-en assurés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2245" docOffset="15">
      <en>We have <Alignment alignment="2417" annotation_id="2253">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2253" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> said that the conflicts in South Ossetia and Abkhazia must be resolved at the negotiating table, and by exclusively peaceful means.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="2253" annotation_id="2417">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2417" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2431">que</DiscourseConnective> les conflits d'Ossétie du Sud <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2465">et</DiscourseConnective> d'Abkhazie doivent être résolus par le biais de négociations, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2530">et</DiscourseConnective> exclusivement par des moyens pacifiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2390" docOffset="16">
      <en>There can be no military solution to that problem either.</en>
      <fr>Une solution militaire ne convient pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2613">non plus</DiscourseConnective> dans ce cas-là.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2448" docOffset="17">
      <en>In a resolution that we approved last month here in Strasbourg, we called upon Russia to put an end to all acts of repression and harassment against people of Georgian origin living in Russia and to revoke any measures recently taken against your country, including the suspension of all transport links and postal services.</en>
      <fr>Dans une résolution adoptée le mois dernier ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2686">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg, nous avons incité la Russie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2728">à</DiscourseConnective> mettre un terme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2746">à</DiscourseConnective> tout acte de répression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2772">et</DiscourseConnective> de harcèlement vis-à-vis des personnes d'origine géorgienne habitant sur son territoire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2863">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2866">à</DiscourseConnective> abroger toute mesure adoptée récemment contre votre pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2926">notamment</DiscourseConnective> la suspension de l'intégralité des liaisons de transport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2993">et</DiscourseConnective> des services postaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2773" docOffset="18">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3018" annotation_id="2773">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2773" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we would <Alignment alignment="3048" annotation_id="2796">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2796" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> call for restraint in any verbal comments from all sides that may raise the tension unnecessarily.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2773" annotation_id="3018">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3018" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous souhaiterions <Alignment alignment="2796" annotation_id="3048">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3048" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> encourager chacune des parties à s'abstenir de tout commentaire verbal susceptible d'exacerber inutilement les tensions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2900" docOffset="19">
      <en>We believe that the Council and the Commission must find a way to help your country to overcome and compensate for the economic and social effects of the Russian measures against you.</en>
      <fr>Nous estimons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3193">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3208">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission devraient trouver un moyen d'aider votre pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3271">à</DiscourseConnective> surmonter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3283">et</DiscourseConnective> compenser les répercussions économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3326">et</DiscourseConnective> sociales des mesures russes prises à votre encontre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3084" docOffset="20">
      <en>Mr President, we would like to express the European Parliament's support for the approval of the Action Plan on the European Neighbourhood Policy by the EU-Georgia Cooperation Council, which has taken place today in Brussels.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, permettez-nous d'exprimer le soutien du Parlement européen en faveur de l'adoption du plan d'action relatif à la politique européenne de voisinage par le Conseil de coopération UE-Géorgie qui s'est tenu aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3620">à</DiscourseConnective> Bruxelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3310" docOffset="21">
      <en>We welcome you once again <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3336" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I hope that your presence here will give us the opportunity, through dialogue, to overcome the problems faced by your country <Alignment alignment="3818" annotation_id="3466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3466" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which affect all of us.</en>
      <fr>Nous vous souhaitons encore une fois la bienvenue. J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3693">que</DiscourseConnective> votre présence en ce lieu nous offrira la possibilité, via le dialogue, d'éliminer les problèmes qui touchent votre pays <Alignment alignment="3466" annotation_id="3818">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3818" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> affectent chacun d'entre nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3494" docOffset="22">
      <en>You have the floor, Mr President.</en>
      <fr>Vous avez la parole, Monsieur le Président.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3528" docOffset="23">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3539" id="114" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3539" docOffset="24">
      <en>(in Georgian) Thank you very much for your words, Mr President.</en>
      <fr>(<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3916">en</DiscourseConnective> géorgien) Je vous remercie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3946">pour</DiscourseConnective> votre discours, Monsieur le Président.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3603" docOffset="25">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3614" docOffset="26">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4009" annotation_id="3614">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3614" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you can see, my Georgian is far worse than your Spanish.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3614" annotation_id="4009">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4009" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous pouvez voir, mon géorgien est bien pire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4060">que</DiscourseConnective> votre espagnol.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3674" docOffset="27">
      <en>It is, in any case, a way of showing you how warmly you are received by the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Mais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4085">en tout cas</DiscourseConnective>, c'est une façon de vous exprimer l'affection avec laquelle le Parlement européen vous a reçu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3771" docOffset="28">
      <en>The European Parliament is a friend of Georgia. It demonstrated that in its recent resolution calling for an end to attacks against Georgian citizens.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen s'est lié d'amitié avec la Géorgie, ce qu'il a démontré dans sa dernière résolution appelant à la fin des agressions contre les citoyens géorgiens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3922" docOffset="29">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4362" annotation_id="3922">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3922" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it hopes that your presence and your words in the European Parliament will contribute to improving the situation in terms of relations between your country and Russia.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3922" annotation_id="4362">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4362" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4382">que</DiscourseConnective> votre présence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4401">et</DiscourseConnective> vos paroles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4416">en</DiscourseConnective> cette Assemblée contribueront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4449">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4474">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les relations entre votre pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4524">et</DiscourseConnective> la Russie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4103" docOffset="30">
      <en>You can count on us, Mr President.</en>
      <fr>Vous pouvez compter sur nous, Monsieur le Président.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4138" docOffset="31">
      <en>Didi madloba.</en>
      <fr>Didi madloba.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
