<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statement by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclaration de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="27" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I have been asked to make the following statement.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, il m'a été demandé de faire la déclaration suivante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="100" docOffset="2">
      <en>This week marks the 60th anniversary of the deportation of hundreds of thousands of citizens from the Baltic states.</en>
      <fr>Cette semaine marque le soixantième anniversaire de la déportation de centaines de milliers de citoyens des États baltes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="217" docOffset="3">
      <en>On the night of 24 March 1949, a wave of Soviet deportations began, during which tens of thousands of Estonians, Latvians and Lithuanians were forcibly expelled from their homelands.</en>
      <fr>La nuit du 24 mars 1949, une vague de déportations soviétiques a commencé, au cours de laquelle des dizaines de milliers d'Estoniens, de Lettons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="372">et</DiscourseConnective> de Lituaniens ont été expulsés de force de leur patrie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="400" docOffset="4">
      <en>They were robbed of their civil and human rights, and perished as a result of the hard, inhuman conditions they faced in the Soviet prison camps.</en>
      <fr>Ils ont été déchus de leurs droits civiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="475">et</DiscourseConnective> humains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="486">et</DiscourseConnective> ont péri <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="498">à</DiscourseConnective> cause des conditions de détention pénibles et inhumaines dans les camps pénitentiaires soviétiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="546" docOffset="5">
      <en>Almost every family in Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia, as well as in other former Soviet republics, suffered as a result of the horrific violence perpetrated by the totalitarian, Communist regime.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="600">En</DiscourseConnective> Lettonie, en Lituanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="625">et</DiscourseConnective> en Estonie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="640">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="646">que</DiscourseConnective> dans d'autres républiques de l'ex-Union soviétique, pratiquement chaque famille a souffert des violences atroces commises par le régime communiste totalitaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="742" docOffset="6">
      <en>Almost every family had relatives who went missing in Siberia, persecuted by the KGB <Alignment alignment="909" annotation_id="827">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="827" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> who were incarcerated and oppressed.</en>
      <fr>Presque chaque famille a des membres qui ont disparu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="863">en</DiscourseConnective> Sibérie, qui ont été persécutés par le KGB <Alignment alignment="827" annotation_id="909">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="909" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui ont été incarcérés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="935">et</DiscourseConnective> opprimés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="867" docOffset="7">
      <en>The events we are talking about did not take place in some dark, distant past.</en>
      <fr>Les événements dont nous parlons ne remontent pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="998">à</DiscourseConnective> un passé sombre et lointain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="946" docOffset="8">
      <en>They remain vivid memories for many people who, today, are EU citizens.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1029">Pour</DiscourseConnective> de nombreuses personnes, aujourd'hui citoyens de l'Union européenne, ces événements demeurent un souvenir très vif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1018" docOffset="9">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1157" annotation_id="1018">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1018" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is our duty, on the basis of our common values, and in order to commemorate the many victims of these deportations, to clearly and decisively condemn these abhorrent crimes perpetrated by the totalitarian, Communist regime in the Soviet Union.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="1018" annotation_id="1157">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1157" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de notre devoir, sur le fondement de nos valeurs communes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1220">et</DiscourseConnective> aux fins de commémoration des multiples victimes de ces déportations, de condamner clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1317">et</DiscourseConnective> fermement ces crimes épouvantables perpétrés par le régime communiste totalitaire de l'Union soviétique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1271" docOffset="10">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1271" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">For</DiscourseConnective> we owe it to the victims to assess the past in an objective, in-depth and careful manner, <Alignment alignment="1500" annotation_id="1365">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1365" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> reconciliation can only ever be based on truth and remembrance.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1437">à</DiscourseConnective> ces victimes une évaluation objective <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1477">et</DiscourseConnective> minutieuse du passé <Alignment alignment="1322" annotation_id="1500">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1500" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la vérité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1514">et</DiscourseConnective> la commémoration sont les fondements indispensables de toute réconciliation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
