<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Review of recommendation 2001/331/EC providing for minimum criteria for environmental inspection in the Member States (debate)</en>
    <fr>Réexamen de la recommandation 2001/331/CE prévoyant des critères minimaux applicables aux inspections environnementales dans les États membres (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="127" id="075" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="127" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the Oral Question - B6-0479/2008) by Mr Ouzký to the Commission, on behalf of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, on the review of Recommendation 2001/331/EC providing for minimum criteria for environmental inspections in the Member States.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle la question orale - B6-0479/2008) de M. Ouzký, au nom de la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="287">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="318">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur le réexamen de la recommandation 2001/331/CE prévoyant des critères minimaux applicables aux inspections environnementales dans les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="414" id="076" name="Miroslav Ouzký">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="414" docOffset="2">
      <en>author. - Madam President, it is difficult to stand up now after that particularly lively debate and switch to another topic!</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, il est difficile d'intervenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="552">après</DiscourseConnective> ce débat particulièrement animé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="590">et</DiscourseConnective> de passer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="603">à</DiscourseConnective> un autre thème!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="540" docOffset="3">
      <en>I would like to stress that the good and consistent enforcement of environmental legislation is essential for its credibility, for a level playing field and for ensuring that the environmental objectives will be met.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais souligner le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="651">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une bonne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="664">et</DiscourseConnective> cohérente application de la législation environnementale est essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="740">pour</DiscourseConnective> sa crédibilité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="761">pour</DiscourseConnective> garantir des conditions égales pour tous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="807">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="810">pour</DiscourseConnective> s'assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="825">que</DiscourseConnective> les objectifs environnementaux seront atteints.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="757" docOffset="4">
      <en>The issue of environmental inspections is, <Alignment alignment="16376" annotation_id="800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="800" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, very important for the work of my committee, the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="800" annotation_id="877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="877" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la question des inspections environnementales est très importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="958">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail de ma commission, la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1047">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="921" docOffset="5">
      <en>On 14 November the Commission published the communication on environmental inspections in the Member States.</en>
      <fr>La Commission a publié le 14 novembre 2007 la communication sur les inspections environnementales dans les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1030" docOffset="6">
      <en>This communication reviewed Recommendation 2001/331/EC of the European Commission, providing minimum criteria for environmental inspections.</en>
      <fr>Cette communication concernait le réexamen de la recommandation 2001/331/CE de la Commission européenne prévoyant des critères minimaux applicables aux inspections environnementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1171" docOffset="7">
      <en>The communication contains some worrying messages.</en>
      <fr>La communication renferme quelques enseignements inquiétants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1222" docOffset="8">
      <en>It states that the information submitted by the Member States on the implementation of the recommendation is incomplete or difficult to compare.</en>
      <fr>Elle affirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1458">que</DiscourseConnective> les informations présentées par les États membres sur la mise en œuvre de la recommandation sont incomplètes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1571">ou</DiscourseConnective> difficilement comparables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1367" docOffset="9">
      <en>It states that there are still large differences in the way environmental inspections are being carried out in the EU.</en>
      <fr>Elle affirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1614">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il subsiste toujours d'importantes disparités dans la façon dont les inspections environnementales sont réalisées au sein de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1486" docOffset="10">
      <en>It states that the scope of the recommendation is inadequate <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1547" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that it does not include many important activities such as Natura 2000 and the control of illegal waste shipping.</en>
      <fr>Elle affirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1761">que</DiscourseConnective> le champ d'application de la recommandation est inadéquat, plusieurs activités importantes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1857">comme</DiscourseConnective> Natura 2000 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1875">et</DiscourseConnective> le contrôle des transferts illégaux de déchets, en étant exclues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1665" docOffset="11">
      <en>It states that inspection plans have not been implemented <Alignment alignment="4356" annotation_id="1723">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1723" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> where they do exist that they are often not publicly available.</en>
      <fr>Elle affirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1957">que</DiscourseConnective> les plans d'inspection n'ont pas été mis en œuvre <Alignment alignment="1723" annotation_id="2011">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2011" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2019">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>ils existent, ils ne sont que très peu mis à la disposition du public.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1791" docOffset="12">
      <en>My committee noted with concern the conclusions from the Commission stating that the full implementation of the environmental legislation in the Community cannot be ensured.</en>
      <fr>Ma commission a pris note avec inquiétude des conclusions de la Commission selon lesquelles la mise en œuvre intégrale de la législation environnementale dans la Communauté ne peut être garantie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1965" docOffset="13">
      <en>This would not only lead to continuing damage to the environment, but also to the distortion of competition within and between the Member States.</en>
      <fr>Une telle situation risque d'occasionner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2334">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> la poursuite de la destruction de l'environnement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2399">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> une distorsion de concurrence au sein des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2466">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'entre eux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2111" docOffset="14">
      <en>My committee <Alignment alignment="2486" annotation_id="2124">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2124" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> formulated four questions to the Commission, which can be summarised <Alignment alignment="2585" annotation_id="2203">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2203" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> follows.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2124" annotation_id="2486">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2486" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ma commission a formulé quatre questions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2542">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission, qui peuvent être résumées <Alignment alignment="2203" annotation_id="2585">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2585" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> suit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2215" docOffset="15">
      <en>First, why does the Commission only wish to amend the recommendation - why does it not propose a directive on environmental inspections?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2597">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, pourquoi la Commission souhaite-t-elle uniquement modifier la recommandation? Pourquoi ne propose-t-elle pas une directive sur les inspections environnementales?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2352" docOffset="16">
      <en>Second, why has the Commission opted instead for attaching environmental inspection requirements to existing directives individually, a process that will take a lot of time?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2773">Deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, pourquoi la Commission a-t-elle préféré lier les exigences en matière d'inspections environnementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2889">à</DiscourseConnective> chaque directive existante, processus qui prendra beaucoup de temps?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2526" docOffset="17">
      <en>Third, why is the Commission not prepared to use a directive to define terms such as 'inspection' and 'audit', which are interpreted in different ways by Member States?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2960">Troisièmement</DiscourseConnective>, pourquoi la Commission n'est-elle pas disposée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3022">à</DiscourseConnective> recourir à une directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3049">pour</DiscourseConnective> définir des termes tels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3078">que</DiscourseConnective> "inspection" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3095">et</DiscourseConnective> "audit", qui sont interprétés de différentes façons par les États membres?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2695" docOffset="18">
      <en>Fourth, why is the Commission not prepared to transform IMPEL into an effective EU environmental inspection force?</en>
      <fr>Quatrièmement, pourquoi la Commission n'est-elle pas disposée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3235">à</DiscourseConnective> faire de l'IMPEL un instrument européen efficace d'inspection environnementale?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2810" docOffset="19">
      <en>I would like to thank the Commission in advance for its reply <Alignment alignment="10042" annotation_id="2872">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2872" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would like to conclude by emphasising that, in my opinion, the implementation and enforcement of environmental legislation should get the same political attention as the adoption of the legislation in the Commission, in the Council and in Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Je remercie d'ores et déjà la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3358">pour</DiscourseConnective> sa réponse <Alignment alignment="2872" annotation_id="3374">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3374" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je voudrais conclure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3398">en</DiscourseConnective> insistant sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3423">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à mon sens, la mise en œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3455">et</DiscourseConnective> l'application de la législation environnementale devraient bénéficier de la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3534">même</DiscourseConnective> attention politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3559">que</DiscourseConnective> l'adoption de la législation au sein de la Commission, du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3629">et</DiscourseConnective> du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3129" id="077" name="Siim Kallas">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3129" docOffset="20">
      <en>Vice-President of the Commission. - Madam President, I am very happy to be presenting my green credentials in addition to my anti-fraud credentials, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3278" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective> changing topics is <Alignment alignment="6395" annotation_id="3300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3300" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a pleasure.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, je suis ravi de présenter ma légitimation verte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3756">en</DiscourseConnective> complément de ma légitimation antifraude; c'est <Alignment alignment="3300" annotation_id="3807">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3807" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avec plaisir que je change de thème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3317" docOffset="21">
      <en>I would like to thank the European Parliament for this discussion on the very important topic of environmental inspections.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3858">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3892">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette discussion relative au thème très important des inspections environnementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3441" docOffset="22">
      <en>Recognising the need for EU-wide action, Parliament and the Council adopted the recommendation on environmental inspections in 2001.</en>
      <fr>Reconnaissant la nécessité de mener une action à l'échelle de l'UE, le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4063">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil ont adopté la recommandation sur les inspections environnementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4144">en</DiscourseConnective> 2001.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3574" docOffset="23">
      <en>The objective was to lay down common criteria for environmental inspections in order to ensure a better and more consistent implementation of environmental legislation through the Community.</en>
      <fr>L'objectif consistait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4175">à</DiscourseConnective> définir des critères communs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4206">pour</DiscourseConnective> les inspections environnementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4245">dans le but de</DiscourseConnective> garantir une meilleure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4283">et</DiscourseConnective> plus cohérente mise en œuvre de la législation environnementale dans l'ensemble de la Communauté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3765" docOffset="24">
      <en>At the time there was a long discussion on whether these criteria should be binding or non-binding.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4384">À</DiscourseConnective> l'époque, il y a eu de longues discussions sur la question de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4455">si</DiscourseConnective> ces critères devaient être contraignants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4499">ou</DiscourseConnective> non.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3865" docOffset="25">
      <en>As a compromise, a non-binding recommendation was adopted.</en>
      <fr>En guise de compromis, une recommandation non contraignante a été adoptée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3924" docOffset="26">
      <en>Member States pledged to implement it fully <Alignment alignment="4647" annotation_id="3968">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3968" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commission was asked to review this decision on the basis of the experience with the implementation of the recommendation by the Member States.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres ont promis de la mettre en œuvre intégralement <Alignment alignment="3968" annotation_id="4647">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4647" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission a été invitée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4678">à</DiscourseConnective> réexaminer cette décision sur la base de l'expérience acquise par la mise en œuvre de la recommandation par les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4120" docOffset="27">
      <en>The Commission launched the review process with its communication of November 2007.</en>
      <fr>La Commission a lancé le processus de révision avec sa communication de novembre 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4204" docOffset="28">
      <en>In this communication the Commission concluded that, <Alignment alignment="6404" annotation_id="4257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4257" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the recommendation has led to improvements in environmental inspections in some Member States, it has unfortunately not been fully implemented in all Member States.</en>
      <fr>Dans cette communication, la Commission a conclu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4943">que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="4257" annotation_id="4948">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4948" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la recommandation ait entraîné des améliorations des inspections environnementales dans certains États membres, elle n'a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5078">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> pas été intégralement mise en œuvre dans l'ensemble de ces derniers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4431" docOffset="29">
      <en>The Commission <Alignment alignment="5179" annotation_id="4446">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4446" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> put forward its preliminary views on how the situation could be improved.</en>
      <fr>La Commission a <Alignment alignment="4446" annotation_id="5179">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5179" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> présenté ses points de vue préliminaires sur la manière dont la situation pourrait être améliorée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4525" docOffset="30">
      <en>The measures that we deem necessary are: firstly, a modification of the recommendation to make it stronger and clearer, including a better reporting mechanism; secondly, where necessary, to complement the recommendation with legally binding inspection requirements in individual directives; and thirdly, to continue supporting the exchange of information and best practice between inspectorates in the context of IMPEL.</en>
      <fr>Les mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5295">que</DiscourseConnective> nous jugeons nécessaires sont les suivantes: primo, une modification de la recommandation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5389">afin de</DiscourseConnective> la rendre plus forte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5418">et</DiscourseConnective> plus claire, y compris l'amélioration du mécanisme de notification; secundo, ajouter, le cas échéant, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5523">à</DiscourseConnective> la recommandation des exigences juridiquement contraignantes en matière d'inspection dans les différentes directives; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5643">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5646">troisièmement</DiscourseConnective>, continuer à soutenir l'échange d'informations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5707">et</DiscourseConnective> des meilleures pratiques entre les services d'inspection dans le cadre de l'IMPEL.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4945" docOffset="31">
      <en>The Commission is now gathering the input of the other institutions and of stakeholders on these initial proposals and will <Alignment alignment="34269" annotation_id="5069">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5069" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> present its final proposals.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est actuellement en train de rassembler les suggestions des autres institutions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5887">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que celles des parties concernées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5927">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de ces propositions initiales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5967">et</DiscourseConnective> elle présentera <Alignment alignment="5069" annotation_id="5986">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5986" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ses propositions définitives.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5103" docOffset="32">
      <en>Now, coming to the questions raised, I would like to make the following remarks.</en>
      <fr>J'en viens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6035">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> aux questions soulevées et je voudrais faire remarquer ce qui suit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5184" docOffset="33">
      <en>Firstly, I would like to clarify that the views presented in the Commission's communication of November 2007 do not exclude the possibility of the Commission presenting a proposal for a directive on environmental inspections in the future.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6114">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais préciser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6149">que</DiscourseConnective> les points de vue présentés dans la communication de la Commission de novembre 2007 n'excluent pas la possibilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6267">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission présente une proposition de directive sur les inspections environnementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6361">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5424" docOffset="34">
      <en>The Commission's view, <Alignment alignment="35469" annotation_id="5447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5447" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> expressed in its communication, is that there is a need for EU-wide legally binding rules to ensure effective environmental inspections.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5447" annotation_id="6373">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6373" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il ressort de sa communication, la Commission estime nécessaire d'établir des règles juridiquement contraignantes dans l'ensemble de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6517">dans le but de</DiscourseConnective> garantir des inspections environnementales efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5587" docOffset="35">
      <en>In that respect we have the same position as Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6598">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, un avis identique à celui du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5644" docOffset="36">
      <en>The question is, <Alignment alignment="2710" annotation_id="5661">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5661" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, whether such rules should be horizontal and cover all environmental inspections <Alignment alignment="5017" annotation_id="5750">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5750" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whether they should be sectoral and apply to specific installations or activities.</en>
      <fr>La question est <Alignment alignment="5661" annotation_id="6667">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6667" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6687">si</DiscourseConnective> de telles règles doivent être horizontales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6733">et</DiscourseConnective> couvrir l'ensemble des inspections environnementales, <Alignment alignment="5750" annotation_id="6790">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6790" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6793">si</DiscourseConnective> elles devraient être sectorielles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6830">et</DiscourseConnective> s'appliquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6845">à</DiscourseConnective> des installations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6865">ou</DiscourseConnective> activités spécifiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5836" docOffset="37">
      <en>Both of these approaches have their advantages and disadvantages.</en>
      <fr>Les deux méthodes présentent des avantages <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6934">et</DiscourseConnective> des inconvénients.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5902" docOffset="38">
      <en>A horizontal approach would be simpler and quicker to put in place.</en>
      <fr>Un système horizontal serait plus simple <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6997">et</DiscourseConnective> plus rapide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7012">à</DiscourseConnective> instaurer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5970" docOffset="39">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7025" annotation_id="5970">
          <Alignment alignment="10027" annotation_id="5970">
            <Alignment alignment="7025" annotation_id="5970">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5970" sense="Comparison.Contrast">On the other hand</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the sectoral approach would enable us to better address the specific aspects of the different installations or activities.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="16992" annotation_id="7025">
          <Alignment alignment="5970" annotation_id="7025">
            <Alignment alignment="5970" annotation_id="7025">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7025" sense="Comparison.Contrast">D'autre part</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, la méthode sectorielle nous permettrait de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7082">mieux</DiscourseConnective> aborder les aspects spécifiques des différentes installations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7150">ou</DiscourseConnective> activités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6112" docOffset="40">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8995" annotation_id="6112">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6112" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">For instance</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the requirements for inspections of waste shipments are completely different from those for the inspection of industrial installations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6112" annotation_id="7164">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7164" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">Par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, les exigences en matière d'inspection des transferts de déchets sont tout à fait différentes de celles qui régissent l'inspection des installations industrielles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6262" docOffset="41">
      <en>By being more targeted we could set more effective requirements.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7340">En</DiscourseConnective> ciblant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7351">mieux</DiscourseConnective> les choses, nous pourrions définir des exigences plus efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6327" docOffset="42">
      <en>To some extent, the sectoral approach is the one that we have already been practising for several years.</en>
      <fr>La méthode sectorielle est, dans une certaine mesure, celle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7482">que</DiscourseConnective> nous utilisons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7501">déjà</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7506">depuis</DiscourseConnective> plusieurs années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6432" docOffset="43">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7539" annotation_id="6432">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6432" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">For example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in the Seveso II Directive, we have provisions on inspections of installations in order to prevent accidents.</en>
      <fr>Il y a, <Alignment alignment="6432" annotation_id="7539">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7539" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans la directive Seveso II, des dispositions concernant les inspections d'installations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7641">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> prévenir les accidents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6555" docOffset="44">
      <en>These provisions have proven to be very successful.</en>
      <fr>Ces dispositions se sont avérées très utiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6607" docOffset="45">
      <en>We have now included inspection requirements in our proposal to revise the IPPC Directive.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons désormais inclus des exigences en matière d'inspection dans notre proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7810">en</DiscourseConnective> vue du réexamen de la directive IPPC.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6698" docOffset="46">
      <en>Another sector where we see the need for further action is the implementation of the EU Waste Shipment Regulation.</en>
      <fr>La mise en œuvre du règlement de l'UE sur les transferts de déchets est un autre secteur qui, selon nous, doit faire l'objet de nouvelles mesures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6813" docOffset="47">
      <en>The growing problem of illegal waste shipments is a risk for human health and the environment.</en>
      <fr>Le problème croissant des transferts illégaux de déchets constitue un risque <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8075">pour</DiscourseConnective> la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8098">et</DiscourseConnective> l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6908" docOffset="48">
      <en>There is clear evidence of illegal shipments recorded during joint EU waste shipment inspections coordinated by IMPEL.</en>
      <fr>Nous disposons de preuves tangibles de transferts illégaux grâce à des inspections communes de l'UE sur le transfert de déchets coordonnées par l'IMPEL.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7027" docOffset="49">
      <en>Recent trade data and studies on the export of certain waste streams, in particular electrical and electronic waste and end-of-life vehicles, indicate that significant volumes leave the EU.</en>
      <fr>De récentes études <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8290">et</DiscourseConnective> données commerciales sur les exportations de certains flux de déchets, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8364">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> les déchets électroniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8405">et</DiscourseConnective> électriques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8420">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les véhicules en fin de vie, montrent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8468">que</DiscourseConnective> des volumes importants quittent l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7217" docOffset="50">
      <en>In many cases these shipments seem to violate the EU Waste Shipment Regulation's export bans.</en>
      <fr>Dans de nombreux cas, ces transferts semblent enfreindre les interdictions d'exportation visées par le règlement de l'UE sur les transferts de déchets.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7311" docOffset="51">
      <en>Serious incidents of EU exports for dumping of waste in developing countries, such as the Côte d'Ivoire incident in 2006, as well as a recent Greenpeace report about waste illegally shipped to West Africa, underline the severity of the problem.</en>
      <fr>De graves incidents portant sur des exportations de déchets de l'UE vers des pays en développement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8762">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'incident en Côte d'Ivoire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8796">en</DiscourseConnective> 2006, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8805">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'un récent rapport de Greenpeace concernant le transfert illégal de déchets vers l'Afrique occidentale, soulignent la gravité du problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7556" docOffset="52">
      <en>The Commission is currently examining the need for additional initiatives, including improved legislative requirements, in order to further and strengthen the inspections and controls of waste shipments.</en>
      <fr>La Commission se penche actuellement sur la nécessité de prendre des initiatives supplémentaires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9050">notamment</DiscourseConnective> une amélioration des exigences législatives, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9105">en vue d'</DiscourseConnective>améliorer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9124">et</DiscourseConnective> de renforcer les inspections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9156">et</DiscourseConnective> les contrôles des transferts de déchets.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7760" docOffset="53">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23251" annotation_id="7760">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7760" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we stated in our communication, we <Alignment alignment="9268" annotation_id="7798">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7798" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> see a need to establish common definitions for terms that are relevant for inspections.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5416" annotation_id="9200">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9200" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous l'avons souligné dans notre communication, nous estimons <Alignment alignment="7798" annotation_id="9268">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9268" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nécessaire d'établir des définitions communes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9324">pour</DiscourseConnective> certains termes relatifs aux inspections.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7891" docOffset="54">
      <en>For this purpose we think that a horizontal recommendation would be an appropriate instrument.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9371">Pour ce faire</DiscourseConnective>, nous pensons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9399">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une recommandation horizontale constituerait un instrument approprié.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7986" docOffset="55">
      <en>As regards the idea of transforming IMPEL into an EU environmental inspection force, IMPEL was created as an informal network of Member States' inspection authorities.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9472">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne l'idée de faire de l'IMPEL un instrument européen d'inspection environnementale, l'IMPEL a été créé en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9594">tant que</DiscourseConnective> réseau informel des autorités d'inspection des États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8154" docOffset="56">
      <en>Its objective is to facilitate exchange of information and best practice between the people who are actually applying environmental legislation in the Member States.</en>
      <fr>Son objectif consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9687">à</DiscourseConnective> faciliter l'échange d'informations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9724">et</DiscourseConnective> des meilleures pratiques entre les autorités chargées de l'application de la législation environnementale dans les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8320" docOffset="57">
      <en>I think we should preserve this role of IMPEL of bringing together the expertise of inspectors and allowing for an informal exchange of ideas at European level.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions, selon moi, conserver ce rôle attribué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9910">à</DiscourseConnective> l'IMPEL et qui consiste à rassembler les compétences des inspecteurs et à permettre un échange informel d'idées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10024">à</DiscourseConnective> l'échelon européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8481" docOffset="58">
      <en>From the Commission's side we will continue our support to IMPEL and reinforce our successful cooperation.</en>
      <fr>La Commission entend continuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10077">à</DiscourseConnective> soutenir l'IMPEL <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10096">et</DiscourseConnective> à renforcer notre fructueuse coopération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8588" docOffset="59">
      <en>This year IMPEL was transformed from an informal network into an international association.</en>
      <fr>L'IMPEL est passé cette année d'un réseau informel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10192">à</DiscourseConnective> une association internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8680" docOffset="60">
      <en>This will not only give IMPEL more visibility but also open new possibilities of activities for IMPEL.</en>
      <fr>Cette transformation confèrera à l'IMPEL <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10267">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> davantage de visibilité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10306">mais</DiscourseConnective> elle ouvrira <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10324">également</DiscourseConnective> de nouvelles possibilités d'actions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10370">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'IMPEL.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8783" docOffset="61">
      <en>To go further and create an EU environmental inspection force with powers of entry and powers to refer Member States to the Court of Justice is an interesting and ambitious idea.</en>
      <fr>Aller plus loin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10400">et</DiscourseConnective> créer un instrument européen d'inspection environnementale doté de pouvoirs d'action <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10488">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que du pouvoir de traduire des États membres devant la Cour de justice est une idée intéressante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10591">et</DiscourseConnective> ambitieuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8962" docOffset="62">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10623" annotation_id="8962">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8962" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it would raise important legal and institutional questions.</en>
      <fr>Elle susciterait <Alignment alignment="8962" annotation_id="10623">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10623" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'importantes questions juridiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10668">et</DiscourseConnective> institutionnelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9031" docOffset="63">
      <en>We should <Alignment alignment="10736" annotation_id="9041">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9041" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> look at the instruments for the improvement of the enforcement of EU environmental legislation at our disposal at present and consider whether these could be further developed or put to better use.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions <Alignment alignment="9041" annotation_id="10704">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10704" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> réfléchir aux instruments destinés à améliorer l'application de la législation environnementale de l'UE dont nous disposons actuellement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10852">et</DiscourseConnective> examiner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10864">si</DiscourseConnective> ceux-ci ne pourraient pas être davantage développés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10919">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10922">mieux</DiscourseConnective> utilisés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9244" docOffset="64">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10938" annotation_id="9244">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9244" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">For example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the horizontal infringement cases that the Commission launched against Member States for systematic failure to enforce certain obligations, such as for the presence of thousands of illegal landfills in some Member States, have led to the establishment of improved enforcement strategies in the Member States.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9244" annotation_id="10938">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10938" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">Ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, les procédures d'infraction horizontales lancées par la Commission à l'encontre des États membres en raison de la non-exécution systématique de certaines de leurs obligations, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11121">comme</DiscourseConnective> la présence de plusieurs milliers de décharges illégales dans certains États membres, ont conduit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11225">à</DiscourseConnective> l'amélioration de stratégies d'exécution dans les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9566" docOffset="65">
      <en>Another example of an initiative that has led to better enforcement is the joint inspections of waste shipments throughout the Community organised within the framework of IMPEL with the support of the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Les inspections conjointes de transferts de déchets dans l'ensemble de la Communauté, organisées dans le cadre de l'IMPEL avec le soutien de la Commission, constituent un autre exemple d'une initiative ayant permis d'améliorer l'exécution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9779" docOffset="66">
      <en>We would consider ways to reinforce this cooperation and encourage all Member States to participate in it.</en>
      <fr>Nous allons étudier certains moyens de renforcer cette coopération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11599">et</DiscourseConnective> d'encourager l'ensemble des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11644">à</DiscourseConnective> y participer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9886" id="078" name="Caroline Jackson">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9886" docOffset="67">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - Madam President, I find what the Commissioner has said rather disappointing.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, je trouve le discours du commissaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11751">plutôt</DiscourseConnective> décevant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9996" docOffset="68">
      <en>I know that he is standing in for Mr Dimas and could not help but read out what was given to him, <Alignment alignment="11856" annotation_id="10094">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10094" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I think we need rather more than that.</en>
      <fr>Je sais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11776">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il remplace M. Dimas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11800">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'il ne pouvait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11820">que</DiscourseConnective> lire ce qui lui a été transmis, <Alignment alignment="10094" annotation_id="11856">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11856" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je trouve que cela ne suffit pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10137" docOffset="69">
      <en>Environmental legislation is something that most people - perhaps all people - in this Chamber are in favour of - perhaps even including UKIP, who are apparently not here and are perhaps ironing their Union Jacks.</en>
      <fr>La législation environnementale est un thème qui recueille les faveurs de la plupart des députés de l'Assemblée - peut-être même de l'ensemble des députés -, y compris éventuellement les députés de l'UKIP, qui semblent être absents; peut-être sont-ils en train de repasser leurs drapeaux britanniques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10351" docOffset="70">
      <en>The trouble is that we do not know what is happening in the Member States, <Alignment alignment="11848" annotation_id="10426">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10426" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the proposals from the European Commission go only a very little way to improving that situation.</en>
      <fr>Le problème, c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12216">que</DiscourseConnective> nous ignorons ce qui se passe dans les États membres <Alignment alignment="10426" annotation_id="12273">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12273" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les propositions de la Commission européenne n'améliorent que très légèrement cette situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10528" docOffset="71">
      <en>We, in the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, are still in favour of having a directive rather than a recommendation.</en>
      <fr>Les membres de la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12441">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire restent favorables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12490">à</DiscourseConnective> une directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12506">plutôt qu'</DiscourseConnective>à une recommandation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10672" docOffset="72">
      <en>I do not, myself, see why we could not have a general directive regarding environmental inspections and specific rules attached to specific directives where that is appropriate.</en>
      <fr>Pour ma part, je ne comprends pas pourquoi nous ne pourrions pas disposer d'une directive générale concernant les inspections environnementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12682">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que de règles spécifiques liées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12720">à</DiscourseConnective> des directives spécifiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12749">lorsque</DiscourseConnective> cela <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12762">s'</DiscourseConnective>avère nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10850" docOffset="73">
      <en>Let me <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10857" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> turn to the question of an EU environmental inspection force.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi maintenant d'aborder la question d'un instrument européen d'inspection environnementale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10924" docOffset="74">
      <en>It is perhaps a little strange that this idea comes forward from the mouth of a British Conservative - vote Blue, go Green - <Alignment alignment="17252" annotation_id="11049">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11049" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we do need this, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11070" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="13061" annotation_id="11079">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11079" sense="Expansion.Alternative">otherwise</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Commission is entirely dependent on the Member States for the information that they choose to give it.</en>
      <fr>Il peut sembler un peu étrange <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12916">que</DiscourseConnective> cette idée sorte de la bouche d'une députée britannique conservatrice - votez bleu, passez au vert -, <Alignment alignment="7913" annotation_id="13022">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13022" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un tel instrument est nécessaire, <Alignment alignment="11079" annotation_id="13061">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13061" sense="Expansion.Alternative">faute de quoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission dépendra totalement des États membres et des informations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13147">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils voudront bien lui donner.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11197" docOffset="75">
      <en>It is extraordinary that nine years <Alignment alignment="13211" annotation_id="11233">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11233" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Landfill Directive came into force, Spain is now being prosecuted before the European Court of Justice for having 60 000 illegal landfills, taking up more than half-a-million tonnes of illegally dumped waste.</en>
      <fr>Il est incroyable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13198">que</DiscourseConnective> neuf ans <Alignment alignment="604" annotation_id="13211">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13211" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'entrée en vigueur de la directive concernant la mise en décharge, l'Espagne est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13299">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> traduite devant la Cour de justice européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13356">pour</DiscourseConnective> 60 000 décharges illégales, soit plus d'un demi-million de tonnes de déchets versés illégalement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11452" docOffset="76">
      <en>We think we know what is happening south of Naples.</en>
      <fr>Nous pensons savoir ce qui se passe au sud de Naples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11504" docOffset="77">
      <en>The Birds Directive adopted in 1979 is still being widely neglected.</en>
      <fr>La directive oiseaux adoptée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13542">en</DiscourseConnective> 1979 est toujours négligée dans une très large mesure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11573" docOffset="78">
      <en>The Commission often finds that its prosecutions before the Court of Justice on environmental matters are initiated by private citizens.</en>
      <fr>La Commission découvre souvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13631">que</DiscourseConnective> les poursuites engagées contre elle devant la Cour de justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13697">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de questions environnementales le sont par de simples citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11710" docOffset="79">
      <en>I do not think that this is good enough.</en>
      <fr>Cela ne suffit pas, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13790">à</DiscourseConnective> mon sens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11751" docOffset="80">
      <en>We should tell the people of Europe that we cannot be sure that the environmental legislation which we are adopting is being complied with.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions dire aux citoyens européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13844">que</DiscourseConnective> nous ne pouvons être sûrs du respect de la législation environnementale adoptée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11891" docOffset="81">
      <en>Given the fact that we are now looking at climate change legislation, that is very serious.</en>
      <fr>Cette situation est très grave eu égard <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13969">au fait</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13977">que</DiscourseConnective> nous examinons actuellement une législation sur le changement climatique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11983" docOffset="82">
      <en>We must return to the issue of an EU environmental inspection force, which I fully support.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons revenir à la question d'un instrument européen d'inspection environnementale, auquel je suis totalement favorable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12075" id="079" name="Genowefa Grabowska">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12075" docOffset="83">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (PL) Madam President, on behalf of my group and as a member of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, may I express my full support for the questions.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (PL) Madame la Présidente, au nom de mon groupe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14254">et</DiscourseConnective> en qualité de membre de la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14336">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire, je tiens à exprimer mon soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14399">total</DiscourseConnective> aux questions posées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12282" docOffset="84">
      <en>I share Members' concerns expressed in these questions.</en>
      <fr>Je partage les inquiétudes exprimées dans ces questions par les députés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12338" docOffset="85">
      <en>The Commission's Communication of November 2007 does <Alignment alignment="42318" annotation_id="12391">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12391" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">indeed</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> give rise to many controversies and to doubts among all those concerned about the environment and those who wish environmental law not simply to be made in the European Parliament, but to be enforced, and to be enforced in the spirit in which it was intended.</en>
      <fr>La communication de la Commission de novembre 2007 suscite <Alignment alignment="1959" annotation_id="14559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14559" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">effectivement</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de nombreuses controverses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14600">et</DiscourseConnective> de nombreux doutes parmi toutes les personnes préoccupées par l'environnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14681">et</DiscourseConnective> toutes celles qui souhaitent que la législation environnementale ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14752">soit</DiscourseConnective> pas seulement réalisée au sein du Parlement européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14811">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14816">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle soit aussi appliquée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14846">et</DiscourseConnective> appliquée dans l'esprit dans lequel elle a été conçue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12658" docOffset="86">
      <en>To achieve this, we need an effective system of monitoring introduction and compliance with the law, which we still have not developed.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14904">Pour</DiscourseConnective> cela, nous devons disposer d'un système efficace de contrôle relatif à l'introduction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14995">et</DiscourseConnective> au respect de la législation, système <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15036">que</DiscourseConnective> nous n'avons toujours pas élaboré.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12794" docOffset="87">
      <en>We have national systems which operate divergently and differently, <Alignment alignment="15155" annotation_id="12862">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12862" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> at the EU level we have a recommendation.</en>
      <fr>Il y a des systèmes nationaux qui opèrent de façons divergentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15139">et</DiscourseConnective> différentes, <Alignment alignment="12862" annotation_id="15155">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15155" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>à l'échelon de l'UE nous disposons d'une recommandation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12910" docOffset="88">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12910" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> we all know, recommendations are not binding.</en>
      <fr>Nous savons tous que les recommandations ne sont pas contraignantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12959" docOffset="89">
      <en>This is stipulated in Article 249 of the Treaty of Rome, which specifies the differences between a directive and a recommendation.</en>
      <fr>C'est ce qui figure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15310">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 249 du traité de Rome, qui précise les différences entre une directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15393">et</DiscourseConnective> une recommandation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13090" docOffset="90">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="43722" annotation_id="13098">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13098" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ask the Commission to treat the matter with all seriousness and to present the whole system of compliance monitoring, inspection and the resultant reports in the form of a binding instrument, a directive on compliance with environmental law in the European Union.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13098" annotation_id="15416">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15416" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je voudrais demander à la Commission d'examiner ce problème avec sérieux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15504">et</DiscourseConnective> de présenter l'ensemble du système de contrôle et d'inspection du respect de la législation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15600">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les rapports qui en découlent, sous la forme d'un instrument contraignant, c'est-à-dire une directive sur le respect de la législation environnementale au sein de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13372" docOffset="91">
      <en>We cannot leave the matter where it is now <Alignment alignment="15849" annotation_id="13415">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13415" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we cannot expect that amending one of the 2001 recommendations, that is, adding new Member State duties to the recommendation, will change anything.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pouvons laisser les choses telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15835">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles sont <Alignment alignment="13415" annotation_id="15849">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15849" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne pouvons espérer changer quelque chose en modifiant une des recommandations de 2001, c'est-à-dire ajouter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15965">à</DiscourseConnective> la recommandation les obligations des nouveaux États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13568" docOffset="92">
      <en>Commissioner, it will change nothing at all.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, cela ne changera rien du tout.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13613" docOffset="93">
      <en>The fact is that it we want to have effective environmental laws, we must have an effective enforcement and monitoring system.</en>
      <fr>La réalité est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16100">que si</DiscourseConnective> nous voulons disposer d'une législation environnementale efficace, nous devons disposer d'un système efficace d'exécution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16229">et</DiscourseConnective> de contrôle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13740" docOffset="94">
      <en>To repeat: you have asked whether we should introduce sectoral or global monitoring regulations.</en>
      <fr>Je le répète: vous nous avez demandé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16282">s'</DiscourseConnective>il fallait introduire des règlements sectoriels en matière de contrôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16355">ou</DiscourseConnective> des règlements généraux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13837" docOffset="95">
      <en>I <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13839" sense="Comparison.Contrast">on the other hand</DiscourseConnective> want to ask whether you would like to protect the whole of the environment or only individual sectors.</en>
      <fr>De mon côté, je vous pose la question suivante: voulez-vous protéger l'environnement dans son ensemble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16486">ou</DiscourseConnective> seulement certains secteurs?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13960" docOffset="96">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13960" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">And</DiscourseConnective> this gives you the answer.</en>
      <fr>Poser la question est y répondre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13991" id="080" name="Johannes Blokland">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13991" docOffset="97">
      <en>on behalf of the IND/DEM Group. - (NL) Madam President, in recent years, we in the European Parliament have approved a great deal of environmental legislation.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, le Parlement européen a approuvé ces dernières années un grand nombre de lois environnementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14151" docOffset="98">
      <en>The environment is at the top of the agenda, and rightly so.</en>
      <fr>L'environnement est une priorité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16704">et</DiscourseConnective> ce n'est que justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14212" docOffset="99">
      <en>The important thing, <Alignment alignment="4863" annotation_id="14233">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14233" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, is not just to produce legislation: it <Alignment alignment="22986" annotation_id="14280">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14280" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> needs to be implemented, <Alignment alignment="16821" annotation_id="14310">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14310" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is exactly where the problems appear to be.</en>
      <fr>L'important n'est <Alignment alignment="3833" annotation_id="16747">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16747" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas de produire une législation; elle doit <Alignment alignment="8579" annotation_id="16800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16800" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être appliquée <Alignment alignment="16600" annotation_id="16821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16821" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est exactement là que le bât blesse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14363" docOffset="100">
      <en>According to information from the European Commission, the implementation of environmental policy leaves something to be desired at times.</en>
      <fr>Selon les informations émanant de la Commission européenne, la mise en œuvre de la politique environnementale laisse parfois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16988">à</DiscourseConnective> désirer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14502" docOffset="101">
      <en>Current environmental inspection policy is contained in the recommendation, which is interpreted quite differently in various Member States.</en>
      <fr>La politique actuelle en matière d'inspection environnementale figure dans la recommandation, qui est interprétée de multiples façons dans les différents États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14643" docOffset="102">
      <en>It has <Alignment alignment="17180" annotation_id="14650">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14650" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> been reported that environmental inspections have been carried out incompletely, all of which means that, despite existing environmental legislation, the environment does not always benefit.</en>
      <fr>Il apparaît <Alignment alignment="14650" annotation_id="17180">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17180" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17190">que</DiscourseConnective> les inspections environnementales n'ont pas été réalisées dans leur intégralité. Tout cela signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17294">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> dépit de la législation environnementale, l'environnement n'en sort pas toujours gagnant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14846" docOffset="103">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17390" annotation_id="14846">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14846" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want the quality of the environment to improve, we must, as an absolute priority, put effective controls in place to ensure that this legislation is implemented.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4378" annotation_id="17390">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17390" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons une amélioration de la qualité de l'environnement, nous devons - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17471">et</DiscourseConnective> c'est une priorité absolue - instaurer des contrôles efficaces <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17537">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> garantir la mise en œuvre de cette législation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15014" docOffset="104">
      <en>Commissioner, you claim to be presenting your green credentials.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, vous prétendez présenter votre légitimation verte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15079" docOffset="105">
      <en>In this respect, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15096" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>, there is still quite a bit to be done.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17671">À cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, il reste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17693">encore</DiscourseConnective> pas mal de choses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17718">à</DiscourseConnective> faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15143" docOffset="106">
      <en>I myself was rapporteur for a regulation on the transfer of waste in 2007 and before, <Alignment alignment="17849" annotation_id="15229">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15229" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is much room for improvement in that area.</en>
      <fr>J'ai personnellement été rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17763">en</DiscourseConnective> 2007 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17771">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que précédemment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17794">pour</DiscourseConnective> un règlement concernant le transfert des déchets, <Alignment alignment="15229" annotation_id="17849">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17849" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est un domaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17869">à propos</DiscourseConnective> duquel de nombreuses améliorations sont encore nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15282" docOffset="107">
      <en>In the context of better implementation of environmental policy, would you be prepared to make the existing recommendation binding?</en>
      <fr>Dans le cadre d'une meilleure mise en œuvre de la politique environnementale, seriez-vous prêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18033">à</DiscourseConnective> rendre l'actuelle recommandation contraignante?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15414" id="081" name="Bogusław Sonik">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15414" docOffset="108">
      <en>(PL) Madam President, I share the view of the European Commission that large discrepancies exist between the different methods of monitoring environmental compliance used by different Member States, which make it impossible to ensure consistent introduction and enforcement of EU law.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Madame la Présidente, je partage l'avis de la Commission européenne selon lequel il existe d'importantes disparités entre les différentes méthodes de contrôle du respect de la législation environnementale utilisées par les différents États membres et ces disparités ne permettent pas de garantir une bonne introduction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18407">et</DiscourseConnective> une bonne application de la législation européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15699" docOffset="109">
      <en>In my work as an MEP I have had the opportunity to study the results of a number of IMPEL projects, including one concerning the crossborder movement of waste through sea ports.</en>
      <fr>Dans mon travail de député européen, j'ai eu l'occasion d'étudier les résultats d'un certain nombre de projets IMPEL, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18580">notamment</DiscourseConnective> un projet concernant les mouvements transfrontaliers de déchets par des ports maritimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15877" docOffset="110">
      <en>I have discovered that cooperation between the various IMPEL inspection services consists not only of the sharing of experience, but also, and perhaps even most importantly, of joint monitoring operations and exchange of information about environmental crimes and offences.</en>
      <fr>J'ai découvert <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18694">que</DiscourseConnective> la coopération entre les différents services d'inspection de l'IMPEL ne consiste pas seulement en un partage d'expériences, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18822">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18827">également</DiscourseConnective> - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18839">et</DiscourseConnective> c'est peut-être le plus important - en des opérations conjointes de contrôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18919">et</DiscourseConnective> d'échanges d'informations relatives à des délits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18971">et</DiscourseConnective> à des infractions environnementaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16151" docOffset="111">
      <en>Some dishonest companies deliberately transfer their unlawful operations to countries where they know the control system to be weaker and where they can continue to operate with impunity.</en>
      <fr>Certaines sociétés malhonnêtes transfèrent délibérément leurs opérations illicites vers des pays où elles savent que le système de contrôle est moins performant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19171">et</DiscourseConnective> où elles peuvent continuer d'agir impunément.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16339" docOffset="112">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11791" annotation_id="16339">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16339" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> control systems in all Member States were uniform, this would not be happening.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="16339" annotation_id="19220">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19220" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les systèmes de contrôle étaient uniformes dans l'ensemble des États membres, cela n'arriverait pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16422" docOffset="113">
      <en>This is another argument in favour of the European Union having an efficient and uniform system for monitoring facilities for compliance with environmental requirements.</en>
      <fr>C'est là un autre argument <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19351">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur de l'instauration dans l'Union européen d'un système uniforme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19423">et</DiscourseConnective> efficace de contrôle du respect des exigences environnementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16592" docOffset="114">
      <en>Inspections are an important instrument in the process of introduction and enforcement of EU laws, <Alignment alignment="19624" annotation_id="16691">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16691" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in spite of this Member States give them different political priorities.</en>
      <fr>Les inspections représentent un instrument important dans le processus d'introduction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19577">et</DiscourseConnective> d'application de la législation européenne, <Alignment alignment="16691" annotation_id="19624">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19624" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19630">en</DiscourseConnective> dépit de cela, les États membres lui octroient des priorités politiques diverses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16768" docOffset="115">
      <en>This is why I fully support the European Commission's proposal amending the existing recommendations to make them more effective.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle je soutiens totalement la proposition de la Commission européenne visant à modifier les recommandations actuelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19859">afin de</DiscourseConnective> les rendre plus efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16898" docOffset="116">
      <en>I agree with the proposal to include legally binding requirements concerning the inspection of specific facilities and operations in sectoral regulations.</en>
      <fr>Je suis favorable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19912">à</DiscourseConnective> la proposition visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19936">à</DiscourseConnective> inclure des exigences juridiquement contraignantes concernant les inspections d'installations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20032">et</DiscourseConnective> d'opérations spécifiques dans les règlements sectoriels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17053" docOffset="117">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7523" annotation_id="17053">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17053" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have done this, we will be able to give inspections a higher political priority and improve enforcement of environmental laws throughout the Community.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6398" annotation_id="20092">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20092" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela sera fait, les inspections bénéficieront d'une plus grande priorité politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20183">et</DiscourseConnective> l'application des lois environnementales sera améliorée dans l'ensemble de la Communauté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17213" id="082" name="Daciana Octavia Sârbu">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17213" docOffset="118">
      <en>- (RO) Inspections represent an important element for guaranteeing application of and compliance with Community environmental legislation.</en>
      <fr>(RO) Les inspections représentent un élément important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20331">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> garantir l'application <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20364">et</DiscourseConnective> le respect de la législation environnementale de la Communauté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17352" docOffset="119">
      <en>In this sense, the Commission recommendation providing for minimum criteria for environmental inspections in the Member States was an important step forward <Alignment alignment="15270" annotation_id="17509">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17509" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it was adopted in 2001.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce sens, la recommandation de la Commission prévoyant des critères minimaux applicables aux inspections environnementales dans les États membres a été une étape importante <Alignment alignment="10764" annotation_id="20608">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20608" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">au moment de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> son adoption <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20634">en</DiscourseConnective> 2001.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17538" docOffset="120">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20856" annotation_id="17538">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17538" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the evaluation of this recommendation's application has highlighted more matters for concern.</en>
      <fr>L'évaluation de l'application de cette recommandation a <Alignment alignment="10347" annotation_id="20699">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20699" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> révélé de nombreux sujets d'inquiétude.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17641" docOffset="121">
      <en>The Commission's Communication records the fact that there are still large disparities in the way environmental inspections are being carried out at local, region and national level.</en>
      <fr>La communication de la Commission signale l'existence d'importantes disparités dans la manière dont les inspections environnementales sont réalisées aux échelons local, régional <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20927">et</DiscourseConnective> national.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17824" docOffset="122">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="22135" annotation_id="17824">
          <Alignment alignment="20461" annotation_id="17824">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17824" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, it has been noted that the national measures adopted in the Communication's wording differ very greatly, both in terms of application and control.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17824" annotation_id="20940">
          <Alignment alignment="17824" annotation_id="20940">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20940" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">D'autre part</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, il apparaît <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20966">que</DiscourseConnective> les mesures nationales adoptées dans la formulation de la communication diffèrent considérablement, tant sur le plan de leur application <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21107">que</DiscourseConnective> sur celui du contrôle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17984" docOffset="123">
      <en>The shortcomings with this recommendation do not seem to have been remedied satisfactorily in the Commission's Communication.</en>
      <fr>Les lacunes que présente cette recommandation ne semblent pas avoir été corrigées d'une manière satisfaisante dans la communication de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18110" docOffset="124">
      <en>Even <Alignment alignment="28733" annotation_id="18115">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18115" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is proposed to accommodate the problems mentioned above, it is missing one key element, which has brought about modest success for the recommendation.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1304" annotation_id="21284">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21284" sense="Contingency.Condition">Même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21302">à</DiscourseConnective> tenir compte des problèmes cités préalablement, il y a un élément essentiel qui manque et qui est responsable du peu de succès de la recommandation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18274" docOffset="125">
      <en>I mean the very legal nature of this document.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agit du caractère juridique de ce document.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18321" docOffset="126">
      <en>I believe <Alignment alignment="21511" annotation_id="18331">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18331" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that only revising this recommendation will do no more than maintain the current state of uncertainty.</en>
      <fr>J'estime <Alignment alignment="18331" annotation_id="21511">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21511" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21516">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une simple révision de cette recommandation ne fera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21571">que</DiscourseConnective> maintenir l'incertitude actuelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18444" docOffset="127">
      <en>Only a directive can bring about a significant and effective improvement for environmental inspections.</en>
      <fr>Seule une directive peut entraîner une amélioration sensible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21670">et</DiscourseConnective> efficace des inspections environnementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18548" id="083" name="Siim Kallas">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18548" docOffset="128">
      <en>Vice-President of the Commission. - Madam President, I wish to thank the honourable Members for their remarks and observations concerning environmental issues, which are so sensitive, <Alignment alignment="21946" annotation_id="18732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18732" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are all in favour of improving the environment.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21788">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier les honorables députés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21823">pour</DiscourseConnective> leurs remarques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21844">et</DiscourseConnective> observations relatives aux problèmes qui touchent l'environnement; ces problèmes sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21933">si</DiscourseConnective> sensibles <Alignment alignment="17333" annotation_id="21946">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21946" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous sommes tous favorables à une amélioration de l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18786" docOffset="129">
      <en>Two remarks concerning them raised observations.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens à formuler deux remarques à ce propos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18835" docOffset="130">
      <en>The Commission shares the view that legally binding requirements for environmental inspections are really needed and are valuable.</en>
      <fr>La Commission partage le point de vue selon lequel il serait nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22137">et</DiscourseConnective> précieux de disposer d'exigences juridiquement contraignantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22202">pour</DiscourseConnective> les inspections environnementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18966" docOffset="131">
      <en>The Commission is working in that direction.</en>
      <fr>La Commission travaille dans ce sens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19011" docOffset="132">
      <en>The question is where to have those binding requirements as regards the transformation of IMPEL into a European inspection force.</en>
      <fr>La question est de savoir comment associer ces exigences contraignantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22352">à</DiscourseConnective> la transformation de l'IMPEL en un instrument européen d'inspection.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19141" docOffset="133">
      <en>The Commission still takes the view that it is better to preserve IMPEL <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19213" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> it is.</en>
      <fr>La Commission continue de penser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22456">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est préférable de maintenir l'IMPEL tel qu'il est.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19223" id="084" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19223" docOffset="134">
      <en>I have received one motion for a resolutionpursuant to Rule 108(5) of the Rules of Procedure.</en>
      <fr>J'ai reçu une proposition de résolution, déposée sur la base de l'article 108, paragraphe 5 du règlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19317" docOffset="135">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19339" docOffset="136">
      <en>The vote will take place today at 12 noon.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22668">à</DiscourseConnective> 12 heures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19382" docOffset="137">
      <en>(The sitting was suspended at 11.55 a.m. pending voting time, and resumed at 12.05 p.m.)</en>
      <fr>(La séance, suspendue à 11 h 55 dans l'attente de l'Heure des votes, est reprise à 12 h 05)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
