<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statements by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclarations de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="28" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="28" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, this is the first of our meetings to be held in the new year 2008.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, c'est notre première réunion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="82">en</DiscourseConnective> cette nouvelle année 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="117" docOffset="2">
      <en>May I wish every one of you health and happiness and hope that together we are successful in the tasks that have been entrusted to us, namely to take the European Union forward to a positive future.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais vous souhaiter à tous santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="152">et</DiscourseConnective> bonheur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="163">et</DiscourseConnective> j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="175">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ensemble, nous parviendrons à mener à bien les tâches qui nous ont été confiées, à savoir guider l'Union européenne vers un avenir positif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="316" docOffset="3">
      <en>Allow me to make a few remarks about the work we have to do.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de faire quelques remarques au sujet du travail qui nous attend.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="377" docOffset="4">
      <en>On the day the European Parliament held its last sitting here in Strasbourg, namely 13 December 2007, the Reform Treaty was signed in Lisbon.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="397">Le jour où</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen a tenu sa dernière séance ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="460">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg, à savoir le 13 décembre 2007, le traité rectificatif a été signé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="539">à</DiscourseConnective> Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="519" docOffset="5">
      <en>In a short speech that I made - in the presence of the President of the European Council, José Socrates, and EC President, José Manuel Barroso - I expressed the will of the great majority of the European Parliament that the Reform Treaty should become a legal, and hence a political, reality by 1 January 2009.</en>
      <fr>Dans la brève allocution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="576">que</DiscourseConnective> j'ai prononcée - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="597">en</DiscourseConnective> présence du président du Conseil européen, M. Socrates, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="656">et</DiscourseConnective> du président de la CE, M. Barroso - j'ai exprimé le souhait de la grande majorité du Parlement européen de voir le traité rectificatif devenir une réalité juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="824">et</DiscourseConnective>, par là même, politique d'ici le 1er janvier 2009.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="830" docOffset="6">
      <en>This objective remains the priority of priorities for the year 2008.</en>
      <fr>Cet objectif reste la priorité des priorités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="923">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'année 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="899" docOffset="7">
      <en>On 21 December border restrictions were lifted for those nine countries that joined the European Union on 1 May 2004.</en>
      <fr>Le 21 décembre, les restrictions aux frontières ont été levées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1005">pour</DiscourseConnective> les neuf pays qui ont rejoint l'Union européenne le 1er mai 2004.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1017" docOffset="8">
      <en>These were indeed moving events.</en>
      <fr>Ces événements ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1095">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective> été émouvants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1050" docOffset="9">
      <en>For hundreds of years soldiers had forced their way across the national borders of our continent to inflict war, misery and suffering on others.</en>
      <fr>Pendant des centaines d'années, des soldats ont traversé de force les frontières nationales de notre continent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1232">pour</DiscourseConnective> apporter la guerre, la misère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1267">et</DiscourseConnective> la souffrance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1195" docOffset="10">
      <en>The removal of the barriers between our nations means this: our neighbours welcome us.</en>
      <fr>La suppression des barrières entre nos nations signifie ceci: nos voisins nous accueillent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1282" docOffset="11">
      <en>We are all common citizens of the European Union, <Alignment alignment="1429" annotation_id="1332">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1332" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="1433" annotation_id="1336">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1336" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it says in the Berlin Declaration of 25 March 2007: 'We are united for the better'.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes tous des citoyens de l'Union européenne <Alignment alignment="1332" annotation_id="1429">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1429" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="274" annotation_id="1433">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1433" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le dit la Déclaration de Berlin du 25 mars 2007: "Nous sommes unis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1506">pour</DiscourseConnective> le meilleur".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1423" docOffset="12">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1434" docOffset="13">
      <en>Malta and Cyprus joined the European Monetary Union on 1 January.</en>
      <fr>Malte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1550">et</DiscourseConnective> Chypre ont rejoint l'Union monétaire européenne le 1er janvier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1500" docOffset="14">
      <en>Our common currency, the Euro, is <Alignment alignment="1652" annotation_id="1534">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1534" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the official means of payment in both these countries.</en>
      <fr>Notre monnaie commune, l'euro, est <Alignment alignment="1534" annotation_id="1652">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1652" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le moyen de paiement officiel dans ces deux pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1599" docOffset="15">
      <en>We extend our warmest welcome to Malta and Cyprus.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons chaleureusement la bienvenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1752">à</DiscourseConnective> Malte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1760">et</DiscourseConnective> à Chypre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1650" docOffset="16">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1661" docOffset="17">
      <en>The European Year of Intercultural Dialogue was celebrated in Ljubljana on 9 January at an impressive ceremony attended by members of the European Council, Commission and Parliament.</en>
      <fr>L'Année européenne du dialogue interculturel a été célébrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1852">à</DiscourseConnective> Ljubljana le 9 janvier lors d'une cérémonie impressionnante à laquelle ont assisté des membres du Conseil européen, de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1987">et</DiscourseConnective> du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1844" docOffset="18">
      <en>The Intercultural Dialogue will be a key feature of our work during the coming year and will remain so.</en>
      <fr>Le dialogue interculturel sera un élément clé de notre travail au cours de l'année à venir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2095">et</DiscourseConnective> après.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1948" docOffset="19">
      <en>I would ask you all to be present tomorrow for the statement by the Grand Mufti of Syria, Sheikh Ahmad Badr Al-Din Hassoun.</en>
      <fr>Je vous demanderais à tous d'être présents demain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2155">pour</DiscourseConnective> la déclaration du Grand Mufti de Syrie, Sheikh Ahmad Badr Al-Din Hassoun.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2072" docOffset="20">
      <en>Let me now move on to two final items: our legislative work this year will be significantly influenced by climate and environmental issues.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi à présent de passer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2268">à</DiscourseConnective> deux derniers points: notre travail législatif de cette année sera considérablement influencé par les problèmes climatiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2394">et</DiscourseConnective> environnementaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2212" docOffset="21">
      <en>As legislators we owe much responsibility to climate and environmental protection, on the one hand, and to the protection of European competitiveness and to the safeguarding of jobs, on the other.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2418">tant que</DiscourseConnective> législateurs, nous avons une grande responsabilité en matière de protection du climat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2513">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'environnement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2536">d'une part</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2548">et</DiscourseConnective> de protection de la compétitivité européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2596">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'emploi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2612">d'autre part</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2409" docOffset="22">
      <en>Together we have to strike the right balance between the economy and the ecology.</en>
      <fr>Ensemble, nous devons trouver le juste équilibre entre l'économie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2692">et</DiscourseConnective> l'écologie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2491" docOffset="23">
      <en>The European Union is based on values, rights and responsibilities.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne est fondée sur des valeurs, des droits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2765">et</DiscourseConnective> des responsabilités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2559" docOffset="24">
      <en>On 12 December 2007 the Presidents of the European Parliament, the Council and the Commission signed the Charter of Fundamental Rights here in this very Chamber.</en>
      <fr>Le 12 décembre 2007, les présidents du Parlement européen, du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2859">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission ont signé la Charte des droits fondamentaux ici même, au Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2721" docOffset="25">
      <en>This marked a significant event for the citizens of the European Union and for the European Parliament too.</en>
      <fr>Cette signature a été un événement significatif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2995">pour</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3035">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3045">pour</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2829" docOffset="26">
      <en>During the signing a number of members interrupted the proceedings with loud heckling and attempted to prevent the speakers from being heard.</en>
      <fr>Au cours de celle-ci, plusieurs députés ont interrompu les travaux par leur chahut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3156">et</DiscourseConnective> ont essayé d'empêcher les orateurs de se faire entendre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2971" docOffset="27">
      <en>Nothing can justify such behaviour.</en>
      <fr>Rien ne peut justifier un tel comportement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3007" docOffset="28">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3018" docOffset="29">
      <en>Free speech is the basis of democracy and of parliamentarianism.</en>
      <fr>La liberté de parole est la base de la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3329">et</DiscourseConnective> du parlementarisme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3083" docOffset="30">
      <en>Every Member of the European Parliament is entitled freely to express his or her opinion in any of the designated debates.</en>
      <fr>Chaque député du Parlement européen a le droit d'exprimer librement son opinion lors de tout débat désigné comme tel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3206" docOffset="31">
      <en>It is our common duty to protect this right at all times.</en>
      <fr>Il est de notre devoir commun de protéger ce droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3521">à</DiscourseConnective> tout moment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3264" docOffset="32">
      <en>What is more, to prevent speakers from addressing the European Parliament, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3339" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> especially <Alignment alignment="3620" annotation_id="3354">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3354" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are guests in this House, offends against the basic rights of freedom, democracy and parliamentarianism.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3536">En outre</DiscourseConnective>, empêcher des orateurs de s'adresser au Parlement européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3605">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="3354" annotation_id="3620">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3620" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils sont invités au sein de cette Assemblée, va à l'encontre des droits fondamentaux de la liberté, de la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3744">et</DiscourseConnective> du parlementarisme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3469" docOffset="33">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3480" docOffset="34">
      <en>This <Alignment alignment="3800" annotation_id="3485">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3485" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> means that it contravenes our Rules of Procedure, which cannot be accepted under any circumstances.</en>
      <fr>Cela signifie <Alignment alignment="1251" annotation_id="3800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3800" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3806">que</DiscourseConnective> notre règlement a été enfreint, ce qui ne peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3857">en</DiscourseConnective> aucun cas être accepté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3590" docOffset="35">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="3889" annotation_id="3592">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3592" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> intend to take action, <Alignment alignment="3940" annotation_id="3625">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3625" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> provided for in the Rules of Procedure, against those Members who continued in their attempt to interrupt the proceedings, despite repeated requests from the Chair to desist.</en>
      <fr>J'ai <Alignment alignment="3592" annotation_id="3889">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3889" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'intention de prendre des mesures, <Alignment alignment="3625" annotation_id="3940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3940" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le règlement le prévoit, à l'encontre des députés qui ont continué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4013">à</DiscourseConnective> essayer d'interrompre les travaux, malgré les demandes répétées de la présidence de mettre un terme à ces agissements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3803" docOffset="36">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3814" docOffset="37">
      <en>The same applies to those Members who behaved in an unseemly way towards our ushers, who were only carrying out their proper duties.</en>
      <fr>Cela s'applique également aux députés qui se sont comportés de manière inconvenante envers nos huissiers, qui ne faisaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4276">que</DiscourseConnective> leur travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3947" docOffset="38">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3958" docOffset="39">
      <en>The new year will pose great challenges for us.</en>
      <fr>Cette nouvelle année nous place face à de grands défis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4006" docOffset="40">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4377" annotation_id="4006">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4006" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I am convinced that we will overcome these by showing respect and consideration for each other.</en>
      <fr>Je suis <Alignment alignment="4006" annotation_id="4377">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4377" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> convaincu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4397">que</DiscourseConnective> nous les relèverons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4421">en</DiscourseConnective> nous montrant un respect <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4449">et</DiscourseConnective> une considération mutuels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4111" docOffset="41">
      <en>It is very much with this in mind that I would again wish you all the very best for 2008.</en>
      <fr>C'est dans cet esprit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4501">que</DiscourseConnective> je voudrais à nouveau vous souhaiter le meilleur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4554">pour</DiscourseConnective> 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4201" docOffset="42">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
