<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>1.</en>
    <fr>1.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Residence permits: uniform format (vote)</en>
    <fr>Modèle uniforme de titre de séjour pour les ressortissants de pays tiers (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="44" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Coelho report</en>
    <fr>- Rapport Coelho</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="60" docOffset="3">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="102">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="79" id="085" name="Carlos Coelho ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="79" docOffset="4">
      <en>rapporteur. - (PT) Mr President, in 2003, Parliament rejected two Commission initiatives on this issue.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="139">en</DiscourseConnective> 2003, le Parlement a rejeté deux initiatives de la Commission sur cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="183" docOffset="5">
      <en>I congratulate the Commission on accepting Parliament's idea of separating the issue of residence permits from that of visas.</en>
      <fr>Je félicite la Commission d'avoir accepté l'idée formulée par le Parlement de séparer la question des titres de séjour de celle des visas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="309" docOffset="6">
      <en>Quite apart from technical issues involved in radio collisions between the different chips used, these are indeed separate issues.</en>
      <fr>Outre les aspects techniques liés aux collisions radio entre les différentes puces utilisées, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="460">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit là de questions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="483">de fait</DiscourseConnective> distinctes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="440" docOffset="7">
      <en>It is one thing to have an identity document to be used within the Schengen area, <Alignment alignment="598" annotation_id="522">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="522" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> having a travel document to be used outside the Schengen area is quite another.</en>
      <fr>Disposer d'un document d'identité utilisable à l'intérieur de l'espace Schengen est une chose, <Alignment alignment="227" annotation_id="598">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="598" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> disposer d'un document de voyage utilisable en dehors de l'espace Schengen en est une autre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="606" docOffset="8">
      <en>This will enable all third-country nationals living legally in the Schengen area to be identified in the same way.</en>
      <fr>Cela permettra à tous les ressortissants de pays tiers qui vivent légalement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="773">à</DiscourseConnective> l'intérieur de l'espace Schengen d'être identifiés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="826">de la même manière</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="721" docOffset="9">
      <en>I should <Alignment alignment="846" annotation_id="730">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="730" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to congratulate the Commission on proposing to us the introduction of biometric identifiers containing an image and fingerprints in interoperable formats.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="683" annotation_id="846">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="846" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je souhaiterais féliciter la Commission de nous avoir proposé l'introduction d'éléments d'identification biométriques contenant une image <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1000">et</DiscourseConnective> des empreintes digitales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1028">en</DiscourseConnective> formats interopérables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="900" docOffset="10">
      <en>The use of these biometric data is the best way of preventing the use of false identities and identity theft.</en>
      <fr>L'utilisation de ces données biométriques est la meilleure façon de lutter contre l'utilisation d'identités fictives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1172">et</DiscourseConnective> l'usurpation d'identité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1010" docOffset="11">
      <en>I should like to draw the Commission's attention, <Alignment alignment="528210" annotation_id="1060">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1060" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, to the need for such changes of residence to meet the same high levels of security required for the issuing of national identity cards.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="566" annotation_id="1200">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1200" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je souhaiterais attirer l'attention de la Commission sur la nécessité de veiller <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1292">à</DiscourseConnective> ce que ces changements de résidence répondent au <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1343">même</DiscourseConnective> niveau élevé de sécurité applicable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1384">à</DiscourseConnective> la délivrance des cartes nationales d'identité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1205" docOffset="12">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="1446" annotation_id="1207">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1207" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> wish to draw the Commission's attention to the gaps regarding the way in which data are gathered, especially in the case of children, or people who are unable to provide fingerprints due to various forms of incapacity.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite <Alignment alignment="620" annotation_id="1446">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1446" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> attirer l'attention de la Commission sur les lacunes qui peuvent être observées dans la manière dont les données sont recueillies, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1587">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans le cas des enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1621">ou</DiscourseConnective> des personnes incapables de fournir des empreintes digitales en raison de diverses formes d'incapacité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1431" docOffset="13">
      <en>Lastly, let me draw the Commission's attention to data protection standards and to the need to draw up a detailed list of the authorities that will have access to those data, and of the authorities permitted to carry out checks on residence permits, in order to prevent the misuse of the most sensitive data.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1728">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, permettez-moi d'attirer l'attention de la Commission sur les normes de protection des données <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1829">et</DiscourseConnective> sur la nécessité d'établir une liste détaillée des autorités qui auront accès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1910">à</DiscourseConnective> ces données, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1925">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que des autorités autorisées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1960">à</DiscourseConnective> contrôler les titres de séjour, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1994">afin de</DiscourseConnective> prévenir toute utilisation abusive des données les plus sensibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
