<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>EC/Mauritania Fisheries Partnership Agreement for the period 1 August 2008 to 31 July 2012 (debate)</en>
    <fr>Possibilités de pêche et contrepartie financière prévues par l'accord CE/Mauritanie de partenariat dans le secteur de la pêche (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="100" id="490" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="100" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Mrs Carmen Fraga Estévez, on behalf of the Committee on Fisheries, on the proposal for a Council regulation on the conclusion of the Protocol setting out the fishing opportunities and financial contribution provided for in the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community and the Islamic Republic of Mauritania for the period 1 August 2008 to 31 July 2012 - C6-0199/2008 -.</en>
      <fr>(PT) L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de Mme Carmen Fraga Estévez, au nom de la commission de la pêche, sur la proposition de règlement du Conseil relatif à la conclusion du protocole fixant les possibilités de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="354">et</DiscourseConnective> la contrepartie financière prévues par l'accord de partenariat dans le secteur de la pêche entre la Communauté européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="479">et</DiscourseConnective> la République islamique de Mauritanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="520">pour</DiscourseConnective> la période allant du 1er août 2008 au 31 juillet 2012 - C6-0199/2008 -.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="523" id="491" name="Joe Borg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="523" docOffset="2">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, let me first extend my gratitude to the Fisheries Committee and especially to its rapporteur, Mrs Fraga, for her report.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) M le Président, j'aimerais exprimer ma gratitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="678">à</DiscourseConnective> la commission de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="706">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="709">plus particulièrement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="731">à</DiscourseConnective> son rapporteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="686" docOffset="3">
      <en>This revised protocol has set the fishing possibilities and the financial contribution for the period 1 August 2010 to 31 July 2012.</en>
      <fr>Ce protocole révisé fixe les possibilités de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="800">et</DiscourseConnective> la contrepartie financière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="830">pour</DiscourseConnective> la période allant du 1er août 2008 au 31 juillet 2012.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="819" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is the result of a long and complex negotiation process between the European Commission and Mauritania that was launched in October 2007, following serious under-utilisation of the protocol by European ship-owners, namely under-utilisation for cephalopods and the small pelagic species.</en>
      <fr>Ce texte est le fruit d'un processus de négociation long <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="947">et</DiscourseConnective> complexe lancé entre la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="996">et</DiscourseConnective> la Mauritanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1013">en</DiscourseConnective> octobre 2007, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1030">après</DiscourseConnective> une importante sous-exploitation du protocole par les armateurs européens, en particulier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1126">pour</DiscourseConnective> les espèces céphalopodes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1156">et</DiscourseConnective> les petites espèces pélagiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>

<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1110" docOffset="6">
      <en>The main changes introduced in the new protocol are, firstly, related to the duration of the protocol, which we have extended from two to four years, and, secondly, a reduction of the fishing possibilities for cephalopods, following scientific advice, and for small pelagics, following the actual utilisation and the forecasts for the European Union fleet.</en>
      <fr>Le premier porte sur la durée du protocole, qui passe de deux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1313">à</DiscourseConnective> quatre ans. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1327">Ensuite</DiscourseConnective>, nous avons réduit les possibilités de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1380">pour</DiscourseConnective> les céphalopodes, sur avis scientifique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1426">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1429">pour</DiscourseConnective> les petites espèces pélagiques, compte tenu de l'exploitation actuelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1505">et</DiscourseConnective> des prévisions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1523">pour</DiscourseConnective> la flotte de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1467" docOffset="7">
      <en>Thirdly, an overall reduction of the financial contribution over a four-year period, from an average of EUR 86 million per year to an average of EUR 72.25 million per year, but with an increase within this allocation of the part dedicated to supporting the country's fisheries policy: from EUR 11 million per year in 2008-9 to EUR 20 million per year in 2011-2012.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1561">Troisièmement</DiscourseConnective>, nous avons décidé d'une réduction générale de la contrepartie financière - passant d'une moyenne de 86 millions d'euros par an <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1703">à</DiscourseConnective> 72,25 millions d'euros, moyennant toutefois une augmentation de la part réservée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1786">pour</DiscourseConnective> le soutien à la politique de pêche mauritanienne, de 11 millions d'euros par an <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1871">en</DiscourseConnective> 2008-2009 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1884">à</DiscourseConnective> 20 millions d'euros <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1906">en</DiscourseConnective> 2011-2012.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1832" docOffset="8">
      <en>Fourthly, there is a revised procedure for dealing with infringements in Mauritanian waters.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1920">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, une procédure révisée est prévue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1960">pour</DiscourseConnective> le traitement des infractions dans les eaux mauritaniennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1925" docOffset="9">
      <en>This is a well-balanced protocol which conciliates the different interests: the need to adjust the EU financial contribution to reduced fishing possibilities for the EU fleet, and the importance of giving greater support to the fisheries sector in Mauritania <Alignment alignment="23988" annotation_id="2184">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2184" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2187" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> to encourage the integration of this sector into the Mauritanian National Development strategy.</en>
      <fr>Ce protocole est équilibré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2052">et</DiscourseConnective> concilie les différents intérêts en présence: d'une part, l'obligation d'adapter la contrepartie financière compte tenu de la réduction des possibilités de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2217">pour</DiscourseConnective> la flotte européenne et, d'autre part, l'importance d'un renforcement du soutien au secteur de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2326">en</DiscourseConnective> Mauritanie <Alignment alignment="2184" annotation_id="2340">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2340" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>encourager l'intégration de ce secteur dans la stratégie nationale de développement du pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2286" docOffset="10">
      <en>The Fisheries Partnership Agreement contributes 20% of the budgetary revenues of the Mauritanian state, compared to approximately 30-35% in the period 2004-2005.</en>
      <fr>L'accord de partenariat dans le secteur de la pêche apporte 20 % des recettes budgétaires de l'État mauritanien, contre 30-35 % au cours de la période 2004-2005.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2448" docOffset="11">
      <en>The Fisheries Partnership Agreement amounts to 80% of the overall revenues from the fisheries sector within the state budget.</en>
      <fr>L'accord couvre par ailleurs 80 % de l'ensemble des revenus générés par le secteur de la pêche dans le budget de l'État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2574" docOffset="12">
      <en>The European Community fishing effort in the Mauritanian EEZ represents 20% of the overall effort - that is both artisanal and industrial fleets.</en>
      <fr>L'effort de pêche de la Communauté européenne dans la ZEE mauritanienne représente 20 % de l'effort global -comprenant les flottes artisanales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2866">et</DiscourseConnective> commerciales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2720" docOffset="13">
      <en>During the negotiations, the Mauritanian side asked the Commission to make every effort to pay the first annual financial contribution by the end of August 2008.</en>
      <fr>Au cours des négociations, nos interlocuteurs mauritaniens ont demandé à la Commission de faire tout ce qui était en son pouvoir afin de verser la première compensation financière annuelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3072">avant</DiscourseConnective> la fin du mois d'août 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2882" docOffset="14">
      <en>This contribution is crucial for the Mauritanian national budget considering, <Alignment alignment="3260" annotation_id="2960">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2960" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I said earlier, that annual payments under the Fisheries Partnership Agreement represent 15 to 20% of the country's budget.</en>
      <fr>Cette enveloppe est en effet essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3147">pour</DiscourseConnective> le budget mauritanien puisque les paiements annuels versés dans le cadre de l'accord de pêche représentent, <Alignment alignment="24931" annotation_id="3260">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3260" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai déjà dit, de 15 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3290">à</DiscourseConnective> 20 % des recettes du budget national.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3087" docOffset="15">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="3357" annotation_id="3093">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3093" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> of vital importance for EU operators in the region whose activities may suffer in the event of non-payment before that date - that is due to non-ratification on the Community side.</en>
      <fr>Elle est par ailleurs tout <Alignment alignment="3093" annotation_id="3357">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3357" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3374">pour</DiscourseConnective> les acteurs de l'Union présents dans la région et dont les activités pourraient être mises en péril <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3479">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de non-versement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3503">avant</DiscourseConnective> la date prévue - en raison de la non-ratification par la Communauté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3279" docOffset="16">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="3589" annotation_id="3287">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3287" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to make reference to the question of relative stability, which was <Alignment alignment="49136" annotation_id="3364">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3364" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> raised by one of the Member States during the June Council, and to remind you that the Commission has no legal obligation to apply the previous allocation of fishing possibilities (i.e. relative stability) under the Fisheries Partnership Agreement, that is agreements which have a financial compensation, such as the one we are considering today.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais <Alignment alignment="7775" annotation_id="3589">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3589" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> m'attarder sur la question de la stabilité relative, <Alignment alignment="3364" annotation_id="3652">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3652" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> soulevée par l'un des États membres lors du Conseil de juin, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3723">et</DiscourseConnective> vous rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3740">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission n'est pas légalement tenue d'appliquer la précédente répartition des possibilités de pêche (<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3850">soit</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité relative) dans le cadre de l'accord de pêche. Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3917">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'accords intégrant une contrepartie financière, tel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3977">que</DiscourseConnective> celui que nous débattons aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3716" docOffset="17">
      <en>This is <Alignment alignment="34749" annotation_id="3724">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3724" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it needs to guarantee that the allocation reflects the best possible option for ensuring value for money (i.e. optimisation of the utilisation for the financial contribution).</en>
      <fr>Il convient <Alignment alignment="6276" annotation_id="4031">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4031" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">en effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de s'assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4053">que</DiscourseConnective> la répartition reflète la meilleure solution possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4111">pour</DiscourseConnective> optimiser l'utilisation de la contrepartie financière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3908" docOffset="18">
      <en>Under these agreements, fishing possibilities should be allocated according to other criteria such as the utilisation rate of the previous protocol, the Member States' requests during negotiations and historical fishing possibilities allocated to the Member States and also the situation/capacity of the fleet.</en>
      <fr>En vertu de ces accords, les possibilités de pêche devraient être affectées en fonction d'autres critères tels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4282">que</DiscourseConnective> le taux d'exploitation sous le précédent protocole, les demandes formulées par les États membres lors des négociations, les possibilités de pêche historiques attribuées aux États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4473">ou encore</DiscourseConnective> la situation/capacité de la flotte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4219" id="492" name="Carmen Fraga Estévez">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4219" docOffset="19">
      <en>rapporteur. - (ES) Mr President, I would like to say that, once again, we have worked very hard in the Committee on Fisheries <Alignment alignment="4642" annotation_id="4345">
          <Alignment alignment="36700" annotation_id="4345">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4345" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the Commission and the European Union can honour their commitments.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (ES) M le Président, j'aimerais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4565">dire que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons une fois de plus travaillé dur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4616">en</DiscourseConnective> commission de la pêche <Alignment alignment="24879" annotation_id="4642">
          <Alignment alignment="4345" annotation_id="4642">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4642" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4665">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne puissent respecter leurs engagements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4421" docOffset="20">
      <en>It was perhaps the Commission's initial lack of interest in the negotiations that led to some of the criticisms in the report about the procedure that was followed, despite the fact that Mauritania continues to be one of the European Union's major fishing partners and despite the fact that the financial contribution is still one of the largest and involves ever-greater commitments towards developing the Community fisheries sector.</en>
      <fr>C'est probablement le manque d'intérêt dont a fait preuve la Commission dans un premier temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4819">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard des négociations qui est à l'origine de certaines critiques mentionnées dans le rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4917">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de la procédure suivie. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4950">Pourtant</DiscourseConnective>, la Mauritanie reste l'un des principaux partenaires de pêche de l'Union <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5032">et</DiscourseConnective> la compensation financière demeure l'une des plus considérables qui soient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5110">et</DiscourseConnective> encourage toujours plus le développement du secteur communautaire de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4856" docOffset="21">
      <en>It is therefore difficult to understand why the text that has been negotiated entails a big reduction in the permissible catch of between 25% and 50% for almost all categories of fish <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5040" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> why, in addition to the technical measures, conditions have been accepted which for us are difficult to understand.</en>
      <fr>On comprend <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5204">dès lors</DiscourseConnective> difficilement pourquoi le texte négocié comprend une importante réduction des captures autorisées, de 25 à 50 %, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5326">pour</DiscourseConnective> la plupart des catégories, ni pourquoi, outre les mesures de nature technique, d'autres conditions difficilement compréhensibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5460">à</DiscourseConnective> nos yeux ont été acceptées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5160" docOffset="22">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5490" annotation_id="5160">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5160" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have said on several occasions in this forum, <Alignment alignment="36449" annotation_id="5212">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5212" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="5556" annotation_id="5216">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5216" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europêche said in a letter to you, Mr Borg, there is not much point in negotiating marvellous fishing opportunities - which is not the case in this Agreement - <Alignment alignment="40054" annotation_id="5379">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5379" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we <Alignment alignment="4678" annotation_id="5385">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5385" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> accept technical conditions which prevent us being able to take proper advantage of those possibilities.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5160" annotation_id="5490">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5490" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous l'avons affirmé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5517">à</DiscourseConnective> plusieurs reprises dans ces murs, <Alignment alignment="26620" annotation_id="5553">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5553" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="7308" annotation_id="5556">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5556" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europêche vous l'a déclaré dans une lettre, M. Borg, il est vain de négocier des possibilités de pêche miraculeuse - ce qui n'est pas le cas dans cet accord - <Alignment alignment="8032" annotation_id="5721">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5721" sense="Contingency.Condition">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="5385" annotation_id="5726">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5726" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> se soumettre à des conditions techniques qui nous empêchent de tirer réellement profit de ces possibilités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5495" docOffset="23">
      <en>The minimum size set for octopus bears no relation to the size set for adjacent areas; the additional two-month biological recovery period negotiated at the last minute, virtually unbeknown to the fisheries sector, was based on a poor quality scientific report and was introduced at the request of the Mauritanian party without the necessary prior consultation of the joint scientific committee; it is based solely on cephalopods, despite the fact that the recovery period affects all categories.</en>
      <fr>La taille minimale fixée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5867">pour</DiscourseConnective> les poulpes n'est pas comparable aux tailles fixées dans les zones adjacentes; la nouvelle période de repos biologique de deux mois négociée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6013">en</DiscourseConnective> dernière minute, pratiquement inconnue jusque-là des acteurs du secteur de la pêche, repose sur un rapport scientifique de qualité moyenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6155">et</DiscourseConnective> a été introduite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6175">à</DiscourseConnective> la demande des négociateurs mauritaniens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6218">sans</DiscourseConnective> consultation préalable du comité scientifique conjoint - elle se base uniquement sur les céphalopodes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6325">alors que</DiscourseConnective> la période de repos affecte toutes les catégories d'espèces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5992" docOffset="24">
      <en>All of this is a disturbing indication of how the European Commission sometimes negotiates.</en>
      <fr>Tous ces éléments ont de quoi laisser perplexe quant aux méthodes de négociation parfois appliquées par la Commission européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6084" docOffset="25">
      <en>It is for this reason, Mr President, Mr Borg, that we must renew our insistence on greater involvement for the European Parliament, at least as an observer at the joint committee meetings, as a minimum institutional transparency requirement, which should have been met some time ago.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6542">pour</DiscourseConnective> laquelle, M le Président, M. Borg, nous devons réitérer notre souhait de voir le Parlement européen être davantage impliqué, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6672">à</DiscourseConnective> tout le moins en qualité d'observateur, lors des réunions du comité conjoint, gage d'un minimum de transparence institutionnelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6803">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devrions appliquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6831">depuis</DiscourseConnective> un certain temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6855">déjà</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6368" docOffset="26">
      <en>It would not be a bad thing, given the new powers which we hope the European Parliament will acquire with the entry into force of the Lisbon Treaty - which was imminent <Alignment alignment="62637" annotation_id="6537">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6537" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am convinced must take place soon - for the Council and the Commission to prepare themselves for involving Parliament in a role which, sooner or later, it will be called upon to fulfil.</en>
      <fr>Il ne serait pas inutile, compte tenu des nouvelles compétences que le Parlement européen devrait -espérons-le - acquérir avec l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6997">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur du Traité de Lisbonne, qui était imminente <Alignment alignment="6537" annotation_id="7051">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7051" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui, j'en suis persuadée, ne devrait plus tarder, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7104">si</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7121">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil s'apprêtaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7149">à</DiscourseConnective> confier au Parlement un rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7180">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il sera tôt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7195">ou</DiscourseConnective> tard amené <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7209">à</DiscourseConnective> jouer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6729" docOffset="27">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="7250" annotation_id="6732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6732" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hinted in the report that we were disappointed that the Commission, and here I am afraid that I have to disagree with you, Mr Borg, had failed to respect the relative stability of the Agreement, by giving itself powers to relax a criterion which on other occasions it has regarded as virtually sacrosanct, an action which we will keep a very close watch on, as our remit demands.</en>
      <fr>Dans le rapport, nous indiquons <Alignment alignment="11705" annotation_id="7250">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7250" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être déçus par la Commission - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7291">et</DiscourseConnective> je crains de devoir marquer mon désaccord avec M. Borg <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7349">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective> - qui n'a pas respecté la stabilité relative fixée par l'accord, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7426">en</DiscourseConnective> se donnant les pouvoirs d'assouplir un critère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7476">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle considérait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7496">comme</DiscourseConnective> sacrosaint dans d'autres circonstances. Nous continuerons donc à faire preuve de vigilance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7593">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7606">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que nous l'oblige notre mandat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7117" docOffset="28">
      <en>I hope that in the case to which you referred, that of cephalopods, the allocation keys based on relative stability and on the historic fishing rights in this fishing ground will be respected.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7653">que</DiscourseConnective> dans le cas mentionné, celui des céphalopodes, les clés de répartition établies en fonction de la stabilité relative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7774">et</DiscourseConnective> des droits de pêche historiques dans cette zone seront respectées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7310" docOffset="29">
      <en>We will be very keen to know the outcome of the meetings which have been scheduled in various fora and joint committees to resolve some of the technical questions to which I referred in the report <Alignment alignment="8025" annotation_id="7507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7507" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which can, as is still the case in Morocco, tie up a fleet which desperately needs access to the fishing opportunities for which it is paying large amounts of money.</en>
      <fr>Nous aimerions connaître l'issue des réunions prévues avec diverses instances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7922">et</DiscourseConnective> divers comités conjoints <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7950">afin de</DiscourseConnective> répondre à certaines questions techniques évoquées dans le rapport <Alignment alignment="3647" annotation_id="8025">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8025" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8033">comme</DiscourseConnective> dans le cas du Maroc, peuvent bloquer une flotte entière qui recherche désespérément un accès aux possibilités de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8159">pour</DiscourseConnective> lesquelles elle débourse d'importantes sommes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7677" docOffset="30">
      <en>Despite all this, with its duration increased to four years, <Alignment alignment="48614" annotation_id="7738">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7738" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you said, this protocol continues, along with the Morocco protocol, to be the most important fisheries collaboration between the European Union and developing countries, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7911" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> for this reason we obviously seek a vote against the two new amendments proposed and swift approval of the Commission proposal.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8211">Malgré tout</DiscourseConnective>, avec l'augmentation de la durée du protocole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8269">à</DiscourseConnective> quatre ans, celui-ci reste <Alignment alignment="7738" annotation_id="8298">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8298" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous l'avez dit, avec le protocole conclu avec le Maroc, la plus importante collaboration en matière de pêche entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8439">et</DiscourseConnective> les pays en développement. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8469">Pour</DiscourseConnective> cette raison, nous souhaitons que les deux nouveaux amendements déposés soient rejetés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8561">et</DiscourseConnective> nous sommes favorables à une adoption rapide de la proposition de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8043" id="493" name="Cornelis Visser">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8043" docOffset="31">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (NL) The fisheries agreement with Mauritania, concluded as recently as 1 August 2006, was due to be extended this year.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe du PPE-DE. - (NL) L'accord de pêche conclu avec la Mauritanie le 1er août 2006 arrivait à terme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8758">à</DiscourseConnective> la fin de cette année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8196" docOffset="32">
      <en>On 14 December last year the Commission suddenly suggested that it should be terminated <Alignment alignment="8876" annotation_id="8284">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8284" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the fishing opportunities were not being fully used by the European fishing fleet, particularly those relating to small pelagic species.</en>
      <fr>Le 14 décembre de l'année dernière, la Commission a soudainement proposé d'y mettre un terme <Alignment alignment="8284" annotation_id="8876">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8876" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">étant donné que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la flotte européenne n'exploitait pas pleinement es possibilités de pêche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8967">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> pour les petites espèces pélagiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8427" docOffset="33">
      <en>This came as a great surprise to us.</en>
      <fr>Cette décision fut prise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9044">à</DiscourseConnective> notre plus grande surprise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8464" docOffset="34">
      <en>Partly at the urging of Parliament itself talks were held to re-negotiate the fisheries protocol.</en>
      <fr>En partie grâce aux pressions exercées par ce Parlement, des discussions ont été mises en place <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9170">afin de</DiscourseConnective> renégocier le protocole de pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8562" docOffset="35">
      <en>The new protocol now put to us by the Commission represents very rigorous cuts compared with the old one.</en>
      <fr>Le nouveau texte soumis par la Commission présente d'importantes coupes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9284">en comparaison</DiscourseConnective> avec l'ancien protocole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8668" docOffset="36">
      <en>Not only are the fishing opportunities for species not fully taken up in previous years cut, <Alignment alignment="26693" annotation_id="8761">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8761" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are severe cuts for all fish species: 25% for cephalopods, 10 to 50% for demersal species and 43% for pelagics, whilst the financial compensation paid to Mauritania remains unchanged or only slightly reduced in the years ahead.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9324">Non seulement</DiscourseConnective> les possibilités de pêche ont été réduites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9381">pour</DiscourseConnective> des espèces qui n'étaient pas pleinement prises en compte jusque là, <Alignment alignment="8761" annotation_id="9455">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9455" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le texte prévoit également d'importantes réductions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9512">pour</DiscourseConnective> toutes les espèces: 25 % <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9542">pour</DiscourseConnective> les céphalopodes, 10 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9568">à</DiscourseConnective> 50 % <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9575">pour</DiscourseConnective> les catégories de pêche démersale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9614">et</DiscourseConnective> 43 % <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9622">pour</DiscourseConnective> les espèces pélagiques. Par ailleurs, la compensation financière reste inchangée, voire légèrement restreinte, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9738">pour</DiscourseConnective> les années à venir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8999" docOffset="37">
      <en>We wonder <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9009" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> these cuts were really necessary <Alignment alignment="31866" annotation_id="9045">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9045" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> what was the rationale behind them, especially <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9096" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective> the fishery sector is currently experiencing great difficulties due to the crisis over fuel prices and the cuts in fishing opportunities.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous interrogeons sur la nécessité de ces réductions <Alignment alignment="9045" annotation_id="9821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9821" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sur la logique sous-jacente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9853">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> compte tenu des grandes difficultés auxquelles se heurte le secteur de la pêche en ces temps de crise, fruits d'une hausse des prix des carburants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10015">et</DiscourseConnective> des réductions des possibilités de pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9240" docOffset="38">
      <en>There would <Alignment alignment="10075" annotation_id="9252">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9252" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> seem to be no obvious reason to limit fishing opportunities further, certainly <Alignment alignment="10166" annotation_id="9336">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9336" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there was no biological or scientific need to do so.</en>
      <fr>Il nous semble <Alignment alignment="9252" annotation_id="10075">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10075" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'aucune raison valable n'existe pour justifier ces nouvelles réductions, a fortiori <Alignment alignment="444" annotation_id="10166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10166" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles ne sont basées sur aucune preuve scientifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10225">ou</DiscourseConnective> biologique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9394" docOffset="39">
      <en>The fishery sector must be able to use any fishing opportunity there is just at present.</en>
      <fr>Le secteur de la pêche doit pouvoir exploiter toutes les possibilités de pêche existantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9483" docOffset="40">
      <en>One possibility, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9500" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>, might be to switch the Mediterranean tuna fishery to Mauritania.</en>
      <fr>L'une des solutions pourrait consister <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10370">à</DiscourseConnective> transférer la pêche au thon en Méditerranée vers la Mauritanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9578" docOffset="41">
      <en>The Dutch pelagic fishing fleet is <Alignment alignment="10487" annotation_id="9613">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9613" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hit by the proposed restrictions, especially on pollock, herring and mackerel.</en>
      <fr>La flotte de pêche pélagique des Pays-Bas est elle <Alignment alignment="21886" annotation_id="10487">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10487" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> durement touchée par ces nouvelles restrictions, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10542">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> concernant le lieu noir, le hareng <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10592">et</DiscourseConnective> le maquereau.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9697" docOffset="42">
      <en>So much for Mauritania.</en>
      <fr>Voilà <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10615">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Mauritanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9721" docOffset="43">
      <en>A brief word or two on the Commission's proposals.</en>
      <fr>Quelques mots <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10649">encore</DiscourseConnective> sur deux des propositions de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9772" docOffset="44">
      <en>I am very happy with these, if not with the proposals on Mauritania.</en>
      <fr>Contrairement aux propositions concernant la Mauritanie, j'accueille ces propositions avec enthousiasme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9841" docOffset="45">
      <en>I think there are many useful pointers for adapting the fleet in response to the fuel crisis and I hope that these new measures will be enough to prevent job losses in the sector.</en>
      <fr>Je pense qu'il existe suffisamment d'indices précieux en faveur d'une adaptation de la flotte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10899">en</DiscourseConnective> réaction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10911">à</DiscourseConnective> la crise du carburant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10935">et</DiscourseConnective> j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10947">que</DiscourseConnective> ces nouvelles mesures suffiront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10983">à</DiscourseConnective> empêcher de nouvelles pertes d'emplois dans le secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10021" id="494" name="Rosa Miguélez Ramos">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10021" docOffset="46">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (ES) Mr President, the noteworthy fact about this new protocol is that <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10122" sense="Comparison.Concession">although</DiscourseConnective> its duration has been extended from two to four years, fishing opportunities have been reduced.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe du PSE. - (ES) M le Président, s'il y a une chose à retenir de ce nouveau protocole, c'est bien que malgré la révision à la hausse de sa durée, les possibilités de pêche ont-elles été revues à la baisse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10227" docOffset="47">
      <en>The allocation of licences under the protocol for category 5 (cephalopods), which gives Spain 24 licences, will not please the Spanish administration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10377" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> that number is not enough to satisfy the applications from the sector directly affected by this category.</en>
      <fr>La répartition des licences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11290">pour</DiscourseConnective> la catégorie 5 (les céphalopodes), qui octroie 24 licences à l'Espagne, n'est pas de nature à plaire aux autorités espagnoles. Ce quota n'est en effet pas suffisant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11460">pour</DiscourseConnective> répondre aux demandes de ce secteur directement concernés par cette catégorie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10491" docOffset="48">
      <en>The Council has the power to decide on a new allocation of licences, taking utilisation into account.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil a le pouvoir de modifier cette répartition des licences en tenant compte de l'exploitation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10593" docOffset="49">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="47346" annotation_id="10593">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10593" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in this case it has not been based on averages but on the period between late 2007 and early 2008, <Alignment alignment="10154" annotation_id="10701">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10701" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the situation engendered by the disputes with Mauritania, due to the use of certain technical measures, led to a large part of the European fleet being reluctant to conclude this Agreement, due to the fear of boarding, <Alignment alignment="12030" annotation_id="10925">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10925" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> happened in the first quarter of 2008.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7630" annotation_id="11647">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11647" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans le cas présent, ce ne sont pas des moyennes qui ont été prises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11726">en</DiscourseConnective> compte, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11737">mais</DiscourseConnective> bien la période entre fin 2007 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11773">et</DiscourseConnective> début 2008, <Alignment alignment="10701" annotation_id="11788">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11788" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les litiges provoqués par le recours des autorités mauritaniennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11862">à</DiscourseConnective> des mesures techniques ont abouti <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11898">à</DiscourseConnective> une situation où les bateaux européens ne souhaitaient plus réellement conclure cet accord par crainte d'être victimes de saisies <Alignment alignment="28333" annotation_id="12030">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12030" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce fut le cas lors du premier trimestre de 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10967" docOffset="50">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10967" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Since</DiscourseConnective> the new protocol has solved the technical problems and opened up a more secure procedure for settling technical differences between the parties, that will surely lead to a greater number of vessels wanting to access this fishing ground, which is becoming safer by the day, and <Alignment alignment="43565" annotation_id="11250">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11250" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> offering more guarantees, than in the previous protocol.</en>
      <fr>Le nouveau protocole apporte des solutions aux problèmes techniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12153">et</DiscourseConnective> prévoit une nouvelle procédure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12187">pour</DiscourseConnective> le traitement des différends techniques entre les parties. Cette évolution devrait assurément inciter davantage de navires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12315">à</DiscourseConnective> accéder aux zones de pêche, de plus en plus sûres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12368">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="11250" annotation_id="12371">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12371" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> offrir de meilleures garanties <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12407">que</DiscourseConnective> dans le cadre de l'ancien protocole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11317" id="495" name="Marie Anne Isler Béguin">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11317" docOffset="51">
      <en>on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group. - (FR) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, <Alignment alignment="12618" annotation_id="11408">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11408" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it comes to fisheries agreements, we Greens have an interpretation which is slightly different from those of the other groups.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. - Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, les Verts ont une analyse légèrement différente de celle des autres partis <Alignment alignment="11408" annotation_id="12618">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12618" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce qui concerne ces accords de pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11540" docOffset="52">
      <en>We regard fisheries agreements as falling not only under the heading of purely and strictly commercial agreements, but also under the heading of European policies.</en>
      <fr>En effet, nous situons les accords de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12703">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> au niveau purement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12736">et</DiscourseConnective> strictement commercial, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12763">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> au niveau des politiques européennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11704" docOffset="53">
      <en>That is why I shall be referring to the opinion of the Committee on Development, which <Alignment alignment="27352" annotation_id="11791">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11791" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> emphasises our commitments on providing development aid and supporting democracy and good governance.</en>
      <fr>Et c'est pour cela que je ferai référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12854">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avis de la commission du développement qui relève <Alignment alignment="11791" annotation_id="12908">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12908" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nos engagements en matière d'aide au développement, de soutien à la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12997">et</DiscourseConnective> de bonne gouvernance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11898" docOffset="54">
      <en>The question which we have already asked in the discussions within the Committee on Fisheries is why the Commission has threatened to terminate the fisheries agreements with Mauritania barely a year <Alignment alignment="59640" annotation_id="12097">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12097" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they were signed.</en>
      <fr>La question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13034">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13049">déjà</DiscourseConnective> posée dans le cadre des discussions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13090">à</DiscourseConnective> la commission de la pêche est: pourquoi la Commission a-t-elle menacé de dénoncer les accords de pêche signés avec la Mauritanie à peine un an <Alignment alignment="12097" annotation_id="13235">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13235" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leur signature?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12121" docOffset="55">
      <en>As far <Alignment alignment="49678" annotation_id="12128">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12128" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are concerned, fisheries agreements are not merely agreements in which we are allowed to utilise a resource and pay for it, <Alignment alignment="13391" annotation_id="12258">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12258" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="13394" annotation_id="12262">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12262" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we utilise less we pay less.</en>
      <fr>Les accords de pêche, <Alignment alignment="12128" annotation_id="13279">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13279" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous, ne sont pas seulement des accords, où d'un côté, on permet de prélever une ressource <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13375">et</DiscourseConnective> on compense, <Alignment alignment="12258" annotation_id="13391">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13391" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="4061" annotation_id="13394">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13394" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'on prélève moins, on compense moins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12296" docOffset="56">
      <en>No, we are cutting fishing opportunities <Alignment alignment="63145" annotation_id="12337">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12337" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European fishing fleet has utilised less in the areas concerned.</en>
      <fr>Non, on réduit <Alignment alignment="2903" annotation_id="13456">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13456" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la flotte européenne a moins prélevé dans ces zones.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12414" docOffset="57">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="40613" annotation_id="12414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12414" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Yet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> is it Mauritania's responsibility, is it Mauritania's fault, <Alignment alignment="16654" annotation_id="12479">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12479" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European fleet has gone elsewhere for certain fishing categories?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5122" annotation_id="13519">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13519" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> est-ce que c'est de la responsabilité, de la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13570">faute de</DiscourseConnective> la Mauritanie, <Alignment alignment="12479" annotation_id="13594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13594" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la flotte européenne s'est dirigée ailleurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13641">pour</DiscourseConnective> certaines catégories de pêche?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12552" docOffset="58">
      <en>We have always asked that fisheries resources be respected in other fisheries agreements, <Alignment alignment="13783" annotation_id="12642">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12642" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have always said that too much was being utilised <Alignment alignment="13828" annotation_id="12699">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12699" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that in any case there would come a time <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12744" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> resources would be reduced.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons toujours demandé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13705">que</DiscourseConnective> la ressource halieutique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13734">soit</DiscourseConnective> respectée dans les autres accords de pêche, <Alignment alignment="25346" annotation_id="13783">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13783" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on a toujours dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13804">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on prélevait trop <Alignment alignment="12699" annotation_id="13828">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13828" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13831">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à un moment donné, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13853">de toute façon</DiscourseConnective>, il y aurait une réduction de la ressource.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12777" docOffset="59">
      <en>This is exactly what is happening at the moment.</en>
      <fr>C'est exactement ce qui se passe actuellement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12826" docOffset="60">
      <en>We agree with the Commission that resources should be restored to the level at which fishing is viable, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12930" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that that is a good thing.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes d'accord avec la Commission pour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14004">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut restaurer la ressource au niveau halieutique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14066">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est une bonne chose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12961" docOffset="61">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14093" annotation_id="12961">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12961" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, there is something else which we certainly do not agree with. During the discussions which took place we asked what would happen <Alignment alignment="3015" annotation_id="13099">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13099" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the compensation is reduced in line with the level of fishing, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13167" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective> the compensation would be reduced from EUR 86 million to EUR 70 million, which would mean that Mauritania's income would be reduced by EUR 40 million over a period of three years.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="22438" annotation_id="14093">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14093" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> là où on n'est pas du tout d'accord, c'est que durant les discussions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14168">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on a eues, nous avons demandé ce qui allait se passer <Alignment alignment="26263" annotation_id="14228">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14228" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">à partir du moment où</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous réduisez la compensation au niveau de la pêche, La compensation passerait donc de 86 millions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14349">à</DiscourseConnective> 70 millions, ce qui veut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14376">dire que</DiscourseConnective> les rentrées financières seraient moindres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14428">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Mauritanie, de l'ordre de 40 millions sur trois ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13355" docOffset="62">You told us, 'There is no problem.</ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13390" docOffset="63">
      <en>We cannot switch from the fishing quota to something different, and decide to work on development <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13488" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">instead</DiscourseConnective>'. We understand this too, <Alignment alignment="14656" annotation_id="13522">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13522" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you undertook, on behalf of the Commission, to ensure that there would be compensation for those EUR 40 million as part of development policy.</en>
      <fr>Donc, vous nous avez dit, "Il n'y a pas de problème, on ne peut pas passer du quota pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14580">à</DiscourseConnective> autre chose, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14595">et</DiscourseConnective> décider de faire du développement"; on le comprend <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14649">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="13522" annotation_id="14656">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14656" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous vous êtes engagés au nom de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14706">à</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14711">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il y ait une compensation de ces 40 millions dans le cadre de la politique du développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13669" docOffset="64">
      <en>Yet today, in this agreement, we cannot see any sign of this compensation except in a footnote which says that the possibility of compensation exists.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14807">Or</DiscourseConnective>, aujourd'hui, dans cet accord, nous ne voyons pas cette compensation sauf dans une note de bas de page qui dit évidemment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14932">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans les faits, la possibilité existe de compenser.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13820" docOffset="65">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14989" annotation_id="13820">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13820" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we do not believe in this compensation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13863" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I think that you have deceived Mauritania to some extent in this agreement, <Alignment alignment="31294" annotation_id="13943">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13943" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> no provision has been made for the agreed compensation.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6070" annotation_id="14989">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14989" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> là, on ne croit pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15014">à</DiscourseConnective> cette compensation, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15045">que</DiscourseConnective> vous avez un peu trompé le pays, la Mauritanie, dans cet accord, <Alignment alignment="13943" annotation_id="15114">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15114" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la compensation accordée n'est pas prévue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14007" docOffset="66">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="15194" annotation_id="14007">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14007" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you will permit, I should just like to remind you that <Alignment alignment="15220" annotation_id="14065">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14065" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I was head of the EU mission covering the elections in Mauritania, the European Union undertook to support this young democracy, yet our first political act is to threaten to terminate the fisheries agreements.</en>
      <fr>Je vous rappellerai juste, <Alignment alignment="14007" annotation_id="15194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15194" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le permettez, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15216">que</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="14065" annotation_id="15220">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15220" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'étais chef de mission pour l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15276">pour</DiscourseConnective> les élections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15295">en</DiscourseConnective> Mauritanie, l'Union européenne s'est engagée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15343">à</DiscourseConnective> soutenir cette jeune démocratie. Le premier acte politique qu'on pose: on menace de dénoncer les accords de pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14281" docOffset="67">
      <en>This is not, in my opinion, a policy of development aid, <Alignment alignment="15525" annotation_id="14338">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14338" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I should really like to know what guarantee you can give us, as MEPs, regarding this compensation for the reduction decided on.</en>
      <fr>Je trouve que ce n'est pas une politique d'aide au développement <Alignment alignment="14338" annotation_id="15525">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15525" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'aimerais vraiment savoir quelle garantie, nous, en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15581">tant que</DiscourseConnective> parlementaires, on peut avoir sur cette compensation par rapport à la réduction qui avait été établie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14470" id="496" name="Jean-Claude Martinez">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14470" docOffset="68">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, the fisheries agreement between Europe and Mauritania, about which our fellow Member and friend Mrs Fraga Estévez has written a report, covers one of the richest regions of the world in terms of fish stocks.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, l'accord de pêche entre l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15749">et</DiscourseConnective> la Mauritanie sur lequel notre collègue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15792">et</DiscourseConnective> amie Carmen a élaboré un rapport concerne une des régions les plus poissonneuses de la planète.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14697" docOffset="69">
      <en>That is why, <Alignment alignment="15918" annotation_id="14710">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14710" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in Dakhla, the former Spanish capital Villa Cisneros, in that part of Western Sahara now under Moroccan control, there is a 40 km sea inlet which is called the Rio de Oro, or Gold River, because of the reflection of sunlight on the scales of the shoals of fish.</en>
      <fr>C'est d'ailleurs pour cela <Alignment alignment="14710" annotation_id="15918">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15918" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'à Dakhla, l'ancienne capitale espagnole de Villa Cisneros, aujourd'hui sous souveraineté marocaine, un bras de mer de 40 km de long <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16065">s'</DiscourseConnective>appelle le Rio de Oro, la rivière d'or, en raison du reflet du soleil sur les écailles des bancs de poissons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14985" docOffset="70">
      <en>In the past, this abundance of fish has actually caused us problems with Morocco.</en>
      <fr>Cette richesse halieutique nous avait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16215">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective> posé un problème avec le Maroc.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15067" docOffset="71">
      <en>Now we are having to tackle a similar problem, but one which concerns fishing in Mauritania from 2008 to 2012. This is an area where octopus and cephalopod stocks, <Alignment alignment="16388" annotation_id="15231">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15231" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, may decline, hence the biological recovery period, <Alignment alignment="39649" annotation_id="15295">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15295" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> where, <Alignment alignment="45544" annotation_id="15306">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15306" sense="Comparison.Contrast">conversely</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is essential to fish for sardines, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15356" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective> the sardine is a predator of the octopus.</en>
      <fr>Là, nous abordons un problème équivalent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16299">mais</DiscourseConnective> concernant la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16324">en</DiscourseConnective> Mauritanie, de 2008 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16347">à</DiscourseConnective> 2012, c'est-à-dire dans une région où, <Alignment alignment="15231" annotation_id="16388">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16388" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la ressource en poulpes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16425">et</DiscourseConnective> en céphalopodes peut baisser, d'où les repos biologiques, <Alignment alignment="15295" annotation_id="16486">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16486" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> où en revanche, <Alignment alignment="15306" annotation_id="16507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16507" sense="Comparison.Contrast">inversement</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il faut pêcher la sardine qui, elle, est un prédateur du poulpe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15404" docOffset="72">
      <en>In practical terms, this means first of all distributing the fishing quotas, the licences, between five European countries, including Spain, obviously, and Italy, but also Portugal, Mr President, <Alignment alignment="16771" annotation_id="15600">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15600" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are some other vessels, freezer trawlers, perhaps from the Baltic States.</en>
      <fr>Concrètement, il s'agit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16609">d'abord</DiscourseConnective> de répartir des quotas de pêche, des licences, entre cinq pays européens: l'Espagne, évidemment, l'Italie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16723">mais</DiscourseConnective>, Monsieur le Président, le Portugal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16764">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="14292" annotation_id="16771">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16771" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il y a quelques navires, peut-être des États baltes, des chalutiers-congélateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15684" docOffset="73">
      <en>After that, it is a matter of reducing catches from approximately 400 000 tons to 250 000 tonnes <Alignment alignment="52670" annotation_id="15781">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15781" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, strangely enough, these quotas are not being used, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15841" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this <Alignment alignment="30184" annotation_id="15850">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15850" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> applies to Moroccan-controlled Western Sahara, which is something, General Morillon, that our Mediterranean tuna fishermen can only dream about.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16856">Ensuite</DiscourseConnective>, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16868">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de ramener les prises de 400 000 tonnes environ <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16923">à</DiscourseConnective> 250 000 tonnes <Alignment alignment="15781" annotation_id="16940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16940" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, curieusement, ces quotas ne sont pas utilisés, ce qui est pareil <Alignment alignment="8766" annotation_id="17016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17016" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> du côté du Sahara marocain, ce qui ferait rêver, mon général Morillon, nos pêcheurs de thon de Méditerranée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16000" docOffset="74">
      <en>In Mauritania, the average use of fishing opportunities ranges from 90% for crustaceans to a mere 22% for tuna.</en>
      <fr>Ici, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17141">en</DiscourseConnective> Mauritanie, l'utilisation des possibilités moyennes de pêche va de 90 % <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17216">pour</DiscourseConnective> les crustacés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17235">à</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17237">simplement</DiscourseConnective> 22 % <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17253">pour</DiscourseConnective> le thon.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16112" docOffset="75">
      <en>As in all these agreements and protocols, there is obviously a financial contribution which is paid for the right to fish, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16235" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> which is round EUR 300-305 million over four years, at the rate of EUR 70 or 80 million a year. Mr Borg has told us how important this contribution is, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16391" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective> it represents approximately 15% of Mauritania's annual budget.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17267">Comme</DiscourseConnective> dans tous ces accords <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17295">et</DiscourseConnective> protocoles, il y a évidemment une contribution financière qui est versée, comme un droit de pêche, qui tourne autour de 300-305 millions sur quatre ans, au rythme de 70 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17467">ou</DiscourseConnective> 80 millions par an, et M. le commissaire nous disait combien ce chiffre est important, représentant à peu près 15 % du budget annuel de la Mauritanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16460" docOffset="76">
      <en>This operation is <Alignment alignment="17637" annotation_id="16478">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16478" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> advantageous for Mauritania <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16511" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> the contribution remains at more or less the same level whereas catches, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16592" sense="Comparison.Contrast">by contrast</DiscourseConnective>, are declining.</en>
      <fr>L'opération est <Alignment alignment="858" annotation_id="17637">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17637" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> intéressante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17661">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Mauritanie qui voit la contribution rester <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17712">à</DiscourseConnective> peu près au <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17726">même</DiscourseConnective> niveau, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17739">alors que</DiscourseConnective> les prises, elles, diminuent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16620" docOffset="77">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17786" annotation_id="16620">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16620" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Mauritanians are causing a serious problem by their harassment of our vessels, and by the boardings which they carry out simply in order to collect fines along the way, <Alignment alignment="42062" annotation_id="16807">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16807" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is true that the European Commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16857" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> Mrs Isler Béguin reminded us just now, has not been particularly sympathetic here, and is now putting pressure on the Mauritanian Government.</en>
      <fr>Il y a <Alignment alignment="3706" annotation_id="17786">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17786" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tout de même</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> du côté mauritanien un problème sérieux tenant au harcèlement de nos navires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17876">et</DiscourseConnective> aux saisies de navires que le pays pratique histoire d'avoir des amendes au passage, <Alignment alignment="16807" annotation_id="17964">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17964" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17981">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne, Mme Isler Béguin le rappelait tout à l'heure, n'a pas été spécialement sympathique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18094">et</DiscourseConnective> a mis le couteau, sinon le poisson, sous la gorge du gouvernement mauritanien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17002" docOffset="78">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18176" annotation_id="17002">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17002" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> fishing is obviously very important in these areas, on the Moroccan side, <Alignment alignment="18264" annotation_id="17085">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17085" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in Dakhla, the fish is exported to Brazil and provides a living for the entire town, hence the concern, on the part of the FAO and the ACP countries, to have a sustainable fishing industry and a code of good conduct.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4035" annotation_id="18176">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18176" sense="Comparison.Concession">Alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans ces régions, la pêche est évidemment très importante, du côté marocain, <Alignment alignment="17085" annotation_id="18264">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18264" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18276">à</DiscourseConnective> Dakhla, le poisson est exporté vers le Brésil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18324">et</DiscourseConnective> fait vivre toute la ville, d'où le souci de la FAO, des ACP, d'avoir une pêche durable, un code de bonne conduite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17314" docOffset="79">
      <en>Mr President, perhaps in spite of the conduct of the European Commission, which has not always been very 'good' during these negotiations with the young democracy of Mauritania, we should <Alignment alignment="19560" annotation_id="17502">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17502" sense="Comparison.Contrast">nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcome this agreement, <Alignment alignment="18663" annotation_id="17539">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17539" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is perhaps one of the last that we shall obtain in this region, <Alignment alignment="18736" annotation_id="17614">
          <Alignment alignment="22458" annotation_id="17614">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17614" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">now that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> Morocco wants to preserve and resume control of its natural resources.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18465">en</DiscourseConnective> dépit peut-être de la conduite de la Commission européenne qui n'a pas toujours été très bonne dans ses négociations avec la jeune démocratie mauritanienne, il faut <Alignment alignment="17502" annotation_id="18633">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18633" sense="Comparison.Contrast">quand même</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> saluer cet accord, <Alignment alignment="17539" annotation_id="18663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18663" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est peut-être un des derniers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18699">que</DiscourseConnective> nous obtiendrons dans la région, <Alignment alignment="7683" annotation_id="18736">
          <Alignment alignment="10382" annotation_id="18736">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18736" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">après que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> le Maroc a voulu conserver <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18773">et</DiscourseConnective> reprendre la maîtrise de ses ressources naturelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17694" id="497" name="Daniel Varela Suanzes-Carpegna">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17694" docOffset="80">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, we had great hopes that renegotiation of the protocol to the Agreement with Mauritania might be able to make up for the previous poor negotiation; we <Alignment alignment="19047" annotation_id="17899">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17899" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> thought that it would serve to rectify the unsatisfactory outcome to the negotiation of the Morocco Agreement for the commercially important cephalopod fleet, which has huge socioeconomic significance in Galicia and has <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18124" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective> been suffering the effects of these two poorly negotiated agreements, in addition to the general crisis in the fisheries sector.</en>
      <fr>(ES) M le Président, M. le commissaire, mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18877">et</DiscourseConnective> messieurs, Nous avions bon espoir que cette renégociation du protocole d'accord avec la Mauritanie compense les faiblesses des négociations précédentes; nous pensions <Alignment alignment="2524" annotation_id="19047">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19047" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19057">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle permettrait de corriger le tir par rapport au <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19111">résultat</DiscourseConnective> décevant de l'accord conclu avec le Maroc <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19162">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'importante flotte de pêche de céphalopodes, qui est particulièrement importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19249">en</DiscourseConnective> Galice sur le plan socioéconomique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19287">et</DiscourseConnective> qui, outre la crise générale du secteur de la pêche, subit tout le poids des deux précédents accords si mal négociés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18263" docOffset="81">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18263" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>, it was not to be, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18290" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="11613" annotation_id="18294">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18294" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we cannot praise or congratulate the Commission on this outcome.</en>
      <fr>C'est malheureusement loin d'être le cas. Nous ne pouvons <Alignment alignment="18294" annotation_id="19466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19466" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> féliciter la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19495">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19503">résultat</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18362" docOffset="82">
      <en>In general, there is a huge reduction in fishing opportunities <Alignment alignment="42419" annotation_id="18425">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18425" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> financial compensation is not tailored to that reduction.</en>
      <fr>D'une manière générale, les possibilités de pêche sont largement réduites <Alignment alignment="4897" annotation_id="19587">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19587" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le montant de la compensation financière ne reflète <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19642">en</DiscourseConnective> rien cette baisse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18487" docOffset="83">
      <en>Little heed has been paid to the sector affected, <Alignment alignment="19722" annotation_id="18537">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18537" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the technical measures which have been agreed, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18588" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">besides</DiscourseConnective> being ambiguous, are prejudicial to the Community fleet.</en>
      <fr>La Commission n'a fait que peu de cas du secteur concerné <Alignment alignment="18537" annotation_id="19722">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19722" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les mesures techniques convenues, au delà de leur ambiguïté, porteront préjudice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19806">à</DiscourseConnective> la flotte communautaire. Si l'on prend le cas des céphalopodes, la taille minimale fixée pour le poulpe est, comme le souligne le rapport, la plus élevée de la région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18653" docOffset="84">
      <en>In the case of cephalopods, the minimum size for octopus, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18711" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> the report said, is the highest in the region, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18761" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> there is no need for it, with the result that this cephalopod fleet has effectively been finished off <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18867" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="32893" annotation_id="18872">
          <Alignment alignment="39726" annotation_id="18872">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18872" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">as if</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> that were not enough, the allocation of licences is damaging to relative stability, which is harmful to the Spanish fleet.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19976">De plus</DiscourseConnective> cette mesure ne répond à aucun besoin et a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20027">pour</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20032">résultat</DiscourseConnective> de porter un coup fatal à la flotte de céphalopodes. Par ailleurs, <Alignment alignment="14694" annotation_id="20108">
          <Alignment alignment="18872" annotation_id="20108">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20108" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">comme si</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> cela ne suffisait pas, la répartition des licences met <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20172">à</DiscourseConnective> mal la stabilité relative, au détriment de la flotte de pêche espagnole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19001" docOffset="85">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19001" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> you will understand, Mr Borg, <Alignment alignment="48791" annotation_id="19034">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19034" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we very much regret the fact, all these considerations mean that we cannot congratulate you on the results achieved in this case, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19173" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> I believe that they could and should have been much better.</en>
      <fr>Vous le comprendrez aisément, M. Borg, <Alignment alignment="7315" annotation_id="20286">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20286" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous le déplorions, tous ces éléments nous empêchent de vous féliciter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20366">pour</DiscourseConnective> les résultats obtenus. Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20403">en effet</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20412">que</DiscourseConnective> vous pourriez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20430">et</DiscourseConnective> devriez viser plus haut.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19241" id="498" name="Joe Borg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19241" docOffset="86">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, first of all I would like to thank you for the interesting comments and the debate that we have had.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) M le Président, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20515">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20526">à</DiscourseConnective> vous remercier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20543">pour</DiscourseConnective> toutes ces remarques dignes d'intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20586">et</DiscourseConnective> pour le débat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20603">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons eu aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19384" docOffset="87">
      <en>I would like to pick up on a couple of points that have been raised.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais m'arrêter sur certains des points soulevés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19453" docOffset="88">
      <en>First of all you are correct to point out that there are fewer fishing opportunities under this revised protocol.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20689">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, vous avez raison d'affirmer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20731">que</DiscourseConnective> les possibilités de pêche qu'offre ce nouveau protocole sont réduites.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19567" docOffset="89">
      <en>This was precisely the reason behind our decision to effect a renegotiation, <Alignment alignment="49335" annotation_id="19644">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19644" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we needed to ensure maximum utilisation of the fishing opportunities, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19722" sense="Comparison.Contrast">whereas</DiscourseConnective> under the previous situation there was significant under-utilisation of the fishing possibilities both with regard to small pelagics and with regard to cephalopods.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20812">par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective> ce qui nous a motivés à entamer une renégociation <Alignment alignment="4937" annotation_id="20875">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20875" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">étant donné que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devions garantir une exploitation maximale des possibilités de pêche. Jusque-là, nous observions d'importantes sous-exploitations de ces possibilités tant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21051">pour</DiscourseConnective> les petites espèces pélagiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21087">que</DiscourseConnective> pour les céphalopodes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19895" docOffset="90">
      <en>On the issue of technical requirements, <Alignment alignment="21177" annotation_id="19935">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19935" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> with regard to dredges, we hope that we will find a solution quickly to this issue, <Alignment alignment="21252" annotation_id="20031">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20031" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Mauritanian authorities are very well disposed to finding a solution to the satisfaction of both sides.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21114">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les obligations techniques, pour le dragage <Alignment alignment="19935" annotation_id="21177">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21177" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous espérons trouver une solution dans les plus brefs délais <Alignment alignment="5725" annotation_id="21252">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21252" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les autorités mauritaniennes sont disposées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21299">à</DiscourseConnective> œuvrer en faveur d'une solution qui satisfait les deux parties.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20143" docOffset="91">
      <en>Regarding rest periods, this request came originally from the industry <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20214" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective> they maintain that, after such rest periods, catches become more profitable.</en>
      <fr>Concernant les périodes de repos, cette demande émane au départ de l'industrie elle-même qui estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21465">que</DiscourseConnective> les prises sont plus rentables lorsqu'elles suivent une période de repos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20297" docOffset="92">
      <en>On the question of setting the minimum size for octopus at 500 g, I need to make the point that we are dealing with a third country, a sovereign nation, Mauritania, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20462" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> its own regulation specifies that the minimum size for octopus is 500 g.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21543">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la taille minimale du poulpe, établie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21600">à</DiscourseConnective> 500 g, il me faut rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21629">que</DiscourseConnective> nous négocions ici avec un pays souverain, la Mauritanie et que sa propre réglementation dans ce domaine fixe à 500 g la taille minimale de cette espèce.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20539" docOffset="93">
      <en>This was a line we could not cross during negotiations: one cannot ask a third country to change its legislation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20652" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> it is interesting to our own fishermen to catch smaller-sized cephalopods.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pouvions pas franchir cette ligne: comment demander à un pays de modifier sa législation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21884">pour</DiscourseConnective> la simple raison que nos pêcheurs souhaitent capturer de plus petits céphalopodes?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20735" docOffset="94">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20735" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>, we do recognise that there is not one harmonised regulation on the subject in the region.</en>
      <fr>Nous reconnaissons bien entendu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22004">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il n'existe pas de réglementation harmonisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22052">en</DiscourseConnective> la matière dans cette région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20834" docOffset="95">
      <en>There are other countries which allow catches of cephalopods of smaller size, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20912" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="37161" annotation_id="20916">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20916" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a decision on this matter should be taken within the COPACE organisation.</en>
      <fr>D'autres pays autorisent les prises de céphalopodes de moindre taille. Il conviendrait <Alignment alignment="20916" annotation_id="22172">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22172" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de prendre une décision sur ce point dans le cadre du COPACE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21000" docOffset="96">
      <en>On the issue of allocation keys, i.e. what is known as 'relative stability', <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21077" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> I said before the Commission is not bound to transfer relative stability from one agreement to another or from one protocol to another.</en>
      <fr>Concernant les clés de répartition, ce que l'on appelle la "stabilité relative", j'ai déjà affirmé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22338">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission n'était nullement tenue de transférer une stabilité relative d'un accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22429">à</DiscourseConnective> l'autre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22439">ou</DiscourseConnective> d'un protocole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22457">à</DiscourseConnective> l'autre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21216" docOffset="97">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="25720" annotation_id="21216">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21216" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is provided for in the agreement and in the protocol that, should Member States need more opportunities, and should such requests be based on science, on the state of the stock, then such requests could certainly be considered, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21456" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I would undertake to take them up with Mauritania in order to negotiate increases, as in the case <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21558" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective> of cephalopods, <Alignment alignment="22863" annotation_id="21586">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21586" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is a specific request to do so.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3729" annotation_id="22468">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22468" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22488">et</DiscourseConnective> le protocole prévoient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22514">que si</DiscourseConnective> les États membres souhaitent bénéficier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22561">de plus</DiscourseConnective> de possibilités de pêche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22595">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22598">si</DiscourseConnective> ces demandes se basent sur des faits scientifiques et sur l'état des stocks, celles-ci pourraient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22699">alors</DiscourseConnective> être prises en considération. Je me chargerais alors de les soumettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22775">à</DiscourseConnective> la Mauritanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22791">afin de</DiscourseConnective> négocier des révisions à la hausse, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22835">comme pour</DiscourseConnective> les céphalopodes <Alignment alignment="14204" annotation_id="22863">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22863" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une demande spécifique est soumise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22901">en ce sens</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21627" docOffset="98">
      <en>I need to make the point that with regard to cephalopods licences were utilised on 22 occasions <Alignment alignment="23016" annotation_id="21723">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21723" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in the new protocol there is provision for 25, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21774" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective> we are actually catering for creating a buffer, allowing for utilisation.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22922">à</DiscourseConnective> signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22933">que</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22937">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce qui est des céphalopodes, les licences ont été utilisées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23002">à</DiscourseConnective> 22 reprises <Alignment alignment="3719" annotation_id="23016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23016" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le nouveau protocole en prévoit 25. Nous veillons donc <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23074">à</DiscourseConnective> mettre en place une certaine marge susceptible d'être exploitée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21851" docOffset="99">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11441" annotation_id="21851">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21851" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the particular Member State involved maintains that they have requests in excess of 25, <Alignment alignment="11782" annotation_id="21942">
          <Alignment alignment="23228" annotation_id="21942">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21942" sense="Contingency.Condition">as long as</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> they give us the specific facts, we will take those up with Mauritania in order to bring about an increase, always as long as the state of the stock allows.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="21851" annotation_id="23141">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23141" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un État membre particulier maintien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23180">que</DiscourseConnective> ses demandes dépassent le chiffre de 25, et <Alignment alignment="21942" annotation_id="23228">
          <Alignment alignment="21942" annotation_id="23228">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23228" sense="Contingency.Condition">pour autant qu'</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>il nous livre des éléments spécifiques, nous soumettrons la demande de révision à la hausse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23335">à</DiscourseConnective> la Mauritanie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23352">dans la mesure où</DiscourseConnective> l'état des stocks le permet bien entendu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22110" docOffset="100">
      <en>I need to underline the fact that with regard to cephalopods we do have problems concerning the sustainability and the health of the stock.</en>
      <fr>J'insiste sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23434">que</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23438">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce qui est des céphalopodes, il n'existe aucun problème en termes de santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23518">et</DiscourseConnective> de viabilité des stocks.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22250" docOffset="101">
      <en>Again on the question of this whole issue of relative stability, I would <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22323" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> like to point out that one cannot have one's cake and eat it.</en>
      <fr>Pour revenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23559">à</DiscourseConnective> la question de la stabilité relative, on ne peut avoir à la fois le beurre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23636">et</DiscourseConnective> l'argent du beurre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22390" docOffset="102">
      <en>On one hand, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22403" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> it comes to the allocation of cephalopods, the allocation seems not to please one particular Member State. <Alignment alignment="23760" annotation_id="22515">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22515" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22519" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22524" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> it comes to tuna where there is a significant increase of allocations for that same Member State, then that works out in the Member State's favour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22676" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> we have received no complaints in that regard.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23659">D'un côté</DiscourseConnective>, la répartition concernant les céphalopodes ne semble pas plaire à un certain État membre, <Alignment alignment="2938" annotation_id="23760">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23760" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je n'ai pas entendu ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23788">même</DiscourseConnective> État membre se plaindre de l'augmentation de la répartition dont il a bénéficié concernant la pêche au thon.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22727" docOffset="103">
      <en>Concerning the reason for the denunciation and the renegotiation of the protocol, namely that it was under-utilised, again I would like to make the point made by Mrs Isler Béguin that such agreements are not only about fisheries but also about development assistance.</en>
      <fr>En ce qui concerne les motivations qui ont conduit à l'annulation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23968">et</DiscourseConnective> à la renégociation du protocole - sa sous-exploitation -, j'aimerais revenir sur le point soulevé par Mme Isler Béguin selon lequel ces accords ne concernent pas uniquement la pêche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24154">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> l'aide au développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22995" docOffset="104">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24190" annotation_id="22995">
          <Alignment alignment="24190" annotation_id="22995">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22995" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="58339" annotation_id="23004">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23004" sense="Comparison.Contrast">whereas</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have decreased the financial component for fishing opportunities, there is a clear undertaking on our part to increase the development component, <Alignment alignment="12528" annotation_id="23161">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23161" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are fully committed to respect this.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10459" annotation_id="24190">
          <Alignment alignment="11784" annotation_id="24190">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24190" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En réalité</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="11221" annotation_id="24202">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24202" sense="Comparison.Contrast">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons diminué la contrepartie financière des possibilités de pêche, nous nous engageons également clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24319">à</DiscourseConnective> consolider le volet "développement" <Alignment alignment="9224" annotation_id="24357">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24357" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons la ferme intention de tenir nos promesses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23205" docOffset="105">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24414" annotation_id="23205">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23205" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in total, the financial allocation has been maintained over the four-year term.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19666" annotation_id="24414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24414" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24430">au total</DiscourseConnective>, l'enveloppe financière est maintenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24477">pour</DiscourseConnective> la période de quatre ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23296" docOffset="106">
      <en>The budgetary support to the 10th EDF will compensate for the remaining EUR 40 million for 2009/10-2012 at the rate of EUR 10 million per year <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23439" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this means that Mauritania will be receiving a financial package which, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23515" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> you take into account both what they are receiving by way of compensation for fishing opportunities - which have been reduced on the basis of what was actually being fished in Mauritanian waters - and the increase to the budgetary support through the 10th EDF ad hoc compensation within this protocol, we end up with a situation where the total package is equivalent to the fishing package that they had under the previous financial protocol.</en>
      <fr>Le soutien budgétaire au titre du 10e FED compensera les 40 millions d'euros restants pour la période 2009/10-2012 au rythme de 10 millions par an. En d'autres termes, la Mauritanie recevra une enveloppe financière qui équivaudra, compte tenu de la contrepartie financière versée pour les possibilités de pêche - et réduites en fonction des captures réellement effectuées dans les eaux mauritaniennes - et de la hausse du soutien budgétaire par l'intermédiaire du 10e FED, à l'enveloppe prévue pour la pêche dans le cadre de l'ancien protocole financier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23963" docOffset="107">
      <en>Finally on the issue of boarding I would like to say that a meeting of the working group will be held this Sunday, this weekend, in order to discuss this specific issue and to agree on recommendations and guidelines that should solve the issue.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25063">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, en ce qui concerne les saisies, je signale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25113">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une réunion du groupe de travail se tiendra dimanche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25169">afin de</DiscourseConnective> débattre de la question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25201">et</DiscourseConnective> de convenir de lignes directrices <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25238">et</DiscourseConnective> de recommandations destinées à apporter une réponse au problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24208" docOffset="108">
      <en>On the point made by Mrs Fraga at the very outset concerning participation of MEPs, the Commission considers that the same approach that is followed for the participation of MEPs in bilateral negotiations has to be followed as regards joint committees where the two parties are officially represented.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25306">Pour</DiscourseConnective> répondre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25320">à</DiscourseConnective> Mme Fraga <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25332">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de la participation des députés européens, la Commission estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25405">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut appliquer aux comités conjoints la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25451">même</DiscourseConnective> approche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25465">que</DiscourseConnective> pour les négociations bilatérales où les deux parties sont officiellement représentées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24510" docOffset="109">
      <en>The Commission will, <Alignment alignment="25582" annotation_id="24531">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24531" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, continue to cooperate with Parliament on the basis of the framework agreement that exists.</en>
      <fr>La Commission continuera <Alignment alignment="13258" annotation_id="25582">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25582" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de coopérer avec le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25622">en</DiscourseConnective> se basant sur l'accord-cadre existant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="24631" id="499" name="Carmen Fraga Estévez">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="24631" docOffset="110">
      <en>rapporteur. - (ES) Mr President, I will try to be systematic.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (ES) M le Président, Je vais essayer de faire preuve de méthode.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24693" docOffset="111">
      <en>In the first place, with regard to the point made by Mrs Isler Béguin, I would point out that the funds for development cooperation increase over the four years that the protocol is in force.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25743">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, concernant le point soulevé par Mme Isler Béguin, j'aimerais souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25828">que</DiscourseConnective> les fonds alloués à la coopération au développement seront plus élevés au cours des quatre années de vie du protocole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>

<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24886" docOffset="113">
      <en>It is the total financial contribution which is being reduced by 19 %, but amounts allocated to development cooperation are increasing to EUR 11 million, EUR 16 million, EUR 18 million and EUR 20 million, so as far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25101" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> development cooperation is concerned you need have no worries, <Alignment alignment="2281" annotation_id="25167">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25167" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> those amounts are actually being increased.</en>
      <fr>Les montants consacrés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26051">à</DiscourseConnective> la coopération au développement augmentent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26096">et</DiscourseConnective> passent respectivement à 11 millions d'euros, 16 millions d'euros, 18 millions d'euros et 20 millions d'euros. Vous n'avez donc aucune inquiétude à avoir sur le plan de la coopération au développement <Alignment alignment="26755" annotation_id="26300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26300" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les sommes allouées augmenteront.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25219" docOffset="114">
      <en>Mr Borg, as regards the minimum size for octopus, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25269" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="26398" annotation_id="25273">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25273" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the technical measures are important for take-up of fishing opportunities, I would say that this is not a problem which needs to be dealt with at this juncture.</en>
      <fr>M. Borg, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26347">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la taille minimale des poulpes, <Alignment alignment="21451" annotation_id="26398">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26398" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">étant donné que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les mesures techniques jouent un rôle important dans l'exploitation des possibilités de pêche, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26518">que</DiscourseConnective> le moment n'est pas venu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26547">pour</DiscourseConnective> traiter ce problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25440" docOffset="115">
      <en>You know very well that the matter is still pending.</en>
      <fr>Vous savez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26584">que</DiscourseConnective> la question reste à ce jour pendante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25493" docOffset="116">
      <en>I keep on saying this: the size is the highest in the whole region.</en>
      <fr>Je n'ai de cesse de le répéter: la taille fixée est la plus élevée de la région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25561" docOffset="117">
      <en>The Fishery Committee for the Eastern Central Atlantic (CECAF) said at its meeting this year that a common minimum size should be set for the whole region <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25716" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I think that here the Commission should make an effort to ensure that this matter ceases to be an issue.</en>
      <fr>Le Comité des pêches <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26728">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Atlantique Centre-Est (COPACE) a déclaré lors de la réunion tenue cette année <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26813">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une taille minimale commune devrait être établie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26865">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble de la région. Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26904">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission devrait prendre l'initiative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26951">afin que</DiscourseConnective> cette question ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26978">soit</DiscourseConnective> plus considérée comme un problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25825" docOffset="118">
      <en>The report drawn up by the Mauritanian scientific committee states that in November, <Alignment alignment="27099" annotation_id="25910">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25910" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, 50% of the catch in the Mauritanian fishing ground can be octopus of between 300 and 500 grams, <Alignment alignment="27216" annotation_id="26019">
          <Alignment alignment="64247" annotation_id="26019">
            <Alignment alignment="27398" annotation_id="26019">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26019" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> there is a problem with minimum size in the Mauritanian fishing ground and elsewhere.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport rédigé par le comité scientifique mauritanien affirme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27083">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> novembre, <Alignment alignment="25910" annotation_id="27099">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27099" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, 50 % des prises effectuées dans la zone mauritanienne sont formées de poulpes entre 300 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27200">et</DiscourseConnective> 500 grammes. <Alignment alignment="26019" annotation_id="27216">
          <Alignment alignment="1488" annotation_id="27216">
            <Alignment alignment="26019" annotation_id="27216">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27216" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, il y a manifestement un problème concernant la taille minimale dans la zone de pêche mauritanienne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27335">et</DiscourseConnective> ailleurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26120" docOffset="119">
      <en>With regard to relative stability, I am not going to get into an argument with you, <Alignment alignment="27431" annotation_id="26204">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26204" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is a topic which we have discussed in Parliament, one which is in the basic regulation which we have been discussing along with the regulation of licences for third countries, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26389" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> the initial allocation is another matter.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27348">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la stabilité relative, je ne tiens pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27406">à</DiscourseConnective> me disputer avec vous, <Alignment alignment="26204" annotation_id="27431">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27431" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons déjà discuté de la question au Parlement. Nous en avons déjà discuté dans le cadre de la réglementation générale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27560">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que de la réglementation des licences aux pays tiers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>


<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26437" docOffset="122">
      <en>The initial allocation needs to respect historical rights <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26495" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26499" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="28607" annotation_id="26504">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26504" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, under that allocation, fishing opportunities are not taken up, the Commission may, I agree, give them to whoever wants them and applies for them, <Alignment alignment="46034" annotation_id="26654">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26654" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> initially it is the historical rights which must be respected <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26720" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>, in the case of category five in Mauritania, this has not been the case, Mr Borg.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="26504" annotation_id="27735">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27735" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les possibilités de pêche ne sont pas exploitées dans le cadre de cette répartition, alors la Commission - je vous l'accorde - est autorisée à les attribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27895">à</DiscourseConnective> quiconque en formule la demande. <Alignment alignment="26654" annotation_id="27930">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27930" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans un premier temps, il convient de respecter les droits historiques, ce qui n'a pas été le cas pour la catégorie 5 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28053">en</DiscourseConnective> Mauritanie, M. Borg.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26806" docOffset="123">
      <en>I will not elaborate any further.</en>
      <fr>Je vais m'arrêter là.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26840" docOffset="124">
      <en>I could answer more questions, <Alignment alignment="30919" annotation_id="26871">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26871" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I think that, even <Alignment alignment="3677" annotation_id="26894">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26894" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I cannot see very well without my glasses, I have run out of time.</en>
      <fr>Je pourrais répondre à d'autres questions, <Alignment alignment="26871" annotation_id="28142">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28142" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28156">que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="26894" annotation_id="28161">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28161" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je n'y voie pas grand-chose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28198">sans</DiscourseConnective> mes lunettes, le temps qui m'était imparti est dépassé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="26968" id="500" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="26968" docOffset="125">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>(PT) Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26990" docOffset="126">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow, 10 July 2008.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain, le 10 juillet 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
