<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>10.</en>
    <fr>10.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Lifelong learning for knowledge, creativity and innovation - 'Education and Training 2010 work programme' (</en>
    <fr>L'éducation et la formation tout au long de la vie au service de la connaissance, de la créativité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="103">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'innovation - Mise en œuvre du programme de travail «Éducation et formation 2010» (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="112" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="196">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="131" id="093" name="Ljudmila Novak">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="131" docOffset="3">
      <en>rapporteur. - (SL) It is clear from the joint report of the Council and the Commission for 2008 that some progress has been made as regards lifelong learning, <Alignment alignment="414" annotation_id="290">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="290" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we cannot be satisfied with the achievements so far.</en>
      <fr>rapporteure. - (SL) Il ressort clairement du rapport conjoint du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="283">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="303">pour</DiscourseConnective> 2008 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="313">que</DiscourseConnective> certains progrès ont été réalisés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="351">en</DiscourseConnective> matière d'éducation et de formation tout au long de la vie, <Alignment alignment="698" annotation_id="414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="414" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne pouvons pas nous satisfaire des accomplissements actuels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="347" docOffset="4">
      <en>Some of the greatest challenges are students dropping out of education at an early age, poor participation in lifelong learning amongst older and low-skilled workers and poor skills levels amongst migrant workers.</en>
      <fr>Parmi les plus grands défis figurent la déscolarisation précoce de certains jeunes, la faible participation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="593">à</DiscourseConnective> l'apprentissage tout au long de la vie des travailleurs âgés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="656">et</DiscourseConnective> des personnes peu qualifiées, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="689">et</DiscourseConnective> les faibles niveaux de compétences des travailleurs migrants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="561" docOffset="5">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="754" annotation_id="561">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="561" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, a knowledge-based economy will need an increasingly better skilled labour force.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="561" annotation_id="754">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="754" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, une économie fondée sur la connaissance aura besoin d'une main-d'œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="835">de plus</DiscourseConnective> en plus qualifiée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="651" docOffset="6">
      <en>I have stressed in my report that we need to improve the quality of education on all levels <Alignment alignment="970" annotation_id="743">
          <Alignment alignment="970" annotation_id="743">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="743" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> it can equip children and young people for autonomous, creative and innovative thinking and learning.</en>
      <fr>J'ai insisté dans mon rapport sur la nécessité d'améliorer la qualité de l'enseignement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="950">à</DiscourseConnective> tous les échelons <Alignment alignment="743" annotation_id="970">
          <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="970">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="970" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de sorte que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> les enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="995">et</DiscourseConnective> les jeunes puissent penser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1025">et</DiscourseConnective> apprendre de façon autonome, créative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1066">et</DiscourseConnective> innovante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="853" docOffset="7">
      <en>Curricula need to be continuously modernised and the use of information technology increased amongst older people.</en>
      <fr>Les cursus doivent être modernisés en permanence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1129">et</DiscourseConnective> l'utilisation des technologies de l'information par les personnes plus âgées doit être accrue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="968" docOffset="8">
      <en>Lifelong learning programmes must be related to the economy and support entrepreneurship, enabling citizens to acquire the kind of knowledge that will help them establish, run and develop their own businesses.</en>
      <fr>Les programmes d'apprentissage tout au long de la vie doivent répondre aux besoins de l'économie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1324">et</DiscourseConnective> militer en faveur de l'esprit d'entreprise, en permettant à des citoyens d'acquérir les connaissances qui les aideront à fonder, diriger <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1464">et</DiscourseConnective> développer leurs propres entreprises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1178" docOffset="9">
      <en>It is important to take into account local and regional needs, potentials and characteristics.</en>
      <fr>Il est important de tenir compte des possibilités, des caractéristiques et des besoins à l'échelle locale et régionale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1273" docOffset="10">
      <en>I call on the governments of the Member States and the institutions of the European Union not to cut resources for education at this time of financial crisis, <Alignment alignment="507662" annotation_id="1432">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1432" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> high-quality education that is available to all sections of the population is the best weapon against poverty and the best tool for finding a solution to the crisis.</en>
      <fr>J'exhorte les gouvernements des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1671">et</DiscourseConnective> les institutions de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1713">à</DiscourseConnective> ne pas réduire les ressources affectées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1755">à</DiscourseConnective> l'enseignement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1772">en</DiscourseConnective> cette période de crise financière, <Alignment alignment="616" annotation_id="1810">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1810" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un enseignement de qualité accessible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1852">à</DiscourseConnective> toutes les couches de la population est la meilleure arme contre la pauvreté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1931">et</DiscourseConnective> le meilleur outil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1952">pour</DiscourseConnective> trouver une solution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1978">à</DiscourseConnective> la crise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1606" docOffset="11">
      <en>Thank you to all my fellow Members and to the Bureau for your cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Merci <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1996">à</DiscourseConnective> tous mes collègues parlementaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2032">et</DiscourseConnective> au Bureau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2045">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur coopération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1681" docOffset="12">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
