<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>1.</en>
    <fr>1.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Nicaragua</en>
    <fr>Nicaragua</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="13" id="220" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13" docOffset="2">
      <en>The next point is the three draft resolutions on Nicaragua.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle trois propositions de résolutions sur le Nicaragua.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="73" id="221" language="PL" name="Bogusław Sonik">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="73" docOffset="3">
      <en>Mr President, the policy of the current President of Nicaragua, Daniel Ortega, proves the continued relevance of the old communist maxim: 'once we have gained power we will never give it up'.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, la politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="125">que</DiscourseConnective> poursuit l'actuel président du Nicaragua, Daniel Ortega, démontre que l'ancienne maxime communiste "<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="229">lorsque</DiscourseConnective> nous serons arrivés au pouvoir, nous ne l'abandonnerons jamais" est toujours d'actualité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="265" docOffset="4">
      <en>In the 1980s, the Sandinistas were unable to maintain an armed dictatorship and, forced by international opinion, had to accept democratic rules of play.</en>
      <fr>Dans les années 80, les sandinistes n'ont pas pu maintenir une dictature armée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="406">et</DiscourseConnective>, poussés par l'opinion internationale, ils ont dû accepter des règles démocratiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="419" docOffset="5">
      <en>Ortega was elected President in elections in 2006.</en>
      <fr>Ortega est devenu président du Nicaragua <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="535">à</DiscourseConnective> l'issue des élections de 2006.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="470" docOffset="6">
      <en>The Sandinistas returned to power.</en>
      <fr>Les sandinistes sont revenus au pouvoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="505" docOffset="7">
      <en>From the very outset, he began to use the tried and tested methods of intimidation and elimination, under a variety of pseudo-legal pretexts, of any kind of political competition.</en>
      <fr>Dès le début, Ortega a eu recours à des méthodes testées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="666">et</DiscourseConnective> éprouvées d'intimidation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="694">et</DiscourseConnective> d'élimination, sous une série de prétextes pseudo-légaux, à l'encontre de ses opposants politiques de tous bords.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="685" docOffset="8">
      <en>The Sandinista apparatus began to duplicate state apparatus, following the example of the Cuban Committees for the Defence of the Revolution.</en>
      <fr>L'appareil sandiniste a commencé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="844">à</DiscourseConnective> reproduire l'appareil d'État, suivant l'exemple des comités cubains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="914">pour</DiscourseConnective> la défense de la révolution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="827" docOffset="9">
      <en>In December 2008, the European Parliament drew attention to the campaign of harassment being perpetrated by state authorities, parties and people associated with the Sandinistas against human rights organisations and their members, journalists and representatives of the media.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="948">En</DiscourseConnective> décembre 2008, le Parlement européen a attiré l'attention sur la campagne de harcèlement dont font l'objet les organisation de défense des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1108">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que leurs membres, les journalistes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1150">et</DiscourseConnective> les représentants des médias de la part des autorités gouvernementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1224">et</DiscourseConnective> d'individus et de partis liés aux sandinistes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1105" docOffset="10">
      <en>Amnesty International wrote of the violence which followed local authority elections.</en>
      <fr>Amnesty International a écrit sur la violence qui a suivi les élections locales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1191" docOffset="11">
      <en>Attacks and beatings of journalists multiplied.</en>
      <fr>Le nombre de journalistes agressés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1390">et</DiscourseConnective> victimes de violences est monté en flèche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1239" docOffset="12">
      <en>Now, by manipulating the Supreme Court, Ortega is trying to bring about changes to the Constitution which would allow him to stand for re-election.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1449">en</DiscourseConnective> manipulant la Cour suprême, Ortega essaie de modifier la Constitution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1522">afin qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle lui permette de se représenter lors des prochaines élections.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1387" docOffset="13">
      <en>We can foresee, with a high degree of certainty, that the next step will be proclaiming himself President for life, for Fidel Castro is the model for the populists of Managua and Caracas, <Alignment alignment="36485" annotation_id="1575">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1575" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there have never been free elections under Castro.</en>
      <fr>Nous pouvons prévoir avec un degré élevé de certitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1651">que</DiscourseConnective> sa prochaine manœuvre sera de se proclamer président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1708">à</DiscourseConnective> vie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1715">car</DiscourseConnective> Fidel Castro est le modèle des populistes de Managua <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1772">et</DiscourseConnective> de Caracas, <Alignment alignment="1575" annotation_id="1787">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1787" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'il n'y a jamais eu d'élections libres sous Castro.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1630" docOffset="14">
      <en>I call on the European Commission to draw conclusions from this situation and to check, in a situation of the violation of international human rights standards, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1791" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> there is not a need to reconsider existing cooperation agreements with this country, <Alignment alignment="6548" annotation_id="1879">
          <Alignment alignment="8285" annotation_id="1879">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1879" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the human rights clauses do not turn out to be merely empty words.</en>
      <fr>Je demande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1855">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne de tirer les conclusions de cette situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1926">et</DiscourseConnective> d'envisager la nécessité, dans ce contexte de violation des normes internationales en matière de droits de l'homme, de reconsidérer les accords de coopération existants avec ce pays, <Alignment alignment="15552" annotation_id="2112">
          <Alignment alignment="1879" annotation_id="2112">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2112" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> les clauses relatives aux droits de l'homme ne soient pas de simples paroles creuses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1954" id="222" language="PL" name="Adam Bielan">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1954" docOffset="15">
      <en>Mr President, last Saturday, in response to an appeal from opposition politicians, tens of thousands of Nicaraguan citizens demonstrated against the policy of President Daniel Ortega, a policy which is leading directly to the introduction of a dictatorship in Nicaragua.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, samedi dernier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2246">à</DiscourseConnective> la suite d'un appel lancé par les hommes politiques de l'opposition, des dizaines de milliers de citoyens nicaraguayens ont manifesté contre la politique du président Ortega, une politique qui conduit tout droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2460">à</DiscourseConnective> l'instauration d'une dictature au Nicaragua.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2225" docOffset="16">
      <en>I will remind you that on 19 October, the Supreme Court decided to remove constitutional obstacles which prevented President Ortega from standing for a further term of office.</en>
      <fr>Je vous rappelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2524">que</DiscourseConnective> le 19 octobre, la Cour suprême a décidé de lever les obstacles constitutionnels qui empêchaient le président Ortega de se présenter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2660">à</DiscourseConnective> un second mandat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2401" docOffset="17">
      <en>The fact of this change itself is not outrageous, <Alignment alignment="2713" annotation_id="2451">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2451" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, of course, there is no such law in many European countries, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2520" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> what is outrageous is the way in which this decision was made.</en>
      <fr>Cela n'est pas scandaleux en soi <Alignment alignment="2451" annotation_id="2713">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2713" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, évidemment, une telle loi n'existe pas dans bon nombre des pays européens. Ce qui est scandaleux par contre, c'est la manière dont cette décision a été prise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2587" docOffset="18">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2877" annotation_id="2587">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2587" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we all know, President Ortega does not have a two-thirds majority in Parliament, <Alignment alignment="34416" annotation_id="2671">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2671" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="23870" annotation_id="2675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2675" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he had to turn to violating the constitution in order to remove the ban on his re-election.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2587" annotation_id="2877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2877" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous le savons tous, le président Ortega ne dispose pas d'une majorité des deux tiers au parlement, <Alignment alignment="2671" annotation_id="2983">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2983" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il a <Alignment alignment="2675" annotation_id="2991">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2991" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dû enfreindre la constitution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3026">afin de</DiscourseConnective> lever l'interdiction pesant sur sa réélection.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2770" docOffset="19">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3081" annotation_id="2770">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2770" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we allow Daniel Ortega to run for President again in 2011, we may wake up in a situation in which Nicaragua is controlled by a real dictatorship.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2770" annotation_id="3081">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3081" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous permettons à Daniel Ortega de se représenter aux élections présidentielles de 2011, le Nicaragua pourrait tomber sous l'emprise d'une une véritable dictature.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2919" docOffset="20">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3259" annotation_id="2919">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2919" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I would ask the European Commission to draw attention to this problem during further negotiations on the EU-Central America Association Agreement and to use every possible means to turn President Ortega back from this road.</en>
      <fr>Je demande <Alignment alignment="2919" annotation_id="3259">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3259" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à la Commission européenne d'attirer l'attention sur ce problème dans le cadre des futures négociations relatives à l'accord d'association UE - Amérique centrale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3426">et</DiscourseConnective> d'utiliser tous les moyens dont elle dispose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3474">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire faire marche arrière au président Ortega.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3154" id="223" name="Johannes Cornelis van Baalen">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3154" docOffset="21">
      <en>author. - Mr President, I am very thankful for the support in this House for the delegation of Liberal International which I led to Managua.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je remercie vivement cette Assemblée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3587">pour</DiscourseConnective> le soutien qu'elle a apporté à la délégation de l'Internationale libérale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3666">que</DiscourseConnective> j'ai dirigée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3683">à</DiscourseConnective> Managua.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3295" docOffset="22">
      <en>We came in peace on the invitation of a parliamentary majority to speak about the Constitution, the election, the election campaign and human rights and civil liberties.</en>
      <fr>Nous y sommes allés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3714">en</DiscourseConnective> paix, sur l'invitation d'une majorité parlementaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3770">afin de</DiscourseConnective> parler de la Constitution, des élections, de la campagne électorale, des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3869">et</DiscourseConnective> des libertés civiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3465" docOffset="23">
      <en>We were cursed, we were called pirates and that kind of thing.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons été insultés, nous avons été traités de "pirates" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3955">et</DiscourseConnective> autres choses du genre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3528" docOffset="24">
      <en>We were threatened with expulsion from the country, threatened with being persona non grata, <Alignment alignment="17606" annotation_id="3621">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3621" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it was said that we were staging a golpe - a coup d'état.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons été menacés d'être expulsés et déclarés persona non grata, <Alignment alignment="3621" annotation_id="4052">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4052" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il a été dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4068">que</DiscourseConnective> nous préparions un golpe - un coup d'État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3683" docOffset="25">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3683" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>, more importantly than that, they cursed my country <Alignment alignment="4168" annotation_id="3739">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3739" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they oppress their own people.</en>
      <fr>Plus important encore, ces gens ont insulté mon pays <Alignment alignment="3739" annotation_id="4168">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4168" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils oppriment leur propre peuple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3774" docOffset="26">
      <en>I think that the European Union should monitor what happens in Nicaragua and should send observers to the elections in 2011 and support the democratic opposition.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4214">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne devrait surveiller ce qui se passe au Nicaragua <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4285">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'elle devrait envoyer des observateurs lors des élections de 2011 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4356">et</DiscourseConnective> soutenir l'opposition démocratique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3937" docOffset="27">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="26121" annotation_id="3939">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3939" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hope that we will do the same and will be objective regarding the result of the election in Honduras.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <Alignment alignment="3939" annotation_id="4404">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4404" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4414">que</DiscourseConnective> nous en ferons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4433">de même</DiscourseConnective> au Honduras, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4454">et</DiscourseConnective> que nous serons objectifs concernant le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4497">résultat</DiscourseConnective> des élections qui vont s'y tenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4046" docOffset="28">
      <en>Let us see whether the elections on Sunday are free and fair, and let us make a decision <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4135" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>.</en>
      <fr>Voyons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4547">si</DiscourseConnective> les élections de dimanche seront libres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4590">et</DiscourseConnective> justes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4601">et</DiscourseConnective> prenons alors une décision.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4141" docOffset="29">
      <en>It could be that, <Alignment alignment="4643" annotation_id="4159">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4159" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we recognise the result of the elections, it will put an end to the constitutional crisis in that country.</en>
      <fr>Il se peut <Alignment alignment="4159" annotation_id="4643">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4643" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous reconnaissons le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4672">résultat</DiscourseConnective> des élections, cela mette fin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4711">à</DiscourseConnective> la crise constitutionnelle dans ce pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4269" id="224" name="Tunne Kelam">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4269" docOffset="30">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE Group. - Mr President, there is an alarming trend in today's Latin America to consolidate populist regimes by extending the mandate of current presidents - preferably for eternity.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, il existe aujourd'hui une tendance alarmante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4822">en</DiscourseConnective> Amérique latine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4841">à</DiscourseConnective> consolider les régimes populistes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4877">en</DiscourseConnective> prolongeant le mandat des présidents actuels - de préférence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4941">à</DiscourseConnective> vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4471" docOffset="31">
      <en>This was Hitler's way to power.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4948">C'est ainsi qu'</DiscourseConnective>Hitler est arrivé au pouvoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4503" docOffset="32">
      <en>Lenin's was that of indifference, <Alignment alignment="24399" annotation_id="4537">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4537" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the results were just the same.</en>
      <fr>Lénine, lui, a utilisé l'indifférence, <Alignment alignment="5363" annotation_id="5032">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5032" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5040">résultat</DiscourseConnective> a été le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5058">même</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4573" docOffset="33">
      <en>These presidents with extended powers have not been able or willing to improve the quality of life of their subjects.</en>
      <fr>Ces présidents aux pouvoirs étendus n'ont pas pu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5113">ou</DiscourseConnective> voulu améliorer la qualité de vie de leurs sujets.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4691" docOffset="34">
      <en>Cuba is a murky and painful example of how lives of normal people have been mutilated and spoiled for decades.</en>
      <fr>Cuba est un exemple sombre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5194">et</DiscourseConnective> douloureux de la manière dont la vie des citoyens lambda a été gâchée pendant des décennies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4802" docOffset="35">
      <en>In Nicaragua, we can see a warning example that such kinds of rulers do not change.</en>
      <fr>Nous pouvons voir au Nicaragua un avertissement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5338">que</DiscourseConnective> les dirigeants de ce genre ne changent pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4886" docOffset="36">
      <en>They return to power only to misuse it once again.</en>
      <fr>Ils ne reviennent au pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5415">que</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5419">pour</DiscourseConnective> en abuser à nouveau.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4937" docOffset="37">
      <en>It is, <Alignment alignment="5461" annotation_id="4944">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4944" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, our task now to condemn strongly these violations of the Nicaraguan Constitution and to link this issue with much more efficient control over the use of funds given to Nicaragua for development.</en>
      <fr>Il nous incombe <Alignment alignment="4944" annotation_id="5461">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5461" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de condamner vivement ces violations de la Constitution nicaraguayenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5537">et</DiscourseConnective> de lier cette question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5563">à</DiscourseConnective> un contrôle bien plus efficace de l'usage des fonds versés au Nicaragua <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5637">pour</DiscourseConnective> des projets de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5150" docOffset="38">
      <en>It is very disappointing that the Organisation of American States has not reacted to these flagrant violations of the constitution by one of its member states.</en>
      <fr>Il est très décevant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5693">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Organisation des États américains n'ait pas réagi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5749">à</DiscourseConnective> ces violations flagrantes de la Constitution par un de ses États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5310" id="225" language="FR" name="Véronique De Keyser">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5310" docOffset="39">
      <en>Mr President, I am pleased to see that Mr van Baalen has returned to Europe safely <Alignment alignment="6135" annotation_id="5393">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5393" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that he was only expelled <Alignment alignment="10126" annotation_id="5423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5423" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he was already on the plane.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe S&amp;D. - Monsieur le Président, je suis contente de voir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5897">que</DiscourseConnective> M. van Baalen est bien rentré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5931">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <Alignment alignment="5393" annotation_id="5941">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5941" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5944">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il n'a été expulsé que <Alignment alignment="10960" annotation_id="5970">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5970" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5985">déjà</DiscourseConnective> dans l'avion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5457" docOffset="40">
      <en>Having said this <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5474" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> on a more serious note, I would like to say on behalf of my group that we are not getting involved in this game.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6004">Ceci dit</DiscourseConnective>, plus sérieusement, je voudrais dire, au nom de mon groupe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6073">qu'</DiscourseConnective>on ne joue pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6091">à</DiscourseConnective> ce jeu-là.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5591" docOffset="41">
      <en>What I mean is that, <Alignment alignment="6122" annotation_id="5612">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5612" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) refused us an urgent debate on Uganda about the laws against homosexuals and another urgent debate on Iran about the executions being carried out there, they would now like us to get involved in the game of being for or against Ortega, with the demonstrations going on over there.</en>
      <fr>Je veux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6112">dire que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="5612" annotation_id="6122">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6122" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le PPE nous a refusé une urgence sur l'Ouganda, qui traitait des lois contre les homosexuels, qu'on nous refusé une urgence sur l'Iran, qui traitait des exécutions en Iran, on voudrait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6317">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> nous faire entrer dans le jeu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6358">pour</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6363">ou</DiscourseConnective> contre Ortega, avec les manifestations qui se passent là-bas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5962" docOffset="42">
      <en>That is just not on!</en>
      <fr>Eh bien, non!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5983" docOffset="43">
      <en>I think that the urgent debates held in this House, with the aim of actually providing assistance to people <Alignment alignment="35036" annotation_id="6091">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6091" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> causes experiencing difficulties, must not be used to serve our MEPs' personal political interests.</en>
      <fr>Je ne pense pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6458">que</DiscourseConnective> les urgences, ici, dont le but est réellement d'apporter une aide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6528">à</DiscourseConnective> des personnes <Alignment alignment="2818" annotation_id="6544">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6544" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à des causes en difficulté, doivent servir des intérêts politiques particuliers de nos députés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6194" docOffset="44">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="39059" annotation_id="6194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6194" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, my group has decided not only not to sign this resolution, <Alignment alignment="6718" annotation_id="6264">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6264" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not to vote and to oppose what is going on here.</en>
      <fr>Mon groupe a <Alignment alignment="8099" annotation_id="6656">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6656" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> décidé, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6669">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> de ne pas signer cette résolution, <Alignment alignment="9900" annotation_id="6718">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6718" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de ne pas voter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6739">et</DiscourseConnective> de s'inscrire en faux contre ce qui se passe ici.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6317" docOffset="45">
      <en>This brings discredit upon the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>C'est un discrédit pour le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6369" id="226" language="ES" name="Raül Romeva i Rueda">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6369" docOffset="46">
      <en>Mr President, along the same lines, I think that it is not only sad but clearly shameful that a sitting as important as this, on urgent matters, is being manipulated in this way, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6548" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I am therefore surprised not only that the subject today is Nicaragua, but also that on other occasions <Alignment alignment="7193" annotation_id="6656">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6656" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we were supposed to have discussed much more serious matters, that did not happen.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. - (ES) Monsieur le Président, dans la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6905">même</DiscourseConnective> lignée, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6927">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est triste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6944">mais</DiscourseConnective> également très clairement honteux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6983">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une séance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6997">aussi</DiscourseConnective> importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7014">que</DiscourseConnective> celle-ci, portant sur des problèmes urgents, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7063">soit</DiscourseConnective> manipulée de la sorte. Je ne suis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7102">donc</DiscourseConnective> pas surpris que le sujet d'aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7146">soit</DiscourseConnective> le Nicaragua ni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7167">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> d'autres occasions, <Alignment alignment="1705" annotation_id="7193">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7193" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous aurions dû discuter de questions bien plus sérieuses, cela n'ait pas été le cas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6744" docOffset="47">
      <en>Today, <Alignment alignment="39369" annotation_id="6751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6751" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we have the added factor that other subjects that were on the agenda have been dropped precisely <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6858" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> this one has been included.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1171" annotation_id="7289">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7289" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans le cas d'aujourd'hui, d'autres sujets qui étaient inscrits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7367">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre du jour ont été abandonnés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7404">précisément</DiscourseConnective> à cause de l'inscription de celui-ci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6894" docOffset="48">
      <en>This is entirely inappropriate from the point of view of the content of debates on urgent matters.</en>
      <fr>C'est tout à fait inapproprié du point de vue de la teneur des débats sur des problèmes urgents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6993" docOffset="49">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28516" annotation_id="6993">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6993" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">For example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we could and should have discussed the Western Sahara.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9747" annotation_id="7551">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7551" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">Par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous pourrions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7579">et</DiscourseConnective> devrions discuter du Sahara occidental.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7061" docOffset="50">
      <en>We should have discussed the current situation of people such as Aminatou Haidar, who is at present suffering as a result of a clear violation and deprival of her most fundamental rights.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions parler de la situation actuelle de personnes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7681">comme</DiscourseConnective> Aminatou Haidar, qui souffre actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7729">à</DiscourseConnective> la suite d'une violation claire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7763">et</DiscourseConnective> une privation de ses droits les plus fondamentaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7249" docOffset="51">
      <en>We should <Alignment alignment="7831" annotation_id="7259">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7259" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be discussing the situation of the very many people who are in refugee camps, or in the occupied areas of Morocco, a context on which a clear position is really needed.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions <Alignment alignment="408" annotation_id="7831">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7831" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> débattre de la situation des très nombreuses personnes qui se trouvent dans des camps de réfugiés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7939">ou</DiscourseConnective> dans les zones occupées du Maroc, une situation qui requiert réellement une position claire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7433" docOffset="52">
      <en>All of this could have been debated today, <Alignment alignment="13620" annotation_id="7476">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7476" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is not the case <Alignment alignment="11062" annotation_id="7501">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7501" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) is making us talk about a subject that I do not think deserves the consideration or has the significance appropriate to this type of sitting.</en>
      <fr>Tous ces sujets auraient pu être débattus aujourd'hui, <Alignment alignment="7476" annotation_id="8090">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8090" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce n'est pas le cas <Alignment alignment="8458" annotation_id="8113">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8113" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le groupe du Parti populaire européen (Démocrates-Chrétiens) nous oblige à parler d'un sujet qui, selon moi, ne mérite pas d'être considéré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8263">ou</DiscourseConnective> n'a pas l'importance appropriée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8298">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce type de séance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7714" id="227" language="PT" name="Ilda Figueiredo">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7714" docOffset="53">
      <en>Mr President, this is a regrettable debate about a false state of urgency that does nothing but discredit the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. - (PT) Monsieur le Président, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8381">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un débat regrettable sur un faux état d'urgence qui ne fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8450">que</DiscourseConnective> discréditer le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7845" docOffset="54">
      <en>The urgent thing would have been to debate the recent tragedy caused by Hurricane Ida <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7931" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> it hit El Salvador at the beginning of November.</en>
      <fr>Il aurait été urgent de débattre de la récente tragédie provoquée par l'ouragan Ida lors de son passage au Salvador début novembre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7985" docOffset="55">
      <en>This hurricane caused more than 200 deaths and missing persons, destroyed infrastructures and essential equipment, particularly in the areas of health, education, water and sanitation, exacerbating poverty in the country.</en>
      <fr>Cet ouragan a fait plus de 200 morts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8658">et</DiscourseConnective> disparus, il a détruit des infrastructures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8704">et</DiscourseConnective> des équipements essentiels, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8735">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> dans le domaine de la santé, de l'éducation, de l'eau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8804">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'hygiène, exacerbant la pauvreté dans le pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8207" docOffset="56">
      <en>The urgent thing would have been to discuss the availability of extraordinary funds and the redirection of available EU funds to the emergency situation, launch a plan for reconstruction and risk reduction, and support the people of El Salvador.</en>
      <fr>Il aurait été urgent de discuter de la disponibilité de fonds extraordinaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8936">et</DiscourseConnective> de la réorientation des fonds de l'UE disponibles vers la situation d'urgence, de lancer un plan de reconstruction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9054">et</DiscourseConnective> de réduction des risques, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9083">et</DiscourseConnective> d'aider la population du Salvador.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8453" docOffset="57">
      <en>The urgent thing would have been for this Parliament to condemn the military coup in Honduras and demand the return to power of President Zelaya, who was legally elected by the Honduran people.</en>
      <fr>Il aurait été urgent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9142">que</DiscourseConnective> ce Parlement condamne le coup d'État militaire au Honduras <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9205">et</DiscourseConnective> demande le retour au pouvoir du président Zelaya, qui a été légalement élu par le peuple hondurien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8647" docOffset="58">
      <en>The urgent thing would have been to demand respect for the fundamental rights of the people of the Western Sahara.</en>
      <fr>Il aurait été urgent de demander le respect des droits fondamentaux des citoyens du Sahara occidental.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8762" docOffset="59">
      <en>Unfortunately, none of this was possible due to opposition by the Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats).</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9411">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, rien de tout cela n'a été possible du fait de l'opposition du groupe du Parti populaire européen (Démocrates-Chrétiens).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8888" docOffset="60">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9549" annotation_id="8888">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8888" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="9337" annotation_id="8899">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8899" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> my colleagues have already stated, we refuse to collaborate with this false state of urgency, which is a disgrace to the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1475" annotation_id="9549">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9549" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">En conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="8899" annotation_id="9565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9565" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9577">déjà</DiscourseConnective> dit mes collègues, nous refusons de participer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9629">à</DiscourseConnective> ce faux état d'urgence, qui fait honte au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9044" id="228" name="Jürgen Klute">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9044" docOffset="61">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, I agree wholeheartedly with the previous speakers.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, je suis tout à fait d'accord avec les orateurs précédents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9114" docOffset="62">
      <en>I would like to remind everyone that the Colombian President <Alignment alignment="2720" annotation_id="9175">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9175" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> attempted to extend his term of office in breach of current Colombian law <Alignment alignment="17967" annotation_id="9254">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9254" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="28749" annotation_id="9259">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9259" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this matter should <Alignment alignment="9982" annotation_id="9289">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9289" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be taken up.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais rappeler à tous mes collègues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9822">que</DiscourseConnective> le président colombien a <Alignment alignment="10053" annotation_id="9851">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9851" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> essayé de prolonger son mandat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9892">en</DiscourseConnective> violation de la législation colombienne actuelle, <Alignment alignment="569" annotation_id="9945">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9945" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette situation devrait <Alignment alignment="9259" annotation_id="9972">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9972" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être <Alignment alignment="824" annotation_id="9982">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9982" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> abordée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9307" docOffset="63">
      <en>Most importantly, <Alignment alignment="29014" annotation_id="9325">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9325" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I would like to highlight the fact that the Friedrich-Naumann foundation in Germany, a foundation which has close links with the German Free Democratic Party, was involved in the coup in Honduras.</en>
      <fr>Plus important <Alignment alignment="3082" annotation_id="10016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10016" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je voudrais souligner le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10057">que</DiscourseConnective> la fondation allemande Friedrich-Naumann, qui maintient des liens étroits avec le parti libéral-démocrate allemand, a participé au coup d'État au Honduras.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9531" docOffset="64">
      <en>There was a debate about this at least in Germany.</en>
      <fr>Il y a eu un débat sur ce sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10249">en</DiscourseConnective> Allemagne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10262">du moins</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9582" docOffset="65">
      <en>The foundation's scholarship holders distanced themselves from this policy in an open letter.</en>
      <fr>Les boursiers de la fondation ont pris leurs distances par rapport à cette politique dans une lettre ouverte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9676" docOffset="66">
      <en>We must not forget that Mr van Baalen is the president of Liberal International <Alignment alignment="1179" annotation_id="9756">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9756" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on the website of the Friedrich-Naumann foundation, it states that he discussed the possibility of a coup with the armed forces in Nicaragua.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne devons pas oublier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10409">que</DiscourseConnective> M. van Baalen est le président de l'Internationale libérale <Alignment alignment="5978" annotation_id="10473">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10473" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, sur le site web de la fondation Friedrich-Naumann, il déclare avoir discuté de la possibilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10575">d'un coup</DiscourseConnective> d'État avec les forces armées nicaraguayennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9902" docOffset="67">
      <en>I think it is appropriate that in these circumstances - and this has not been contradicted - a country such as Nicaragua is bold enough to expel a politician of this kind.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10641">que</DiscourseConnective> dans ces circonstances, qui n'ont pas été contredites, un pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10708">comme</DiscourseConnective> le Nicaragua peut bien faire preuve d'un courage suffisant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10773">pour</DiscourseConnective> expulser un homme politique de ce genre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10074" docOffset="68">
      <en>In all honesty, we must admit that the situation would be just the same in Europe.</en>
      <fr>Franchement, nous devons reconnaître <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10856">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il en irait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10871">de même</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10879">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10157" docOffset="69">
      <en>What is happening here is nothing more than a transparent attempt to discredit and publicly shame those countries, states and governments in Latin America which are trying to introduce more social policies.</en>
      <fr>Ce qui se passe ici constitue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10920">simplement</DiscourseConnective> une tentative claire de discréditer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10967">et</DiscourseConnective> de faire publiquement honte aux pays, États <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11014">et</DiscourseConnective> gouvernements d'Amérique latine qui tentent d'introduire des politiques plus sociales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10364" docOffset="70">
      <en>On behalf of the Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left, I would like to say clearly once again that we will not support this.</en>
      <fr>Au nom du groupe confédéral de la Gauche unitaire européenne/Gauche verte nordique, je voudrais dire clairement une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11225">encore que</DiscourseConnective> nous ne soutiendrons pas cela.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10517" id="229" name="Ioannis Kasoulides">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10517" docOffset="71">
      <en>Mr President, I do not understand the reaction from our esteemed colleagues on my right-hand side in this hemicycle on the choice of subjects that we are debating today.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, je ne comprends pas la réaction des collègues situés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11348">à</DiscourseConnective> ma droite dans cet hémicycle quant au choix des sujets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11405">que</DiscourseConnective> nous débattons aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10687" docOffset="72">
      <en>I do not understand why it is not urgent to take the floor, discussing the issue of the treatment of one of the Members of this Parliament who has visited a country exercising his right as President of Liberal International.</en>
      <fr>Je ne comprends pas pourquoi il n'est pas urgent de parler du traitement réservé à un député de ce Parlement qui a visité un pays dans l'exercice de ses droits en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11600">tant que</DiscourseConnective> président de l'Internationale libérale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10912" docOffset="73">
      <en>I do not understand why we cannot take the floor and speak about this issue and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10992" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> speak about this new tendency in Latin America to try to change arbitrarily the constitution of the country and stop a tradition that has always existed concerning one or two terms of office of the Head of State in that country.</en>
      <fr>Je ne comprends pas pourquoi nous ne pouvons pas parler de ce sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11717">et</DiscourseConnective> de cette nouvelle tendance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11747">en</DiscourseConnective> Amérique latine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11766">à</DiscourseConnective> tenter de changer arbitrairement la Constitution d'un pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11827">et</DiscourseConnective> de mettre fin à une tradition qui a toujours existé concernant le nombre de mandats d'un chef d'État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11226" docOffset="74">
      <en>Already, our esteemed friends here have talked about four other subjects, <Alignment alignment="26313" annotation_id="11300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11300" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would like to know <Alignment alignment="7410" annotation_id="11325">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11325" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are going to discuss the matter at hand, given that there are only three subjects on the agenda.</en>
      <fr>Nos collègues ont déjà parlé ici de quatre autres sujets <Alignment alignment="4598" annotation_id="11989">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11989" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je voudrais savoir <Alignment alignment="11042" annotation_id="12011">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12011" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous allons parler du sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12045">en</DiscourseConnective> question, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12058">vu qu'</DiscourseConnective>il n'y a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12073">que</DiscourseConnective> trois sujets inscrits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12099">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre du jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11430" docOffset="75">
      <en>(The President cut off the speaker)</en>
      <fr>(Le Président retire la parole à l'orateur)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11466" id="230" name="Justas Vincas Paleckis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11466" docOffset="76">
      <en>(LT) I wholeheartedly support the opinion of my group that this matter should not be included on the agenda, <Alignment alignment="34609" annotation_id="11575">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11575" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are much more relevant and much more pressing problems throughout the world.</en>
      <fr>(LT) Je suis tout à fait d'accord avec mon groupe qui estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12223">que</DiscourseConnective> cette question ne devrait pas être inscrite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12271">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre du jour, <Alignment alignment="11575" annotation_id="12290">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12290" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">étant donné qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il y a des problèmes bien plus pertinents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12347">et</DiscourseConnective> bien plus urgents dans le monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11661" docOffset="77">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28382" annotation_id="11661">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11661" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are to discuss Nicaragua, we should firstly talk about the fact that this is a country with the highest debt in the world <Alignment alignment="761" annotation_id="11789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11789" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that it is one of the poorest countries in Latin America.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11661" annotation_id="12383">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12383" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons parler du Nicaragua, nous devrions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12434">d'abord</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12442">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12453">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit du pays qui a la dette la plus élevée au monde <Alignment alignment="5862" annotation_id="12507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12507" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12510">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est l'un des pays les plus pauvres d'Amérique latine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11851" docOffset="78">
      <en>The communist experiment was not the answer there, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11902" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> neither was the neo-liberal experiment.</en>
      <fr>L'expérience communiste n'était pas la réponse au problème là-bas, pas plus que l'expérience néolibérale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11946" docOffset="79">
      <en>It is a country where there was too much interference by the superpowers, America and the Soviet Union, <Alignment alignment="15417" annotation_id="12050">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12050" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is why that country is constantly on the verge of civil war.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12679">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un pays où l'ingérence des superpuissances, l'Amérique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12743">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Union soviétique, a été trop importante, <Alignment alignment="9530" annotation_id="12789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12789" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est la raison pour laquelle il est constamment au bord de la guerre civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12120" docOffset="80">
      <en>It is understandable that there are strong-arm tendencies there <Alignment alignment="12941" annotation_id="12184">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12184" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> those must be condemned.</en>
      <fr>Il est compréhensible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12892">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il y ait des tendances brutales dans ce pays, <Alignment alignment="18248" annotation_id="12941">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12941" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elles doivent être condamnées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12213" docOffset="81">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17420" annotation_id="12213">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12213" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, let us not forget that we <Alignment alignment="30893" annotation_id="12248">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12248" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have strong-arm tendencies in Europe.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2081" annotation_id="12975">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12975" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous ne devons pas oublier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13013">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons <Alignment alignment="15532" annotation_id="13028">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13028" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des tendances brutales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13061">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12291" docOffset="82">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="46992" annotation_id="12291">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12291" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, let us concentrate on far more important matters.</en>
      <fr>Concentrons-nous <Alignment alignment="12291" annotation_id="13089">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13089" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sur des questions bien plus importantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12352" id="231" name="Gesine Meissner">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12352" docOffset="83">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, various things have already been said on this matter.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, plusieurs choses ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13184">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été dites sur le sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12425" docOffset="84">
      <en>One speaker explained that this is the wrong subject for debate, <Alignment alignment="13277" annotation_id="12490">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12490" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are more urgent issues that involve more significant violations of human rights.</en>
      <fr>Un orateur a expliqué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13235">que</DiscourseConnective> ce n'est pas le bon sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13265">à</DiscourseConnective> débattre, <Alignment alignment="12490" annotation_id="13277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13277" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il existe des questions plus urgentes qui impliquent des violations plus flagrantes des droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12585" docOffset="85">
      <en>That may be the case, <Alignment alignment="3372" annotation_id="12607">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12607" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I believe that we Europeans, who work to ensure that values such as human rights and freedoms - <Alignment alignment="34817" annotation_id="12707">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12707" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the freedom of the press - are respected everywhere, must defend this freedom whenever we become aware that it is under threat.</en>
      <fr>Peut-être est-ce le cas, <Alignment alignment="19708" annotation_id="13413">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13413" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13427">que</DiscourseConnective> nous, les Européens qui œuvrons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13463">afin de</DiscourseConnective> veiller au respect, partout, de valeurs telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13518">que</DiscourseConnective> les libertés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13535">et</DiscourseConnective> les droits de l'homme - <Alignment alignment="12707" annotation_id="13562">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13562" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la liberté de la presse -, nous devons défendre cette liberté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13637">dès que</DiscourseConnective> nous apprenons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13660">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle est menacée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12848" docOffset="86">
      <en>It was <Alignment alignment="13688" annotation_id="12855">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12855" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> said, <Alignment alignment="32124" annotation_id="12866">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12866" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, that the Friedrich-Naumann foundation was involved in the coup.</en>
      <fr>Il y a <Alignment alignment="12855" annotation_id="13688">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13688" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> été dit, <Alignment alignment="6368" annotation_id="13707">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13707" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13720">que</DiscourseConnective> la fondation Friedrich-Naumann avait participé au coup d'État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12943" docOffset="87">
      <en>As a member of the FDP, I explicitly reject this claim.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13790">tant que</DiscourseConnective> membre du FDP, je réfute catégoriquement cette affirmation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12999" docOffset="88">
      <en>These are rumours which have been spread around <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13047" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> which are completely without foundation.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agit d'une rumeur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13882">sans</DiscourseConnective> aucun fondement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13092" docOffset="89">
      <en>My third point is that it was said that Mr van Baalen was accused of discussing a coup <Alignment alignment="40463" annotation_id="13179">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13179" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is why he was expelled from the country.</en>
      <fr>Ma troisième <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13917">remarque</DiscourseConnective> est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13930">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il a été dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13946">que</DiscourseConnective> M. van Baalen avait été accusé d'avoir parlé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13995">d'un coup</DiscourseConnective> d'État <Alignment alignment="13179" annotation_id="14012">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14012" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que c'est la raison pour laquelle il a été expulsé du pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13229" docOffset="90">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1652" annotation_id="13229">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13229" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you cannot openly discuss all kinds of subjects - for us this is part of the freedom of the press and of speech, two freedoms which we have here <Alignment alignment="5057" annotation_id="13377">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13377" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which we value highly - is this really a reason for expelling someone from the country, simply because a subject of whatever kind was discussed?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13229" annotation_id="14075">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14075" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous ne pouvez pas ouvertement aborder n'importe quel sujet - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14140">pour</DiscourseConnective> nous, cela fait partie de la liberté de la presse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14195">et</DiscourseConnective> de la liberté d'expression, deux libertés dont nous jouissons ici <Alignment alignment="13377" annotation_id="14264">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14264" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui revêtent une grande importance à nos yeux - le fait de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14326">simplement</DiscourseConnective> aborder un sujet, quel qu'il soit, justifie-t-il réellement l'expulsion du pays d'une personne?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13526" docOffset="91">
      <en>The fact that this happens in public is no justification for expelling someone from the country, simply <Alignment alignment="14533" annotation_id="13630">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13630" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a discussion took place.</en>
      <fr>Le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14441">que</DiscourseConnective> cela se produise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14462">en</DiscourseConnective> public ne justifie pas l'expulsion de quelqu'un du pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14522">simplement</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="10358" annotation_id="14533">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14533" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il y a eu une discussion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13663" docOffset="92">
      <en>This is totally the wrong approach.</en>
      <fr>C'est certainement la mauvaise approche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13699" id="232" name="Charles Tannock">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13699" docOffset="93">
      <en>Mr President, Nicaragua remains one of the poorest countries in the Americas.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, le Nicaragua reste l'un des pays les plus pauvres du continent américain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13777" docOffset="94">
      <en>The fact that President Daniel Ortega has failed to improve his country's situation, despite myriad Socialist utopian promises upon taking office, would suggest that Nicaragua needs a change of leadership now.</en>
      <fr>Le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14719">que</DiscourseConnective> le président Ortega n'ait pas réussi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14760">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la situation du pays, en dépit de la kyrielle de promesses utopiques socialistes qu'il avait faites à son arrivée au pouvoir, donne à penser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14913">que</DiscourseConnective> le Nicaragua a aujourd'hui besoin d'un changement de dirigeant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13987" docOffset="95">
      <en>The country's constitution permits Heads of State to serve only one term, sometimes a wise policy in a region prone to instability, <Alignment alignment="21452" annotation_id="14119">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14119" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Ortega is once again showing his contempt for parliamentary democracy and the rule of law by abusing the Constitutional Court's powers.</en>
      <fr>La Constitution du pays n'accorde qu'un seul mandat au chef de l'État, ce qui est parfois une sage politique dans une région encline <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15114">à</DiscourseConnective> l'instabilité, <Alignment alignment="14119" annotation_id="15131">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15131" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Ortega fait une fois de plus fait montre de son mépris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15191">pour</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie parlementaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15224">et</DiscourseConnective> l'État de droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15243">en</DiscourseConnective> abusant des pouvoirs de la Cour constitutionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14259" docOffset="96">
      <en>In this respect, he is no different from his fellow leftist Hugo Chávez of Venezuela.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15297">À cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, il n'est pas différent de son collègue Hugo Chávez au Venezuela.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14345" docOffset="97">
      <en>Both men have made their names denouncing caudillos, <Alignment alignment="15439" annotation_id="14398">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14398" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they themselves are turning into caudillos of the Left and, as such, represent a genuine threat to regional democratic stability, especially given the chaos in nearby Honduras.</en>
      <fr>Ils sont tous deux devenus célèbres en dénonçant les caudillos, <Alignment alignment="14398" annotation_id="15439">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15439" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils se transforment eux-mêmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15474">en</DiscourseConnective> caudillos de la gauche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15500">et</DiscourseConnective>, en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15507">tant que</DiscourseConnective> tels, ils constituent une véritable menace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15559">pour</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité démocratique de la région, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15604">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> vu le chaos qui règne au Honduras voisin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14579" docOffset="98">
      <en>Daniel Ortega has failed his people and his country many times over.</en>
      <fr>Daniel Ortega a manqué de nombreuses fois à ses devoirs envers son peuple <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15735">et</DiscourseConnective> son pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14648" docOffset="99">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="34527" annotation_id="14648">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14648" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we truly believe in democracy and freedom, we cannot ignore the plight of the citizens of Nicaragua.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14648" annotation_id="15748">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15748" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous croyons réellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15775">en</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15792">et</DiscourseConnective> en la liberté, nous ne pouvons pas fermer les yeux devant la situation critique dans laquelle se trouvent les citoyens du Nicaragua.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14752" id="233" name="Reinhard Bütikofer">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14752" docOffset="100">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, one thing has come out of this rather difficult debate. The Member from the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe has indirectly confirmed that the question of a coup really was the subject of these discussions.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, une chose ressort de ce débat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15986">plutôt</DiscourseConnective> difficile: la députée du groupe de l'Alliance des démocrates <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16054">et</DiscourseConnective> des libéraux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16070">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe a indirectement confirmé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16109">que</DiscourseConnective> la question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16125">d'un coup</DiscourseConnective> d'État était réellement le sujet de ce débat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15004" docOffset="101">
      <en>She has defended what took place by using the argument that it must be possible to talk about anything, even a coup.</en>
      <fr>Elle a défendu ce qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16203">s'</DiscourseConnective>est passé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16215">en</DiscourseConnective> prétendant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16229">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on doit pouvoir parler de tout, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16267">même</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16272">d'un coup</DiscourseConnective> d'État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15121" docOffset="102">
      <en>That is one remarkable result of this debate which helps to clarify the situation <Alignment alignment="42343" annotation_id="15203">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15203" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am grateful for this.</en>
      <fr>C'est un <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16299">résultat</DiscourseConnective> remarquable de ce débat, qui aide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16342">à</DiscourseConnective> clarifier la situation, <Alignment alignment="7252" annotation_id="16368">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16368" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je lui en sais gré.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15231" id="234" name="Karel De Gucht">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15231" docOffset="103">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, honourable colleagues, <Alignment alignment="29842" annotation_id="15296">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15296" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you know, the European Union is engaged in a difficult dialogue with this country aimed at preserving democracy and restoring its citizens' trust in the country's democratic institutions.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, <Alignment alignment="15296" annotation_id="16431">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16431" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez, l'Union européenne a entamé un dialogue difficile avec ce pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16515">afin de</DiscourseConnective> préserver la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16547">et</DiscourseConnective> de restaurer la confiance des citoyens dans les institutions démocratiques du pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15487" docOffset="104">
      <en>At the same time, the EU is trying to maintain a balance with our long-standing commitment to support the development and stability of this developing country and the Central American region more generally.</en>
      <fr>L'UE essaie dans le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16654">même</DiscourseConnective> temps de maintenir un équilibre avec notre engagement de longue date <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16728">à</DiscourseConnective> soutenir le développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16756">et</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité de ce pays en développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16800">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'Amérique centrale de manière plus générale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15694" docOffset="105">
      <en>Since the municipal elections held in November 2008, which were tainted with allegations of widespread fraud, international donors' confidence in the current government has fallen to an all-time low.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16852">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> les élections municipales de novembre 2008, teintées d'allégations de fraude généralisée, la confiance des donateurs internationaux dans le gouvernement actuel a chuté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17027">à</DiscourseConnective> son niveau le plus bas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15894" docOffset="106">
      <en>Failure to respect fundamental democratic principles, including free and fair elections, led the donor community to systematically review their cooperation portfolios and, in certain instances, reorient or suspend cooperation activities <Alignment alignment="30926" annotation_id="16131">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16131" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">until</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> conditions improved.</en>
      <fr>L'incapacité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17066">à</DiscourseConnective> respecter les principes démocratiques fondamentaux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17120">notamment</DiscourseConnective> des élections libres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17151">et</DiscourseConnective> justes, a conduit la communauté des donateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17200">à</DiscourseConnective> revoir systématiquement ses portefeuilles de coopération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17259">et</DiscourseConnective>, dans certains cas, à réorienter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17295">ou</DiscourseConnective> suspendre les activités de coopération <Alignment alignment="4874" annotation_id="17337">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17337" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">jusqu'à ce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les conditions s'améliorent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16158" docOffset="107">
      <en>Commissioner Ferrero-Waldner took the decision to suspend all budgetary support payments to Nicaragua as of 1 January 2009.</en>
      <fr>La commissaire Ferrero-Waldner a pris la décision de suspendre tous les paiements au titre de l'aide budgétaire au Nicaragua dès le 1er janvier 2009.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16282" docOffset="108">
      <en>This decision had been preceded by a discussion with Member States in the Council.</en>
      <fr>Cette décision a été précédée d'une discussion avec les États membres au Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16365" docOffset="109">
      <en>Following numerous contacts with the Nicaraguan authorities which gave credible commitments that corrective steps would be taken, the Commission proceeded at the beginning of October with a single payment of EUR 10 million of our budget support programme to the education sector.</en>
      <fr>À la suite des nombreux contacts avec les autorités nicaraguayennes, qui ont pris des engagements crédibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17721">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre des mesures correctrices, la Commission a effectué début octobre un paiement unique de 10 millions d'euros dans le cadre de notre programme de soutien budgétaire au secteur de l'éducation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16645" docOffset="110">
      <en>This represents a small part of the funds that have been suspended, which amount to an additional EUR 46 million.</en>
      <fr>Cela représente une faible partie des fonds qui ont été suspendus, qui s'élèvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18001">à</DiscourseConnective> 46 millions d'euros supplémentaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16759" docOffset="111">
      <en>There was criticism last week in the Development Council that there were no previous discussions on this with the Member States.</en>
      <fr>La semaine dernière, des critiques ont été émises lors du Conseil "Développement" selon lesquelles il n'y a eu aucune discussion préalable sur ce sujet avec les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16888" docOffset="112">
      <en>Without going into the details of this, I think it is very important that, <Alignment alignment="38879" annotation_id="16963">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16963" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we take that kind of decision, we have a kind of a procedure whereby we at least try to make sure that the European Commission and the Member States are taking the same line with respect to individual states.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18216">Sans</DiscourseConnective> entrer dans les détails, je pense qu'il est très important, <Alignment alignment="2869" annotation_id="18281">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18281" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous prenons ce type de décision, de disposer d'une sorte de procédure grâce à laquelle nous tentons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18390">au moins</DiscourseConnective> de veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18415">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18444">et</DiscourseConnective> les États membres adoptent la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18477">même</DiscourseConnective> position <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18491">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard d'États individuels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17177" docOffset="113">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18522" annotation_id="17177">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17177" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in the end, it is not possible, then of course everybody is allowed to do what he or she thinks to be necessary.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17177" annotation_id="18522">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18522" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18526">en fin de compte</DiscourseConnective>, ce n'est pas possible, tout le monde pourra <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18588">alors</DiscourseConnective> faire ce qu'il estime nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17294" docOffset="114">
      <en>The government of Nicaragua has announced that the next regional elections in 2010 and the general election in 2011 will have national and international observation teams.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement nicaraguayen a annoncé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18667">que</DiscourseConnective> des équipes d'observateurs nationaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18708">et</DiscourseConnective> internationaux surveilleront les prochaines élections régionales de 2010 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18784">et</DiscourseConnective> les élections législatives de 2011.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17466" docOffset="115">
      <en>The government has already officially invited the EU to carry out an observation mission.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18841">déjà</DiscourseConnective> officiellement invité l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18873">à</DiscourseConnective> envoyer une mission d'observation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17556" docOffset="116">
      <en>The government has <Alignment alignment="18932" annotation_id="17575">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17575" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> committed, inter alia, to improving its civil registry and electoral role with the support of an EC project and to appoint credible and professional electoral authorities next year.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement s'est <Alignment alignment="17575" annotation_id="18932">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18932" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> engagé, entre autres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18964">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer son système de registre civil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19006">et</DiscourseConnective> ses listes électorales avec l'aide d'un projet de la CE, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19066">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19069">à</DiscourseConnective> désigner l'année prochaine des autorités professionnelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19129">et</DiscourseConnective> crédibles chargées des élections.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17762" docOffset="117">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19166" annotation_id="17762">
          <Alignment alignment="2321" annotation_id="17762">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17762" sense="Comparison.Contrast">On the other hand</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, recent developments, such as the ruling by the Constitutional Chamber, certainly cast a shadow on the seriousness of the Nicaraguan Government to live up to its commitments.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1023" annotation_id="19166">
          <Alignment alignment="17762" annotation_id="19166">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19166" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, les récents événements, tels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19209">que</DiscourseConnective> l'arrêt de la Cour constitutionnelle, font planer le doute sur l'intention du gouvernement nicaraguayen de respecter ses engagements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17955" docOffset="118">
      <en>The EU has, on a number of occasions, most recently by means of a local troika démarche on Monday 21 November, expressed concern on this development.</en>
      <fr>L'UE a exprimé ses inquiétudes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19378">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet à maintes reprises, et récemment encore par une démarche de la troïka locale le lundi 21 novembre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18105" docOffset="119">
      <en>At the end of the day, implementation of these commitments will be crucial for the progressive resumption of our budgetary support programmes.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19488">En fin de compte</DiscourseConnective>, le respect de ces engagements sera crucial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19549">pour</DiscourseConnective> la reprise progressive de nos programmes de soutien budgétaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18248" docOffset="120">
      <en>We continue to work in close cooperation with the Member Sates as well as with the European Parliament, <Alignment alignment="4594" annotation_id="18352">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18352" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this debate shows.</en>
      <fr>Nous continuons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19634">à</DiscourseConnective> travailler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19647">en</DiscourseConnective> étroite collaboration avec les États membres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19696">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'avec le Parlement européen, <Alignment alignment="8457" annotation_id="19733">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19733" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le montre ce débat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18374" docOffset="121">
      <en>Whether it is timely or not is, of course, a matter that should be looked at by Parliament itself.</en>
      <fr>L'opportunité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19773">ou</DiscourseConnective> non de ce dernier est évidemment une question qui devrait être examinée par le Parlement lui-même.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18473" id="235" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18473" docOffset="122">
      <en>The item is hereby closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18500" docOffset="123">
      <en>The vote will take place at the end of the debate.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19912">à</DiscourseConnective> la fin des débats.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
