<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Welcome</en>
    <fr>Souhaits de bienvenue</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="012" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="38" annotation_id="16">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to say a word of welcome to a delegation from Iraq.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaiterais <Alignment alignment="79" annotation_id="38">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> adresser quelques mots de bienvenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="84">à</DiscourseConnective> une délégation venue d'Irak.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="78" docOffset="2">
      <en>It is a cause of great joy to me to be able to welcome as guests of this Parliament, this afternoon, a delegation of five members of the Parliament of Iraq, led by Mr Hamid Mousa.</en>
      <fr>Je suis très honoré de pouvoir accueillir cet après-midi cinq membres du parlement irakien invités par ce Parlement dans le cadre d'une délégation conduite par M. Hamid Mousa.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="258" docOffset="3">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="269" docOffset="4">
      <en>The situation in Iraq is a matter of constant concern to us, <Alignment alignment="373" annotation_id="330">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="330" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a visit by our counterparts there, which gives us the opportunity to learn at first hand about how things are developing there, is both very necessary and welcome.</en>
      <fr>La situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="323">en</DiscourseConnective> Irak est une source de préoccupation constante <Alignment alignment="330" annotation_id="373">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="373" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la visite de nos homologues irakiens, grâce auxquels nous obtenons des informations de première main sur l'évolution de la situation dans ce pays, est à la fois absolument nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="559">et</DiscourseConnective> grandement appréciée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="498" docOffset="5">
      <en>I have already had the opportunity to meet them - I did so yesterday - <Alignment alignment="635" annotation_id="569">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="569" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am very well aware of the extremely difficult conditions under which their parliament's members have to work.</en>
      <fr>J'ai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="589">déjà</DiscourseConnective> eu l'occasion de les rencontrer - hier - <Alignment alignment="569" annotation_id="635">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="635" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ai parfaitement conscience des conditions extrêmement difficiles dans lesquelles les députés de leur parlement doivent travailler.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="685" docOffset="6">
      <en>I am sure that their talks with the Committee on Foreign Affairs and with other Members of this House were useful and will prove beneficial to both sides.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="789">que</DiscourseConnective> les discussions tenues avec la commission des affaires étrangères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="859">et</DiscourseConnective> avec les autres députés de ce Parlement ont été utiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="917">et</DiscourseConnective> s'avéreront bénéfiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="943">pour</DiscourseConnective> les deux parties.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="840" docOffset="7">
      <en>I trust that the ongoing process of constitutional reform will offer all groups in Iran the opportunity to reach broad consensus on the essential issues and to prepare a way for their country to move forward into the future.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="975">que</DiscourseConnective> le processus de réforme constitutionnelle actuellement en cours permettra à tous les groupes d'Irak de dégager un large consensus sur les questions essentielles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1140">et</DiscourseConnective> de préparer leur pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1165">à</DiscourseConnective> s'engager ultérieurement dans la voie du progrès.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1065" docOffset="8">
      <en>I wish you, our honoured guests, and your country, all the best, and hope that your visit will help to forge solid parliamentary relations between our two Houses - your parliament in Iraq and this, the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Chers invités, je vous souhaite bonne chance, à vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1270">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à votre pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1293">et</DiscourseConnective> j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1305">que</DiscourseConnective> votre visite favorisera l'instauration de solides relations parlementaires entre nos deux Assemblées - votre parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1428">en</DiscourseConnective> Irak <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1436">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1288" docOffset="9">
      <en>My best wishes go with you <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1315" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> you return to your suffering country.</en>
      <fr>Je vous souhaite un bon retour dans votre pays durement éprouvé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
