<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Policy coherence for development and the effects of the EU's exploitation of certain biological natural resources on development in West Africa (debate)</en>
    <fr>Cohérence des axes de développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36">et</DiscourseConnective> effets sur le développement de l'Afrique de l'Ouest de l'exploitation par l'UE de certaines ressources naturelles biologiques (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="153" id="220" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="153" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next and last item is the debate on the report by Frithjof Schmidt, on behalf of the Committee on Development, on policy coherence for development and the effects of the EU's exploitation of certain biological natural resources on development in West Africa (INI/2007/2183).</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le dernier débat sur le rapport élaboré par Frithjof Schmidt, au nom de la commission du développement, sur la cohérence des politiques au service du développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="361">et</DiscourseConnective> les effets sur le développement de l'Afrique de l'Ouest de l'exploitation par l'UE de certaines ressources naturelles biologiques (INI/2007/2183).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="432" id="221" name="Frithjof Schmidt">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="432" docOffset="2">
      <en>rapporteur. - (DE) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, let me begin by translating the title of my report. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="553" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective> we speak of 'biological natural resources', we are referring to timber and fish.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, chers collègues, permettez-moi de commencer par vous traduire le titre de mon rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="639" docOffset="3">
      <en>Timber and fish are the key resources for the social and economic development of the West African region. It follows that we are <Alignment alignment="19591" annotation_id="768">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="768" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> speaking of deforestation.</en>
      <fr>Par "ressources naturelles biologiques", il faut entendre le bois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="729">et</DiscourseConnective> le poisson, qui sont deux produits clés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="772">pour</DiscourseConnective> le développement économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="805">et</DiscourseConnective> social de l'Afrique de l'Ouest C'est pour cette raison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="863">que</DiscourseConnective> nous parlons <Alignment alignment="768" annotation_id="880">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="880" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de la déforestation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="800" docOffset="4">
      <en>We all know how alarming this development is.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons tous conscience du caractère alarmant de ce phénomène.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="846" docOffset="5">
      <en>Of the forestry that existed in West Africa fifty years ago, only about 13% is still standing today.</en>
      <fr>Il ne reste plus aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1006">qu'</DiscourseConnective>environ 13 % de la superficie forestière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1050">que</DiscourseConnective> comptait l'Afrique de l'Ouest il y a cinquante ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="947" docOffset="6">
      <en>This means that 87% of the land that was once afforested has already been cleared.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1106">Autrement dit</DiscourseConnective>, 87 % des terres forestières ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1153">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été détruites.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1030" docOffset="7">
      <en>We all know what impact this has on climatic trends and the desertification process.</en>
      <fr>Nul n'en ignore les incidences sur les tendances climatiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1234">et</DiscourseConnective> le processus de désertification.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1115" docOffset="8">
      <en>We have equally alarming statistics on overfishing in that area of the Atlantic and the grave problems it is creating.</en>
      <fr>Nous disposons de statistiques tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1306">aussi</DiscourseConnective> alarmantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1323">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la surexploitation des ressources halieutiques dans cette partie de l'Atlantique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1423">et</DiscourseConnective> les graves problèmes que cela provoque.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1234" docOffset="9">
      <en>We are all familiar, of course, with the images of overloaded canoes landing on the Canary Islands with cargos of migrants from West Africa.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons tous vu ces images de canoës surchargés de migrants originaires d'Afrique de l'Ouest débarquant aux îles Canaries.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1375" docOffset="10">
      <en>The connection between the trends I have described and the increased migration to the European Union from West Africa is obvious and incontrovertible and is <Alignment alignment="16457" annotation_id="1532">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1532" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a subject of political debate, of course, within our societies.</en>
      <fr>Il existe un lien manifeste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1620">et</DiscourseConnective> indéniable entre les tendances que je viens de décrire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1678">et</DiscourseConnective> la hausse de l'immigration des pays de l'Afrique de l'Ouest vers l'Union européenne, lien qui suscite <Alignment alignment="1532" annotation_id="1783">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1783" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un débat politique au sein de nos sociétés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1601" docOffset="11">
      <en>The European Union is the main market for timber and fish.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne représente le principal marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1888">pour</DiscourseConnective> le bois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1901">et</DiscourseConnective> le poisson.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1660" docOffset="12">
      <en>We ourselves say that we buy some 80% of these products.</en>
      <fr>Nous reconnaissons nous-mêmes acheter environ 80 % de ces produits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1717" docOffset="13">
      <en>For this reason, it is prudent, and indeed essential, to review the coherence of our development policy, our fisheries policy and our policy on trade in timber in order to establish the extent to which they interact fruitfully <Alignment alignment="2179" annotation_id="1944">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1944" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whether their aims may <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1970" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> be mutually obstructive in some respects.</en>
      <fr>Il est donc prudent, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2005">et même</DiscourseConnective> essentiel, d'examiner la cohérence de nos politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2066">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de développement, de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2104">et</DiscourseConnective> de commerce du bois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2127">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>établir si leur conjonction est une réussite <Alignment alignment="1944" annotation_id="2179">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2179" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou bien</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2187">s'</DiscourseConnective>il peut arriver que leurs objectifs se fassent mutuellement obstruction.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2017" docOffset="14">
      <en>In the case of both products there is a need to prevent illegal plundering and to establish sustainable resource management.</en>
      <fr>Il est impératif d'empêcher l'exploitation illégale des deux produits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2332">en</DiscourseConnective> question, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2345">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que d'en assurer une gestion durable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2142" docOffset="15">
      <en>In the case of both products there is a need to ensure that the needs of the local economy and local consumers take precedence over international trade.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2392">s'</DiscourseConnective>impose également de garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2423">que</DiscourseConnective> ces deux produits servent à satisfaire en priorité les besoins de l'économie locale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2511">et</DiscourseConnective> des consommateurs locaux, et non pas ceux du commerce international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2295" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2295" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective> we do not achieve these aims, any self-sustaining development will be undermined, <Alignment alignment="2707" annotation_id="2380">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2380" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the success of any development cooperation will be put at risk.</en>
      <fr>La non-réalisation de ces objectifs compromettrait les possibilités de développement dans une perspective d'autosuffisance, <Alignment alignment="2380" annotation_id="2707">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2707" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que la réussite de la coopération au développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2448" docOffset="17">
      <en>That is why it is so important to conduct this coherence review in order to ensure that the other policies we pursue do not impair and undermine our development policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2765">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2787">si</DiscourseConnective> important de procéder à cette évaluation de la cohérence de nos politiques au service du développement, qui a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2900">pour</DiscourseConnective> but de garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2921">que</DiscourseConnective> les autres politiques que nous menons n'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2965">en</DiscourseConnective> compromettent pas l'efficacité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2617" docOffset="18">
      <en>We know the instruments with which we can improve the situation.</en>
      <fr>Nous savons quels sont les instruments qui peuvent nous permettre d'améliorer la situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2682" docOffset="19">
      <en>We need better monitoring of fish stocks and forests and better surveillance of the timber and fishing industries.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons améliorer, d'une part, le suivi des stocks halieutiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3160">et</DiscourseConnective> des forêts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3174">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3178">d'autre part</DiscourseConnective>, la surveillance des industries du bois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3231">et</DiscourseConnective> de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2797" docOffset="20">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="3260" annotation_id="2800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2800" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> need the establishment of the appropriate infrastructure for research into stock development and for the control and surveillance of economic activities.</en>
      <fr>Il nous faut <Alignment alignment="2800" annotation_id="3260">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3260" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> créer les infrastructures nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3304">pour</DiscourseConnective> la recherche sur le développement des stocks <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3354">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3357">pour</DiscourseConnective> le contrôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3374">et</DiscourseConnective> la surveillance des activités économiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2959" docOffset="21">
      <en>We have known this for a long time, <Alignment alignment="2784" annotation_id="2995">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2995" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> indeed that is the political course we have been steering for some time too.</en>
      <fr>Nous le savons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3435">depuis</DiscourseConnective> longtemps, <Alignment alignment="8833" annotation_id="3453">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3453" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3462">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective> cette direction politique que nous suivons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3516">depuis</DiscourseConnective> quelque temps maintenant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3076" docOffset="22">
      <en>In this context we must focus our efforts chiefly on combating illegal logging, illegal fishing and trade in illegal products.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte, nous devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3579">surtout</DiscourseConnective> centrer nos efforts sur la lutte contre l'exploitation et le commerce illégaux du bois, la pêche illicite et le commerce de produits issus de sources illégales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3203" docOffset="23">
      <en>We must do that locally in West Africa.</en>
      <fr>Et nous devons le faire localement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3783">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique de l'Ouest.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3243" docOffset="24">
      <en>To that end, we must support our partner countries in West Africa, which includes helping them to gain access to the EU market.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3806">Pour ce faire</DiscourseConnective>, nous devons soutenir nos pays partenaires d'Afrique de l'Ouest, ce qui implique notamment de les aider <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3924">à</DiscourseConnective> avoir accès au marché européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3371" docOffset="25">
      <en>We must develop our monitoring systems.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons développer nos systèmes de contrôle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3411" docOffset="26">
      <en>One of the vital tasks in the realm of development policy is to redirect our efforts towards a sustainable conservationist approach to logging, forestry management and fishing.</en>
      <fr>L'une des tâches essentielles qui nous incombent dans le cadre de la politique de développement consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4112">à</DiscourseConnective> réorienter nos efforts vers une approche durable en matière de gestion et d'exploitation du bois, des forêts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4223">et</DiscourseConnective> des ressources halieutiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3588" docOffset="27">
      <en>Allow me to deal with one more point and refer to a conflict concerning the report.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi d'évoquer un autre point, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4295">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'un conflit concernant mon rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3672" docOffset="28">
      <en>We stated in the report that we must improve the conditions for joint ventures between companies in the European Union and African partners <Alignment alignment="4497" annotation_id="3812">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3812" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that we must provide for the protection of investments.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons dit dans le rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4370">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons améliorer les conditions de création de sociétés mixtes entre entreprises européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4472">et</DiscourseConnective> partenaires africains <Alignment alignment="5944" annotation_id="4497">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4497" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> assurer la protection des investissements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3872" docOffset="29">
      <en>I find that right and proper, <Alignment alignment="25667" annotation_id="3902">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3902" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these are necessary measures, <Alignment alignment="4607" annotation_id="3936">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3936" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must ensure that they do not create excess capacities which undermine the pursuit of our other measures, such as those designed to combat overfishing.</en>
      <fr>Ces mesures me semblent tout à fait appropriées <Alignment alignment="8625" annotation_id="4591">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4591" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nécessaires, <Alignment alignment="9719" annotation_id="4607">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4607" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4637">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles ne créent pas de capacités excédentaires de nature à compromettre la mise en œuvre de nos autres mesures, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4752">notamment</DiscourseConnective> celles qui visent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4780">à</DiscourseConnective> lutter contre la surpêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4094" docOffset="30">
      <en>It is absolutely imperative that we resolve this conflict of aims.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons impérativement régler ce conflit d'objectifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4161" docOffset="31">
      <en>For this reason we added this statement to the opinion of the Committee on Fisheries as an additional point.</en>
      <fr>C'est d'ailleurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4884">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette raison que nous avons ajouté cette déclaration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4942">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avis de la commission de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4270" docOffset="32">
      <en>I am anxious that the procedural conflict about who is entitled to make additions to what <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4360" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> where <Alignment alignment="5085" annotation_id="4370">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4370" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4374" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> such additions can be made should not obscure the substance of the addition.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens vraiment à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5004">que</DiscourseConnective> ce désaccord quant aux personnes qui sont habilitées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5061">à</DiscourseConnective> procéder à des ajouts <Alignment alignment="4370" annotation_id="5085">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5085" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les conditions dans lesquelles ces ajouts sont autorisés n'obscurcisse pas la substance de l'ajout en question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4456" docOffset="33">
      <en>It is of prime importance, in my view, to uphold the principle that no new excess capacities should be created.</en>
      <fr>Il est, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5208">à</DiscourseConnective> mon sens, primordial de soutenir le principe consistant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5266">à</DiscourseConnective> interdire la création de capacités excédentaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4568" docOffset="34">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5318" annotation_id="4568">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4568" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you know, there has been a motion to delete this point from the report, <Alignment alignment="5390" annotation_id="4643">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4643" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must not allow that to happen.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4568" annotation_id="5318">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5318" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez, il a été proposé de supprimer ce point du rapport, <Alignment alignment="4643" annotation_id="5390">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5390" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons empêcher <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5416">que</DiscourseConnective> cela se produise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4681" id="222" name="Danuta Hübner">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4681" docOffset="35">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, I would like to start by congratulating the rapporteur, Mr Schmidt, on this report.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - Monsieur le Président, je tiens tout d'abord à féliciter le rapporteur, M. Schmidt, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5549">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4807" docOffset="36">
      <en>Policy coherence for development is an important issue, and let me assure you that reducing the adverse effects and fully exploiting synergies between European policies and development is an integral part of our efforts to achieve the Millennium Development Goals.</en>
      <fr>La cohérence des politiques au service du développement est une question importante, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5651">et</DiscourseConnective> je peux vous assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5675">que</DiscourseConnective> la réduction des incidences négatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5717">et</DiscourseConnective> l'exploitation des synergies entre les politiques européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5782">et</DiscourseConnective> le développement font partie intégrante des efforts que nous consentons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5857">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> réaliser les objectifs du Millénaire pour le développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5072" docOffset="37">
      <en>Other policies apart from development policy can <Alignment alignment="5927" annotation_id="5121">
          <Alignment alignment="5927" annotation_id="5121">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5121" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> contribute significantly to development, <Alignment alignment="6054" annotation_id="5170">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5170" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this naturally has a direct impact on the effectiveness of our aid.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5121" annotation_id="5927">
          <Alignment alignment="5121" annotation_id="5927">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5927" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, des politiques autres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5958">que</DiscourseConnective> la politique de développement peuvent contribuer de manière significative au développement, <Alignment alignment="4853" annotation_id="6054">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6054" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ceci a naturellement une incidence directe sur l'efficacité de notre aide.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5242" docOffset="38">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6132" annotation_id="5242">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5242" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you rightly state in your report, tropical deforestation is a matter of concern for us all <Alignment alignment="42758" annotation_id="5336">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5336" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I consider that a distinction should be made here between two aspects: deforestation and climate change on the one hand and combating illegal exploitation of forests on the other.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5242" annotation_id="6132">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6132" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le signalez à juste titre dans votre rapport, la déforestation tropicale est un sujet qui nous préoccupe tous, <Alignment alignment="11376" annotation_id="6254">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6254" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je considère à cet égard <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6282">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une distinction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6301">s'</DiscourseConnective>impose entre deux aspects, c'est-à-dire entre la déforestation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6366">et</DiscourseConnective> le changement climatique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6395">d'une part</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6407">et</DiscourseConnective> la lutte contre l'exploitation illégale des forêts, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6462">d'autre part</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5520" docOffset="39">
      <en>In Bali, the international community clearly identified the destruction of forests as one of the main causes of climate change.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6476">À</DiscourseConnective> Bali, la communauté internationale a clairement recensé la destruction des forêts parmi les principales causes du changement climatique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5648" docOffset="40">
      <en>In keeping with the spirit of the UN Climate Change Conference the Commission intends to contribute EUR 5 million in 2008 to the Forest Carbon Partnership Facility, which is run by the World Bank.</en>
      <fr>Conformément à l'esprit de la conférence des Nations unies sur le changement climatique, la Commission a l'intention de contribuer, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6747">en</DiscourseConnective> 2008, à hauteur de 5 millions d'euros au Fonds de partenariat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6812">pour</DiscourseConnective> le carbone forestier qui est géré par la Banque mondiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5845" docOffset="41">
      <en>An additional EUR 60 million will be earmarked up to 2010 to finance the Global Alliance against Climate Change, an initiative we launched last year to underpin the efforts of the poorest countries to adapt to climate change.</en>
      <fr>Une enveloppe supplémentaire de 60 millions d'euros sera affectée jusqu'en 2010 au financement de l'alliance mondiale contre le changement climatique, cette initiative que nous avons lancée l'année dernière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7082">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>appuyer les efforts des pays les plus pauvres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7135">pour</DiscourseConnective> s'adapter au changement climatique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6071" docOffset="42">
      <en>Lastly, several countries including Ghana, Cameroon, Mali, Sierra Leone and Cote d'Ivoire have <Alignment alignment="7383" annotation_id="6166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6166" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> included measures on the management of natural resources and governance of this sector in their national programmes for the 10th European Development Fund.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7176">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, plusieurs pays, dont le Ghana, le Cameroun, le Mali, la Sierra Leone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7252">et</DiscourseConnective> la Côte d'Ivoire, ont <Alignment alignment="17970" annotation_id="7277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7277" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> intégré dans leurs programmes nationaux au titre du 10e Fonds européen de développement des mesures relatives à la gestion des ressources naturelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7436">et</DiscourseConnective> à la gouvernance de ce secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6327" docOffset="43">
      <en>West Africa is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6342" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> an important partner of the Union <Alignment alignment="28965" annotation_id="6381">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6381" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it comes to combating the illegal exploitation of forests, <Alignment alignment="7594" annotation_id="6445">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6445" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> are Cameroon, Ghana, Liberia and Cote d'Ivoire, which export considerable amounts of timber to Europe.</en>
      <fr>L'Afrique de l'Ouest est un partenaire important de l'Union <Alignment alignment="12432" annotation_id="7531">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7531" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> matière de lutte contre l'exploitation illégale des forêts, <Alignment alignment="6445" annotation_id="7594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7594" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">au même titre que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Cameroun, le Ghana, le Liberia <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7646">et</DiscourseConnective> la Côte d'Ivoire, qui exportent des quantités considérables de bois vers l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6551" docOffset="44">
      <en>Two of these countries, Cameroon and Ghana, are at this very moment finalising a voluntary FLEGT partnership agreement with the Union, <Alignment alignment="40673" annotation_id="6686">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6686" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Liberia should be embarking on similar negotiations very shortly.</en>
      <fr>Deux de ces pays, le Cameroun <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7762">et</DiscourseConnective> le Ghana, finalisent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7786">en</DiscourseConnective> ce moment-même un accord de partenariat FLEGT volontaire avec l'Union, <Alignment alignment="6686" annotation_id="7860">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7860" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Liberia devrait se lancer dans des négociations similaires très prochainement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6756" docOffset="45">
      <en>In relation to fisheries policy, <Alignment alignment="7990" annotation_id="6789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6789" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you rightly emphasised, the new fisheries partnership agreements have brought about greater coherence between the common fisheries policy and development policy; these new agreements are no longer confined to offering fishing opportunities to Community vessels, <Alignment alignment="8299" annotation_id="7054">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7054" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="23651" annotation_id="7058">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7058" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> make it possible to embark on a dialogue with other partners in order to help them introduce a real sustainable and responsible fisheries policy in their waters.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7945">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la politique de la pêche, <Alignment alignment="6789" annotation_id="7990">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7990" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous l'avez souligné à juste titre, les nouveaux accords de partenariat dans le domaine de la pêche ont renforcé la cohérence entre la politique commune de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8161">et</DiscourseConnective> la politique de développement; ces nouveaux accords ne se limitent plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8236">à</DiscourseConnective> offrir des possibilités de pêche aux navires communautaires, <Alignment alignment="7054" annotation_id="8299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8299" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> permettent <Alignment alignment="7058" annotation_id="8315">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8315" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'engager un dialogue avec d'autres partenaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8369">afin de</DiscourseConnective> les aider à instaurer une pêche durable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8417">et</DiscourseConnective> responsable dans leurs eaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7225" docOffset="46">
      <en>In addition to the financial compensation granted under the fisheries agreements, which often contribute significantly to our partner countries' revenue and hence to their macroeconomic stability, these agreements form an essential political and legal basis.</en>
      <fr>Au-delà de leurs contreparties financières, qui représentent souvent une part significative des revenus de nos pays partenaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8577">et</DiscourseConnective> contribuent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8592">dès lors</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8601">à</DiscourseConnective> leur stabilité macroéconomique, les accords de pêche constituent une base politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8687">et</DiscourseConnective> juridique essentielle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7484" docOffset="47">
      <en>This enables the Community to facilitate the development of their fisheries policies on the basis of dialogue and in the light of the priorities our partners have established in their fisheries policies.</en>
      <fr>Cela permet à la Communauté de faciliter l'application des politiques de pêche de nos partenaires sur la base du dialogue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8835">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8838">à</DiscourseConnective> la lumière des priorités qu'ils ont définies dans leurs politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7688" docOffset="48">
      <en>Where I cannot agree with you, <Alignment alignment="8908" annotation_id="7719">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7719" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, is the statement in the report linking immigration and fisheries agreements.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7719" annotation_id="8908">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8908" sense="Comparison.Contrast">En revanche</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je ne peux être d'accord avec vous lorsque vous établissez un lien entre l'immigration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9008">et</DiscourseConnective> les accords de pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7805" docOffset="49">
      <en>Even the countries concerned - take <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7841" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for instance</DiscourseConnective> Senegal, in the person of its minister of state, Mr Djibo Ka - have publicly rejected the accusations that the presence of Community vessels is having a significant impact on resources and on the decline in profitability for non-industrial fishermen who are often the people most affected by illegal immigration.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9033">Même</DiscourseConnective> les pays concernés - prenez l'exemple du Sénégal, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9088">en</DiscourseConnective> la personne de son ministre d'État, M. Djibo Ka -, ont publiquement rejeté les accusations selon lesquelles la présence de navires communautaires aurait un impact significatif sur les ressources <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9286">et</DiscourseConnective> sur la baisse de la rentabilité de l'activité des pêcheurs non industriels, qui sont souvent les plus touchés par l'immigration clandestine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8167" docOffset="50">
      <en>We are indeed working with fishermen, NGOs and private partners in Europe and in these countries precisely to try and reduce as much as possible all negative interaction and unfair competition between our fishermen and the most vulnerable fishermen in these countries.</en>
      <fr>Nous travaillons avec les pêcheurs, des ONG <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9474">et</DiscourseConnective> des partenaires privés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9501">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9511">et</DiscourseConnective> dans ces pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9529">précisément</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9541">pour</DiscourseConnective> chercher <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9555">à</DiscourseConnective> réduire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9565">autant</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9572">que</DiscourseConnective> possible toutes les interactions négatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9619">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la concurrence déloyale entre nos pêcheurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9672">et</DiscourseConnective> les pêcheurs les plus vulnérables de ces pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8436" docOffset="51">
      <en>At the moment there is no European fleet competing with the non-industrial fleets of these countries in West Africa, <Alignment alignment="12321" annotation_id="8553">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8553" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the same cannot be said of other foreign industrial fleets.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9722">À</DiscourseConnective> l'heure actuelle, aucune flotte européenne ne fait concurrence aux flottes non industrielles de ces pays d'Afrique de l'Ouest, <Alignment alignment="11505" annotation_id="9851">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9851" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on ne peut pas en dire autant de toutes les autres flottes industrielles étrangères.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8622" id="223" name="Carmen Fraga Estévez">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8622" docOffset="52">
      <en>draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Fisheries. - (ES) First, I regret the unacceptable conduct of the Committee on Development, which is under the impression it is not subject to the Rules of Procedure of the European Parliament. It has circumvented the strengthened cooperation procedure set out in Rule 47 and corrected the Committee on Fisheries' statements on issues that are strictly within the latter's competence.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur pour avis de la commission de la pêche. - (ES) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9999">Avant</DiscourseConnective> tout, je tiens à dire que je déplore le comportement inacceptable de la commission du développement qui, ignorant le règlement du Parlement européen, s'est permis de se dérober <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10182">à</DiscourseConnective> la procédure de coopération renforcée prévue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10229">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 47 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10244">et</DiscourseConnective> de corriger les propos de la commission de la pêche sur des questions qui relèvent exclusivement de sa compétence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9052" docOffset="53">
      <en>It has <Alignment alignment="10369" annotation_id="9059">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9059" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> behaved in a completely untrustworthy way from the start of this report by obstinately trying to usurp the competence of the Committee on Fisheries on the issue of Fisheries Partnership Agreements.</en>
      <fr>Elle a <Alignment alignment="9059" annotation_id="10369">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10369" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> affiché un comportement absolument indigne dès le début de l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10440">histoire de</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10463">en</DiscourseConnective> cherchant obstinément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10488">à</DiscourseConnective> usurper la compétence de la commission de la pêche sur la question des accords de partenariat dans le domaine de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9262" docOffset="54">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="35993" annotation_id="9262">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9262" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Committee on Fisheries has issued an opinion that consciously sought to be completely respectful to the sensibilities we know this issue awakens in the Committee on Development, the latter has, <Alignment alignment="26529" annotation_id="9466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9466" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it intended from the beginning, intervened in purely common fishing policy matters.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9262" annotation_id="10613">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10613" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la commission de la pêche a rendu un avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10665">en</DiscourseConnective> s'efforçant consciencieusement de respecter pleinement les sensibilités que, comme chacun sait, ce sujet éveille chez les membres de la commission du développement, cette dernière a fini, <Alignment alignment="9466" annotation_id="10856">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10856" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle avait d'ailleurs cherché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10892">à</DiscourseConnective> le faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10903">depuis</DiscourseConnective> le début, par intervenir sur des questions relevant exclusivement de la politique commune de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9553" docOffset="55">
      <en>Mr President, some committee chairmen have a tendency to think they can do no wrong <Alignment alignment="26574" annotation_id="9637">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9637" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the Rules of Procedure do not apply to them, <Alignment alignment="44229" annotation_id="9691">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9691" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they should be their most prominent defenders.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, certains présidents de commission ont tendance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11083">à</DiscourseConnective> croire qu'il leur est impossible de faire mal <Alignment alignment="9637" annotation_id="11131">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11131" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11134">que</DiscourseConnective> le règlement du Parlement ne les concerne pas, <Alignment alignment="9691" annotation_id="11185">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11185" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils devraient en être les premiers défenseurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9747" docOffset="56">
      <en>The result is sterile confrontation between committees that damages the credibility of the whole institution.</en>
      <fr>Il en résulte des affrontements stériles entre commissions qui portent atteinte à la crédibilité de toute l'institution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9857" docOffset="57">
      <en>I hope that this case serves to stifle these temptations to abuse power <Alignment alignment="13968" annotation_id="9929">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9929" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that all those who are interested in learning about the role played by the Fisheries Partnership Agreements in the development of the villages and national fisheries of West Africa can make an analysis based on a comprehensive and uncensored report.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11371">que</DiscourseConnective> ce cas servira <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11390">à</DiscourseConnective> étouffer ces tentations d'abus de pouvoir <Alignment alignment="9929" annotation_id="11434">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11434" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11437">que</DiscourseConnective> tous ceux qui souhaitent connaître le rôle que jouent les accords de partenariat dans le domaine de la pêche dans le développement des villages <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11585">et</DiscourseConnective> des pêcheries nationales d'Afrique de l'Ouest pourront faire une analyse sur la base d'un rapport complet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11694">et</DiscourseConnective> non censuré.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10183" docOffset="58">
      <en>By presenting this amendment on behalf of the PPE-DE Group, this rapporteur wants to show our willingness to get back on course, <Alignment alignment="21890" annotation_id="10312">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10312" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have announced that <Alignment alignment="37095" annotation_id="10344">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10344" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the other political groups do not support the amendment, we will ask for the report to be returned to the competent committee for the fund.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11710">En</DiscourseConnective> présentant cet amendement au nom du groupe du PPE-DE, le rapporteur veut montrer notre volonté d'obtenir que le dossier reprenne son cours, <Alignment alignment="4119" annotation_id="11853">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11853" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ayons annoncé <Alignment alignment="5447" annotation_id="11881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11881" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les autres groupes politiques n'approuvent pas l'amendement, nous demanderons le renvoi du rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11987">à</DiscourseConnective> la commission compétente au fond.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10487" id="224" name="Filip Kaczmarek">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10487" docOffset="59">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (PL) Mr President, I would like to thank Mr Schmidt for a very thorough and detailed report.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12087">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier M. Schmidt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12110">pour</DiscourseConnective> son rapport très approfondi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12143">et</DiscourseConnective> détaillé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10613" docOffset="60">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12156" annotation_id="10613">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10613" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our development policy is really to be cohesive, then we need such detailed reports on issues relating to various aspects of development work.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="878" annotation_id="12156">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12156" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons vraiment que notre politique de développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12218">soit</DiscourseConnective> cohérente, il faut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12242">alors que</DiscourseConnective> nous élaborions des rapports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12281">aussi</DiscourseConnective> détaillés sur les différents aspects liés au développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10759" docOffset="61">
      <en>Of course, cooperation with other committees needs regulation, <Alignment alignment="2710" annotation_id="10822">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10822" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="12418" annotation_id="10827">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10827" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are to speak of policy cohesion, then clarification is needed regarding how individual parliamentary committees should work together.</en>
      <fr>Bien sûr, la coopération entre commissions doit être réglementée <Alignment alignment="17244" annotation_id="12412">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12412" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="10827" annotation_id="12418">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12418" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons pouvoir parler de cohérence des politiques, il faut clarifier les modalités de collaboration des commissions parlementaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10967" docOffset="62">
      <en>The analysis of the exploitation of natural resources in West Africa by the European Union provides a real, rather than a half-hearted, assessment of the role of the European Union in this African region.</en>
      <fr>L'analyse qui est faite de l'exploitation par l'Union européenne de certaines ressources naturelles de l'Afrique de l'Ouest offre une évaluation vraiment réaliste du rôle de l'UE dans cette région africaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11172" docOffset="63">
      <en>We should be aware that the use of natural resources has very concrete, and, sometimes, very painful and complex social consequences.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne devons pas oublier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12794">que</DiscourseConnective> l'exploitation des ressources naturelles a des conséquences sociales très concrètes qui sont parfois terribles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12909">et</DiscourseConnective> complexes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11306" docOffset="64">
      <en>In this context it is very worrying that fish resources in West Africa are being over-exploited, which could pose a danger for local development <Alignment alignment="13083" annotation_id="11451">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11451" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these resources provide food security in this region.</en>
      <fr>La surexploitation des ressources halieutiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12970">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique de l'Ouest est très préoccupante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13014">dans la mesure où</DiscourseConnective> elle risque de compromettre le développement local <Alignment alignment="5265" annotation_id="13083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13083" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce sont ces ressources qui assurent la sécurité alimentaire de cette région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11511" docOffset="65">
      <en>It is true that African nations often do not concern themselves with sustainable use of natural resources <Alignment alignment="38353" annotation_id="11617">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11617" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="13307" annotation_id="11622">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11622" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they do, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11634" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> it is to an insufficient degree.</en>
      <fr>Il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13180">que</DiscourseConnective> les nations africaines ne cherchent pas souvent à garantir une exploitation durable de leurs ressources naturelles <Alignment alignment="11617" annotation_id="13299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13299" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, <Alignment alignment="11622" annotation_id="13307">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13307" sense="Contingency.Condition">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles s'en soucient, leurs efforts restent insuffisants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11672" docOffset="66">
      <en>For this reason, we should view our activities in this region from both economic and ethical standpoints.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13371">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous devrions envisager les activités que nous exerçons dans cette région sous un angle tant économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13490">qu'</DiscourseConnective>éthique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11778" docOffset="67">
      <en>I can understand that many politicians prefer to see European fishermen on the west coast of Africa rather than in the streets of Brussels.</en>
      <fr>Je peux comprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13521">que</DiscourseConnective> les politiques préfèrent voir les pêcheurs européens sur la côte ouest de l'Afrique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13609">plutôt que</DiscourseConnective> dans les rues de Bruxelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11918" docOffset="68">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13648" annotation_id="11918">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11918" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we must be careful not to act hypocritically <Alignment alignment="15767" annotation_id="11972">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11972" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we cannot speak of a cohesive development policy without a sustainable fisheries economy in West Africa.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11918" annotation_id="13648">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13648" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons veiller à ne pas être faire preuve d'hypocrisie <Alignment alignment="9573" annotation_id="13713">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13713" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les politiques au service du développement ne sauraient être cohérentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13789">sans</DiscourseConnective> chercher à assurer la durabilité des activités de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13850">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique de l'Ouest.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12085" docOffset="69">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12085" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Similarly</DiscourseConnective>, we should not try to export our own social problems because, even <Alignment alignment="13958" annotation_id="12162">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12162" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we could export them, they could well come back to haunt us in the form of migration problems.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne devrions pas non plus chercher <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13912">à</DiscourseConnective> exporter nos propres problèmes sociaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13953">car</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="2902" annotation_id="13958">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13958" sense="Contingency.Condition">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous y parvenions, ils pourraient bien revenir nous hanter sous la forme de problèmes migratoires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12260" docOffset="70">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="19319" annotation_id="12262">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12262" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have the impression that we are using a kind of blackmail on ourselves by saying that, <Alignment alignment="20107" annotation_id="12354">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12354" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we take our fleets from West Africa, other fleets may take our place <Alignment alignment="14220" annotation_id="12426">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12426" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they will have even worse standards than those used at present.</en>
      <fr>J'ai <Alignment alignment="6367" annotation_id="14070">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14070" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'impression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14093">que</DiscourseConnective> nous nous faisons du chantage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14127">à</DiscourseConnective> nous-mêmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14140">en</DiscourseConnective> disant <Alignment alignment="699" annotation_id="14150">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14150" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous retirons nos flottes d'Afrique de l'Ouest, il se pourrait <Alignment alignment="12426" annotation_id="14220">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14220" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'autres flottes suivant des normes encore moins bonnes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14285">que</DiscourseConnective> celles qui sont appliquées actuellement prennent notre place.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12494" docOffset="71">
      <en>This is a dangerous way to think <Alignment alignment="14388" annotation_id="12527">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12527" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I do not believe that we should use such arguments.</en>
      <fr>Cette façon de faire est dangereuse, <Alignment alignment="12527" annotation_id="14388">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14388" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je ne crois pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14407">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14413">soit</DiscourseConnective> bon d'utiliser de tels arguments.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12583" id="225" name="Thijs Berman">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12583" docOffset="72">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (NL) Mr President, <Alignment alignment="29669" annotation_id="12632">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12632" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we fish out the sea off the coast of Mauritania, that causes the very poorest people to come to Europe as immigrants, <Alignment alignment="29787" annotation_id="12753">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12753" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they can no longer see any future at home.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (NL) Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="2385" annotation_id="14504">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14504" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous exploitons toutes les ressources au large des côtes mauritaniennes, cela incitera les populations les plus pauvres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14627">à</DiscourseConnective> émigrer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14637">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <Alignment alignment="12753" annotation_id="14647">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14647" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elles n'auront plus aucun avenir chez elles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12804" docOffset="73">
      <en>It is our poorest areas that have to deal with that, not the well-off areas.</en>
      <fr>Et ce sont nos régions les plus pauvres qui devront y faire face, et non les plus riches.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12881" docOffset="74">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="30502" annotation_id="12881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12881" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europe loses the support of its voters, especially those on very low incomes.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe perdra <Alignment alignment="12881" annotation_id="14802">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14802" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le soutien de ses électeurs, et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14842">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> de ceux dont les revenus sont les plus faibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12964" docOffset="75">
      <en>For that reason, too, cohesion policy is an absolute necessity.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14911">aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14917">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette raison que la politique de cohésion est une nécessité absolue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13028" docOffset="76">
      <en>It is sad in very many ways, but also entirely understandable, that Ireland has rejected the Lisbon Treaty.</en>
      <fr>Il est triste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15005">à</DiscourseConnective> de nombreux égards, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15027">mais</DiscourseConnective> à la fois parfaitement compréhensible, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15071">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Irlande ait rejeté le traité de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13136" docOffset="77">
      <en>The Lisbon Treaty is a real step forward for development policy.</en>
      <fr>Le traité de Lisbonne représente une réelle avancée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15171">pour</DiscourseConnective> la politique de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13201" docOffset="78">
      <en>It is the first text to establish coherence properly.</en>
      <fr>Ce texte est le premier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15231">à</DiscourseConnective> bien établir la cohérence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13255" docOffset="79">
      <en>The Union should not take away from the poor countries with one hand what is given with the other.</en>
      <fr>L'Union ne devrait pas reprendre d'une main aux pays pauvres ce qu'elle leur donne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15343">de l'autre</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13354" docOffset="80">
      <en>The policy of the Union on agriculture, fisheries, trade should not run counter to development policy.</en>
      <fr>Les politiques de l'Union dans les domaines de l'agriculture, de la pêche et du commerce ne doivent pas aller à l'encontre de la politique de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13457" docOffset="81">
      <en>Certainly it relates to several policy areas, <Alignment alignment="15563" annotation_id="13503">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13503" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is not a question of rivalry between committees in this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15512">Certes</DiscourseConnective>, il s'agit de domaines d'action différents, <Alignment alignment="638" annotation_id="15563">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15563" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il n'est pas question de rivalité entre commissions dans ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13580" docOffset="82">
      <en>That is an unimportant detail.</en>
      <fr>C'est un détail sans importance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13611" docOffset="83">
      <en>The Treaty of Nice only required the Union to show itself a coherent force in the world.</en>
      <fr>Le traité de Nice exigeait seulement de l'Union qu'elle se montre cohérente sur la scène internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13700" docOffset="84">
      <en>That turned out not to be enough.</en>
      <fr>Cela s'est révélé insuffisant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13734" docOffset="85">
      <en>The agricultural policy shamelessly allowed our surpluses, such as sugar and grain, to be dumped on the world market with export subsidies.</en>
      <fr>La politique agricole nous a permis sans vergogne d'écouler nos excédents, de sucre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15892">et</DiscourseConnective> de céréales par exemple, sur le marché mondial grâce aux subventions à l'exportation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13874" docOffset="86">
      <en>Fortunately those are now more or less a thing of the past.</en>
      <fr>Heureusement, ces subventions ont quasiment disparu aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13934" docOffset="87">
      <en>It is only in the Lisbon Treaty, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13967" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>, that supporters of the poor countries can find a legal basis enabling them to safeguard solidarity with the poorest people in the world.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16055">que</DiscourseConnective> dans le traité de Lisbonne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16086">que</DiscourseConnective> les défenseurs des pays pauvres peuvent trouver une base juridique leur permettant de préserver la solidarité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16200">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard des populations les plus pauvres du monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14112" docOffset="88">
      <en>Ireland <Alignment alignment="10824" annotation_id="14120">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14120" sense="Comparison.Contrast">nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> voted against it.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9774" annotation_id="16253">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16253" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Irlande a voté contre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14151" docOffset="89">
      <en>It was mainly the people with the lowest incomes who said no, <Alignment alignment="30982" annotation_id="14213">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14213" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the poorest in Europe do not identify enough with this European Union.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16291">surtout</DiscourseConnective> ceux dont les revenus sont les plus faibles qui ont voté non, <Alignment alignment="14213" annotation_id="16361">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16361" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les Européens les plus pauvres ne s'identifient pas assez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16423">à</DiscourseConnective> cette Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14292" docOffset="90">
      <en>Too much insecurity, too many risks for them, they have to put up with the consequences of this incoherent and anti-social policy.</en>
      <fr>Trop d'insécurité, trop de risques, ils doivent supporter les conséquences de cette politique incohérente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16555">et</DiscourseConnective> antisociale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14423" docOffset="91">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="30710" annotation_id="14423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14423" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the rapporteur, Mr Schmidt, has made crystal clear, the task is <Alignment alignment="16662" annotation_id="14490">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14490" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> to show solidarity with all citizens of Europe and in the developing countries, whilst respecting the environment.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19928" annotation_id="16571">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16571" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le rapporteur, M. Schmidt, l'a expliqué de manière on ne peut plus claire, il s'agit <Alignment alignment="13635" annotation_id="16662">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16662" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de faire preuve de solidarité à l'égard de tous les citoyens d'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16737">et</DiscourseConnective> des pays en développement tout en respectant l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14610" docOffset="92">
      <en>That is no small task.</en>
      <fr>Et ce n'est pas chose facile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14633" docOffset="93">
      <en>There is a strong temptation to trade one of those solidarities against the other.</en>
      <fr>On serait facilement tenté d'échanger une de ces solidarités contre l'autre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14716" docOffset="94">
      <en>All the same, they are not opposed.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16909">Or</DiscourseConnective>, elles n'ont rien de contradictoire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14752" docOffset="95">
      <en>Solidarity with developing countries is necessary for genuine solidarity with people on low incomes in Europe and the rest of the world.</en>
      <fr>La solidarité avec les pays en développement est nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17009">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire naître une solidarité authentique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17054">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard des personnes à faibles revenus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17096">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17106">et</DiscourseConnective> dans le reste du monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14889" id="226" name="Hélène Goudin">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14889" docOffset="96">
      <en>on behalf of the IND/DEM Group. - (SV) <Alignment alignment="17166" annotation_id="14928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14928" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> EU countries exploit the natural resources of poorer countries, they leave large footprints behind them.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe IND/DEM. - (SV) <Alignment alignment="11975" annotation_id="17166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17166" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les États membres de l'UE exploitent les ressources naturelles de pays plus pauvres, ils laissent de lourdes empreintes derrière eux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15038" docOffset="97">
      <en>Fisheries in West African waters are close to being exhausted, trade in illegal timber is destroying the environment, <Alignment alignment="32056" annotation_id="15156">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15156" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the exploitation of other natural resources has proved to have huge consequences in a poor and politically unstable region.</en>
      <fr>Les ressources halieutiques ouest-africaines sont proches de l'épuisement, le commerce illégal du bois détruit l'environnement <Alignment alignment="15156" annotation_id="17435">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17435" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'exploitation des autres ressources naturelles s'est révélée avoir de lourdes conséquences dans cette région pauvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17555">et</DiscourseConnective> politiquement instable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15284" docOffset="98">
      <en>Our activities have effects on the local population.</en>
      <fr>Nos activités ne sont pas sans avoir d'incidences sur la population locale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15337" docOffset="99">
      <en>The report seeks more cohesion between the EU countries and wants the European Parliament to have more of a say.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport cherche à renforcer la cohésion entre les États membres de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17733">et</DiscourseConnective> souhaite que le Parlement européen ait voix au chapitre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15450" docOffset="100">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17793" annotation_id="15450">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15450" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> many special interests are represented in this Parliament, which means that a European aid policy is bound to fail.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="15450" annotation_id="17793">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17793" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, une multitude d'intérêts particuliers étant représentés au Parlement, une politique d'aide européenne est vouée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17909">à</DiscourseConnective> l'échec.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15570" docOffset="101">
      <en>The international work should be conducted by the United Nations and other organisations.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont les Nations unies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17946">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres organisations qui devraient diriger l'action internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15660" docOffset="102">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18019" annotation_id="15660">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15660" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we really want to change the world <Alignment alignment="18062" annotation_id="15698">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15698" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we say, we must resort to other measures.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4391" annotation_id="18019">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18019" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous tenons vraiment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18043">à</DiscourseConnective> changer le monde <Alignment alignment="3862" annotation_id="18062">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18062" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous le déclarons, nous devons avoir recours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18113">à</DiscourseConnective> d'autres mesures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15743" docOffset="103">
      <en>What the EU should do is to review and reform its own policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18133">En fait</DiscourseConnective>, l'UE devrait revoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18162">et</DiscourseConnective> réformer sa propre politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15805" docOffset="104">
      <en>The EU must cease to subsidise failed European agriculture, end the hidden protectionism which characterises its trade policy and abandon its immoral fisheries agreements.</en>
      <fr>Elle doit cesser de subventionner l'agriculture européenne en faillite, mettre fin au protectionnisme dissimulé qui caractérise sa politique commerciale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18348">et</DiscourseConnective> abandonner ses accords de pêche immoraux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15977" id="227" name="Bogdan Golik">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15977" docOffset="105">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, according to the resolutions passed by the European Union, most Member States concentrate their aid activities on subsaharan Africa, which <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16135" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> includes the states of West Africa.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, conformément aux résolutions votées par l'Union européenne, la plupart des États membres concentrent leurs activités d'aide sur l'Afrique subsaharienne, qui englobe les États d'Afrique de l'Ouest.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16176" docOffset="106">
      <en>This region has the greatest development needs.</en>
      <fr>C'est dans cette région que les besoins de développement sont les plus importants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16224" docOffset="107">
      <en>Poland, too, supports the European Union's standpoint as regards development policy and supports the realisation of the Millennium Development Goals in this region.</en>
      <fr>La Pologne soutient elle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18726">aussi</DiscourseConnective> la position de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18766">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de politique de développement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18808">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la réalisation des objectifs du Millénaire pour le développement dans cette région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16389" docOffset="108">
      <en>There is growing support in Polish public opinion for aid to developing countries.</en>
      <fr>L'opinion publique polonaise soutient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18940">de plus</DiscourseConnective> en plus le principe de l'aide aux pays en développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16472" docOffset="109">
      <en>Last year this stood at 77%.</en>
      <fr>77 % de l'opinion publique y étaient favorables l'année dernière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16501" docOffset="110">
      <en>At the same time we are aware of the need to increase the efforts made by individual Member States to fulfil their obligations and to increase the cohesiveness and effectiveness of European development policy.</en>
      <fr>Dans le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19079">même</DiscourseConnective> temps, nous avons conscience de la nécessité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19129">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres redoublent d'efforts pour se conformer à leurs obligations, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19211">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que de la nécessité de renforcer la cohérence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19263">et</DiscourseConnective> l'efficacité de la politique de développement européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16711" docOffset="111">
      <en>At present a very important issue, in view of the existing divisions here, is the preparation of a common standpoint of the European Union and of the Parliament for the conferences in Accra and Doha.</en>
      <fr>Eu égard aux divergences existantes, il est aujourd'hui essentiel de préparer une position commune de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19445">et</DiscourseConnective> du Parlement en vue des conférences d'Accra <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19492">et</DiscourseConnective> de Doha.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16911" docOffset="112">
      <en>Africa, as a region with the largest number of developing countries, has little experience of protecting its own biological resources.</en>
      <fr>L'Afrique, qui est la région qui regroupe le plus grand nombre de pays en développement, a peu d'expérience en matière de protection de ses propres ressources biologiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17046" docOffset="113">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12661" annotation_id="17046">
          <Alignment alignment="19782" annotation_id="17046">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17046" sense="Comparison.Contrast">On the other hand</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, it is very important for Europe to have access to African mineral resources, <Alignment alignment="19773" annotation_id="17142">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17142" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is a policy that it is pursuing together with China and the Russian Federation.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="10177" annotation_id="19683">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19683" sense="Comparison.Contrast">à</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la fois très important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19708">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe d'avoir accès aux ressources minérales africaines, <Alignment alignment="17142" annotation_id="19773">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19773" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est <Alignment alignment="17046" annotation_id="19782">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19782" sense="Comparison.Contrast">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19807">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle mène conjointement avec la Chine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19848">et</DiscourseConnective> la Fédération de Russie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17231" docOffset="114">
      <en>It is vital for European partners to improve their commercial attractiveness and to make development aid less dependent on democratic reforms in Africa.</en>
      <fr>Il est vital <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19889">que</DiscourseConnective> les partenaires européens améliorent leur attrait commercial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19954">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'ils fassent en sorte que l'aide au développement soit moins subordonnée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20032">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en mise en œuvre de réformes démocratiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20085">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17384" docOffset="115">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17384" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In particular</DiscourseConnective>, access to EU food markets is important to African nations.</en>
      <fr>L'accès aux marchés alimentaires européens est particulièrement important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20171">pour</DiscourseConnective> les nations africaines.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17458" docOffset="116">
      <en>We should give them this access, before Brazil, the USA or Australia.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions donc leur permettre d'y accéder, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20247">avant</DiscourseConnective> le Brésil, les États-Unis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20279">ou</DiscourseConnective> l'Australie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17528" docOffset="117">
      <en>What is needed is greater complementarity, cohesion and coordination in the aid programmes of the EU and of individual Member States.</en>
      <fr>Il faut améliorer la complémentarité, la cohésion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20345">et</DiscourseConnective> la coordination entre les programmes d'aide de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20400">et</DiscourseConnective> ceux des États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17662" docOffset="118">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20427" annotation_id="17662">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17662" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> regards the use of natural resources in West Africa, it is necessary to have an effective system for assessing the extent of this use, as well as better controls over it.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17662" annotation_id="20427">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20427" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">S'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>agissant de l'exploitation des ressources naturelles de l'Afrique de l'Ouest, il faut mettre en place un système efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20551">pour</DiscourseConnective> en évaluer l'ampleur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20577">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20580">en</DiscourseConnective> améliorer le contrôle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17836" docOffset="119">
      <en>I would like to thank Mr Schmidt for drawing attention to all these issues.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20615">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier M. Schmidt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20638">pour</DiscourseConnective> avoir attiré notre attention sur toutes ces questions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17912" id="229" name="Danuta Hübner">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17912" docOffset="120">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the discussion at this very late hour has clearly indicated the importance we all attach to this issue, <Alignment alignment="20883" annotation_id="18058">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18058" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> once again I thank Parliament for the report.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - Monsieur le Président, ce débat qui s'est tenu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20772">à</DiscourseConnective> une heure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20784">aussi</DiscourseConnective> tardive a clairement indiqué l'importance que nous attachons tous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20856">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet, et je remercie <Alignment alignment="18058" annotation_id="20883">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20883" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à nouveau le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20911">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18107" docOffset="121">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23486" annotation_id="18107">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18107" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> has rightly been pointed out, timber and fish are two key products for the economic and social development of West Africa.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7950" annotation_id="20928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20928" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il a été dit, le bois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20956">et</DiscourseConnective> le poisson sont deux produits clés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20994">pour</DiscourseConnective> le développement économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21027">et</DiscourseConnective> social de l'Afrique de l'Ouest.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18233" docOffset="122">
      <en>Let me emphasise strongly once again that ensuring that the exploitation of these natural resources is consistent with development goals must remain a priority for the European Union and for the countries of West Africa.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens à rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21082">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est primordial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21103">que</DiscourseConnective> la cohérence de l'exploitation de ces ressources naturelles avec les objectifs de développement reste une priorité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21222">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21246">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21249">pour</DiscourseConnective> les pays d'Afrique de l'Ouest.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18454" docOffset="123">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21285" annotation_id="18454">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18454" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I explained in my initial presentation and would like to reiterate now, the Commission is committed to this objective, <Alignment alignment="21376" annotation_id="18576">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18576" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the resolution Parliament is going to adopt tomorrow will be an important contribution to our work.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18454" annotation_id="21285">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21285" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai expliqué dans mon exposé initial, la Commission est attachée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21360">à</DiscourseConnective> cet objectif, <Alignment alignment="18576" annotation_id="21376">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21376" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la résolution que le Parlement va adopter demain représentera une contribution importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21469">à</DiscourseConnective> notre travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18680" id="230" name="Frithjof Schmidt">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18680" docOffset="124">
      <en>rapporteur. - (DE) Mr President, the first thing I wish to do - and this may come as a surprise in the light of her intervention - is to express my thanks to Mrs Fraga Estévez, <Alignment alignment="21654" annotation_id="18857">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18857" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">for</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we personally cooperated very constructively on the report and resolved numerous problems too.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21528">avant</DiscourseConnective> toute chose - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21548">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21551">aussi</DiscourseConnective> étonnant que cela puisse paraître vu son intervention - je souhaite remercier Mme Fraga Estévez, <Alignment alignment="9675" annotation_id="21654">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21654" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons coopéré de manière très constructive sur ce rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21721">et</DiscourseConnective> avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21730">aussi</DiscourseConnective> résolu de nombreux problèmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18956" docOffset="125">
      <en>We should keep that separate from the institutional conflict which exists between the Committee on Fisheries and the Committee on Development regarding the interpretation of the Rules of Procedure.</en>
      <fr>Cela doit en effet rester <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21792">en</DiscourseConnective> dehors du conflit institutionnel qui existe entre la commission de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21871">et</DiscourseConnective> la commission du développement concernant l'interprétation du règlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19154" docOffset="126">
      <en>The latter has something to do with the fact that, as a result of the ICEI study, we have been allocated the new task of performing coherence checks.</en>
      <fr>Ce conflit est lié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21966">au fait</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21974">que</DiscourseConnective>, suite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21985">à</DiscourseConnective> l'étude de l'ICEI, nous nous sommes vus confier la nouvelle mission d'effectuer des contrôles de cohérence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19304" docOffset="127">
      <en>The Council decided that measures in 12 policy areas were to be checked for consistency with development policy.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil a décidé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22115">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il fallait contrôler la cohérence des mesures adoptées dans douze domaines d'action avec la politique de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19417" docOffset="128">
      <en>These policy areas are always part of the remit of other committees. This naturally keeps causing institutional conflicts.</en>
      <fr>Et ces domaines relèvent toujours de la compétence d'autres commissions, ce qui, naturellement, ne manque pas de provoquer des conflits institutionnels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19540" docOffset="129">
      <en>It is a problem, <Alignment alignment="22410" annotation_id="19557">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19557" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19569" sense="Comparison.Contrast">nevertheless</DiscourseConnective> like to thank you for our good personal cooperation on the substance of the report.</en>
      <fr>C'est un problème, <Alignment alignment="317" annotation_id="22410">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22410" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je tiens tout de même <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22437">à</DiscourseConnective> vous remercier de la coopération que vous m'avez apportée à titre personnel sur le fond du rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19666" docOffset="130">
      <en>Commissioner, I believe that the Commission has been on the right lines with the FLEGT process and with the new Fisheries Partnership Agreement since 2002.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Commissaire, je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22571">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission suit la bonne voie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22608">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 20002 avec le processus FLEGT <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22645">et</DiscourseConnective> les nouveaux accords de partenariat dans le domaine de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19822" docOffset="131">
      <en>That is a sound basis for further progress, <Alignment alignment="22756" annotation_id="19866">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19866" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would like to encourage you to proceed resolutely along that path towards the promotion of sustainable development.</en>
      <fr>C'est une bonne base <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22734">pour</DiscourseConnective> pouvoir avancer, <Alignment alignment="19866" annotation_id="22756">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22756" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'aimerais vous encourager <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22786">à</DiscourseConnective> continuer de suivre résolument cette voie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22830">pour</DiscourseConnective> la promotion du développement durable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19988" docOffset="132">
      <en>There is still a lot to be done here.</en>
      <fr>Il reste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22883">encore</DiscourseConnective> beaucoup <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22899">à</DiscourseConnective> faire dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20026" docOffset="133">
      <en>This sound approach must be further developed.</en>
      <fr>Cette approche solide demande à être développée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20073" docOffset="134">
      <en>In so doing, you can surely rely on the support of this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Et vous pouvez compter sur le soutien du Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23024">pour ce faire</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20141" docOffset="135">
      <en>Let me say one final word on the link between migration and overfishing.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de dire un dernier mot sur le lien entre l'immigration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23108">et</DiscourseConnective> la surpêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20214" docOffset="136">
      <en>I need hardly say that it is not the sole cause of migration, for which there are many reasons.</en>
      <fr>Évidemment, ce n'est pas la seule cause d'émigration. Il en existe en effet beaucoup d'autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20310" docOffset="137">
      <en>There are, <Alignment alignment="23247" annotation_id="20321">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20321" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, clear indications that overfishing does play a part.</en>
      <fr>Certains éléments indiquent <Alignment alignment="854" annotation_id="23247">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23247" sense="Comparison.Contrast">néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de manière claire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23275">que</DiscourseConnective> la surpêche y est pour quelque chose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20383" docOffset="138">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23317" annotation_id="20383">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20383" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">And</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Union, among others, is involved in that overfishing.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="21198" annotation_id="23317">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23317" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne, entre autres, contribue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23364">à</DiscourseConnective> cette surpêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20454" docOffset="139">
      <en>The International Organization for Migration has just provided very tangible evidence of this link in relation to Senegal.</en>
      <fr>L'Organisation internationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23412">pour</DiscourseConnective> les migrations vient de communiquer des éléments tangibles qui prouvent l'existence de ce lien dans le cas du Sénégal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20577" docOffset="140">
      <en>To that extent the President of Senegal would be very ill-advised to close his eyes to the reality within his country and off its shores.</en>
      <fr>Il serait dès lors malavisé de la part du Président du Sénégal de fermer les yeux sur cette réalité qui touche son pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23657">et</DiscourseConnective> en particulier les zones côtières.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20715" docOffset="141">
      <en>We should examine these matters more critically and address and resolve these problems together.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions étudier ces questions sous un angle plus critique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23759">et</DiscourseConnective> chercher <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23771">à</DiscourseConnective> résoudre tous ces problèmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20812" id="231" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20812" docOffset="142">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20834" docOffset="143">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow at 12 noon.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23846">à</DiscourseConnective> midi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
