<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>7.</en>
    <fr>7.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Communication infrastructure for the Schengen Information System environment (decision) (vote)</en>
    <fr>Infrastructure de communication <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'environnement du système d'information Schengen (décision) (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="98" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Report: Carlos Coelho (A6-0357-2007)</en>
    <fr>- Rapport: Carlos Coelho (A6-0357-2007)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="137" docOffset="3">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="150">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="156" id="125" name="Carlos Coelho ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="156" docOffset="4">
      <en>rapporteur. - (PT) Mr President, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="189" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> we are running late, just three brief comments: firstly, Parliament regrets the delay in SIS II; secondly Parliament is facing an emergency situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="342" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="350" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> we do not decide now, the Member States may have to re-establish internal borders, which is unacceptable; thirdly, Parliament prefers the technical solution of extending the agreement with SISNET and regards the alternative solution of the agreement with s-Testa to be a financially damaging solution, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="655" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> unfortunately we have to keep both on the table to prevent the raising of borders that no one wants.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (PT) M. le Président, comme nous sommes en retard, simplement trois brefs commentaires: d'abord, le Parlement regrette le retard du SIS II; ensuite, le Parlement est confronté à une situation d'urgence, car si nous ne prenons pas une décision maintenant, les États membres devront peut-être rétablir leurs frontières intérieures, ce qui est inacceptable; troisièmement, le Parlement préfère la solution technique du prolongement de l'accord avec le SISNET et juge la solution de remplacement de l'accord avec s-Testa nuisible financièrement, mais nous devons hélas garder les deux sur la table pour éviter le dressage des frontières que personne ne souhaite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
