<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>7.</en>
    <fr>7.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Coordination of social security systems: implementing Regulation (</en>
    <fr>Coordination des systèmes de sécurité sociale: modalités d'application (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="70" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="78">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="89" id="088" name="Jean Lambert">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="89" docOffset="3">
      <en>rapporteur. - Mr President, I wish to begin by thanking all colleagues who have been involved in this over the last five years and the Commission and the Council for their work on this implementing regulation.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je tiens tout d'abord à remercier tous les collègues qui se sont investis dans ce dossier au cours des cinq dernières années, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="261">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="286">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="300">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail qu'ils ont fourni dans le cadre de ce règlement d'application.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="299" docOffset="4">
      <en>The coordination of social security systems has been in place since 1971 - it is not new, <Alignment alignment="1100" annotation_id="389">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="389" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> some thought the last time we discussed it - <Alignment alignment="2748" annotation_id="437">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="437" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is this regulation that will be discussed in the context of the cross-border health-care debate on Thursday morning.</en>
      <fr>La coordination des systèmes de sécurité sociale existe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="435">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 1971 - elle n'a rien de nouveau, <Alignment alignment="233" annotation_id="475">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="475" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le pensaient certains la dernière fois que nous en avons débattu -, <Alignment alignment="16" annotation_id="549">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="549" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est ce règlement qui sera débattu dans le cadre du débat de jeudi matin sur les soins de santé transfrontaliers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="561" docOffset="5">
      <en>This is the regulation to which that refers, <Alignment alignment="710" annotation_id="606">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="606" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is the implementation of it.</en>
      <fr>C'est de ce règlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="689">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il sera question, <Alignment alignment="1012" annotation_id="710">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="710" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est ce règlement qui en marquera l'application.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="644" docOffset="6">
      <en>We believe we have made considerable progress, not least in terms of the electronic means of communication, which hopefully will speed up the process for all citizens, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="812" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> we in Parliament believe that we have added to citizens' rights within this process, that they are now entitled to much more information, not least in the case of those who have been posted for work purposes.</en>
      <fr>Nous pensons avoir accompli des progrès considérables, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="818">notamment</DiscourseConnective> sur le plan des modes de communication électronique, ce qui permettra, je l'espère, d'accélérer la procédure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="937">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous les citoyens. Au Parlement, nous estimons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="989">que</DiscourseConnective>, par ce processus, nous avons renforcé les droits des citoyens et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1059">que</DiscourseConnective> ceux-ci ont à présent droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1091">à</DiscourseConnective> bien plus d'informations, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1119">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans le cas des informations publiées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1167">à</DiscourseConnective> des fins professionnelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1025" docOffset="7">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="1209" annotation_id="1028">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1028" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> believe we have made minimal progress on deadlines - <Alignment alignment="1279" annotation_id="1086">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1086" sense="Comparison.Concession">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is something that rests with the Member States.</en>
      <fr>Nous pensons <Alignment alignment="1028" annotation_id="1209">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1209" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avoir accompli des progrès minimaux concernant les délais - <Alignment alignment="474" annotation_id="1279">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1279" sense="Comparison.Concession">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette question reste du ressort des États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1148" docOffset="8">
      <en>This is important: it now means we can bring in the updated regulation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1219" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>, hopefully, this will work more rapidly and in the best interests of all citizens.</en>
      <fr>C'est important: nous pouvons à présent présenter le règlement actualisé. Espérons que celui-ci produira ses effets de manière plus rapide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1478">et</DiscourseConnective> dans le meilleur intérêt de tous les citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1306" docOffset="9">
      <en>Again, I would like to thank all colleagues who have been involved in this long, difficult but, hopefully, very fruitful outcome.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1537">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier à nouveau l'ensemble des collègues qui se sont investis dans ce travail long et difficile, que nous espérons malgré tout extrêmement fructueux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1436" docOffset="10">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
