<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>27.</en>
    <fr>27.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Quota system in relation to the production of potato starch (vote)</en>
    <fr>Régime de contingentement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30">pour</DiscourseConnective> la production de fécule de pomme de terre (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="71" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Report: Wojciechowski, Janusz</en>
    <fr>Rapport Wojciechowski, Janusz</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="103" docOffset="3">
    <en>- Before the vote on Amendment 8:</en>
    <fr>
      <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="114">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote sur l'amendement 8</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="137" id="145" name="Janusz Wojciechowski ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="137" docOffset="4">
      <en>rapporteur. - (PL) Mr President, We recently voted on an amendment to extend the system of starch quotas to four years.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, nous avons voté récemment sur un amendement visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="240">à</DiscourseConnective> reconduire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="253">pour</DiscourseConnective> quatre ans le régime de contingentement pour la production de fécule.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="257" docOffset="5">
      <en>This is good news for the old Member States who have 90% of these quotas, which is enough to meet their requirements.</en>
      <fr>C'est une bonne nouvelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="353">pour</DiscourseConnective> les anciens États membres qui détiennent 90 % de ces contingents, ce qui suffit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="438">pour</DiscourseConnective> répondre à leurs exigences.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="375" docOffset="6">
      <en>Let us now do something nice for the new Member States, which are less happy with their quotas, <Alignment alignment="594" annotation_id="471">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="471" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> adopt amendment eight.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="471">Maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, faisons quelque chose de bien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="513">pour</DiscourseConnective> les nouveaux États membres, qui sont moins satisfaits de leurs contingents, <Alignment alignment="471" annotation_id="594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="594" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> adoptons l'amendement 8.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="498" docOffset="7">
      <en>This will allow quotas to be carried over from one year to the next - what the old Member States do not use in one year should be allocated in the following year to the new Member States, with the agreement of the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Cela permettra de reporter d'une année <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="661">à</DiscourseConnective> l'autre les contingents - ce que les anciens États membres n'utilisent pas au cours d'une année devrait être attribué l'année suivante aux nouveaux États membres, avec l'accord de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="724" docOffset="8">
      <en>I would like to point out that in the long term this amendment would not lead to an increase in quotas, <Alignment alignment="956" annotation_id="828">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="828" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I ask that it be approved for the sake of European solidarity.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="879">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="884">à</DiscourseConnective> long terme, cet amendement n'impliquera pas de hausse des contingents <Alignment alignment="828" annotation_id="956">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="956" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je demande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="970">qu'</DiscourseConnective>on l'adopte dans l'intérêt de la solidarité européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="895" docOffset="9">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1029" annotation_id="895">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="895" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this amendment is adopted, I have been authorised by the Union for Europe of the Nations Group to withdraw amendments five, six and seven, which will result in an increase in quotas.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="895" annotation_id="1029">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1029" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cet amendement est adopté, j'ai été autorisé par le groupe Union <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1097">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe des nations de retirer les amendements 5, 6 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1155">et</DiscourseConnective> 7, qui entraînent une augmentation des quotas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1081" id="146" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1081" docOffset="10">
      <en>We have received some information that would have been more appropriate during the course of the debate which has already taken place on the report.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons reçu des informations qui auraient été plus appropriées au cours du débat qui a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1296">déjà</DiscourseConnective> eu lieu sur le rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
