<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statements by the President (membership of Parliament; ETA)</en>
    <fr>Déclarations du Président (composition du Parlement; ETA)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="60" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="60" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, it is a great joy for me to be able to welcome today 18 fellow Members from Bulgaria - the first directly elected MEPS - to this House, and thus into our midst.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="67">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, c'est avec une grande joie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="108">que</DiscourseConnective> j'accueille aujourd'hui 18 députés bulgares - les premiers directement élus - au sein de cette Assemblée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="217">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="220">donc</DiscourseConnective> parmi nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="243" docOffset="2">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="254" docOffset="3">
      <en>The citizens of Bulgaria went to the polls on 20 May 2007 and elected their representatives to the European Parliament in a democratic process.</en>
      <fr>Les citoyens bulgares se sont rendus aux urnes le 20 mai 2007 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="318">pour</DiscourseConnective> élire leurs représentants au Parlement européen dans le cadre d'un scrutin démocratique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="398" docOffset="4">
      <en>This was an important day for Bulgaria, which joined the European Union on 1 January. It completes Bulgaria's integration into the European family after the fall of communism.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agissait d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="428">un jour</DiscourseConnective> important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="446">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Bulgarie, qui a rejoint l'Union européenne le 1er janvier, qui marque l'achèvement de l'intégration de la Bulgarie dans la famille européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="596">après</DiscourseConnective> la chute du communisme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="574" docOffset="5">
      <en>It took over 60 years for Bulgaria to be restored to a free Europe and for our continent to be reunited.</en>
      <fr>Il aura fallu plus de 60 ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="655">pour</DiscourseConnective> ramener la Bulgarie dans une Europe libre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="702">et</DiscourseConnective> réunifier notre continent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="679" docOffset="6">
      <en>Bulgaria's culture is an ancient one, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="717" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> the country is situated at a crossing point between East and West.</en>
      <fr>La Bulgarie est une terre de civilisation séculaire, située au croisement de l'Orient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="818">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'Occident.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="788" docOffset="7">
      <en>It is claimed to be the site of one of the oldest countries in Europe, founded in 681.</en>
      <fr>C'est là, dit-on, que le plus ancien État européen fut fondé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="897">en</DiscourseConnective> 681.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="875" docOffset="8">
      <en>Bulgaria is the country of Orpheus and Eurydice, the home of the Thracians and of Dionysus.</en>
      <fr>La Bulgarie est le pays d'Orphée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="938">et</DiscourseConnective> d'Eurydice, la patrie des Thraces <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="975">et</DiscourseConnective> de Dionysos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="967" docOffset="9">
      <en>It brings with it a rich cultural and intellectual heritage, and will <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1037" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> contribute to the mutual enrichment of the European Union and Bulgaria.</en>
      <fr>Elle apporte un riche patrimoine culturel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1033">et</DiscourseConnective> intellectuel qui contribuera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1065">à</DiscourseConnective> l'enrichissement mutuel de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1113">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Bulgarie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1114" docOffset="10">
      <en>Particular thanks are due to Bulgaria, and especially its people, for their efforts over recent years and the willingness to undertake reforms.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais tout particulièrement remercier la Bulgarie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1189">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1192">surtout</DiscourseConnective> les Bulgares, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1214">pour</DiscourseConnective> les efforts accomplis ces dernières années <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1262">et</DiscourseConnective> la volonté d'entreprendre des réformes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1258" docOffset="11">
      <en>Great progress has been made, <Alignment alignment="1342" annotation_id="1288">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1288" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> many reforms were accomplished in a relatively short period of time.</en>
      <fr>Beaucoup de progrès ont été réalisés <Alignment alignment="1288" annotation_id="1342">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1342" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de nombreuses réformes ont été mises en œuvre sur une période relativement courte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1361" docOffset="12">
      <en>It is now up to our new fellow Members to help ensure that the reforms that remain necessary are implemented with the same determination.</en>
      <fr>Il appartient aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1454">à</DiscourseConnective> nos nouveaux députés de conduire les réformes qui restent à accomplir avec la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1534">même</DiscourseConnective> détermination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1499" docOffset="13">
      <en>I wish you a speedy, successful integration into the work of the European Parliament so that, with your work and efforts, you are able to make a constructive contribution for the benefit of your voters and of Europe.</en>
      <fr>Je vous souhaite une intégration rapide et fructueuse dans les travaux du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1647">afin de</DiscourseConnective> pouvoir y contribuer de manière constructive dans l'intérêt de vos électeurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1732">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1716" docOffset="14">
      <en>You will be the voice of Bulgarian citizens in the European Parliament, and will represent their interests.</en>
      <fr>Vous serez les porte-parole des citoyens bulgares au sein du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1828">et</DiscourseConnective> vous représenterez leurs intérêts.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1824" docOffset="15">
      <en>Let us work together on the further development of our European community!</en>
      <fr>Travaillons ensemble au développement futur de notre communauté européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1899" docOffset="16">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1910" docOffset="17">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, in agreement with the chairmen of the groups and the whole of the European Parliament - and seeing Mrs Dührkop Dührkop in our midst - I should like to make the following statement on behalf of this House.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1970">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1984">en</DiscourseConnective> accord avec les présidents des groupes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2026">et</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble du Parlement européen - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2064">et</DiscourseConnective> en présence de Mme Dührkop Dührkop -, je voudrais faire la déclaration suivante au nom de cette Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2137" docOffset="18">
      <en>The terrorist organisation ETA has declared the 'ceasefire' announced on 22 March 2006 at an end.</en>
      <fr>L'organisation terroriste ETA a rompu le cessez-le-feu décrété le 22 mars 2006.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2235" docOffset="19">
      <en>I should like to express my solidarity with the entire Spanish nation and its democratic institutions in these difficult times.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais exprimer ma solidarité avec toute la nation espagnole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2320">et</DiscourseConnective> ses institutions démocratiques dans ces moments difficiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2363" docOffset="20">
      <en>Parliament firmly condemns the use of violence <Alignment alignment="2444" annotation_id="2410">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2410" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a means to any end.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement condamne énergiquement le recours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2430">à</DiscourseConnective> la violence <Alignment alignment="2410" annotation_id="2444">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2444" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> moyen d'aboutir à un objectif, quel qu'il soit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2433" docOffset="21">
      <en>Today, more than ever, Parliament appeals to all Member States to be determined in their support for the Spanish authorities in their fight against terrorism.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2516">que</DiscourseConnective> jamais, le Parlement invite tous les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2571">à</DiscourseConnective> réaffirmer leur soutien aux autorités espagnoles dans leur lutte contre le terrorisme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2592" docOffset="22">
      <en>This is a fight that can only be carried out on the basis of the rule of law, with the full force of the law and strong democratic institutions.</en>
      <fr>Cette lutte ne peut être menée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2691">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> vertu des principes de base de l'État de droit, avec la pleine force de la loi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2776">et</DiscourseConnective> des institutions démocratiques fortes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2737" docOffset="23">
      <en>We remember the victims of terrorism at this time, with whom we stand in sympathy and solidarity.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons aujourd'hui une pensée pour les victimes du terrorisme. Nous leur témoignons notre plus grande compassion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2935">et</DiscourseConnective> solidarité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2835" docOffset="24">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
