<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>3. (</en>
    <fr>3. (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5" docOffset="1">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="24" id="098" name="Marie Panayotopoulos-Cassiotou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="24" docOffset="2">
      <en>(EL) Mr President, my dear colleagues, <Alignment alignment="67" annotation_id="63">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="63" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we know, the European Commission's original proposal included in a single Regulation the amended proposal for Regulation No 11 abolishing discrimination in prices and terms of transport, and the amendment to Regulation (EC) No 852/2004 on the hygiene of foodstuffs.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, <Alignment alignment="63" annotation_id="67">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="67" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez, la proposition originale de la Commission européenne incluait dans un seul règlement la proposition modifiée de règlement n° 11 supprimant les discriminations en matière de prix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="266">et</DiscourseConnective> conditions de transport, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="294">et</DiscourseConnective> l'amendement au règlement (CE) n° 852/2004 relatif à l'hygiène des denrées alimentaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="332" docOffset="3">
      <en>The Commission's proposal was based on Articles 75, 152 and 95 of the Treaty establishing the European Community, <Alignment alignment="507" annotation_id="446">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="446" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the stipulated procedure for adopting the Resolution was co-decision.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de la Commission se basait sur les articles 75, 152 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="453">et</DiscourseConnective> 95 du traité établissant la Communauté européenne, <Alignment alignment="699" annotation_id="507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="507" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la procédure mentionnée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="534">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'adoption de la résolution était la codécision.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="520" docOffset="4">
      <en>The colegislators - Council and Parliament - decided to split the original proposal into two separate Regulations: one for the amendment of Regulation No 11 on transport, based on Article 75 (3), which does not provide for any intervention by the European Parliament in the legislative procedure, <Alignment alignment="899" annotation_id="817">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="817" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on which the Committee on Transport gave its opinion; and another Regulation concerning amendment of the Regulation on the hygiene of foodstuffs, based on Articles 95 and 152 (4b), on which the Committee on the Environment is to give its opinion shortly.</en>
      <fr>Les colégislateurs - le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="620">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement - ont décidé de scinder la proposition originale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="685">en</DiscourseConnective> deux règlements distincts: un <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="718">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'amendement du règlement n° 11 sur les transports, basé sur l'article 75, paragraphe 3, qui ne prévoit aucune intervention du Parlement européen dans la procédure législative <Alignment alignment="817" annotation_id="899">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="899" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sur lequel la commission des transports a donné son avis; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="960">et</DiscourseConnective> un autre règlement concernant l'amendement du règlement relatif à l'hygiène des denrées alimentaires, basé sur les articles 95 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1090">et</DiscourseConnective> 152, paragraphe 4, point b), sur lequel la commission de l'environnement donnera bientôt son avis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1076" docOffset="5">
      <en>Today we are called upon to decide whether Article 75 (3) provides an adequate legal basis for amending the Regulation on transport.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, nous sommes appelés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1225">à</DiscourseConnective> décider <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1235">si</DiscourseConnective> l'article 75, paragraphe 3, fournit une base juridique adéquate <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1302">pour</DiscourseConnective> modifier le règlement sur les transports.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1209" docOffset="6">
      <en>The amendment to Article 852/2004, <Alignment alignment="1384" annotation_id="1244">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1244" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have said, will be discussed later.</en>
      <fr>L'amendement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1362">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 852/2004, <Alignment alignment="1244" annotation_id="1384">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1384" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous l'avons dit, sera discuté ultérieurement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1286" docOffset="7">
      <en>The proposed Regulation which is submitted today provides for the deletion of Article 5, which ceased to be valid in 1961, and an amendment to Article 6, aimed at reducing the carriers' administrative obligations by abolishing their obligation to retain copies showing full price information, <Alignment alignment="1750" annotation_id="1579">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1579" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this information is included anyway on the consignment notes and in the carriers' accounting systems.</en>
      <fr>Le règlement proposé soumis aujourd'hui prévoit la suppression de l'article 5, qui a cessé d'être valable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1543">en</DiscourseConnective> 1961, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1552">et</DiscourseConnective> un amendement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1569">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 6, visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1591">à</DiscourseConnective> réduire les obligations administratives des transporteurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1651">en</DiscourseConnective> supprimant leur obligation de conserver une copie indiquant toutes les informations tarifaires, <Alignment alignment="998" annotation_id="1750">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1750" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">étant donné que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces informations sont de toute manière incluses sur les notes d'envoi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1836">et</DiscourseConnective> dans la comptabilité des transporteurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1687" docOffset="8">
      <en>This amendment makes it possible to check transport rates and conditions, and identify any discrimination.</en>
      <fr>Cet amendement rend possible le contrôle des tarifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1931">et</DiscourseConnective> des conditions de transport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1962">et</DiscourseConnective> l'identification de toute discrimination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1794" docOffset="9">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2007" annotation_id="1794">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1794" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is an amendment that corresponds exactly to what is provided for in Article 75 (3), second sentence, of the Treaty of the European Communities, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1946" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="2183" annotation_id="1950">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1950" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the amendment to Article 6 is necessary to enable European authorities to check observance of the principle of non-discrimination in the field of transport under Article 75 (3) of the Treaty, the Committee on Legal Affairs made the point that Article 75 (3) is the only legal basis than can be used <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2255" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> amending Regulation No 11.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1794" annotation_id="2007">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2007" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2017">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un amendement qui correspond exactement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2066">à</DiscourseConnective> ce qui est prévu à l'article 75, paragraphe 3, deuxième phrase, du traité établissant les Communautés européennes. <Alignment alignment="150" annotation_id="2183">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2183" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il est nécessaire de modifier l'article 6 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2232">pour</DiscourseConnective> permettre aux autorités européennes de vérifier le respect du principe de non-discrimination dans le domaine des transports, conformément à l'article 75, paragraphe 3, du traité, la commission des affaires juridiques en est venue à affirmer que l'article 75, paragraphe 3, était la seule base juridique pouvant être utilisée lors de la modification du règlement n° 11.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
