<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Welcome</en>
    <fr>Souhaits de bienvenue</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="032" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>Today we have great pleasure in welcoming to our Parliament a delegation from the parliament of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons aujourd'hui le grand plaisir d'accueillir parmi nous une délégation du parlement de la République islamique d'Afghanistan.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="141" docOffset="2">
      <en>This delegation visited our Parliament last December in Strasbourg, <Alignment alignment="259" annotation_id="209">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="209" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are delighted to welcome them in Brussels too.</en>
      <fr>Cette délégation s'est rendue en visite dans notre Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="217">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg au mois de décembre dernier, <Alignment alignment="53" annotation_id="259">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="259" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous sommes très heureux de les accueillir ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="309">à</DiscourseConnective> Bruxelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="263" docOffset="3">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="274" docOffset="4">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I would like to express our deep and sincere condolences to your Assembly and to the Afghan people for the terrorist attack of 6 November 2007 in which six members of your parliament and about 100 Afghan citizens lost their lives.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="350">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais exprimer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="385">à</DiscourseConnective> votre assemblée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="403">et</DiscourseConnective> au peuple afghan nos condoléances profondes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="450">et</DiscourseConnective> sincères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="462">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'attaque terroriste du 6 novembre 2007 au cours de laquelle 6 députés de votre parlement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="558">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'une centaine de citoyens afghans ont perdu la vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="527" docOffset="5">
      <en>Among the victims was Sayed Mustafa Kazemi, who had been a member of the Afghan delegation on its visit to Strasbourg last year.</en>
      <fr>Il y avait parmi les victimes Sayed Mustafa Kazemi, membre de la délégation afghane <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="702">en</DiscourseConnective> visite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="712">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg l'an dernier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="656" docOffset="6">
      <en>The purpose of your visit is to start a regular dialogue which will enable us to arrive more quickly at a better understanding of the political and social situation in Afghanistan, <Alignment alignment="928" annotation_id="837">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="837" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which will give us the opportunity to discuss the assistance your country needs.</en>
      <fr>Votre visite vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="757">à</DiscourseConnective> entamer un dialogue régulier qui, d'une part, nous permettra d'aboutir plus rapidement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="846">à</DiscourseConnective> une meilleure compréhension de la situation politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="902">et</DiscourseConnective> sociale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="913">en</DiscourseConnective> Afghanistan <Alignment alignment="1003" annotation_id="928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="928" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, d'autre part, nous donnera l'opportunité de discuter de l'assistance dont votre pays a besoin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="922" docOffset="7">
      <en>I am confident that you all regard this visit as a symbol of our joint efforts to promote democratic values and full respect for human rights throughout the world.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1045">que</DiscourseConnective> vous considérez cette visite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1078">comme</DiscourseConnective> un symbole de nos efforts conjoints <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1120">pour</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir les valeurs démocratiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1162">et</DiscourseConnective> le respect intégral des droits de l'homme dans le monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1086" docOffset="8">
      <en>I would like to express our satisfaction at your visit, and our commitment to strengthening the cooperation between our governments.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais dire combien nous sommes heureux de votre visite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1283">et</DiscourseConnective> vous assurer de notre engagement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1319">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la coopération entre nos gouvernements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1219" docOffset="9">
      <en>From what I know, you already have fruitful contacts with the European Parliament, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1302" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I wish you a constructive continuation of your mission, an enjoyable stay, and a good journey back to your country.</en>
      <fr>J'ai cru comprendre que vous aviez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1406">déjà</DiscourseConnective> noué des contacts fructueux avec le Parlement européen. Permettez-moi de vous souhaiter une fin de mission constructive, un agréable séjour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1551">et</DiscourseConnective> un excellent retour dans votre pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1422" id="033" name="Gyula Hegyi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1422" docOffset="10">
      <en>Madam President, my point of order is under Rule 9(2), concerning the smooth conduct of parliamentary business.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, c'est une motion de procédure en vertu de l'article 9, paragraphe 2 du règlement, concernant le bon déroulement des travaux parlementaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1534" docOffset="11">
      <en>We have been informed about the presence of asbestos in the Winston Churchill and SDM buildings in Strasbourg.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons été informés de la présence d'amiante dans les bâtiments Winston Churchill <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1844">et</DiscourseConnective> SDM <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1851">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1645" docOffset="12">
      <en>The latest report 'has confirmed a more widespread presence of asbestos' than was initially believed in our places of work there.</en>
      <fr>Le dernier rapport "a confirmé une présence d'amiante plus importante" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1936">que</DiscourseConnective> ce qu'on pensait au départ sur nos lieux de travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1775" docOffset="13">
      <en>Asbestos is one of the most dangerous carcinogens, and can endanger human life.</en>
      <fr>L'amiante est une des substances cancérigènes les plus dangereuses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2060">et</DiscourseConnective> peut mettre la vie humaine en danger.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1855" docOffset="14">
      <en>We should <Alignment alignment="2854" annotation_id="1865">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1865" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> request proper information on the risk assessment and detailed information on the removal of asbestos from Parliament's buildings, including the schedule and safety measures for this.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions <Alignment alignment="1865" annotation_id="2115">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2115" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> réclamer des informations correctes concernant l'évaluation des risques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2196">et</DiscourseConnective> des informations détaillées concernant le désamiantage des bâtiments du Parlement, y compris le calendrier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2306">et</DiscourseConnective> les mesures de sécurité adoptés dans le cadre de celui-ci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2059" docOffset="15">
      <en>The health and safety of MEPs, employees and visitors to Parliament should be an absolute priority.</en>
      <fr>La santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2377">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité des députés européens, des employés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2428">et</DiscourseConnective> des visiteurs du Parlement devraient être une priorité absolue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2159" id="034" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2159" docOffset="16">
      <en>Mr Hegyi, this is essentially not a procedural matter, <Alignment alignment="2568" annotation_id="2214">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2214" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="2573" annotation_id="2218">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2218" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you have raised such a vital issue, I would like to say that an announcement has already been made by the Secretary-General regarding the possible presence of asbestos in our buildings.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur Hegyi, il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2517">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit pas tellement ici d'une motion de procédure <Alignment alignment="1043" annotation_id="2568">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2568" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="2218" annotation_id="2573">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2573" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous soulevez une question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2608">aussi</DiscourseConnective> vitale, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2634">dire que</DiscourseConnective> le secrétaire général a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2667">déjà</DiscourseConnective> diffusé une communication concernant la présence possible d'amiante dans nos bâtiments.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
