<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes</en>
    <fr>Approbation du procès-verbal de la séance précédente: cf. procès-verbal</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="53" id="007" name="Paul Rübig">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="53" docOffset="1">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, it was actually planned that today's sitting should include a debate on the roaming report, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="164" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective> this House, in the trilogue on 2 May, presented the Council with a package of compromises, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="261" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I might add that it did so with the agreement of all groups here <Alignment alignment="388" annotation_id="330">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="330" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> of all the countries represented in the trilogue.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, il était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="109">en fait</DiscourseConnective> prévu d'inclure dans la séance d'aujourd'hui un débat concernant le rapport sur l'itinérance, le Parlement européen ayant présenté au Conseil, lors du trilogue du 2 mai, un paquet de compromis. J'ajouterai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="323">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il l'a fait avec l'accord de tous les groupes ici représentés <Alignment alignment="2181" annotation_id="388">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="388" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de tous les pays impliqués dans le trilogue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="384" docOffset="2">
      <en>It is unfortunate that the Council has not, to date, indicated its agreement to it, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="468" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it is for that reason that we are unable to have the debate today or to vote on the report tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil ne l'a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="454">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> pas encore adopté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="488">à</DiscourseConnective> ce jour; c'est la raison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="515">pour</DiscourseConnective> laquelle nous ne sommes pas en mesure d'organiser le débat aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="591">ou</DiscourseConnective> de voter sur le rapport demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="573" id="008" name="Brian Crowley">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="573" docOffset="3">
      <en>A Uachtaráin, ba mhaith liom comhghairdeas a dhéanamh le Rialtas na hÉireann, le Rialtas na Breataine, agus leis an Rialtas nua i mBéal Feirste.</en>
      <fr>A Uachtaráin, ba mhaith liom comhghairdeas a dhéanamh le Rialtas na hÉireann, le Rialtas na Breataine, agus leis an Rialtas nua i mBéal Feirste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="718" docOffset="4">
      <en>Mr President, yesterday saw the installation of a new government <Alignment alignment="865" annotation_id="783">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="783" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the re-establishment of the devolved assembly in Northern Ireland, representing what would have previously been called the extreme opinion of unionism and the extreme opinion of nationalism, brought together to form a new government for Northern Ireland.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, la journée d'hier a vu la mise en place d'un nouveau gouvernement <Alignment alignment="783" annotation_id="865">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="865" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le rétablissement de l'assemblée autonome d'Irlande du Nord, représentant ce qui aurait autrefois été appelé l'unionisme extrême <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="997">et</DiscourseConnective> le nationalisme extrême, réunis dans un nouveau gouvernement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1061">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Irlande du Nord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1042" docOffset="5">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1085" annotation_id="1042">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1042" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have heard from the Nobel laureates, this is a great opportunity for us not only to congratulate those people who have been involved and to encourage them in finding a new way forward in solving conflict and resolving the difficulties that occur between different communities, but also to congratulate the European Union for its ongoing commitment and help to the people of Northern Ireland over the last 20 years.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="315" annotation_id="1085">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1085" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'ont signalé les lauréats du prix Nobel, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1136">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1143">pour</DiscourseConnective> nous d'une bonne occasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1174">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> de féliciter les différents acteurs impliqués <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1234">et</DiscourseConnective> de les encourager <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1255">à</DiscourseConnective> trouver une nouvelle manière de progresser vers la résolution du conflit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1330">et</DiscourseConnective> de résoudre les difficultés qui se posent entre communautés différentes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1406">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> de féliciter l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1449">pour</DiscourseConnective> son engagement sans relâche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1482">et</DiscourseConnective> son soutien permanent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1507">à</DiscourseConnective> la population d'Irlande du Nord ces vingt dernières années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1463" docOffset="6">
      <en>The reasons such greatness took place yesterday was that the people there were standing on the shoulders of giants - not just the shoulders of John Hume and Lord Trimble, who are here today, but also the shoulders of Jacques Delors, who first came up with the plan and the idea of a peace programme for Northern Ireland, and of Helmut Kohl and others.</en>
      <fr>Si un événement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1585">aussi</DiscourseConnective> exceptionnel a pu voir le jour hier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1628">c'est parce que</DiscourseConnective> les différents protagonistes étaient portés par des géants, pas uniquement John Hume <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1729">et</DiscourseConnective> Lord Trimble, qui sont présents aujourd'hui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1777">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> Jacques Delors, qui est le premier à avoir lancé le projet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1847">et</DiscourseConnective> l'idée d'un programme de paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1880">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Irlande du Nord, Helmut Kohl <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1916">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1815" docOffset="7">
      <en>We should reflect on this today in making sure that we continue our commitment.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions réfléchir aujourd'hui à cette question et veiller à garantir la poursuite de notre engagement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1895" docOffset="8">
      <en>As chairman of the UEN Group and a representative of a government party, I extend my thanks to all my colleagues here and to all my colleagues from Ireland who worked together towards this common cause and common goal.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2041">tant que</DiscourseConnective> président du groupe UEN <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2074">et</DiscourseConnective> représentant d'un parti de gouvernement, je tiens à remercier tous mes collègues en cette Assemblée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2177">et</DiscourseConnective> tous mes collègues irlandais qui ont œuvré de concert au succès de cette cause commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2267">et</DiscourseConnective> de cet objectif partagé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2114" docOffset="9">
      <en>We should <Alignment alignment="2309" annotation_id="2124">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2124" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> reflect on and remember the loss of life, the harm, the impairment and injury to so many, <Alignment alignment="2460" annotation_id="2219">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2219" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, rather than allow those losses to continue to fester and to poison our dialogue, let us understand: that was one of one time, this is of another.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions <Alignment alignment="2124" annotation_id="2309">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2309" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> garder à l'esprit les vies perdues, les douleurs, les meurtrissures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2387">et</DiscourseConnective> les blessures infligées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2414">à</DiscourseConnective> tant de gens et réfléchir à cette tragédie. <Alignment alignment="2219" annotation_id="2460">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2460" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2465">au lieu de</DiscourseConnective> laisser ces souffrances persister <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2510">et</DiscourseConnective> empoisonner notre dialogue, poser les choses clairement: ces souffrances relèvent du passé, nous sommes entrés dans une nouvelle ère.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2370" docOffset="10">
      <en>Our task and our role now is to ensure that our grandchildren have better prospects for the future in Northern Ireland.</en>
      <fr>Notre mission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2661">et</DiscourseConnective> notre rôle sont à présent de garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2702">à</DiscourseConnective> nos petits-enfants de meilleures perspectives d'avenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2759">en</DiscourseConnective> Irlande du Nord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2490" docOffset="11">
      <en>Let us <Alignment alignment="2794" annotation_id="2497">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2497" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remember the words of the old poet who said: 'Even <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2553" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective> my bones may break <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2579" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> even <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2588" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective> my body may bleed, within my heart <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2630" sense="Comparison.Concession">still</DiscourseConnective> beats the hope of mankind to find and fulfil all its needs'.</en>
      <fr>Souvenons-nous <Alignment alignment="2497" annotation_id="2794">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2794" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des mots de ce vieux poète: "Mes os peuvent se briser, mon corps peut se vider de son sang; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2896">en</DiscourseConnective> mon cœur bat toujours l'espoir de voir l'humanité trouver <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2957">et</DiscourseConnective> combler tous ses besoins".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2697" docOffset="12">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2708" id="010" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2708" docOffset="13">
      <en>Thank you for that statement, Mr Crowley.</en>
      <fr>Merci <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3012">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette intervention, Monsieur Crowley.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2750" docOffset="14">
      <en>I would like to inform you that I have sent a letter to the First Minister and Deputy First Minister to congratulate them.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3064">à</DiscourseConnective> vous informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3080">que</DiscourseConnective> j'ai envoyé une lettre au Premier ministre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3127">et</DiscourseConnective> au vice-Premier ministre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3155">pour</DiscourseConnective> les féliciter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2873" docOffset="15">
      <en>We look forward to a good future for Northern Ireland, Ireland, Great Britain and the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons un avenir prometteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3210">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Irlande du Nord, l'Irlande, la Grande-Bretagne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3264">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
