<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>1.</en>
    <fr>1.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Financial year 2008 as modified by the Council (vote)</en>
    <fr>Exercice 2008, modifié par le Conseil (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="57" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Financial year 2008</en>
    <fr>- Exercice 2008</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="79" docOffset="3">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="66">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="98" id="068" name="Kyösti Virrankoski ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="98" docOffset="4">
      <en>rapporteur. - Mr President, the second reading budget conciliation between the two arms of the Budgetary Authority was held on 23 November 2007.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la conciliation sur le budget en deuxième lecture entre les deux organes de l'autorité budgétaire s'est tenue le 23 novembre 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="243" docOffset="5">
      <en>Parliament achieved a budget for results on its major objectives: financing for Galileo (EUR 2.4 billion) via a revision of the 2007-2013 multiannual financial framework (MFF) and the use of the flexibility instrument (EUR 200 million); significant further use of the flexibility instrument (EUR 70 million) to finance an increase in the spending on common foreign and security policy (CFSP).</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement a bouclé un budget de résultats concernant ses principaux objectifs: le financement de Galileo (2,4 milliards d'euros) par le biais de la révision du cadre financier pluriannuel (CFP) 2007-2013 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="461">et</DiscourseConnective> l'utilisation de l'instrument de flexibilité (200 millions d'euros); une utilisation supplémentaire sensible de l'instrument de flexibilité (70 millions d'euros) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="626">pour</DiscourseConnective> financer l'augmentation des dépenses en matière de politique étrangère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="702">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité commune (PESC).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="636" docOffset="6">
      <en>The Committee on Budgets voted its second reading amendments, further to the conciliation outcome, on 29 November 2007.</en>
      <fr>La commission des budgets a voté ses amendements en deuxième lecture, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="803">après</DiscourseConnective> les résultats de la conciliation, le 29 novembre 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="756" docOffset="7">
      <en>After the technical check of the figures, a small number of technical adjustments were necessary to ensure full respect of the conciliation outcome of 23 November <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="919" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> regards revised financial framework ceilings and the overall level of payments.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="864">Après</DiscourseConnective> la vérification technique des montants, un nombre réduit d'ajustements techniques ont été nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="972">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer le respect <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="996">total</DiscourseConnective> du <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1005">résultat</DiscourseConnective> de la conciliation du 23 novembre, concernant les plafonds révisés du cadre financier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1100">et</DiscourseConnective> le niveau général des paiements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1002" docOffset="8">
      <en>The agreed modifications are the following:</en>
      <fr>Les modifications convenues sont les suivantes:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1046" docOffset="9">
      <en>First, in heading 1a, commitment appropriations are adjusted as follows:</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1184">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1198">à</DiscourseConnective> la rubrique 1a, les crédits d'engagement sont ajustés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1254">comme</DiscourseConnective> suit:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1119" docOffset="10">
      <en>Amendment 335:</en>
      <fr>Amendement 335:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1134" docOffset="11">
      <en>06 02 09 01 (Galileo Supervisory Authority) to EUR 7 460 000</en>
      <fr>06 02 09 01 (Autorité de surveillance de Galileo) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1332">à</DiscourseConnective> 7 460 000 EUR</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1195" docOffset="12">
      <en>06 02 09 02 (Galileo Supervisory Authority) to EUR 3 100 000</en>
      <fr>06 02 09 02 (Autorité de surveillance de Galileo) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1398">à</DiscourseConnective> 3 100 000 EUR</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1256" docOffset="13">
      <en>08 07 01 (Research Cooperation - Transport) to EUR 348 922 000</en>
      <fr>08 07 01 (Recherche Coopération - Transport) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1459">à</DiscourseConnective> 348 922 000 EUR</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1319" docOffset="14">
      <en>Amendment 331:</en>
      <fr>Amendement 331:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1334" docOffset="15">
      <en>02 02 01 (Competitiveness and Innovation) to EUR 126 300 000</en>
      <fr>02 02 01 (Compétitivité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1517">et</DiscourseConnective> Innovation) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1532">à</DiscourseConnective> 126 300 000 EUR</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1395" docOffset="16">
      <en>Amendment 69:</en>
      <fr>Amendement 69:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1409" docOffset="17">
      <en>06 03 03 (TENs - T) to EUR 955 852 600</en>
      <fr>06 03 03 (RTE - T) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1584">à</DiscourseConnective> 955 852 600 EUR</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1448" docOffset="18">
      <en>Second, in heading 1b, in order to meet the overall level of payments agreed at the conciliation, payment appropriations are modified on lines:</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1602">Deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1616">à</DiscourseConnective> la rubrique 1b, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1634">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer le niveau général des paiements approuvé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1688">en</DiscourseConnective> conciliation, les crédits de paiement sont ajustés comme suit:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1592" docOffset="19">
      <en>Amendment 27:</en>
      <fr>Amendement 27:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1606" docOffset="20">
      <en>04 02 17 (ESF) to EUR 3 823 198 181</en>
      <fr>04 02 17 (FSE) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1784">à</DiscourseConnective> 3 823 198 181 EUR</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1642" docOffset="21">
      <en>Amendment 140:</en>
      <fr>Amendement 140:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1657" docOffset="22">
      <en>13 03 16 (ERDF convergence) to EUR 10 606 637 496</en>
      <fr>13 03 16 (convergence FEDER) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1849">à</DiscourseConnective> 10 606 637 496 EUR</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1707" docOffset="23">
      <en>Amendment 141:</en>
      <fr>Amendement 141:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1722" docOffset="24">
      <en>13 03 18 (ERDF competitiveness) to EUR 2 540 832 078</en>
      <fr>13 03 18 (compétitivité FEDER) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1917">à</DiscourseConnective> 2 540 832 078 EUR</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1775" docOffset="25">
      <en>All these technical adjustments were unanimously approved by the Committee on Budgets on Monday 10 December.</en>
      <fr>L'ensemble de ces ajustements techniques a été approuvé par la commission des budgets le lundi 10 décembre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1884" docOffset="26">
      <en>Third, a number of technical/nomenclature changes will be made, mainly as regards pilot projects and preparatory actions.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2045">Troisièmement</DiscourseConnective>, un certain nombre de modifications techniques/de nomenclature seront effectuées, principalement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2156">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les projets pilotes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2195">et</DiscourseConnective> les actions préparatoires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2006" docOffset="27">
      <en>These changes have been presented to the President of Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Ces modifications ont été présentées au président du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2072" docOffset="28">
      <en>These modifications do not change any figures, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2119" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">nor</DiscourseConnective> do they change any MFF classifications.</en>
      <fr>Elles ne concernent aucun montant ni aucune classification du cadre financier pluriannuel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2163" docOffset="29">
      <en>(The technical adjustments were accepted)</en>
      <fr>(Les ajustements techniques sont retenus)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2205" docOffset="30">
      <en>- After the vote:</en>
      <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2424">Après</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2223" id="070" name="Emanuel Santos">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2223" docOffset="31">
      <en>President-in-Office of the Council. - (PT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, may I emphasise, <Alignment alignment="2554" annotation_id="2319">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2319" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> going on to comment on the results of the approval of the European Union budget for 2008, that today is a particularly pleasing day for me, not only as a European, but also as a citizen of Portugal.</en>
      <fr>Président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2449">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil. - (PT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2512">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, permettez-moi de vous dire, <Alignment alignment="2319" annotation_id="2554">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2554" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> commenter l'adoption du budget 2008 de l'Union, à quel point ce jour est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2636">un jour</DiscourseConnective> réjouissant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2656">pour</DiscourseConnective> moi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2666">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2683">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>Européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2701">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2706">également</DiscourseConnective> en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2719">tant que</DiscourseConnective> citoyen du Portugal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2525" docOffset="32">
      <en>I am of course referring to that historic event - the signing of the Treaty of Lisbon - due to take place in just over an hour in my country's capital.</en>
      <fr>Je fais évidemment allusion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2777">à</DiscourseConnective> ce palier historique - la signature du traité de Lisbonne - qui sera franchi dans une heure à peine au cœur de la capitale de mon pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2677" docOffset="33">
      <en>Following the enlargement of the European Union to 27 Member States, it is another decisive step in European integration, that will make Europe more democratic, more representative, more flexible and effective in the way it works than it was before.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2915">Après</DiscourseConnective> l'élargissement de l'Union <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2948">à</DiscourseConnective> 27 membres, ceci constitue un pas décisif supplémentaire vers l'intégration d'une Europe qui devient plus démocratique, plus représentative, plus flexible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3105">et</DiscourseConnective> plus efficace qu'elle ne l'a jamais été.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2927" docOffset="34">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3149" annotation_id="2927">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2927" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I might make a brief and early summing up of the achievements of the Portuguese Presidency, I would point to three important areas of success for the future of the European Union. They are the agreement making it possible for the EU Reform Treaty, the Treaty of Lisbon, to be signed today, the holding of the EU-Africa Summit and of the EU-Brazil Summit.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2927" annotation_id="3149">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3149" sense="Contingency.Condition">Pour résumer</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> brièvement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3173">et</DiscourseConnective> prématurément les réalisations à mettre à l'actif de la présidence portugaise, je citerai trois avancées significatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3296">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir de l'Union européenne: l'accord qui a rendu possible le traité modificatif, le traité de Lisbonne, qui sera signé aujourd'hui, la tenue du sommet UE-Afrique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3467">et</DiscourseConnective> la tenue du sommet UE-Brésil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3285" docOffset="35">
      <en>To that we might now <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3306" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> add the important agreement we were able to reach on the financing of the strategic Galileo Programme.</en>
      <fr>Ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3503">à</DiscourseConnective> quoi nous pouvons aujourd'hui ajouter l'important accord conclu sur le financement du programme stratégique Galileo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3414" docOffset="36">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, today we have the second reading of the 2008 budget, the final stage of a long process of negotiation which finally ended very successfully.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3631">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, nous procédons aujourd'hui à la seconde lecture du budget 2008, dernière étape d'un long processus de négociations couronné de succès.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3577" docOffset="37">
      <en>I am pleased to report the agreement reached between our two institutions in the concertation meeting on 23 November, that dealt in full with all the budget proposals for 2008 on which we had agreed by that date.</en>
      <fr>Je suis heureux de pouvoir vous rendre compte de l'accord interinstitutionnel conclu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3865">en</DiscourseConnective> réunion de concertation le 23 novembre et portant sur l'ensemble des propositions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3950">pour</DiscourseConnective> le budget 2008 retenues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3979">à</DiscourseConnective> cette date.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3790" docOffset="38">
      <en>In accordance with the procedures, I must point out that the Council will be able to accept the maximum rate of increase resulting from your second reading.</en>
      <fr>Conformément à la procédure, je vous annonce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4038">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil accepte le taux maximal d'augmentation procédant de la deuxième lecture du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3947" docOffset="39">
      <en>I note, <Alignment alignment="4147" annotation_id="3955">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3955" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, that some small adjustments are still needed as regards the classification of expenditure on which the Council reserves its rights.</en>
      <fr>Je dois <Alignment alignment="2363" annotation_id="4147">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4147" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> préciser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4166">que</DiscourseConnective> certains ajustements mineurs, sur lesquels le Conseil réserve sa décision, seront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4252">encore</DiscourseConnective> nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4271">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de classification des dépenses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4096" docOffset="40">
      <en>In conclusion, Mr President, I should like to take this opportunity to express once more my gratitude to the Chairman of the Committee on Budgets, Mr Böge and to the two rapporteurs, Mr Virrankoski and Mr Itälä, to my colleagues in the Council, to Commissioner Grybauskaité and to all those who have helped to bring this very demanding budgetary procedure to a successful conclusion, culminating in Parliament's approval.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4314">En</DiscourseConnective> conclusion, Monsieur le Président, je voudrais profiter de l'occasion qui m'est donnée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4404">pour</DiscourseConnective> exprimer une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4427">encore</DiscourseConnective> ma gratitude au président de la commission des budgets, M. Böge, aux deux rapporteurs, M. Virrankoski <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4536">et</DiscourseConnective> M. Itälä, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4549">à</DiscourseConnective> mes collègues du Conseil, au commissaire Grybauskaité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4605">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4608">à</DiscourseConnective> tous ceux qui ont contribué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4638">à</DiscourseConnective> mener cette laborieuse procédure vers le succès, dont l'adoption par le Parlement constitue le couronnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4518" id="071" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4518" docOffset="41">
      <en>Minister, you have uttered, among other things, the sentence I was waiting for.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Ministre, vous avez prononcé, entre autres, la phrase que j'attendais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4598" docOffset="42">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="4844" annotation_id="4600">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4600" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> note that the budgetary procedure has been completed in accordance with the treaty provisions and the interinstitutional agreement of 17 May 2006.</en>
      <fr>Je constate <Alignment alignment="2444" annotation_id="4844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4844" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4849">que</DiscourseConnective> la procédure budgétaire s'est achevée conformément aux dispositions du traité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4931">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'accord interinstitutionnel du 17 mai 2006.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4757" docOffset="43">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="4994" annotation_id="4759">
          <Alignment alignment="4997" annotation_id="4759">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4759" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> note that, in accordance with Article 13 of the interinstitutional agreement, the Council and Parliament agree to accept the maximum rate of increase of non-compulsory expenditure that comes out of the second reading in Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Je constate <Alignment alignment="4759" annotation_id="4994">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4994" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, selon l'article 13 dudit accord interinstitutionnel, le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5072">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement conviennent d'accepter le taux maximal d'augmentation des dépenses non obligatoires qui procèderont de la deuxième lecture du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4996" docOffset="44">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5225" annotation_id="4996">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4996" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Consequently</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the budgetary procedure can be declared complete <Alignment alignment="5288" annotation_id="5059">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5059" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the budget definitively adopted.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4996" annotation_id="5225">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5225" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">De ce fait</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la procédure budgétaire peut être déclarée achevée <Alignment alignment="5059" annotation_id="5288">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5288" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le budget définitivement adopté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5096" docOffset="45">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5107" docOffset="46">
      <en>As you know, the President is currently in Lisbon where a small signature ceremony is taking place.</en>
      <fr>Vous savez que notre Président est actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5391">à</DiscourseConnective> Lisbonne où il y a une petite cérémonie de signature.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5207" docOffset="47">
      <en>My powers as vice-president end here.</en>
      <fr>Mon pouvoir de vice-président s'arrête là.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5245" docOffset="48">
      <en>The official signature of the budget for the financial year 2008 will be on Tuesday, 18 December, at the plenary session in Brussels.</en>
      <fr>La signature officielle du budget <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5524">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'exercice 2008 se fera mardi, 18 décembre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5573">en</DiscourseConnective> séance plénière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5592">à</DiscourseConnective> Bruxelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
