<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>13.</en>
    <fr>13.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Draft amending budget No 6/2007 (vote)</en>
    <fr>Projet de budget rectificatif n° 6/2007 (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="43" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Report: Elles</en>
    <fr>- Rapport James Elles</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="59" id="122" name="Benita Ferrero-Waldner">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="59" docOffset="3">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, I would like to make a statement on behalf of the Commission.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, j'aimerais faire une déclaration au nom de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="163" docOffset="4">
      <en>In its preliminary draft amending budget 6/2007, the Commission proposed the creation of a new budget item - 'Damage requests resulting from legal procedures against the Commission's decisions in the field of competition' and the classification of the related expenditure under Heading 1a of the multiannual financial framework <Alignment alignment="565" annotation_id="491">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="491" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it refers to an operational activity in the competition policy area.</en>
      <fr>Dans son avant-projet de budget rectificatif 6/2007, la Commission a proposé la création d'un nouveau poste budgétaire "Demandes de dommages et intérêts résultant de procédures juridiques engagées contre des décisions de la Commission dans le domaine de la concurrence" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="456">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la classification des dépenses correspondantes dans la rubrique 1a du cadre financier pluriannuel, <Alignment alignment="491" annotation_id="565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="565" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">étant donné qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles concernent une activité opérationnelle menée dans le domaine de la politique de concurrence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="563" docOffset="5">
      <en>The Commission would charge against this budget item possible budgetary implications stemming from rulings of the Court of Justice or the Court of First Instance in the field of competition.</en>
      <fr>La Commission imputerait à ce poste budgétaire les éventuelles implications budgétaires des arrêts rendus par la Cour de justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="808">ou</DiscourseConnective> le Tribunal de première instance dans le domaine de la concurrence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="754" docOffset="6">
      <en>The need for this budget item derives from recent judgments of the Court of First Instance and from the structure of the budget.</en>
      <fr>Ce poste budgétaire devient nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="918">en</DiscourseConnective> raison des arrêts récents rendus par le Tribunal de première instance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="991">et</DiscourseConnective> de la structure du budget.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="883" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1021" annotation_id="883">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="883" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> fines in the field of competition policy are entered as general budget revenue, the amounts to be paid require the creation of a budget item in the expenditure side of the budget, which does not exist at the moment.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="883" annotation_id="1021">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1021" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les amendes imposées dans le domaine de la politique de concurrence sont imputées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1113">comme</DiscourseConnective> recettes au budget général, les montants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1160">à</DiscourseConnective> payer nécessitent la création d'un poste du côté "dépenses" du budget, un poste qui n'existe pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1259">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'instant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1105" docOffset="8">
      <en>The Commission takes note that the budgetary authority does not intend to support the creation of this budget item for the year 2007.</en>
      <fr>La Commission prend note <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1300">du fait que</DiscourseConnective> l'autorité budgétaire n'a pas l'intention de soutenir la création de ce poste budgétaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1401">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'année 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1239" docOffset="9">
      <en>Despite this decision, <Alignment alignment="1458" annotation_id="1262">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1262" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> necessary the Commission may have to proceed to payments in order to meet legal obligations that might result from the Court's decisions in 2007 within the limits of the current budget and in application of the relevant rules.</en>
      <fr>Malgré cette décision, la Commission, <Alignment alignment="1262" annotation_id="1458">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1458" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nécessaire, pourrait devoir procéder <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1498">à</DiscourseConnective> des paiements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1514">afin de</DiscourseConnective> se conformer à des obligations juridiques résultant des décisions du Tribunal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1600">en</DiscourseConnective> 2007, dans les limites du budget actuel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1643">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1646">en</DiscourseConnective> application des règles concernées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1492" docOffset="10">
      <en>It does not prejudge the final decision on the creation of the dedicated budget line and on the classification of the related expenditure within the multiannual financial framework.</en>
      <fr>Cette disposition ne préjuge pas de la décision finale concernant la création de la ligne budgétaire spécifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1796">et</DiscourseConnective> la classification des dépenses correspondantes dans le cadre financier pluriannuel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
