<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>8.</en>
    <fr>8.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>'IASCF: review of the constitution - Public accountability and the composition of the IASB proposals for change' (vote)</en>
    <fr>«IASCF: Révision de la constitution - responsabilité publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="65">et</DiscourseConnective> composition de l'IASB - propositions de changement» (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="123" id="115" name="Piia-Noora Kauppi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="123" docOffset="2">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - Mr President, <Alignment alignment="182" annotation_id="170">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="170" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you already said, the PPE-DE Group would like to request the postponement of the vote on this resolution.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="170" annotation_id="182">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="182" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous l'avez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="200">déjà</DiscourseConnective> dit, le groupe PPE-DE voudrait demander le report du vote sur cette résolution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="279" docOffset="3">
      <en>Certainly, the governance of the International Accounting Standards Board is not going to be solved in the next two weeks, <Alignment alignment="435" annotation_id="402">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="402" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have time to vote about this resolution in the next mini-plenary session here in Brussels.</en>
      <fr>Il est douteux que la question de la gouvernance du Conseil des normes comptables internationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="383">soit</DiscourseConnective> résolue au cours des deux prochaines semaines, <Alignment alignment="570" annotation_id="435">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="435" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avons-nous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="452">le temps de</DiscourseConnective> voter cette résolution lors de la prochaine mini-plénière de Bruxelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="499" docOffset="4">
      <en>The reason for this is that we have got some new proposals from the European Commission <Alignment alignment="622" annotation_id="587">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="587" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> maybe it is possible to polish up some of the wordings of the resolution.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="536">En effet</DiscourseConnective> nous avons reçu quelques nouvelles propositions de la Commission européenne, <Alignment alignment="587" annotation_id="622">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="622" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> peut-être pourrons-nous peaufiner certaines formulations de la résolution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="665" docOffset="5">
      <en>The deadline was very tight <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="693" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that is why we want to have more time and to have the vote on this during the next Brussels session.</en>
      <fr>Le délai était très serré; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="727">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous souhaitons davantage de temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="777">et</DiscourseConnective> nous voudrions que le vote sur ce point ait lieu lors de la prochaine session de Bruxelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="798" id="116" language="FR" name="Pervenche Berès">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="798" docOffset="6">
      <en>Mr President, I am speaking as Chairman of the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs.</en>
      <fr>présidente de la commission ECON. - Monsieur le Président, j'interviendrai au titre de la présidence de la commission des affaires économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1015">et</DiscourseConnective> monétaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="889" docOffset="7">
      <en>In the current financial crisis, everybody realises that accounting standards and their potentially procyclical nature are a major issue.</en>
      <fr>Dans la crise financière que nous connaissons, chacun comprend <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1093">que</DiscourseConnective> l'enjeu des normes comptables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1127">et</DiscourseConnective> de leur caractère éventuellement procyclique est un sujet majeur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1027" docOffset="8">
      <en>The governance of the structures that develop these accounting standards is a very important matter.</en>
      <fr>La gouvernance des structures qui élaborent ces normes comptables est une affaire majeure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1128" docOffset="9">
      <en>The European Commission, already addressed on these issues in the Radwan report, has chosen to draft a proposal that does not involve those who are responsible for the stability of the financial markets, that was drawn up hastily with American authorities who are reaching the end of their mandate and have been disowned by all the candidates in the American presidential election, and without consulting the Council or the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>La Commission européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1313">déjà</DiscourseConnective> interpellée par le rapport Radwan sur ces questions-là, a choisi d'élaborer une proposition qui n'associe pas ceux qui sont responsables de la stabilité des marchés financiers, qui est élaborée dans la précipitation avec des autorités américaines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1565">en</DiscourseConnective> fin de mandat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1582">et</DiscourseConnective> désavouées par l'ensemble des candidats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1625">à</DiscourseConnective> l'élection présidentielle américaine, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1665">sans</DiscourseConnective> consultation du Conseil ni du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1573" docOffset="10">
      <en>In a spirit of compromise and openness, we agree to reopen this discussion <Alignment alignment="1821" annotation_id="1648">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1648" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commission for its part agrees to reconsider its proposal and to give a hearing to the European Parliament's proposals.</en>
      <fr>Dans un esprit de compromis, dans un esprit d'ouverture, nous acceptons de réouvrir cette discussion <Alignment alignment="1471" annotation_id="1821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1821" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission elle-même accepte de reconsidérer sa proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1887">et</DiscourseConnective> d'entendre les propositions du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1775" docOffset="11">
      <en>That is why I would like the Commission to make a statement and undertake to reconsider its proposal.</en>
      <fr>C'est pour cela que je voudrais que la Commission puisse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1998">s'</DiscourseConnective>exprimer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2009">et</DiscourseConnective> s'engager <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2022">à</DiscourseConnective> reconsidérer sa proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1877" docOffset="12">
      <en>In that case we would be able to support Mrs Kauppi's proposal.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2053">Dans ce cas-là</DiscourseConnective>, nous pourrions soutenir la proposition de Mme Kauppi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1941" id="117" name="Androula Vassiliou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1941" docOffset="13">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the Commission does not have a position on this point.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la Commission n'a pas d'avis sur ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2038" id="118" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2038" docOffset="14">
      <en>The Commission has not expressed an opinion.</en>
      <fr>La Commission n'a pas exprimé d'avis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2083" docOffset="15">
      <en>Mrs Berès, did I understand correctly that you would support the proposer of this motion, Mrs Kauppi, in these circumstances?</en>
      <fr>Mme Berès, ai-je bien compris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2289">que</DiscourseConnective> vous soutiendriez l'auteur de cette demande, Mme Kauppi, dans ces conditions?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2209" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2209" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Then</DiscourseConnective> we shall take the vote on this motion.</en>
      <fr>Nous allons mettre aux voix cette demande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2253" docOffset="17">
      <en>(Parliament adopted the motion for postponement of the vote)</en>
      <fr>(Le Parlement marque son accord sur la demande de report du vote)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
