<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>17.</en>
    <fr>17.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Economic Partnership Agreement between the EC and Cariforum (</en>
    <fr>Accord de partenariat économique CE/CARIFORUM (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="66" id="127" name="David Martin">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="66" docOffset="2">
      <en>rapporteur. - Madam President, I know how attached colleagues are to their lunches - or should that be the other way round, I am not sure - <Alignment alignment="210" annotation_id="206">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="206" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I want to take just two minutes.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (EN) Madame la Présidente, je sais à quel point mes collègues tiennent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="137">à</DiscourseConnective> leur repas - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="152">à moins que</DiscourseConnective> ce ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="170">soit</DiscourseConnective> l'inverse, je n'en suis pas sûr -, <Alignment alignment="2053" annotation_id="210">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="210" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je voudrais m'exprimer pendant deux petites minutes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="243" docOffset="3">
      <en>On Monday evening we had a very important debate on whether <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="303" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective> not we can give assent on CARIFORUM.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons eu un débat extrêmement important lundi matin sur la question de savoir si nous pouvions donner notre accord au Cariforum.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="343" docOffset="4">
      <en>The Commission and the Council - and it is important that both institutions made these commitments - promised us that, in terms of aid promises, they would deliver on the quality of the aid and in a timely fashion.</en>
      <fr>La Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="416">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil - il est important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="449">que</DiscourseConnective> les deux institutions aient contracté ces engagements - nous ont promis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="525">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="530">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de promesses d'aide, ils assureraient la qualité de l'aide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="599">et</DiscourseConnective> sa fourniture en temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="625">et</DiscourseConnective> en heure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="558" docOffset="5">
      <en>They assured us that nothing in the EPA would affect the Caribbean countries' access to medicines.</en>
      <fr>Ils nous ont assuré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="658">qu'</DiscourseConnective>aucun élément des APE n'affecterait l'accès des pays des Caraïbes aux médicaments.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="657" docOffset="6">
      <en>They assured us that the application of the most-favoured-nation clause would not in any way impact on South-South trade <Alignment alignment="885" annotation_id="778">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="778" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the five-year review at the end of the first phase of this EPA would be a genuine review that would take into account development objectives.</en>
      <fr>Ils nous ont assuré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="764">que</DiscourseConnective> l'application de la clause de la nation la plus favorisée n'aurait pas la moindre incidence sur les échanges sud-sud <Alignment alignment="332" annotation_id="885">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="885" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="888">que</DiscourseConnective> l'évaluation réalisée après cinq ans, au terme de la première phase de cette APE, serait une véritable évaluation qui tiendrait compte des objectifs de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="929" docOffset="7">
      <en>On the basis of these promises - and on the condition, of course, that these are now written into the record of this Parliament <Alignment alignment="1182" annotation_id="1057">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1057" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that both the Council and the Commission promise to honour and obey these commitments - I believe that this House, with a massive majority today, can now give assent to the Caribbean EPA.</en>
      <fr>Sur la base de ces promesses - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1090">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1093">à</DiscourseConnective> la condition, naturellement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1124">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles soient intégrées au compte rendu de ce Parlement <Alignment alignment="383" annotation_id="1182">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1182" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1185">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1200">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission promettent tous deux d'honorer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1248">et</DiscourseConnective> de respecter ces engagements -, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1292">que</DiscourseConnective> cette Assemblée peut aujourd'hui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1330">à</DiscourseConnective> une écrasante majorité, accorder son soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1377">à</DiscourseConnective> l'APE avec les Caraïbes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1249" docOffset="8">
      <en>I would like to thank Commissioner Ashton for her immense cooperation on this, the flexibility that she has shown, and her commitment.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais remercier la commissaire Ashton <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1448">pour</DiscourseConnective> sa très précieuse collaboration sur le sujet, pour la flexibilité dont elle a fait preuve et pour son engagement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1384" docOffset="9">
      <en>The fact that she is here for this vote says much about her.</en>
      <fr>Le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1575">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle assiste aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1603">à</DiscourseConnective> ce vote en dit long sur sa personnalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1445" docOffset="10">
      <en>This vote was scheduled for Tuesday.</en>
      <fr>Ce vote était prévu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1666">pour</DiscourseConnective> mardi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1482" docOffset="11">
      <en>I know she gave up vital commitments to be here today <Alignment alignment="1780" annotation_id="1536">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1536" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> she has made vital commitments to this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Je sais qu'elle a renoncé à des engagements de premier plan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1738">pour</DiscourseConnective> être présente parmi nous aujourd'hui <Alignment alignment="1536" annotation_id="1780">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1780" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'elle s'est profondément engagée auprès de ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1591" docOffset="12">
      <en>I want to thank the Commission for their cooperation, and ask Members to vote for assent.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1851">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1877">pour</DiscourseConnective> sa collaboration, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1900">et</DiscourseConnective> je demanderai à mes collègues de voter en faveur de cet accord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1681" id="128" name="Helmuth Markov">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1681" docOffset="13">
      <en>- (DE) Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, this is a point of order.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Madame la Présidente, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2003">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, ceci est une motion de procédure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1753" docOffset="14">
      <en>I should like to quote from the letter which President Pöttering sent to me as chairman of the Committee on International Trade.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais lire un extrait de la lettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2092">que</DiscourseConnective> le président Pöttering m'a envoyée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2131">en</DiscourseConnective> ma qualité de président de la commission du commerce international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1882" docOffset="15">
      <en>Have no fear, I shall not read the entire letter.</en>
      <fr>Ne vous inquiétez pas, je ne vais pas lire la lettre en entier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1932" docOffset="16">
      <en>'The interpretation of Rule 47 by AFCO to which you refer was announced at Parliament's sitting of 18 February 2009, and, in the absence of objections, was deemed adopted. [...]</en>
      <fr>(EN) "L'interprétation de l'article 47 par la commission AFCO, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2329">à</DiscourseConnective> laquelle vous faites référence, a été exposée lors de la séance parlementaire du 18 février 2009 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2428">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2432">en</DiscourseConnective> l'absence d'objections, a été considérée comme adoptée. (...)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2110" docOffset="17">
      <en>The proposals concerning the two EPAs [i.e. the reports by David Martin and Erika Mann] were formally announced and referred to your committee [i.e. the Committee on International Trade] only at the sitting of 19 February 2009.</en>
      <fr>Les propositions relatives aux deux APE [c'est-à-dire les rapports de David Martin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2580">et</DiscourseConnective> Erika Mann] n'ont été formellement exposées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2627">et</DiscourseConnective> présentées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2641">à</DiscourseConnective> votre commission [la commission du commerce international] <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2702">que</DiscourseConnective> lors de la séance du 19 février 2009.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2338" docOffset="18">
      <en>In the light of the above interpretation, it will no longer be possible to apply Rule 47 in relation to those two procedures, nor to any further procedures.'</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2744">À</DiscourseConnective> la lumière de l'interprétation ci-dessus, il ne sera plus possible de faire valoir l'article 47 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2842">en</DiscourseConnective> relation avec ces deux procédures, ni avec toute autre procédure."</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2496" docOffset="19">
      <en>(DE) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2501" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>, all references in official documents to Rule 47 have to be deleted.</en>
      <fr>(DE) C'est donc pourquoi toutes les références <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2959">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 47 présentes dans les documents officiels doivent être supprimées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2580" docOffset="20">
      <en>This relates both to the cover sheet of the document and to the table of contents, to the opinion page and to the procedure page, the last page of the Committee on International Trade.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agit aussi bien de la page de couverture du document <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3096">que</DiscourseConnective> de la table des matières, de la page de l'avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3147">et</DiscourseConnective> de la page de la procédure, la dernière page de la commission du commerce international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2765" docOffset="21">
      <en>I should like this to be recorded in the minutes.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais que ceci <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3260">soit</DiscourseConnective> consigné dans le procès-verbal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2815" id="131" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2815" docOffset="22">
      <en>- Thank you Mr Markov.</en>
      <fr>Merci, M. Markov.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2838" docOffset="23">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3325" annotation_id="2838">
          <Alignment alignment="2846" annotation_id="2838">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2838" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> I had to inform the House that there is a corrigendum to all language versions of this report deleting the reference to Rule 47.</en>
      <fr>Je devais <Alignment alignment="346" annotation_id="3325">
          <Alignment alignment="2838" annotation_id="3325">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3325" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> informer l'Assemblée de la présence d'un rectificatif applicable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3398">à</DiscourseConnective> toutes les versions linguistiques de ce rapport, qui implique la suppression de la référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3493">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 47.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2975" docOffset="24">
      <en>What you have stated will <Alignment alignment="3524" annotation_id="3001">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3001" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be dealt with.</en>
      <fr>Nous tiendrons <Alignment alignment="472" annotation_id="3524">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3524" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> compte de votre déclaration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3026" docOffset="25">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3558" annotation_id="3026">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3026" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we seem to be in agreement, we can proceed.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1282" annotation_id="3558">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3558" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous semblons d'accord, nous pouvons poursuivre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
