<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Opening of the sitting</en>
    <fr>Ouverture de la séance</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23" docOffset="1">
    <en>(The sitting was opened at 10.05 a.m.)</en>
    <fr>(La séance est ouverte à 10 h 05)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="62" id="005" name="Jim Allister">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="62" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, yesterday afternoon, in an unscheduled announcement in this Chamber, the President made a show of imposing financial sanctions on a number of Members because of the protest in December.</en>
      <fr>(EN) - M. le Président, hier après-midi, lors d'une intervention non programmée devant cette Assemblée, le Président a fait semblant d'imposer des sanctions financières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="226">à</DiscourseConnective> plusieurs membres en raison de la protestation organisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="285">en</DiscourseConnective> décembre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="262" docOffset="3">
      <en>What I want to know is: was it in order for the President to make that announcement without doing those Members the basic courtesy of telling them that such an announcement would be made <Alignment alignment="515" annotation_id="449">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="449" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="453" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> it would be made?</en>
      <fr>Ce que je voudrais savoir, c'est si cette intervention avait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="359">pour</DiscourseConnective> but de permettre au Président de faire cette annonce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="417">sans</DiscourseConnective> avoir la courtoisie élémentaire de dire aux membres concernés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="484">que</DiscourseConnective> cette annonce serait faite <Alignment alignment="53" annotation_id="515">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="515" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à quel moment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="476" docOffset="4">
      <en>The President talked much about showing courtesy to Members in this House, so why, I ask, were those of us affected by his announcement not done the basic courtesy of being told that he would make such an announcement?</en>
      <fr>Le Président s'est déjà exprimé à de nombreuses reprises sur la courtoisie à montrer envers les membres de cette Assemblée. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="657">Donc</DiscourseConnective>, je demande pourquoi ceux d'entre nous qui sont concernés par cette annonce n'ont pas bénéficié de la courtoisie élémentaire qui aurait voulu qu'ils soient informés au préalable de cette annonce.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="695" docOffset="5">
      <en>Is it too much to expect an answer to that?</en>
      <fr>Est-il présomptueux d'escompter une réponse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="902">à</DiscourseConnective> cette question?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="739" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="739" docOffset="6">
      <en>Mr Allister, it is not the duty of the Presidency to judge on courtesy.</en>
      <fr>M. Allister, il n'appartient pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="953">à</DiscourseConnective> la présidence de juger de la courtoisie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="811" docOffset="7">
      <en>Our duty is to apply the rules, <Alignment alignment="1035" annotation_id="843">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="843" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you can be absolutely sure that the rules have been fully respected.</en>
      <fr>Il nous incombe d'appliquer les règles <Alignment alignment="843" annotation_id="1035">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1035" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous pouvez être absolument certain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1074">que</DiscourseConnective> les règles ont été entièrement respectées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="916" id="007" name="Hans-Peter Martin">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="916" docOffset="8">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, with reference among others to Rule 146 of the Rules of Procedure, you just said that it is your duty to apply the Rules.</en>
      <fr>(DE) M. le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1143">en</DiscourseConnective> renvoyant notamment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1166">à</DiscourseConnective> la règle 146 du règlement, vous venez de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1209">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>il vous incombe d'appliquer les règles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1057" docOffset="9">
      <en>I cannot understand why sittings keep starting late, sometimes by several minutes or even a quarter of an hour.</en>
      <fr>Je ne comprends pas pourquoi les séances commencent systématiquement en retard, parfois de quelques minutes, voire d'un quart d'heure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1169" docOffset="10">
      <en>That wastes a lot of taxpayers' money.</en>
      <fr>Nous gaspillons une bonne partie de l'argent des contribuables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1208" docOffset="11">
      <en>You are very strict about observing the Rules vis à vis political opponents, who simply want a referendum or fairness and democracy, but not <Alignment alignment="1625" annotation_id="1349">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1349" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it comes to yourself!</en>
      <fr>Vous êtes très strict sur le respect des règles vis-à-vis de vos opposants politiques, qui recherchent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1559">simplement</DiscourseConnective> le référendum <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1584">ou</DiscourseConnective> la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1598">et</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1616">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas <Alignment alignment="40" annotation_id="1625">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1625" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1634">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de vous-même!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1376" docOffset="12">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1655" annotation_id="1376">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1376" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you treated everybody equally in this House, then you would long since have had to initiate proceedings against the Presidency for countless incidents of serious fraud, <Alignment alignment="1847" annotation_id="1548">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1548" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is precisely what I would call it <Alignment alignment="1911" annotation_id="1595">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1595" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sittings keep starting late, with the resulting waste of taxpayers' money.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="1655">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1655" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous traitiez tout le monde de la même manière au sein de cette Assemblée, vous auriez engagé depuis longtemps une procédure contre la présidence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1804">pour</DiscourseConnective> les innombrables cas de fraude grave, <Alignment alignment="756" annotation_id="1847">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1847" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1863">précisément</DiscourseConnective> la manière dont je les qualifierais <Alignment alignment="1595" annotation_id="1911">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1911" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je vois que les séances continuent à débuter en retard, ce qui entraîne un gaspillage de l'argent des contribuables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1675" docOffset="13">
      <en>Two different yardsticks are being applied here <Alignment alignment="2084" annotation_id="1723">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1723" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you must accept the reproach that this is a Parliament that acts arbitrarily, that deliberately sidelines political opponents on the grounds of technicalities <Alignment alignment="2234" annotation_id="1886">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1886" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> constantly tolerating what happens on its own side and even covering up serious fraud!</en>
      <fr>Ici règne la règle des deux poids, deux mesures <Alignment alignment="1642" annotation_id="2084">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2084" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous devez accepter le reproche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2119">que</DiscourseConnective> ce Parlement agit de manière arbitraire, écarte délibérément les opposants politiques sur des points de détail <Alignment alignment="1886" annotation_id="2234">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2234" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tolère en permanence ce qui se passe de son propre côté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2295">et</DiscourseConnective> va jusqu'à couvrir une fraude grave!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1979" id="008" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1979" docOffset="14">
      <en>Thank you very much, Mr Martin, for your interesting views.</en>
      <fr>Merci beaucoup, M. Martin, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2362">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce point de vue intéressant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
