<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Problems and prospects concerning European citizenship (short presentation)</en>
    <fr>Problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10">et</DiscourseConnective> perspectives concernant la citoyenneté européenne (brève présentation)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="76" id="280" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="76" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is a short presentation of the report by Mrs Gacek, on behalf of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, on problems and prospects concerning European Citizenship.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle une brève présentation du rapport d'Urszula Gacek, au nom de la commission des libertés civiles, de la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="219">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires intérieures, sur les problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="266">et</DiscourseConnective> perspectives concernant la citoyenneté européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="274" id="281" name="Urszula Gacek">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="274" docOffset="2">
      <en>rapporteur. - Mr President, it is my pleasure to present the report on the problems and perspectives concerning European citizenship, which was adopted unanimously by the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs (LIBE) last month.</en>
      <fr>rapporteure. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, j'ai le plaisir de présenter le rapport sur les problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="421">et</DiscourseConnective> les perspectives concernant la citoyenneté européenne, qui a été adopté à l'unanimité par la commission sur les libertés civiles, de la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="568">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires intérieures (LIBE) le mois dernier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="519" docOffset="3">
      <en>European citizenship does not replace national citizenship.</en>
      <fr>La citoyenneté européenne ne remplace pas la citoyenneté nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="579" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is an added bonus, giving EU citizens unique rights, notably the right to the freedom of movement, the right to consular protection and the right to petition Parliament and the European Ombudsman.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="691">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un avantage supplémentaire qui octroie aux citoyens européens des droits uniques, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="782">notamment</DiscourseConnective> le droit de liberté de circulation, le droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="837">à</DiscourseConnective> la protection consulaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="864">et</DiscourseConnective> le droit de pétition devant le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="908">et</DiscourseConnective> le Médiateur européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="779" docOffset="5">
      <en>Parliament's report takes into consideration the Commission's fifth report on European citizenship, covering the period from 1 May 2004 to 30 June 2007.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport du Parlement prend en considération le cinquième rapport de la Commission sur la citoyenneté européenne qui englobe la période allant du 1er mai 2004 au 30 juin 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="932" docOffset="6">
      <en>This is a unique period.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1115">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'une période unique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="957" docOffset="7">
      <en>Five years ago, on 1 May 2004, 10 new Member States joined the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Il y a cinq ans, le 1er mai 2004, dix nouveaux États membres ont rejoint l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1036" docOffset="8">
      <en>The result of that accession, especially of states from Central and Eastern Europe, was a hitherto unseen scale of inter-Union migration.</en>
      <fr>Le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1240">résultat</DiscourseConnective> de cette adhésion, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1268">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> celle des États d'Europe centrale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1317">et</DiscourseConnective> orientale, fut une migration intérieure à l'Union d'une ampleur jamais observée jusqu'alors.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1174" docOffset="9">
      <en>The new citizens of the European Union embraced the rights granted to them, especially the right to free movement.</en>
      <fr>Les nouveaux citoyens de l'Union européenne ont adopté les droits qui leur étaient accordés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1506">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> le droit de libre circulation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1289" docOffset="10">
      <en>They benefited from the opportunity to be educated abroad <Alignment alignment="1617" annotation_id="1347">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1347" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in those countries which opened their labour markets, they undertook legal work.</en>
      <fr>Ils ont bénéficié de l'occasion de faire des études à l'étranger <Alignment alignment="1347" annotation_id="1617">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1617" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans les pays qui ont ouvert leur marché du travail, ils ont entrepris un travail légal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1433" docOffset="11">
      <en>The scale of migration, <Alignment alignment="1745" annotation_id="1457">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1457" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, poses many challenges for the host countries.</en>
      <fr>L'ampleur de la migration comporte <Alignment alignment="2475" annotation_id="1745">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1745" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de nombreux défis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1773">pour</DiscourseConnective> les pays d'accueil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1512" docOffset="12">
      <en>These are challenges for both the central and local authorities.</en>
      <fr>Ces défis se posent aussi bien aux autorités centrales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1853">qu'</DiscourseConnective>aux autorités locales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1577" docOffset="13">
      <en>Local authorities, particularly, where they are responsible for the provision of services such as housing, health care and primary and secondary education, are often confronted with the day-to-day problems of the new immigrants.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités locales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1902">plus particulièrement</DiscourseConnective>, là où elles sont chargées de la prestation de services tels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1985">que</DiscourseConnective> le logement, les soins de santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2021">et</DiscourseConnective> l'enseignement primaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2048">et</DiscourseConnective> secondaire, sont souvent confrontées aux problèmes quotidiens des nouveaux immigrés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1806" docOffset="14">
      <en>Much has been done to aid integration, as well as to help newcomers benefit from the same rights as citizens of their host countries.</en>
      <fr>De gros progrès ont été réalisés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2169">pour</DiscourseConnective> contribuer à l'intégration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2201">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2211">pour</DiscourseConnective> aider les nouveaux arrivants à bénéficier des mêmes droits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2275">que</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens de leurs pays d'accueil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1940" docOffset="15">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2317" annotation_id="1940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1940" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, instances of discrimination remain.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6987" annotation_id="2317">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2317" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, des cas de discrimination subsistent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1990" docOffset="16">
      <en>Sometimes these are the result of legal loopholes and sometimes the result of a lack of knowledge of how to apply the law.</en>
      <fr>Parfois, ceux-ci sont le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2391">résultat</DiscourseConnective> de lacunes du droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2420">et</DiscourseConnective> parfois celui d'un manque de connaissances sur la manière d'appliquer la loi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2113" docOffset="17">
      <en>The LIBE Committee took a very constructive and practical approach in its work.</en>
      <fr>La commission des libertés civiles, de la justice et des affaires intérieures a adopté une méthode très constructive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2618">et</DiscourseConnective> pratique dans son travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2193" docOffset="18">
      <en>There was cross-party agreement that our priority was to highlight the problem areas and undertake steps to remedy them by providing central and local government in Member States with the necessary resources and support.</en>
      <fr>Il y a eu un consensus inter-partis selon lequel notre priorité était de détecter les secteurs problématiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2758">et</DiscourseConnective> de prendre des mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2784">pour</DiscourseConnective> y remédier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2800">en</DiscourseConnective> fournissant les ressources <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2830">et</DiscourseConnective> le soutien nécessaires aux gouvernements central <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2882">et</DiscourseConnective> local dans les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2414" docOffset="19">
      <en>Our primary concern was that the individual citizen should not be hindered in any way from benefiting from his or her rights.</en>
      <fr>Notre principale préoccupation était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2952">que</DiscourseConnective> chaque citoyen ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2974">soit</DiscourseConnective> freiné <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2986">en</DiscourseConnective> aucune manière dans la jouissance de ses droits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2540" docOffset="20">
      <en>The second right I mentioned, that of consular protection, is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2602" sense="Comparison.Contrast">still</DiscourseConnective>, unfortunately, poorly applied.</en>
      <fr>Le second droit que j'ai mentionné, celui de la protection consulaire, est toujours mal appliqué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3135">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2640" docOffset="21">
      <en>This fact was brought starkly to our attention <Alignment alignment="3213" annotation_id="2687">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2687" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our own colleagues found themselves in a dramatic situation during the terrorist attacks in Mumbai.</en>
      <fr>Ce fait a été porté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3172">à</DiscourseConnective> notre attention de façon spectaculaire <Alignment alignment="2687" annotation_id="3213">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3213" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nos propres collègues se sont retrouvés dans une situation dramatique durant les attaques terroristes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3323">à</DiscourseConnective> Mumbai.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2792" docOffset="22">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="16605" annotation_id="2792">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2792" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> MEPs had problems exercising their right to consular protection in such an extreme situation, what chance does the average citizen have in more mundane circumstances?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4262" annotation_id="3333">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3333" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les parlementaires ont eu des problèmes pour exercer leur droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3400">à</DiscourseConnective> la protection consulaire dans une situation si extrême, quelle chance a le citoyen moyen dans des circonstances plus quelconques?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2962" docOffset="23">
      <en>Increasing citizens' awareness of their rights was a key issue raised throughout the report <Alignment alignment="7025" annotation_id="3054">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3054" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a number of measures are suggested for greater awareness building.</en>
      <fr>L'augmentation de la sensibilisation des citoyens vis-à-vis de leurs droits a été une question clef soulevée tout au long du rapport <Alignment alignment="4567" annotation_id="3665">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3665" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> plusieurs mesures sont suggérées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3701">pour</DiscourseConnective> accroître cette sensibilisation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3125" docOffset="24">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="22327" annotation_id="3125">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3125" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> only 31% of citizens consider themselves to be well-informed about their rights, we still have a lot to do.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3125" annotation_id="3739">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3739" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> seulement 31 % des citoyens estiment qu'ils sont bien informés de leurs droits, nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3833">encore</DiscourseConnective> du chemin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3850">à</DiscourseConnective> parcourir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3236" docOffset="25">
      <en>I trust the Commission will take into account Parliament's recommendations and will report back in its sixth report on the concrete progress made.</en>
      <fr>Je ne doute pas que la Commission prendra en compte les recommandations du Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3948">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'elle présentera dans son sixième rapport les progrès concrets réalisés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3383" docOffset="26">
      <en>Finally, I would like to thank my shadow rapporteurs, the staff of the political groups and the LIBE Committee secretariat for their hard work.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4026">Finalement</DiscourseConnective>, j'aimerais remercier mes rapporteurs fictifs, le personnel des groupes politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4120">et</DiscourseConnective> le secrétariat de la commission sur les libertés civiles, de la justice et des affaires intérieures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4223">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur dur labeur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3527" docOffset="27">
      <en>A special word of thanks goes to all those who participated in the public hearing on the report, especially the representatives of the NGOs.</en>
      <fr>Un mot de remerciement spécial est adressé aux personnes qui ont participé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4320">à</DiscourseConnective> l'audience publique sur le rapport, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4358">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> les représentants des ONG.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3668" docOffset="28">
      <en>It is fitting that, in a report on citizenship, the citizen's voice, via the NGOs, was heeded in drawing up the final report.</en>
      <fr>Il est tout à fait opportun <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4428">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans un rapport sur la citoyenneté, la voix des citoyens, par l'intermédiaire des ONG, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4520">soit</DiscourseConnective> prise en considération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4548">pour</DiscourseConnective> la rédaction du rapport final.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3794" id="282" name="Günter Verheugen">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3794" docOffset="29">
      <en>Vice-President of the Commission. - (DE) Mr President, Mrs Gacek, it seems that we are now quite alone in this House.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Madame Gacek, il semble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4671">que</DiscourseConnective> nous soyons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4687">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> seuls dans cette Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3912" docOffset="30">
      <en>On behalf of the Commission, I should like to thank you for this very important, impressive report and to extend our congratulations.</en>
      <fr>Au nom de la Commission, j'aimerais vous remercier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4777">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport très important et impressionnant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4826">et</DiscourseConnective> vous transmettre nos félicitations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4046" docOffset="31">
      <en>The issue here is something very important: European citizenship.</en>
      <fr>Le dossier en cause est une notion très importante: la citoyenneté européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4112" docOffset="32">
      <en>Many think 'European citizenship' is a hollow phrase and means nothing, <Alignment alignment="1995" annotation_id="4184">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4184" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> your report makes quite clear that that is not the case.</en>
      <fr>Nombreux sont ceux qui pensent que la "citoyenneté européenne" est une expression creuse qui ne signifie rien, <Alignment alignment="4184" annotation_id="5055">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5055" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> votre rapport précise assez clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5099">que</DiscourseConnective> ce n'est pas le cas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4245" docOffset="33">
      <en>European citizenship is made a reality by means of rights that are precisely defined in the Treaty, to wit free movement and right of residence, the right to vote and stand for election in local and European elections, the right to consular protection, the right to petition the European Parliament, the right to complain to the European Ombudsman and the right to write to the European institutions.</en>
      <fr>La citoyenneté européenne devient réalité grâce aux droits qui sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5192">précisément</DiscourseConnective> définis dans le traité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5228">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir la libre circulation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5258">et</DiscourseConnective> le droit de résidence, le droit de vote <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5301">et</DiscourseConnective> d'éligibilité aux élections locales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5340">et</DiscourseConnective> européennes, le droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5365">à</DiscourseConnective> la protection consulaire, le droit de pétition devant le Parlement européen, le droit de réclamation devant le Médiateur européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5497">et</DiscourseConnective> le droit d'écrire aux institutions européennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4646" docOffset="34">
      <en>The Commission takes the view that it is high time there was a specific policy programme on European citizenship.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est d'avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5573">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est grand temps d'avoir un programme politique précis sur la citoyenneté européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4760" docOffset="35">
      <en>To this end, the Commission intends to carry out a comprehensive consultation process <Alignment alignment="24349" annotation_id="4846">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4846" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> specific information can be gathered on the problems of European citizenship.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5664">À</DiscourseConnective> cette fin, la Commission a l'intention de diriger un processus de consultation exhaustif en sorte <Alignment alignment="4846" annotation_id="5764">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5764" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des renseignements précis puissent être recueillis au sujet des problèmes de citoyenneté européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4932" docOffset="36">
      <en>This could lead to new proposals, which would <Alignment alignment="5941" annotation_id="4978">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4978" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> form the basis of the Sixth Commission Report on Citizenship of the Union, which is scheduled for 2010.</en>
      <fr>Ce processus pourrait amener de nouvelles propositions, qui formeraient <Alignment alignment="4978" annotation_id="5941">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5941" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la base du sixième rapport de la Commission sur la citoyenneté de l'Union, prévu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6028">pour</DiscourseConnective> 2010.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5087" docOffset="37">
      <en>Aside from this, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5104" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>, the Commission is working and will continue to work day to day to ensure that citizens are indeed able to exercise their civil rights, and are able to do so every day.</en>
      <fr>À part cela, la Commission travaille <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6076">et</DiscourseConnective> continuera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6090">à</DiscourseConnective> travailler jour après jour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6119">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire en sorte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6139">que</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens soient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6163">effectivement</DiscourseConnective> en mesure d'exercer leurs droits civils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6217">et</DiscourseConnective> à ce qu'ils puissent le faire chaque jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5281" docOffset="38">
      <en>In a large number of areas where your report, Mrs Gacek, calls on the Commission to act, the Commission is already taking action to ensure that these rights are reinforced and extended.</en>
      <fr>Dans un grand nombre de secteurs dans lesquels votre rapport, Madame Gacek, invite la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6360">à</DiscourseConnective> agir, la Commission prend <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6388">déjà</DiscourseConnective> des mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6405">pour</DiscourseConnective> s'assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6420">que</DiscourseConnective> ces droits sont renforcés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6450">et</DiscourseConnective> étendus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5467" docOffset="39">
      <en>I should like to give the example of the Commission Action Plan on consular protection, <Alignment alignment="6553" annotation_id="5555">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5555" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> would add that I fully agree with you that this is an area in which something needs to be done.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais donner l'exemple du plan d'action de la Commission sur la protection consulaire <Alignment alignment="761" annotation_id="6553">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6553" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je voudrais ajouter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6576">que</DiscourseConnective> je suis entièrement d'accord avec vous pour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6624">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut faire quelque chose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6660">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5655" docOffset="40">
      <en>After all, just a few weeks ago, we held an extremely instructive debate on the subject in this House that showed the extent of the gulf between aspiration and reality in the very case of consular rights.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6672">Après tout</DiscourseConnective>, il y a quelques semaines à peine, nous avons participé à un débat extrêmement instructif sur le sujet lors de cette Assemblée et celui-ci nous a montré l'étendue du fossé qui sépare les aspirations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6882">et</DiscourseConnective> la réalité dans le cas actuel des droits consulaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5860" docOffset="41">
      <en>The Commission has arranged for citizens to be informed about their rights by means of information campaigns, <Alignment alignment="7022" annotation_id="5970">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5970" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> is endeavouring to put in place guarantees that these rights can actually be exercised - particularly by adopting its report on the application by Member States of the Directive on free movement.</en>
      <fr>La Commission a fait en sorte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6969">que</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens soient informés de leurs droits par l'entremise de campagnes informatives, <Alignment alignment="5970" annotation_id="7061">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7061" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7069">s'</DiscourseConnective>efforce de mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7089">en</DiscourseConnective> place des garanties selon lesquelles ces droits peuvent réellement être exercés - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7174">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7189">en</DiscourseConnective> adoptant ce rapport sur l'application par les États membres de la directive sur la libre circulation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6170" docOffset="42">
      <en>The forthcoming European elections are one of the priorities of interinstitutional public relations.</en>
      <fr>Les prochaines élections européennes constituent l'une des priorités des relations publiques interinstitutionnelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6271" docOffset="43">
      <en>The Commission supports and supplements Parliament's campaign to put in place information measures to increase public awareness of these elections and to call on citizens to exercise their electoral rights.</en>
      <fr>La Commission soutient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7434">et</DiscourseConnective> complète la campagne du Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7471">pour</DiscourseConnective> mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7483">en</DiscourseConnective> place des actions d'information <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7518">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>augmenter la sensibilisation du public à ces élections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7580">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7583">pour</DiscourseConnective> encourager les citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7612">à</DiscourseConnective> exercer leurs droits électoraux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6478" docOffset="44">
      <en>It is fortunate that we are doing so, <Alignment alignment="632" annotation_id="6516">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6516" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I should <Alignment alignment="7705" annotation_id="6529">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6529" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to emphasise that it is not just the Commission that is endeavouring to realise European citizenship in day-to-day life.</en>
      <fr>Heureusement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7660">que</DiscourseConnective> nous agissons de la sorte, <Alignment alignment="6516" annotation_id="7691">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7691" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'aimerais <Alignment alignment="6529" annotation_id="7705">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7705" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> insister sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7732">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il n'y a pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7748">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7770">s'</DiscourseConnective>efforce d'accomplir la citoyenneté européenne dans la vie quotidienne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6660" docOffset="45">
      <en>Other actors, too - this Parliament, all 27 Member States, the regional authorities, the national Parliaments, the local authorities and every municipality in the European Union - play a very important role in the effective development of European citizenship.</en>
      <fr>D'autres acteurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7860">aussi</DiscourseConnective> - ce Parlement, l'ensemble des 27 États membres, les autorités régionales, les parlements nationaux, les autorités locales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7989">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que chaque municipalité de l'Union européenne - jouent un rôle très important dans l'évolution de la citoyenneté européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6921" docOffset="46">
      <en>I am pleased that the report by Mrs Gacek, published in good time before the 2009 European elections, involves some of these very important actors, who should all take ownership of European citizenship in order to make Europe real for its millions of citizens.</en>
      <fr>Je suis heureux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8136">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapport de Madame Gacek, publié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8175">à</DiscourseConnective> point nommé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8189">avant</DiscourseConnective> les élections européennes de 2009, comprenne certains de ces acteurs très importants, qui doivent tous assumer la responsabilité de la citoyenneté européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8353">afin de</DiscourseConnective> rendre l'Europe réelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8384">pour</DiscourseConnective> ses millions de citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7182" docOffset="47">
      <en>I believe we all see it as our shared responsibility to ensure that European citizenship is seen not as a mere symbol but as a specific right to which substance can and must be given in day-to-day life.</en>
      <fr>Je crois que nous voyons tous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8445">comme</DiscourseConnective> notre responsabilité partagée de faire en sorte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8499">que</DiscourseConnective> la citoyenneté européenne ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8532">soit</DiscourseConnective> pas considérée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8552">comme</DiscourseConnective> un simple symbole, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8577">mais</DiscourseConnective> plutôt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8589">comme</DiscourseConnective> un droit précis auquel on peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8626">et</DiscourseConnective> on doit donner du poids au quotidien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7385" id="283" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7385" docOffset="48">
      <en>The item is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le point est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7405" docOffset="49">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7440" docOffset="50">
      <en>Written statements (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclarations écrites (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7470" id="284" name="Slavi Binev ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7470" docOffset="51">
      <en>in writing. - (BG) Transparency and democratic relations between citizens and institutions are fundamental principles in Europe and basic rights of European citizens.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (BG) La transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8781">et</DiscourseConnective> les relations démocratiques entre les citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8831">et</DiscourseConnective> les institutions sont des principes fondamentaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8883">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8893">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les droits essentiels des citoyens européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7637" docOffset="52">
      <en>These are precisely the principles on which the parliamentary elections must take place.</en>
      <fr>Ceux-ci sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8962">précisément</DiscourseConnective> les principes sur lesquels repose la tenue des élections parlementaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7726" docOffset="53">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3818" annotation_id="7726">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7726" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the problem in Bulgaria of vote buying indicates the exact opposite.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6427" annotation_id="9047">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9047" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le problème d'achat de votes en Bulgarie va tout à fait dans le sens inverse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7804" docOffset="54">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="15647" annotation_id="7804">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7804" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">After</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the previous local elections were repeatedly compromised by the blatant buying of votes of GERB (Citizens for European Development of Bulgaria), DPS (Movement for Rights and Freedoms) and BSP (Bulgarian Socialist Party), ordinary citizens were left feeling that they had no right to choose.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7804" annotation_id="9136">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9136" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">Après que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les élections locales précédentes eurent à maintes reprises été mises en péril par l'achat de votes flagrant du parti politique GERB (Citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9289">pour</DiscourseConnective> le développement européen de la Bulgarie) et par le BSP (Parti socialiste bulgare), les citoyens ordinaires ont eu l'impression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9422">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils n'avaient pas le droit de choisir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8101" docOffset="55">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8101" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">As a result</DiscourseConnective>, this makes them much less willing to vote again.</en>
      <fr>Ces pratiques les ont rendu beaucoup moins disposés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9516">à</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9518">encore</DiscourseConnective> voter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8163" docOffset="56">
      <en>In spite of the existing criminal code and the numerous signs of violations of the law, not a single person mentioned in the Commission's report has yet been convicted of these crimes <Alignment alignment="13564" annotation_id="8347">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8347" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the relevant law enforcement authorities are clearly unwilling to stop vote buying.</en>
      <fr>Malgré le code pénal existant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9562">et</DiscourseConnective> les nombreux signes de violations de la loi, pas une seule des personnes mentionnées dans le rapport de la Commission n'a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9687">encore</DiscourseConnective> été déclarée coupable de ces crimes, <Alignment alignment="9481" annotation_id="9731">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9731" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les autorités répressives concernées ne veulent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9783">à</DiscourseConnective> l'évidence pas faire cesser l'achat de votes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8439" docOffset="57">
      <en>In Bulgaria the judiciary still shows a lack of determination <Alignment alignment="20817" annotation_id="8501">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8501" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the well-known culprits are again preparing pre-election campaigns, <Alignment alignment="24490" annotation_id="8573">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8573" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> those who sold their votes are now looking for new buyers offering the best bid.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9831">En</DiscourseConnective> Bulgarie, le pouvoir judiciaire montre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9873">encore</DiscourseConnective> un manque de détermination <Alignment alignment="5823" annotation_id="9907">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9907" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les coupables notoires préparent une nouvelle fois leurs campagnes pré-électorales, <Alignment alignment="8573" annotation_id="9994">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9994" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ceux qui ont vendu leurs votes cherchent à présent de nouveaux acheteurs offrant la meilleure enchère.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8660" docOffset="58">
      <en>I want to stress that as long as these violations of the law are allowed in Bulgaria <Alignment alignment="19953" annotation_id="8745">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8745" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the state continues not to take any action on the issue, honest voters are in actual fact being deprived of their basic human right - the right to choose!</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10117">à</DiscourseConnective> souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10129">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10132">aussi longtemps que</DiscourseConnective> ces violations de la loi seront permises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10193">en</DiscourseConnective> Bulgarie <Alignment alignment="8745" annotation_id="10205">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10205" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que l'État ne prendra aucune mesure pour remédier au problème, les électeurs honnêtes seront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10301">en fait</DiscourseConnective> privés d'un de leurs droits fondamentaux, celui de choisir ses représentants!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8904" docOffset="59">
      <en>This is unacceptable for European citizens.</en>
      <fr>Ceci est inacceptable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10409">pour</DiscourseConnective> des citoyens européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8948" docOffset="60">
      <en>I urge Parliament not to sit back and do nothing.</en>
      <fr>Je prie le Parlement de ne pas rester sans rien faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8998" id="285" language="HU" name="Magda Kósáné Kovács ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8998" docOffset="61">
      <en>The Treaty on the European Union states that every citizen of the Union is equal.</en>
      <fr>Le traité sur l'Union européenne stipule <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10534">que</DiscourseConnective> tous les citoyens de l'Union sont égaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9080" docOffset="62">
      <en>Unfortunately, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9095" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>, this principle is not always fulfilled in reality.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10579">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, ce principe n'est pas toujours respecté dans la réalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9155" docOffset="63">
      <en>The reason for differences is the spread of extreme poverty, social exclusion or deliberate exclusion, regions with multiple disadvantages that have been left out of the information society, <Alignment alignment="10885" annotation_id="9346">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9346" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whose citizens cannot even be expected to have a common European awareness.</en>
      <fr>La raison des différences est la progression de la pauvreté extrême, de l'exclusion sociale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10745">ou</DiscourseConnective> de l'exclusion délibérée, les régions souffrant d'inégalités multiples qui ont été laissées pour compte dans la société de l'information <Alignment alignment="9346" annotation_id="10885">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10885" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dont on suppose que leurs citoyens ne possèdent pas une conscience européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9426" docOffset="64">
      <en>I welcome the fact that the report specifically mentions the Roma.</en>
      <fr>Je salue le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10984">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapport mentionne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11009">précisément</DiscourseConnective> les Roms.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9493" docOffset="65">
      <en>This minority of 10-12 million lives in segregation <Alignment alignment="4864" annotation_id="9545">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9545" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> experience their educational disadvantages and hopeless employment situation as a devaluation of their citizenship.</en>
      <fr>Cette minorité de 10 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11052">à</DiscourseConnective> 12 millions de personnes vit dans l'isolement, <Alignment alignment="9545" annotation_id="11101">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11101" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> subit son désavantage au niveau de l'éducation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11151">et</DiscourseConnective> sa situation d'emploi désespérée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11187">comme</DiscourseConnective> une dévaluation de sa citoyenneté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9665" docOffset="66">
      <en>There are indications that this breakdown of society will have an effect on the European Parliamentary elections as well.</en>
      <fr>Tout porte à croire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11248">que</DiscourseConnective> cette rupture de la société aura un effet sur les élections parlementaires européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11339">également</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9787" docOffset="67">
      <en>The willingness of the most disadvantaged to vote is falling, <Alignment alignment="5860" annotation_id="9849">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9849" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they lack information <Alignment alignment="22248" annotation_id="9877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9877" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> at the margins of society there is less awareness of the significance of the fact that of all the EU institutions, it is only the composition of the European Parliament that they can directly influence.</en>
      <fr>L'envie de voter des plus défavorisés est en recul, <Alignment alignment="9849" annotation_id="11402">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11402" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils manquent d'information, <Alignment alignment="7729" annotation_id="11434">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11434" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11437">en</DiscourseConnective> marge de la société, la conscience est moins forte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11491">que</DiscourseConnective>, parmi toutes les institutions européennes, c'est la composition du Parlement européen qui peut avoir une influence directe sur leur situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10084" docOffset="68">
      <en>It is unfortunate that indifference is particularly great in Central and Eastern European countries, the roots of which is once again to be sought in the inadequacy of information, <Alignment alignment="6424" annotation_id="10265">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10265" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> another contributing factor is that the pace of catching up after the great wave of enlargement has slowed down and caused disappointment.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11639">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, l'indifférence est particulièrement élevée dans les pays d'Europe centrale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11731">et</DiscourseConnective> orientale. Elle trouve sa source une fois de plus dans l'insuffisance de l'information, <Alignment alignment="10265" annotation_id="11822">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11822" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans un autre facteur, en effet le rythme des changements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11891">après</DiscourseConnective> la grande vague d'élargissement a ralenti <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11939">et</DiscourseConnective> causé des déceptions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10408" docOffset="69">
      <en>We hope that the free movement of citizens, workers and service providers will break down borders in people's minds and thinking as well.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11978">que</DiscourseConnective> la libre circulation des citoyens, des travailleurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12034">et</DiscourseConnective> des prestataires de services fera tomber les frontières dans les esprits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12110">et</DiscourseConnective> la pensée des gens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10546" docOffset="70">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8153" annotation_id="10546">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10546" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it becomes natural that moving around within the boundaries of a larger home is the realisation of increased freedom, then the multi-layered and multicoloured European Union can embrace a large number of diverse, yet cohesive and tolerant European citizens.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1974" annotation_id="12133">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12133" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la circulation au sein des frontières d'un plus grand foyer, réalisation d'une liberté accrue, devient quelque chose de plus naturel, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12270">alors</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne aux réalités superposées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12320">et</DiscourseConnective> multicolore pourra englober un grand nombre de citoyens européens différents, certes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12409">mais</DiscourseConnective> également unis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12429">et</DiscourseConnective> tolérants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
