<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Welcome</en>
    <fr>Souhaits de bienvenue</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="058" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, it is a great pleasure for me to welcome the members of the delegation from the parliament of the Republic of Moldova, who are here in Strasbourg on the occasion of the 11th meeting of the EU-Moldova Parliamentary Cooperation Committee which took place yesterday and today.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, c'est avec grand plaisir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="70">que</DiscourseConnective> je souhaite la bienvenue aux membres de la délégation du parlement de la République de Moldavie, qui sont ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="184">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="197">à</DiscourseConnective> l'occasion de la 11e réunion de la commission de coopération parlementaire UE-Moldavie qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="290">s'</DiscourseConnective>est tenue hier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="307">et</DiscourseConnective> aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="304" docOffset="2">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, the fact that you are with us in the European Parliament demonstrates that parliamentary dialogue is the best way of strengthening our relationship and finding solutions for the issues which concern the European Union's eastern neighbours.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="332">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="354">que</DiscourseConnective> vous soyez avec nous au Parlement européen prouve <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="408">que</DiscourseConnective> le dialogue parlementaire est la meilleure manière de renforcer nos relations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="490">et</DiscourseConnective> de trouver des solutions aux questions qui préoccupent les voisins orientaux de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="566" docOffset="3">
      <en>We wish you all every success in the elections next year and in your current and future activities.</en>
      <fr>Nous vous souhaitons à tous beaucoup de succès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="640">pour</DiscourseConnective> les élections de l'année prochaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="680">et</DiscourseConnective> dans vos activités présentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="712">et</DiscourseConnective> futures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="666" docOffset="4">
      <en>A very warm welcome to you all.</en>
      <fr>Soyez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="730">encore</DiscourseConnective> les bienvenus parmi nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="698" docOffset="5">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
