<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>3.</en>
    <fr>3.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Press freedom in Kenya</en>
    <fr>Liberté de la presse au Kenya</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="26" id="219" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="26" docOffset="2">
      <en>The next item is the debate on six motions for resolutions on press freedom in Kenya.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur six propositions de résolutions concernant la liberté de la presse au Kenya.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="112" id="220" name="Marios Matsakis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="112" docOffset="3">
      <en>author. - Mr President, freedom of the press is synonymous with freedom of expression and democracy.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la liberté de la presse est synonyme de liberté d'opinion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="243">et</DiscourseConnective> de démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="213" docOffset="4">
      <en>This does not, of course, apply in an ideal fashion in our society, in which media barons as well as government and political party media interference are not unheard of, but is rather prominent in some western countries, not excluding the USA and some EU Member States.</en>
      <fr>Bien entendu, cette vérité ne s'applique pas sans réserve <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="319">à</DiscourseConnective> notre société, où les connexions entre magnats de la presse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="381">et</DiscourseConnective> gouvernements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="398">et</DiscourseConnective> partis politiques sont loin d'être inexistantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="449">et</DiscourseConnective> sont bien souvent la norme, à commencer par les États-Unis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="511">et</DiscourseConnective> certains États membres de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="484" docOffset="5">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="546" annotation_id="484">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="484" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, at least as far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="509" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> legislation is concerned, the media in our societies are given the theoretical protection of the law they need to function as near properly as possible.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="484" annotation_id="546">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="546" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, sur le plan législatif, nos médias bénéficient de la protection théorique dont ils ont besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="651">pour</DiscourseConnective> travailler dans les meilleures conditions possibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="665" docOffset="6">
      <en>This is where we beg to differ with the Kenyan Government, which is introducing legislative measures that can be used for possible repression and persecution of the press by the state.</en>
      <fr>C'est sur ce point spécifique que nous nous différencions du gouvernement kényan, qui vient de faire adopter des mesures législatives susceptibles d'être invoquées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="873">pour</DiscourseConnective> réprimer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="887">et</DiscourseConnective> persécuter la presse du pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="850" docOffset="7">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="11412" annotation_id="853">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="853" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> call on the Kenyan authorities to reconsider their stance on the matter and give their mass media the legislative freedom they need in order to try, at least, to function as democratically as possible.</en>
      <fr>Nous invitons <Alignment alignment="853" annotation_id="934">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="934" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les autorités kényanes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="962">à</DiscourseConnective> revoir leur position dans ce domaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1001">et</DiscourseConnective> à donner aux médias la liberté juridique dont ils ont besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1065">pour</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1070">au moins</DiscourseConnective> tenter de fonctionner de la manière la plus démocratique qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1140">soit</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1065" docOffset="8">
      <en>The Kenyan Government must understand and accept that the protection of the press is essential for their country's road to betterment of living standards for its citizens.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement kényan doit comprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1185">et</DiscourseConnective> admettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1197">que</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse doit être garantie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1244">s'</DiscourseConnective>il entend améliorer les conditions de vie de ses citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1237" docOffset="9">
      <en>We hope and trust that the plea we have made through this resolution will not be seen as interference but as friendly advice to the Government of Kenya, that it will be taken seriously into consideration <Alignment alignment="13396" annotation_id="1441">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1441" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that there will be wiser reconsideration of what they have been doing so far.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1319">et</DiscourseConnective> sommes convaincus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1340">que</DiscourseConnective> l'appel que nous lançons par le biais de cette résolution ne sera pas vu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1417">comme</DiscourseConnective> une ingérence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1437">mais</DiscourseConnective> bien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1447">comme</DiscourseConnective> un conseil amical, que le gouvernement kényan le prendra au sérieux <Alignment alignment="4090" annotation_id="1521">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1521" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1524">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il reconsidèrera avec attention les initiatives prises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1582">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> présent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1523" id="221" language="PL" name="Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1523" docOffset="10">
      <en>Mr President, Kenya has been in the throes of a serious political crisis for a long time.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, le Kenya est aux prises avec une grave crise politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1677">depuis</DiscourseConnective> longtemps.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1613" docOffset="11">
      <en>The current President, Mr Kibaki, is implementing measures which are clearly intended to restrict the freedom of speech and of the press.</en>
      <fr>Le président actuel, M. Kibaki, met en œuvre des mesures qui visent clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1774">à</DiscourseConnective> restreindre la liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1812">et</DiscourseConnective> de la presse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1751" docOffset="12">
      <en>On 2 January 2009, he violated the provisions of the Declaration of Human Rights and the African Charter of Human Rights by sanctioning amendments to what is known as the Kenya Communications Bill of 1998, giving the national authorities new rights, including the right to dismantle broadcasting and communications equipment, as well as to control and alter the content of mass media publications.</en>
      <fr>Le 2 janvier 2009, il a enfreint les dispositions de la Déclaration des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1919">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Charte africaine des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1967">en</DiscourseConnective> amendant la loi de 1998 sur les communications au Kenya, pour concéder de nouveaux droits aux autorités nationales, y compris celui de démonter les équipements de diffusion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2143">et</DiscourseConnective> de communication, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2164">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que de contrôler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2187">et</DiscourseConnective> modifier le contenu des publications des médias.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2149" docOffset="13">
      <en>The international community unanimously declared this to be a further step towards media censorship in Kenya.</en>
      <fr>La Communauté internationale a été unanime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2282">pour</DiscourseConnective> déclarer qu'il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2302">s'</DiscourseConnective>agissait d'un nouveau pas en avant vers la censure des médias au Kenya.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2259" docOffset="14">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2376" annotation_id="2259">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2259" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in spite of earlier commitments arising from agreements signed to establish Kenya's grand coalition government, the President failed to consult the Prime Minister in office regarding either this decision or any further decisions.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2259" annotation_id="2376">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2376" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, malgré des engagements précédents découlant d'accords signés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2446">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> créer une grande coalition gouvernementale au Kenya, le président n'a pas consulté le Premier ministre concernant cette décision <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2585">ou</DiscourseConnective> toute autre décision.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2499" docOffset="15">
      <en>This exacerbated the crisis in Kenya, which had already lasted for over a year <Alignment alignment="2696" annotation_id="2578">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2578" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which had claimed around 1 000 victims and left 350 000 people homeless.</en>
      <fr>Cela a eu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2620">pour</DiscourseConnective> effet d'exacerber la crise au Kenya, qui dure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2671">déjà</DiscourseConnective> depuis plus d'un an <Alignment alignment="9104" annotation_id="2696">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2696" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui a fait environ 1 000 victimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2733">et</DiscourseConnective> 350 000 sans-abri.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2655" docOffset="16">
      <en>The European Union cannot stand by <Alignment alignment="2806" annotation_id="2690">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2690" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> fundamental freedoms are being blatantly violated.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne ne peut rester les bras croisés <Alignment alignment="7905" annotation_id="2806">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2806" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des libertés fondamentales sont ouvertement bafouées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2747" docOffset="17">
      <en>We should welcome the Kenyan President's assurances that the amendments will be revised <Alignment alignment="23855" annotation_id="2835">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2835" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that all political powers will be consulted on this matter, in order to give these amendments a new, democratic quality and ensure the broad support of Kenyan society.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions saluer le fait que le président kenyan assure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2930">que</DiscourseConnective> les amendements seront revus <Alignment alignment="13892" annotation_id="2963">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2963" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2966">que</DiscourseConnective> toutes les forces politiques seront consultées sur cette question, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3037">afin de</DiscourseConnective> donner à ces amendements une nouvelle qualité démocratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3104">et</DiscourseConnective> garantir un large soutien de la société kenyane.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3007" docOffset="18">
      <en>The European Union must support these measures and monitor them in detail, fostering pluralism during the process of building a civil society.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne doit soutenir ces mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3201">et</DiscourseConnective> les suivre de près, en renforçant le pluralisme dans le processus de construction d'une société civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3150" docOffset="19">
      <en>At the same time, the Kenyan authorities should take stronger action to introduce a state of normality in the country, including the creation of a special committee, consisting of local and international experts, to punish those guilty of violence and of causing the crisis last year.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3308">En même temps</DiscourseConnective>, les autorités kenyanes devraient agir plus vigoureusement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3381">pour</DiscourseConnective> rétablir une situation normale dans le pays, y compris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3441">en</DiscourseConnective> créant une commission spéciale composée d'experts locaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3501">et</DiscourseConnective> internationaux qui serait chargée de punir ceux qui sont coupables de violence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3583">et</DiscourseConnective> qui ont causé la crise l'année dernière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3435" docOffset="20">
      <en>There is a chance that these measures will stabilise the internal situation and prevent a humanitarian disaster, which inevitably threatens this Eastern African country with a population of ten million.</en>
      <fr>Il est possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3643">que</DiscourseConnective> ces mesures stabilisent la situation intérieure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3695">et</DiscourseConnective> empêchent une catastrophe humanitaire, qui menace inévitablement ce pays d'Afrique de l'Est peuplé de dix millions d'habitants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3638" id="222" name="Colm Burke">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3638" docOffset="21">
      <en>author. - Mr President, I regret the signing of the Kenya Communications (Amendment) Bill by President Kibaki.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je déplore sincèrement la ratification de l'amendement à la loi kényane sur les communications par le président Kibaki.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3749" docOffset="22">
      <en>This act disregards the rights to freedom of expression and press freedom as enshrined in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and echoed by other international conventions, including the African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights.</en>
      <fr>Le nouveau texte constitue un déni de la liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4046">et</DiscourseConnective> de la liberté de la presse, deux droits fondamentaux consacrés par la Déclaration universelle des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4165">et</DiscourseConnective> intégrés dans d'autres conventions internationales telles que la Charte africaine sur les droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4276">et</DiscourseConnective> des peuples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3988" docOffset="23">
      <en>This act would give considerable powers to the Kenyan Information Minister to raid media houses deemed to be a threat to national security and to dismantle broadcasting equipment.</en>
      <fr>Cette loi confère au ministère kényan de l'information le droit d'effectuer des perquisitions dans les locaux des médias censés menacer la sécurité nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4450">et</DiscourseConnective> de détruire le matériel de diffusion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4168" docOffset="24">
      <en>The act will <Alignment alignment="4506" annotation_id="4181">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4181" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> give the state the power to regulate contents to be aired and published by electronic and print media respectively.</en>
      <fr>Le texte donne <Alignment alignment="4181" annotation_id="4506">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4506" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aux autorités le pouvoir de réglementer le contenu des émissions diffusées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4591">et</DiscourseConnective> des textes publiés par écrit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4623">ou</DiscourseConnective> sur la toile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4302" docOffset="25">
      <en>I welcome, <Alignment alignment="28468" annotation_id="4313">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4313" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, President Kibaki's recent move to revise this media law and his gesture to consider amendments to legislation proposed by members of the media.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4313" annotation_id="4640">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4640" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je salue l'engagement pris récemment par le président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4705">à</DiscourseConnective> revoir cette loi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4724">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4727">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre en considération les amendements proposés par les acteurs du monde de la presse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4466" docOffset="26">
      <en>Freedom of expression is a fundamental human right, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4518" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> stated in Article 19 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.</en>
      <fr>La liberté d'expression est un droit fondamental consacré par l'article 19 de la Déclaration universelle des droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4588" docOffset="27">
      <en>I call on the Kenyan Government to initiate a stakeholder consultation in order to build consensus on how to better regulate the communications industry without interfering with press freedom and without infringing rights contained within the Universal Declaration.</en>
      <fr>J'invite le gouvernement kényan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4978">à</DiscourseConnective> lancer une consultation des parties prenantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5026">afin de</DiscourseConnective> dégager un consensus sur la manière de réformer la réglementation du secteur des communications <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5130">sans</DiscourseConnective> interférer avec la liberté de la presse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5175">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5178">sans</DiscourseConnective> enfreindre les droits proclamés par la Déclaration universelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4854" docOffset="28">
      <en>Finally, I would like to underline the need to adjust the culture of impunity in Kenya in order to bring those responsible for the post-election violence a year ago to justice.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5247">Pour conclure</DiscourseConnective>, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5271">à</DiscourseConnective> souligner un point important à mes yeux: il est nécessaire de remédier à la culture de l'impunité qui règne au Kenya et de traduire en justice les responsables des violences qui ont fait suite aux élections il y a un an <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5493">déjà</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5031" docOffset="29">
      <en>I call for the setting-up of an independent commission consisting of local and international legal experts who would carry out investigations and prosecutions into the violent events following the flawed elections in December 2007.</en>
      <fr>Je demande la création d'une commission indépendante composée d'experts locaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5578">et</DiscourseConnective> internationaux afin de procéder aux enquêtes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5626">et</DiscourseConnective> aux poursuites qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5648">s'</DiscourseConnective>imposent concernant les violents événements qui ont émaillé les élections truquées de décembre 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5263" id="223" language="NL" name="Erik Meijer">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5263" docOffset="30">
      <en>Mr President, Kenya has a violent past.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, le Kenya a un passé violent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5303" docOffset="31">
      <en>After the Second World War, <Alignment alignment="5838" annotation_id="5331">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5331" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europe slowly came to accept that the independence of African countries was eventually inevitable, Kenya was emphatically excluded, as was the country we now know as Zimbabwe.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5803">Après</DiscourseConnective> la Deuxième Guerre mondiale, <Alignment alignment="13767" annotation_id="5838">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5838" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Europe a lentement accepté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5873">que</DiscourseConnective> l'indépendance des pays africains était inéluctable, le Kenya a été clairement exclu, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5963">tout comme</DiscourseConnective> le pays que nous appelons aujourd'hui le Zimbabwe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5512" docOffset="32">
      <en>According to colonial rulers, there were too many foreign colonists and too many foreign economic interests in those countries to be able to leave them in the hands of the predominantly black populations.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6025">Pour</DiscourseConnective> les puissances coloniales, il y avait bien trop de colons étrangers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6098">et</DiscourseConnective> trop d'intérêts économiques étrangers dans ces pays pour les laisser aux mains des populations principalement noires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5717" docOffset="33">
      <en>Unlike other West African countries, independence in Kenya did not come about peacefully, but only following a protracted and violent struggle by the independence movement Mau Mau.</en>
      <fr>Contrairement à d'autres pays d'Afrique de l'Ouest, l'indépendance du Kenya n'a pas été acquise de manière pacifique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6337">mais</DiscourseConnective> seulement à la suite d'une lutte prolongée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6385">et</DiscourseConnective> violente du mouvement indépendantiste Mau Mau.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5898" docOffset="34">
      <en>This need for a violent struggle has laid the foundations for continued violence and intimidation.</en>
      <fr>Ce recours obligé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6453">à</DiscourseConnective> une lutte violente a jeté les fondations d'une violence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6511">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une intimidation continues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5997" docOffset="35">
      <en>The victors mainly belong to one major tribe, the Kikuyu.</en>
      <fr>Les vainqueurs appartiennent principalement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6588">à</DiscourseConnective> une grande tribu, celle des Kikuyu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6055" docOffset="36">
      <en>Other population groups have always been kept in opposition, where necessary on the strength of rigged election results.</en>
      <fr>D'autres groupes de la population ont toujours été maintenus dans l'opposition, le cas échéant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6721">en</DiscourseConnective> manipulant les résultats électoraux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6176" docOffset="37">
      <en>The latest presidential elections proved once again that a non-Kikuyu cannot become President, not even if the majority of voters vote for him.</en>
      <fr>Les dernières élections présidentielles ont prouvé une fois de plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6829">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un non Kikuyu ne peut pas devenir président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6877">même si</DiscourseConnective> la majorité des électeurs vote <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6916">pour</DiscourseConnective> lui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6320" docOffset="38">
      <en>Thanks to a compromise, the opposition candidate is now Prime Minister <Alignment alignment="37281" annotation_id="6391">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6391" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> domestic peace seems to be restored.</en>
      <fr>Grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6932">à</DiscourseConnective> un compromis, le candidat de l'opposition est à présent Premier ministre <Alignment alignment="6391" annotation_id="7007">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7007" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la paix intérieure semble rétablie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6432" docOffset="39">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6432" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>, out of the two African countries with rigged presidential elections, Zimbabwe is considered the country with the bad compromise, Kenya has been praised as the country with the good compromise.</en>
      <fr>Sur les deux pays africains dont les élections présidentielles ont été manipulées, le Zimbabwe a trouvé un mauvais compromis et le Kenya un bon compromis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6632" docOffset="40">
      <en>For years, Western Europe and America considered Kenya to be a major success story.</en>
      <fr>Pendant des années, l'Europe occidentale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7242">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Amérique ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7260">considéré que</DiscourseConnective> le Kenya constituait une grande réussite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6716" docOffset="41">
      <en>It was a country with relative prosperity, freedom for international businesses, friendship with the West and attention for tourists.</en>
      <fr>Ce pays connaissait une prospérité relative, les entreprises internationales jouissaient de liberté, il avait noué des liens d'amitié avec l'Occident <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7466">et</DiscourseConnective> il recueillait les faveurs des touristes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6850" docOffset="42">
      <en>Kenya has now lost that success-story image.</en>
      <fr>Le Kenya a perdu aujourd'hui cette image de réussite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6895" docOffset="43">
      <en>A food shortage and a new press law have made for renewed tension.</en>
      <fr>Une pénurie alimentaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7589">et</DiscourseConnective> une nouvelle loi concernant la presse ont attisé les tensions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6962" docOffset="44">
      <en>This food shortage is partly attributable to the fact that the President, in exchange for the construction of the port, has leased out 40 000 hectares of farm land to the oil state Qatar for food supplies.</en>
      <fr>Cette pénurie alimentaire peut être en partie attribuée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7711">au fait</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7719">que</DiscourseConnective> le président a loué 40 000 hectares de terre agricole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7777">à</DiscourseConnective> l'État pétrolier du Qatar <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7805">pour</DiscourseConnective> ses fournitures alimentaires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7840">en</DiscourseConnective> échange de la construction du port.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7168" docOffset="45">
      <en>The press law appears to be a lever which the President uses to restrict the power of the coalition government and to eliminate critical opponents.</en>
      <fr>La loi sur la presse apparaît <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7909">comme</DiscourseConnective> un levier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7925">que</DiscourseConnective> le président utilise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7950">pour</DiscourseConnective> limiter le pouvoir du gouvernement de coalition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8003">et</DiscourseConnective> éliminer les opposants critiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7316" docOffset="46">
      <en>This is all the more shocking, given that this law came about without the Prime Minister even being consulted.</en>
      <fr>C'est d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8048">autant</DiscourseConnective> plus choquant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8069">que</DiscourseConnective> cette loi a été introduite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8100">sans que</DiscourseConnective> le Premier ministre ne soit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8137">même</DiscourseConnective> consulté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7427" docOffset="47">
      <en>The coalition compromise between the President and the Prime Minister is in jeopardy <Alignment alignment="19855" annotation_id="7512">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7512" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the President is given the capability of bypassing the Prime Minister, restricting the role of the government and protecting his own role against the critical press.</en>
      <fr>Le compromis de coalition entre le président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8197">et</DiscourseConnective> le Premier ministre est menacé <Alignment alignment="7512" annotation_id="8231">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8231" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le président a la capacité de court-circuiter le Premier ministre en limitant le rôle du gouvernement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8336">et</DiscourseConnective> en protégeant son propre rôle face à la presse critique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7681" id="224" name="Charles Tannock">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7681" docOffset="48">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - Mr President, until last year's violence, Kenya had a reputation as one of Africa's politically more stable countries and had a tradition of a relatively free and robust press.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8451">avant</DiscourseConnective> les violences de l'an dernier, le Kenya avait la réputation d'être l'un des pays africains les plus stables sur le plan politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8587">et</DiscourseConnective> pouvait se targuer de disposer d'une presse relativement libre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8653">et</DiscourseConnective> vigoureuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7891" docOffset="49">
      <en>President Kibaki needs to realise that political stability and a free press are mutually reinforcing.</en>
      <fr>Le président Kibaki doit comprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8704">que</DiscourseConnective> stabilité politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8728">et</DiscourseConnective> liberté de la presse sont deux éléments complémentaires qui se renforcent mutuellement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7993" docOffset="50">
      <en>This restriction of freedom of speech, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8032" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> proposed, is unbecoming for a country led by a man who came to power promising a new era of openness and transparency.</en>
      <fr>Cette proposition d'imposer des restrictions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8864">à</DiscourseConnective> la liberté d'expression ne sied pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8902">à</DiscourseConnective> ce pays dirigé par un homme qui, lors de son arrivée au pouvoir, avait promis une nouvelle période d'ouverture <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9015">et</DiscourseConnective> de transparence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8154" docOffset="51">
      <en>Unfortunately, it seems that many senior politicians in Kenya have still not developed a sufficiently thick skin to handle the inevitable barbs of a free press and a democracy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9035">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, il semble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9062">que</DiscourseConnective> de nombreux hommes politiques kényans de premier plan n'aient pas la peau suffisamment dure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9158">pour</DiscourseConnective> s'accommoder des égratignures que laissent immanquablement les barbelés de la presse libre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9254">et</DiscourseConnective> de la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8331" docOffset="52">
      <en>I hope that President Kibaki will take our advice and change his mind.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9284">que</DiscourseConnective> le président Kibaki tiendra compte de notre conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9340">et</DiscourseConnective> reverra sa position.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8402" docOffset="53">
      <en>That would reassure us of Kenya's purported commitment to a free society under a power-sharing coalition government.</en>
      <fr>Un tel changement de cap nous rassurerait quant à l'engagement du Kenya envers une société libre placée sous la tutelle d'un gouvernement de coalition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9515">et</DiscourseConnective> de partage du pouvoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8519" docOffset="54">
      <en>It would <Alignment alignment="9559" annotation_id="8528">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8528" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> strengthen Kenya's case for moral authority and leadership in an unstable region.</en>
      <fr>Cela renforcerait <Alignment alignment="8528" annotation_id="9559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9559" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'autorité morale du Kenya <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9596">et</DiscourseConnective> sa position dominante dans une région marquée par l'instabilité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8615" docOffset="55">
      <en>I welcome the President's pledge now to consider amendments to this bill and to consult more widely with the media.</en>
      <fr>Je salue l'engagement pris par le président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9708">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre en considération certains amendements au projet de loi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9773">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9776">à</DiscourseConnective> consulter plus largement les acteurs directement concernés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8731" docOffset="56">
      <en>Given that Prime Minister Raila Odinga and the ODM, his party, are vigorously opposed to this legislation, it is <Alignment alignment="4581" annotation_id="8844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8844" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vital for the stability of the Government that it does not become even more of an inflammatory and divisive political issue.</en>
      <fr>Compte tenu de l'opposition vigoureuse du Premier ministre Raila Odinga <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9910">et</DiscourseConnective> de son parti, l'ODM, au projet de loi, il importe <Alignment alignment="15295" annotation_id="9963">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9963" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9973">pour</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité du gouvernement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10007">que</DiscourseConnective> cette question n'envenime pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10041">et</DiscourseConnective> ne divise pas plus la classe politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8974" id="225" name="Catherine Stihler">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8974" docOffset="57">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - Mr President, I am glad to have the opportunity to speak on this joint motion for a resolution on press freedom in Kenya.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je suis ravie de pouvoir m'exprimer à propos de cette motion de résolution conjointe sur la liberté de la presse au Kenya.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9126" docOffset="58">
      <en>A year ago, like many others, I was dismayed and disappointed that, after flawed presidential elections in Kenya, street demonstrations led to riots and ethnic clashes that spread across the country, killing more than a thousand people and leaving another 350 000 people homeless.</en>
      <fr>Il y a un an, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10273">comme</DiscourseConnective> d'autres, j'ai été consternée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10309">et</DiscourseConnective> déçue en apprenant, au lendemain des élections truquées, les émeutes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10381">et</DiscourseConnective> les affrontements ethniques qui ont secoué le pays, faisant plus d'un millier de victimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10474">et</DiscourseConnective> laissant dans leur sillage pas moins de 350 000 sans-abri.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9407" docOffset="59">
      <en>Those responsible for the post-election violence a year ago must be brought to justice <Alignment alignment="7595" annotation_id="9494">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9494" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a period of reconciliation and tolerance is now essential for Kenya.</en>
      <fr>Les responsables de ces violences postélectorales doivent être traduits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10608">en</DiscourseConnective> justice <Alignment alignment="9494" annotation_id="10619">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10619" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Kenya doit à présent passer par une période de tolérance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10682">et</DiscourseConnective> de réconciliation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9567" docOffset="60">
      <en>In this context, it is very bad news that, on Friday 2 January 2009, President Kibaki signed the Kenya Communications (Amendment) Bill 2008, which amends the Kenya Communications Act of 1998.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte, on ne peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10733">que</DiscourseConnective> déplorer la signature, le vendredi 2 janvier 2009, du projet d'amendement à la loi sur les communications de 1998.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9759" docOffset="61">
      <en>This bill flies in the face of press freedom and disregards international conventions signed up to by the Kenyan Government.</en>
      <fr>Ce projet de loi constitue une gifle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10889">pour</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10918">et</DiscourseConnective> un déni des conventions internationales ratifiées par le gouvernement kényan.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9884" docOffset="62">
      <en>Two sections effectively introduce direct media censorship by the Government.</en>
      <fr>Deux articles introduisent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11026">en effet</DiscourseConnective> une censure gouvernementale des médias.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9962" docOffset="63">
      <en>Section 88 gives the Information Minister considerable powers to raid and dismantle broadcasting equipment from a media house that is deemed to be a threat to national security.</en>
      <fr>L'article 88 donne au ministère kényan de l'information le pouvoir de procéder <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11154">à</DiscourseConnective> des perquisitions dans les locaux des médias censés menacer la sécurité nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11238">et</DiscourseConnective> de détruire le matériel de diffusion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10140" docOffset="64">
      <en>Section 46 gives the state the power to regulate contents to be aired and published by both electronic and print media.</en>
      <fr>L'article 46 donne aux autorités le pouvoir de réglementer le contenu des émissions diffusées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11373">et</DiscourseConnective> des textes publiés par écrit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11405">ou</DiscourseConnective> sur l'internet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10260" docOffset="65">
      <en>Within Kenya, the bill has been opposed by journalists, by Prime Minister Odinga and by the ODM, and its passing highlights a serious lack of consultation within the current grand coalition.</en>
      <fr>De nombreuses voix se sont élevées pour dénoncer ce projet de loi, dont des journalistes, le Premier ministre Odinga <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11541">et</DiscourseConnective> l'ODM. Son adoption reflète donc un manque flagrant de consultation au sein même de la coalition au pouvoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10451" docOffset="66">
      <en>I regret the passing of this bill and urge that any revision of the media law takes account of the many, many reservations expressed.</en>
      <fr>Je ne peux que déplorer l'adoption de ce texte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11700">et</DiscourseConnective> j'insiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11713">pour que</DiscourseConnective> toute révision de la législation prenne en considération les très nombreuses réserves exprimées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10585" id="226" language="PL" name="Ewa Tomaszewska">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10585" docOffset="67">
      <en>Mr President, as a member of Solidarność, and someone who has experienced martial law in Poland, I know that freedom of speech is the lifeblood of democracy.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11842">comme</DiscourseConnective> membre de Solidarnośc <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11870">et</DiscourseConnective> pour avoir connu la loi martiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11906">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne, je sais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11926">que</DiscourseConnective> la liberté d'expression est la sève de la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10743" docOffset="68">
      <en>The Kenyan Government signed and ratified the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and other international conventions, including the African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement kenyan a signé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12015">et</DiscourseConnective> ratifié la Déclaration universelle des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12075">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres conventions internationales, dont la Charte africaine des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12163">et</DiscourseConnective> des peuples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10924" docOffset="69">
      <en>These conventions include the right to freedom of speech.</en>
      <fr>Ces conventions incluent le droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12213">à</DiscourseConnective> la liberté d'expression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10982" docOffset="70">
      <en>Today, the Eastern Africa Journalists Association informs us that the government intends to introduce censorship in Kenya.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, l'association des journalistes d'Afrique de l'Est nous informe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12316">que</DiscourseConnective> le gouvernement a l'intention d'introduire la censure au Kenya.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11105" docOffset="71">
      <en>I hope that President Kibaki will refrain from any amendments to legislation concerning the media, which could infringe the freedom of speech.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12393">que</DiscourseConnective> le président Kibaki s'abstiendra d'amender la législation concernant les médias d'une manière qui pourrait empiéter sur la liberté d'expression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11248" docOffset="72">
      <en>I call on the Kenyan authorities to relinquish their plans to introduce censorship, to build consensus in order to foster the freedom of the press and the public communications sector.</en>
      <fr>J'appelle les autorités kenyanes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12575">à</DiscourseConnective> renoncer à leurs projets visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12609">à</DiscourseConnective> introduire la censure et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12636">à</DiscourseConnective> rechercher plutôt un consensus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12669">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>encourager la liberté de la presse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12711">et</DiscourseConnective> du secteur public des communications.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11433" docOffset="73">
      <en>I hope that the rights of religious and ethnic minorities will be respected in Kenya.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12761">que</DiscourseConnective> les droits des minorités religieuses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12802">et</DiscourseConnective> ethniques seront respectés au Kenya.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11519" docOffset="74">
      <en>A year ago, over a thousand people died during protests linked to the elections <Alignment alignment="12948" annotation_id="11599">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11599" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> 350 000 people fled their homes.</en>
      <fr>Il y a un an, plus d'un millier de personnes ont perdu la vie dans des manifestations liées aux élections <Alignment alignment="8132" annotation_id="12948">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12948" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> 350 000 ont fui leur domicile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11636" docOffset="75">
      <en>I hope that those responsible for these incidents will be justly punished.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12991">que</DiscourseConnective> les responsables de ces incidents seront punis comme il se doit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11711" id="227" name="Tadeusz Zwiefka">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11711" docOffset="76">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, even <Alignment alignment="30834" annotation_id="11735">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11735" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is true that some of the private media in Kenya helped to instigate riots following the emotional election campaign, this is no justification for restricting the freedom of speech.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="11735" annotation_id="13088">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13088" sense="Contingency.Condition">même s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13107">que</DiscourseConnective> certains médias privés ont contribué aux émeutes du Kenya, à la suite d'une campagne électorale émotionnelle, cela ne peut justifier la restriction à la liberté d'expression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11922" docOffset="77">
      <en>The attack on the freedom of the press in Kenya <Alignment alignment="13343" annotation_id="11970">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11970" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> involved the violation of the fundamental principles of parliamentary democracy.</en>
      <fr>L'atteinte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13297">à</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse au Kenya a impliqué <Alignment alignment="1830" annotation_id="13343">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13343" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la violation des principes fondamentaux de la démocratie parlementaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12056" docOffset="78">
      <en>It is worth stressing that the new legislation was adopted by 25 out of the 220 members of parliament.</en>
      <fr>Il convient de souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13446">que</DiscourseConnective> la nouvelle législation a été adoptée par 25 parlementaires sur 220.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12159" docOffset="79">
      <en>This is an utterly inconceivable situation.</en>
      <fr>Cette situation est complètement inconcevable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12203" docOffset="80">
      <en>What is worse is that, until that point, Kenya had boasted one of the most developed and pluralistic press networks in the whole of Africa.</en>
      <fr>Pire encore, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13579">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> présent le Kenya pouvait se vanter de posséder un des réseaux de presse les plus développés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13679">et</DiscourseConnective> pluralistes de toute l'Afrique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12343" docOffset="81">
      <en>This will change <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12360" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective> the new legislation is implemented, which will allow special services to interfere in the activities of the media, close down editorial sections and control the printed or spoken word.</en>
      <fr>Cela ne sera plus le cas une fois que la nouvelle loi sera mise en œuvre, qui permettra aux services spéciaux d'interférer dans les activités des médias, de fermer les sections éditoriales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13903">et</DiscourseConnective> de contrôler ce qui est diffusé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13938">ou</DiscourseConnective> écrit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12551" docOffset="82">
      <en>Restricting the freedom of the media sector in the name of national security can only have the opposite effect to the one intended.</en>
      <fr>Restreindre la liberté du secteur des médias au nom de la sécurité nationale ne peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14033">qu'</DiscourseConnective>entraîner un effet inverse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14063">à</DiscourseConnective> l'effet escompté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12683" id="228" name="Laima Liucija Andrikien">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12683" docOffset="83">
      <en>(LT) Why are we concerned with freedom of the press in Kenya?</en>
      <fr>(LT) Pourquoi nous intéressons-nous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14119">à</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse au Kenya?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12745" docOffset="84">
      <en>Why is the European Parliament debating this issue as a case of human rights violation as a matter of urgency?</en>
      <fr>Pourquoi le Parlement européen débat-il dans l'urgence de cette question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14228">comme</DiscourseConnective> d'un cas de violation des droits de l'homme?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12856" docOffset="85">
      <en>Firstly <Alignment alignment="14292" annotation_id="12864">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12864" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> freedom of speech is a fundamental human right, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12920" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> laid down in Article 19 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, to which Kenya is a signatory.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14279">Tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="2947" annotation_id="14292">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14292" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la liberté d'expression est un droit de l'homme fondamental, prévu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14369">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 19 de la Déclaration universelle des droits de l'homme, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14437">que</DiscourseConnective> le Kenya a signée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13024" docOffset="86">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14460" annotation_id="13024">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13024" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it, like other signatory countries, must not only observe its spirit, but follow it to the letter.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13024" annotation_id="14460">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14460" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14476">comme</DiscourseConnective> d'autres pays signataires, il doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14517">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> en respecter l'esprit, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14554">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> la suivre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14575">à</DiscourseConnective> la lettre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13134" docOffset="87">
      <en>The demonstrations which took place almost a year ago after the Presidential elections in Kenya and grew into riots and ethnic conflict, in which more than 1 000 people were killed <Alignment alignment="14774" annotation_id="13315">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13315" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tens of thousands were left homeless, is the strongest argument for not allowing similar events to be repeated.</en>
      <fr>Les manifestations qui ont eu lieu il y a environ un an <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14644">après</DiscourseConnective> l'élection présidentielle au Kenya <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14685">et</DiscourseConnective> qui ont dégénéré en émeutes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14716">et</DiscourseConnective> en conflit ethnique, qui ont causé plus de 1 000 morts <Alignment alignment="17191" annotation_id="14774">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14774" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des dizaines de milliers de sans-abri, sont la meilleure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14834">preuve qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne faut pas permettre que de tels événements se répètent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13431" docOffset="88">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14905" annotation_id="13431">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13431" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Kenyan Government and President should act together and honour their own obligations to respect freedom of the press, speech and assembly.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13431" annotation_id="14905">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14905" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le gouvernement kenyan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14943">et</DiscourseConnective> le président devraient agir ensemble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14983">et</DiscourseConnective> honorer leurs obligations en matière de respect de la liberté de la presse, de la liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15089">et</DiscourseConnective> de liberté de réunion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13585" docOffset="89">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19542" annotation_id="13585">
          <Alignment alignment="79" annotation_id="13585">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13585" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> - and this is particularly important - they should fight impunity and call to account those who are responsible for the riots which took place a year ago.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2318" annotation_id="15115">
          <Alignment alignment="13585" annotation_id="15115">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15115" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15125">et</DiscourseConnective> c'est particulièrement important -, ils devraient lutter contre l'impunité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15203">et</DiscourseConnective> demander des comptes aux responsables des émeutes d'il y a un an.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13752" id="229" name="Marios Matsakis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13752" docOffset="90">
      <en>Mr President, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13766" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective> we are debating humanitarian issues and freedom of the press in third countries, I take the opportunity to inform the House that, according to media reports from Gaza, the offices of the UN which were bombarded earlier on today by the Israeli forces are completely ablaze and all the UN humanitarian aid which was stored there, much of it sent by the EU, has been completely destroyed.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, Je profite de ce débat consacré à l'aide humanitaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15353">et</DiscourseConnective> à la liberté de la presse dans les pays tiers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15402">pour</DiscourseConnective> signaler à l'Assemblée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15430">que</DiscourseConnective>, selon les informations fournies par les médias présents à Gaza, les bureaux des Nations unies ont été bombardés par les forces armées israéliennes plus tôt dans la journée. Les bâtiments ont été soufflés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15639">et</DiscourseConnective> l'aide humanitaire qui y était entreposée, dont une grande partie fournie par l'Union, a été totalement détruite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14158" docOffset="91">
      <en>The same fate has befallen the offices of Reuters and of other international journalists in Gaza.</en>
      <fr>L'armée israélienne a réservé le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15789">même</DiscourseConnective> sort aux bureaux de l'agence Reuters <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15831">et</DiscourseConnective> des autres journalistes internationaux présents sur place.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14256" docOffset="92">
      <en>I wish to record that I share the view of the UN Secretary-General, Mr Ban Ki-moon, currently in Israel, who is reportedly completely outraged at the Israeli authorities.</en>
      <fr>Je partage pleinement le point de vue du Secrétaire général des Nations unies, M. Ban Ki-moon, actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16001">en</DiscourseConnective> Israël, qui s'est dit totalement scandalisé par l'attitude des autorités israéliennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14427" id="230" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14427" docOffset="93">
      <en>Mr Matsakis, thank you for this declaration, <Alignment alignment="23775" annotation_id="14472">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14472" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am not supposed, in theory, to accept it <Alignment alignment="4439" annotation_id="14519">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14519" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the rules require that <Alignment alignment="27561" annotation_id="14550">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14550" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you ask to speak by catching my eye, it must be on the subject under discussion, which is, I would remind you, the freedom of the press in Kenya, even <Alignment alignment="32479" annotation_id="14706">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14706" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the events to which you have referred are indeed dramatic, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14772" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> everybody agrees.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur Matsakis, merci <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16116">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette déclaration <Alignment alignment="14472" annotation_id="16139">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16139" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je n'aurais pas dû, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16164">en</DiscourseConnective> principe, l'accepter <Alignment alignment="14519" annotation_id="16188">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16188" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le règlement veut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16214">que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="14550" annotation_id="16219">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16219" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous demandez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16239">à</DiscourseConnective> intervenir dans le catch the eye, ce doit être sur le sujet qui est, je vous le rappelle, la liberté de la presse au Kenya, <Alignment alignment="14706" annotation_id="16365">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16365" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les événements auxquels vous avez fait référence sont absolument dramatiques, tout le monde en convient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14793" id="231" name="Leopold Józef Rutowicz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14793" docOffset="94">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, the European Parliament's Resolution on press freedom in Kenya highlights an important issue.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, la résolution du Parlement européen concernant la liberté de la presse au Kenya met en exergue une question importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14906" docOffset="95">
      <en>Dictatorships begin with restrictions on the freedom of the press and information, as well as civil rights.</en>
      <fr>Les dictatures commencent par restreindre la liberté de la presse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16692">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'information, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16713">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les droits civils.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15014" docOffset="96">
      <en>I hope that this process will be halted by international and internal action.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16751">que</DiscourseConnective> ce processus sera arrêté par l'action internationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16808">et</DiscourseConnective> interne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15092" docOffset="97">
      <en>I think that President Kibaki and Prime Minister Odinga will take appropriate action.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16829">que</DiscourseConnective> le président Kibaki <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16853">et</DiscourseConnective> le Premier ministre Odinga agiront de manière appropriée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15178" docOffset="98">
      <en>The Resolution, which I support, will certainly help the process of democratisation in Kenya.</en>
      <fr>La résolution, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16929">que</DiscourseConnective> je soutiens, aidera certainement le processus de démocratisation au Kenya.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15272" id="232" name="Janusz Onyszkiewicz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15272" docOffset="99">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, during the Communist period, both in Poland and in other countries, one of the provisions of the criminal code stipulated that any person disseminating information that could lead to civil disorder would be punished.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, durant la période communiste, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17066">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17077">et</DiscourseConnective> dans d'autres pays, une des dispositions du code pénal prévoyait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17145">que</DiscourseConnective> toute personne diffusant des informations susceptibles de conduire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17216">à</DiscourseConnective> des désordres civils serait punie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15508" docOffset="100">
      <en>This kind of provision was exceptionally useful as a stick for beating not only individuals but also, and above all, the press.</en>
      <fr>Ce genre de disposition s'avérait exceptionnellement utile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17312">comme</DiscourseConnective> bâton <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17324">pour</DiscourseConnective> battre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17336">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> les particuliers, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17368">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17379">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17382">surtout</DiscourseConnective> la presse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15636" docOffset="101">
      <en>Today, we see similar intentions behind the legislative endeavours in Kenya.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, nous voyons des intentions comparables derrière les efforts législatifs au Kenya.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15713" docOffset="102">
      <en>One cannot state, as an argument or a threat, that the press must be muzzled <Alignment alignment="12460" annotation_id="15790">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15790" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it might cause trouble in the country.</en>
      <fr>On ne peut pas déclarer, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17521">comme</DiscourseConnective> un argument <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17539">ou</DiscourseConnective> une menace, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17554">que</DiscourseConnective> la presse doit être muselée <Alignment alignment="7103" annotation_id="17586">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17586" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elle pourrait provoquer des troubles dans le pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15832" docOffset="103">
      <en>That is no justification or explanation for this kind of censorship.</en>
      <fr>On ne peut pas justifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17671">ou</DiscourseConnective> expliquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17684">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> ce genre de censure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15901" docOffset="104">
      <en>The press is there to provide people with information, which is a real cornerstone of democracy.</en>
      <fr>La presse est là <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17728">pour</DiscourseConnective> informer la population, ce qui est une véritable pierre angulaire de la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15998" id="233" language="CS" name="Vladimír Špidla">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15998" docOffset="105">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to begin by emphasising that freedom of expression, including television and radio, is one of the pillars on which the EU rests.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17849">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17885">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17898">que</DiscourseConnective> la liberté d'expression, qui comprend la télévision <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17954">et</DiscourseConnective> la radio, constitue un des piliers sur lesquels repose l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16176" docOffset="106">
      <en>This freedom is among the key European values <Alignment alignment="18096" annotation_id="16222">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16222" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it cannot be called into question.</en>
      <fr>Cette liberté figure parmi les valeurs essentielles de l'Europe <Alignment alignment="16222" annotation_id="18096">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18096" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ne peut être remise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18119">en</DiscourseConnective> question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16261" docOffset="107">
      <en>The 'Communication Act' of 2008 which became law in Kenya on 2 January 2009, includes some points which, in our opinion, might encroach upon media freedom.</en>
      <fr>La loi sur la communication de 2008, qui a été transposée le 2 janvier 2009 au Kenya, contient des points qui pourraient, selon nous, empiéter sur la liberté des médias.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16417" docOffset="108">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="30502" annotation_id="16420">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16420" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> noticed with satisfaction the recent decision of President Kibaki on 7 January to revise some disputed sections of this Act.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="20173" annotation_id="18313">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18313" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> noté avec satisfaction la décision récente du président Kibaki, le 7 janvier, de revoir certaines parties litigieuses de cette loi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16555" docOffset="109">
      <en>We are delighted that Mr Kibaki authorised the Minister for Information and Communications and the Attorney General to meet with media representatives in order to propose changes to this law that would eliminate these fears.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes heureux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18470">que</DiscourseConnective> M. Kibaki ait autorisé le ministre de l'information <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18526">et</DiscourseConnective> des communications, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18549">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que le ministre de la justice, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18586">à</DiscourseConnective> rencontrer les représentants des médias <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18628">afin de</DiscourseConnective> proposer des changements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18661">à</DiscourseConnective> cette loi qui apaiseraient leurs craintes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16780" docOffset="110">
      <en>Freedom of expression and freedom of the press form part of public affairs administration in the broadest sense of the term and this, in itself, is at the centre of EU development strategy.</en>
      <fr>La liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18730">et</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse font partie de l'administration des affaires publiques au sens large <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18826">et</DiscourseConnective> se trouvent au cœur de la stratégie de développement de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16970" docOffset="111">
      <en>I frankly take the view that a free and responsible press is an essential precondition for democracy and the legal state, which are integral components for sustainable development.</en>
      <fr>Je pense franchement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18926">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une presse libre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18946">et</DiscourseConnective> responsable constitue une condition préalable essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19007">pour</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19026">et</DiscourseConnective> l'État de droit, composantes intégrales du développement durable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17151" docOffset="112">
      <en>Only on the basis of dialogue will the media and the Kenyan Government be able to develop a common understanding and build mutual respect.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est que sur la base du dialogue que les médias <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19147">et</DiscourseConnective> le gouvernement du Kenya pourront développer une compréhension commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19221">et</DiscourseConnective> bâtir le respect mutuel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17290" docOffset="113">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19281" annotation_id="17290">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17290" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the European Commission looks forward with interest to the results of the various meetings which will take place in Kenya between the parties involved <Alignment alignment="23170" annotation_id="17447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17447" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it hopes that relevant parties will reach agreement on appropriate recommendations for proposals to amend the media law.</en>
      <fr>La Commission européenne attend <Alignment alignment="13247" annotation_id="19281">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19281" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avec intérêt les résultats des différentes réunions qui auront lieu au Kenya entre les parties impliquées <Alignment alignment="9601" annotation_id="19392">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19392" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19407">que</DiscourseConnective> les parties en question parviendront à un accord sur les recommandations de propositions appropriées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19512">pour</DiscourseConnective> amender la loi sur les médias.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17572" docOffset="114">
      <en>As far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17579" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> the post-election violence is concerned, the Commission welcomes the report of the investigative commission on the violence (the Waki Report).</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19548">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les violences post-électorales, la Commission salue le rapport de la commission d'enquête sur les violences (le rapport Waki).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17725" docOffset="115">
      <en>It appreciates the undertaking of the Kenyan Government to implement the report recommendations, including the establishment of a special tribunal to ensure that the people responsible for the violence will have to answer for their acts.</en>
      <fr>Elle apprécie l'engagement du gouvernement kenyan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19744">à</DiscourseConnective> mettre en œuvre les recommandations du rapport, y compris en ce qui concerne la création d'un tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19857">pour</DiscourseConnective> veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19875">que</DiscourseConnective> les responsables de la violence répondent de leurs actes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17963" id="234" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17963" docOffset="116">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17985" docOffset="117">
      <en>The vote will take place immediately.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu immédiatement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18023" docOffset="118">
      <en>Written statements (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclarations écrites (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18053" id="235" language="RO" name="Sebastian Valentin Bodu ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18053" docOffset="119">
      <en>At the start of 2009, democracy in Kenya suffered in the form of a blow against the freedom of the press.</en>
      <fr>Au début de 2009, la démocratie au Kenya a souffert <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20076">d'un coup</DiscourseConnective> porté contre la liberté de la presse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18159" docOffset="120">
      <en>President Mwai Kibaki has signed a law, <Alignment alignment="20166" annotation_id="18199">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18199" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he has subsequently had a change of heart, which grants the Kenyan authorities the right to carry out raids on editorial offices, tap journalists' telephone calls and check the content of broadcasts on the grounds of 'national security'.</en>
      <fr>Le président Mwai Kibaki a signé une loi, <Alignment alignment="18199" annotation_id="20166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20166" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il s'est ravisé ensuite, qui permet aux autorités kenyanes de perquisitionner les rédactions de presse, de mettre les journalistes sous écoute <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20316">et</DiscourseConnective> de vérifier le contenu des émissions sous prétexte de "sécurité nationale".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18446" docOffset="121">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="29751" annotation_id="18446">
          <Alignment alignment="46082" annotation_id="18446">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18446" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">As if</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> these abuses were not enough, the law <Alignment alignment="20335" annotation_id="18490">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18490" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> stipulates huge fines and terms of imprisonment for reporters found guilty of 'anti-government' practices.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18446" annotation_id="20395">
          <Alignment alignment="18446" annotation_id="20395">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20395" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Comme si</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> ces abus ne suffisaient pas, la loi prévoit <Alignment alignment="18490" annotation_id="20448">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20448" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des amendes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20470">et</DiscourseConnective> des peines d'emprisonnement très lourdes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20514">pour</DiscourseConnective> les reporters jugés coupables de pratiques "antigouvernementales".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18602" docOffset="122">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20586" annotation_id="18602">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18602" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> President Kibaki has ordered these provisions to be amended a week later, we are not aware as to what these 'amendments' envisage.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18602" annotation_id="20586">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20586" sense="Comparison.Concession">Bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le président Kibaki ait ordonné de modifier ces dispositions une semaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20668">plus tard</DiscourseConnective>, nous ne savons pas encore ce que ces "amendements" prévoient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18742" docOffset="123">
      <en>This law, in its initial form, is a reminder of the dark days of dictatorship, <Alignment alignment="20821" annotation_id="18821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18821" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Kenyan press was brought to its knees.</en>
      <fr>Dans sa version initiale, cette loi rappelle les jours sombres de la dictature, <Alignment alignment="18821" annotation_id="20821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20821" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la presse kenyane était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20851">à</DiscourseConnective> genoux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18869" docOffset="124">
      <en>Kenya is currently a democracy <Alignment alignment="42848" annotation_id="18900">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18900" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I firmly believe that no one, President Kibaki included, wants to return to those times.</en>
      <fr>Le Kenya est actuellement une démocratie <Alignment alignment="18900" annotation_id="20902">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20902" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je crois fermement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20924">que</DiscourseConnective> personne, même le président Kibaki, ne veut revenir en arrière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18993" docOffset="125">
      <en>An attack against press freedom is an attack against democracy.</en>
      <fr>Une atteinte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21005">à</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse est une atteinte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21048">à</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19057" docOffset="126">
      <en>The international community must continue to put pressure on the Kenyan authorities to treat civil liberties responsibly, especially press freedom.</en>
      <fr>La communauté internationale doit continuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21109">à</DiscourseConnective> faire pression sur les autorités kenyanes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21153">afin qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles traitent les libertés civiles de manière responsable, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21221">surtout</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19205" id="236" language="ET" name="Marianne Mikko ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19205" docOffset="127">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, Kenya is acting in contravention of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and the African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21263">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, le Kenya enfreint la Déclaration universelle des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21344">et</DiscourseConnective> la Charte africaine des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21389">et</DiscourseConnective> des peuples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19359" docOffset="128">
      <en>Such fundamental pillars of democracy as freedom of speech and freedom of the press are not respected.</en>
      <fr>Des piliers fondamentaux de la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21447">comme</DiscourseConnective> la liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21477">et</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse ne sont pas respectés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19462" docOffset="129">
      <en>The free press is in serious danger.</en>
      <fr>La presse libre court un grave danger.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19499" docOffset="130">
      <en>State control and censorship were sections of a draft amendment to a communications bill.</en>
      <fr>Le contrôle de l'État <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21588">et</DiscourseConnective> la censure faisaient partie d'un projet d'amendement de la loi sur la communication.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19589" docOffset="131">
      <en>Through the ill-considered action of President Kibaki, these have now become law.</en>
      <fr>Par l'action irréfléchie du président Kibaki, ils ont été <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21734">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> coulés dans la loi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19671" docOffset="132">
      <en>It is unheard of that the government should possess the right to organise raids on the editorial offices of newspapers and broadcasters and check what is broadcast <Alignment alignment="29547" annotation_id="19835">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19835" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in what form.</en>
      <fr>On n'a jamais vu un gouvernement disposer du pouvoir de perquisitionner les rédactions de presse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21862">et</DiscourseConnective> des radiodiffuseurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21885">et</DiscourseConnective> de vérifier ce qui est diffusé <Alignment alignment="13872" annotation_id="21919">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21919" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sous quelle forme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19853" docOffset="133">
      <en>That is far from a democratic society.</en>
      <fr>C'est très loin d'une société démocratique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19892" docOffset="134">
      <en>It is essential that the existing legal provisions should be amended.</en>
      <fr>Il est essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22002">que</DiscourseConnective> les dispositions juridiques existantes soient modifiées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19962" docOffset="135">
      <en>It is possible to regulate the press without endangering freedom of speech and the freedom of the press.</en>
      <fr>Il est possible de réglementer la presse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22104">sans</DiscourseConnective> mettre en danger la liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22150">et</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de la presse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20067" docOffset="136">
      <en>This must be done as soon as possible.</en>
      <fr>Cela doit être fait le plus vite possible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
