<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Welcome</en>
    <fr>Souhaits de bienvenue</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="052" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>I would now like to welcome a delegation from the Swiss Federal Assembly to the official gallery.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais à présent souhaiter la bienvenue à une délégation de l'Assemblée fédérale suisse, qui se trouve dans la tribune officielle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="106" docOffset="2">
      <en>The Swiss delegation is headed by Mrs Brigitta Gadient.</en>
      <fr>La délégation suisse est emmenée par Mme Brigitta Gadient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="162" docOffset="3">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="173" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is a pleasure for me to welcome you all to the European Parliament in Strasbourg where you have been taking part in the 27th EU-Switzerland interparliamentary meeting yesterday and today.</en>
      <fr>Je suis ravie de vous accueillir tous au Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="296">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg, où vous avez participé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="333">à</DiscourseConnective> la 27e réunion interparlementaire entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="394">et</DiscourseConnective> la Suisse hier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="412">et</DiscourseConnective> aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="364" docOffset="5">
      <en>I know there have been some interesting discussions on developments and the current state of play, and future challenges for the relations between Switzerland and the EU, with special emphasis on the EU-Swiss dialogue on tax issues, free movement of persons and the experiences from the latest EU enlargements, cross-border service provision and the Schengen-Dublin agreements, Swiss financial contributions to the EU enlargement, and free trade in agricultural products.</en>
      <fr>Je sais que plusieurs faits nouveaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="465">et</DiscourseConnective> l'évolution de la situation ont fait l'objet de discussions intéressantes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="543">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les défis concernant les relations entre la Suisse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="604">et</DiscourseConnective> l'UE, avec un accent particulier sur le dialogue UE-Suisse concernant la fiscalité, la libre circulation des personnes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="726">et</DiscourseConnective> l'expérience tirée des derniers élargissements de l'Union, la prestation de services transfrontaliers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="831">et</DiscourseConnective> les accords Schengen-Dublin, la participation financière de la Suisse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="904">à</DiscourseConnective> l'élargissement de l'UE, de même que le libre-échange des produits agricoles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="836" docOffset="6">
      <en>There is a long relationship between our parliaments - almost three decades - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="914" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it has led to the development of a profound knowledge both on the EU side and the Swiss side.</en>
      <fr>Les relations entre nos parlements remontant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1029">à</DiscourseConnective> de nombreuses années - près de trente ans -, tant l'Union <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1089">que</DiscourseConnective> la Suisse ont acquis des connaissances approfondies l'une <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1151">de l'autre</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1012" docOffset="7">
      <en>I am sure that the exchange of views that has taken place this week will enhance our parliamentary cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Je suis persuadée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1181">que</DiscourseConnective> l'échange de vues qui a eu lieu cette semaine renforcera la coopération entre nos parlements respectifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1124" docOffset="8">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
