<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Non-discrimination based on gender and inter-generational solidarity (short presentation)</en>
    <fr>La non-discrimination basée sur le sexe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40">et</DiscourseConnective> la solidarité entre les générations (brève présentation)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="90" id="198" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="90" docOffset="1">
      <en>- The next item is a short presentation of the report by Mrs Záborská, on behalf of the Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality, on non-discrimination based on gender and inter-generational solidarity.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle une brève présentation du rapport d'Anna Záborská, au nom de la commission des droits de la femme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="222">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'égalité des genres, sur la non-discrimination basée sur le sexe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="294">et</DiscourseConnective> la solidarité entre les générations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="300" id="199" language="SK" name="Anna Záborská">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="300" docOffset="2">
      <en>May I first of all sincerely thank all fellow Members for their help with my own-initiative report.</en>
      <fr>rapporteure. - (EN ) Permettez-moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="369">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> d'adresser mes plus sincères remerciements à tout les députés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="444">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'aide qu'ils m'ont apportée pendant la rédaction du rapport d'initiative.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="400" docOffset="3">
      <en>The voting in the Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality was the result of much wide-ranging discussion and accommodation.</en>
      <fr>Le vote <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="532">en</DiscourseConnective> commission des droits de la femme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="569">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'égalité des genres fait suite à de nombreuses discussions des plus variées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="652">et</DiscourseConnective> à bien des adaptations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="532" docOffset="4">
      <en>The men and women who are today involved in establishing inter-generational solidarity networks deserve recognition.</en>
      <fr>Les hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="690">et</DiscourseConnective> les femmes qui, aujourd'hui, participent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="734">à</DiscourseConnective> la création de réseaux de solidarité entre les générations méritent notre reconnaissance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="649" docOffset="5">
      <en>Their determination is an important contribution to national and European wealth and to the common good.</en>
      <fr>Par leur détermination, ils contribuent largement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="876">à</DiscourseConnective> la richesse nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="900">et</DiscourseConnective> européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="914">et</DiscourseConnective> au bien commun.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="754" docOffset="6">
      <en>Unfortunately, this contribution is not included in national statistics and accounts.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="933">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, leur engagement n'apparaît ni dans les statistiques ni dans les comptabilités nationales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="840" docOffset="7">
      <en>This is the reason why men and women are being exposed to hidden forms of discrimination.</en>
      <fr>C'est là une des sources de discriminations cachées envers les hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1110">et</DiscourseConnective> les femmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="930" docOffset="8">
      <en>Women and men are entitled to a free choice of suitable and comfortable activities.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons tous le droit de choisir librement des activités adaptées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1194">et</DiscourseConnective> plaisantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1014" docOffset="9">
      <en>The obligation on society is to guarantee this freedom of choice and not to discriminate against any activity simply <Alignment alignment="1311" annotation_id="1131">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1131" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it does not fall within the usual scope of the formal labour market.</en>
      <fr>La société doit garantir cette liberté de choix, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1258">sans</DiscourseConnective> discrimination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1278">à</DiscourseConnective> l'encontre de quelque activité <Alignment alignment="1131" annotation_id="1311">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1311" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce soit qui ne correspondrait pas aux paramètres du marché officiel de l'emploi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1208" docOffset="10">
      <en>This is a brief summary of my own-initiative report on non-discrimination based on gender and inter-generational solidarity.</en>
      <fr>Voici une <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1406">bref</DiscourseConnective> survol de mon rapport d'initiative sur la non-discrimination basé sur le genre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1490">et</DiscourseConnective> la solidarité entre les générations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1333" docOffset="11">
      <en>The subject of this report is at the heart of discussions on the future of Europe and employment in its Member States.</en>
      <fr>Le thème du rapport est au coeur des discussions sur l'avenir de l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1604">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'emploi dans les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1452" docOffset="12">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11799" annotation_id="1452">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1452" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is a rather technical report, it <Alignment alignment="18195" annotation_id="1497">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1497" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> has a human dimension.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10326" annotation_id="1643">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1643" sense="Comparison.Concession">Bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de nature technique, ce document revêt <Alignment alignment="11952" annotation_id="1691">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1691" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une dimension humaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1525" docOffset="13">
      <en>There is something in it for all of us as each of us lives within networks of broader or narrower family and social relationships, in which we are personally involved.</en>
      <fr>Nous pouvons tous y trouver quelque chose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1762">car</DiscourseConnective> nous vivons tous dans des réseaux plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1805">ou</DiscourseConnective> moins vastes de relations familiales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1845">et</DiscourseConnective> sociales dans lesquels nous sommes personnellement impliqués.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1693" docOffset="14">
      <en>Restricting the concept of inter-generational solidarity to just childcare is a mistaken interpretation.</en>
      <fr>Limiter la solidarité entre générations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1950">à</DiscourseConnective> l'éducation des enfants est une erreur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1798" docOffset="15">
      <en>Inter-generational solidarity <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1828" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> involves responsibility with respect to our parents and elders and care for dependents.</en>
      <fr>Cette solidarité implique le respect à l'égard de nos parents, de nos aînés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2068">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les soins aux personnes dépendantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1921" docOffset="16">
      <en>Inter-generational solidarity <Alignment alignment="23643" annotation_id="1951">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1951" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> involves education of citizens with regard to respect for life, human dignity and environmental protection. It is predominantly a question of social justice.</en>
      <fr>La notion de solidarité entre les générations fait <Alignment alignment="1184" annotation_id="2166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2166" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> appel à l'éducation des citoyens au respect de la vie, de la dignité humaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2253">et</DiscourseConnective> à la protection de l'environnement; c'est principalement une question de justice sociale, fondement de l'avenir de l'Europe et du bien de ses citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2114" docOffset="17">
      <en>It is the basis for the future of Europe and the common good of its inhabitants. Human resources managers agree that human capabilities are comparable to university degrees.</en>
      <fr>Les directeurs en ressources humaines reconnaissent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2460">que</DiscourseConnective> les aptitudes humaines sont comparables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2504">à</DiscourseConnective> des diplômes universitaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2288" docOffset="18">
      <en>It is therefore necessary to assess this value in an explicit and positive manner.</en>
      <fr>Il faut, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2544">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2554">en</DiscourseConnective> estimer la valeur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2575">en</DiscourseConnective> des termes explicites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2600">et</DiscourseConnective> positifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2371" docOffset="19">
      <en>The European Union must create a political framework in order to achieve this target.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne doit se fixer un cadre politique pour pouvoir atteindre cet objectif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2457" docOffset="20">
      <en>Women are the first to contribute to inter-generational solidarity, <Alignment alignment="34416" annotation_id="2525">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2525" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> participating in the creation of social relations.</en>
      <fr>Les femmes sont les chevilles ouvrières de la solidarité entre les générations; elles participent <Alignment alignment="14989" annotation_id="2800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2800" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2805">à</DiscourseConnective> l'établissement de liens sociaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2581" docOffset="21">
      <en>This is why this report is devoted mainly to them.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2841">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2862">à</DiscourseConnective> elles principalement que se consacre le rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2632" docOffset="22">
      <en>Economists use mathematical models to highlight the value of housework.</en>
      <fr>Les économistes recourent à des modèles économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2965">pour</DiscourseConnective> exprimer la valeur du travail domestique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2704" docOffset="23">
      <en>Longstanding research by economists and demographers suggests that women's contribution to gross domestic product could be even higher <Alignment alignment="30815" annotation_id="2839">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2839" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> their unpaid work were factored in.</en>
      <fr>D'anciennes recherches menées par les économistes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3062">et</DiscourseConnective> des démographes suggèrent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3091">que</DiscourseConnective> la contribution des femmes au produit national brut pourrait être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3161">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus élevée <Alignment alignment="2839" annotation_id="3180">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3180" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le travail non rémunéré était pris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3218">en</DiscourseConnective> considération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2878" docOffset="24">
      <en>Ignoring this fact means maintaining the ideas of the past.</en>
      <fr>Ignorer cette réalité revient à alimenter des idées du passé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2938" docOffset="25">
      <en>We must look forward in order to create the conditions for all women and men to become involved in inter-generational solidarity regardless of their social standing.</en>
      <fr>Allons de l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3310">avant</DiscourseConnective> et établissons les conditions qui permettront aux hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3373">et</DiscourseConnective> aux femmes, quel que soit leur statut social, de prendre part <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3438">à</DiscourseConnective> la solidarité entre les générations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3104" docOffset="26">
      <en>The European Union must act <Alignment alignment="3477" annotation_id="3132">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3132" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is serious about non-discrimination and equality of opportunity.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3132" annotation_id="3477">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3477" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'UE prend au sérieux la non-discrimination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3524">et</DiscourseConnective> l'égalité des chances, elle doit agir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3203" docOffset="27">
      <en>My political group, the Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats, is proud of its support for a policy of non-discrimination which pursues the general good and respects the distinct characteristics and complementary nature of men and women.</en>
      <fr>Mon groupe politique, le Groupe du parti populaire européen (Démocrates-chrétiens) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3649">et</DiscourseConnective> des Démocrates européens est fier de soutenir une politique de non-discrimination au nom du bien public, du respect des signes distinctifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3791">et</DiscourseConnective> de la complémentarité homme-femme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3485" docOffset="28">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I should <Alignment alignment="3844" annotation_id="3516">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3516" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to point out that this report is the result of extensive consultations with numerous women's non-governmental organisations.</en>
      <fr>Je préciserais <Alignment alignment="3516" annotation_id="3844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3844" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3854">que</DiscourseConnective> le présent rapport est le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3884">résultat</DiscourseConnective> d'une vaste concertation avec de nombreuses organisations non gouvernementales de femmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3651" docOffset="29">
      <en>In my report, I have <Alignment alignment="3988" annotation_id="3672">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3672" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> taken account of the opinions of three of our Parliament's Intergroups: ATD Quart Monde, the Intergroup on Family and Protection of Childhood and the Intergroup on Carers.</en>
      <fr>J'ai <Alignment alignment="3672" annotation_id="3988">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3988" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tenu compte de l'opinion de trois de nos intergroupes parlementaires: ATD Quart Monde, l'intergroupe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4099">pour</DiscourseConnective> la famille <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4115">et</DiscourseConnective> la protection de l'enfance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4145">et</DiscourseConnective> l'intergroupe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4162">pour</DiscourseConnective> les soignants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3849" docOffset="30">
      <en>The Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality has adopted this report unanimously.</en>
      <fr>La Commission des droits de la femme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4219">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'égalité des genres a adopté le rapport à l'unanimité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3938" docOffset="31">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I should like to invite you to allow us to continue with this cooperation and to vote tomorrow for the FEMM Committee's motion for a resolution.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4290">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je vous inviterais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4323">à</DiscourseConnective> nous permettre de poursuivre cette coopération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4372">et</DiscourseConnective> vous prononcer demain en faveur de la proposition de résolution de la Commission FEMM.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4105" id="200" name="Viviane Reding">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4105" docOffset="32">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, I think Ms Záborská's work is very important <Alignment alignment="4571" annotation_id="4192">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4192" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the subject she is tackling is one which is of the utmost importance in our society.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, j'estime que le travail de Mme Záborská est essentiel <Alignment alignment="11882" annotation_id="4571">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4571" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le sujet abordé est de la plus haute importance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4623">pour</DiscourseConnective> notre société.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4285" docOffset="33">
      <en>The question of dependence will become more and more important in the future because of demographic ageing, but also because of equality between men and women as the care of children <Alignment alignment="4946" annotation_id="4468">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4468" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dependants is still carried out mostly by women.</en>
      <fr>La question de la dépendance est vouée à revêtir une importance croissante dans le futur compte tenu du vieillissement de la population, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4780">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> à cause de l'égalité entre les hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4829">et</DiscourseConnective> les femmes, dans la mesure où celles-ci continuent d'assurer dans une large mesure la prise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4924">en</DiscourseConnective> charge des enfants <Alignment alignment="1544" annotation_id="4946">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4946" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des personnes dépendantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4521" docOffset="34">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5441" annotation_id="4521">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4521" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we have to put into practice measures that help women enter or stay in the labour market by improving family life conditions, especially those that facilitate a balance between professional and private life.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="8157" annotation_id="4988">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4988" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5004">en</DiscourseConnective> place des mesures pratiques permettant aux femmes d'entrer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5066">ou</DiscourseConnective> de rester sur le marché du travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5104">en</DiscourseConnective> améliorant les conditions de vie familiale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5151">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> celles favorisant un équilibre entre vie professionnelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5223">et</DiscourseConnective> vie privée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4740" docOffset="35">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5238" annotation_id="4740">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4740" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> specifically concerns the situation regarding the care of dependants, the Commission has already put the following actions on the table.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2376" annotation_id="5238">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5238" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">En</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce qui concerne plus spécifiquement la prise en charge des personnes dépendantes, la Commission a d'ores et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5349">déjà</DiscourseConnective> mis les actions suivantes sur la table.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4880" docOffset="36">
      <en>Filial leave to care for dependent family members was included in the consultation of the European social partners on the reconciliation of work, private and family life.</en>
      <fr>Les congés filiaux afin de s'occuper d'une personne dépendante ont été inclus dans la consultation auprès des partenaires sociaux européens sur le thème de la conciliation entre vie professionnelle, vie familiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5607">et</DiscourseConnective> vie personnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5051" docOffset="37">
      <en>The Commission is <Alignment alignment="5645" annotation_id="5069">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5069" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> studying the quality of services for elderly dependent people and protection against ill treatment, as well as measures which could be taken at European level in cooperation with the Member States to speed up the development and modernisation of infrastructure and services.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est <Alignment alignment="10805" annotation_id="5645">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5645" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> en train d'étudier la qualité des services <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5698">pour</DiscourseConnective> les personnes âgées dépendantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5735">et</DiscourseConnective> la protection contre les mauvais traitements, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5784">de même que</DiscourseConnective> des mesures qui pourraient être adoptées au niveau européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5856">en</DiscourseConnective> collaboration avec les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5896">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>accélérer le développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5930">et</DiscourseConnective> la modernisation des infrastructures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5970">et</DiscourseConnective> des services.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5349" docOffset="38">
      <en>The EU cohesion policy, through the European Social Fund, will continue to cofinance initiatives at national and local level.</en>
      <fr>La politique de cohésion de l'UE continuera, au travers du Fonds social européen, de cofinancer des initiatives nationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6110">et</DiscourseConnective> locales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5475" docOffset="39">
      <en>The open method of coordination in the field of social protection and social inclusion pays particular attention to the modernisation of pension schemes to take greater account of new forms of work, career breaks and long-term care for dependent people.</en>
      <fr>La méthode ouverte de coordination dans le domaine de la protection sociale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6198">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'inclusion sociale accorde une attention particulière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6259">à</DiscourseConnective> la modernisation des régimes de retraite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6302">afin de</DiscourseConnective> prendre davantage en compte les nouvelles formes de travail, les interruptions de carrière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6401">et</DiscourseConnective> la prise en charge à long terme des personnes dépendantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5729" docOffset="40">
      <en>We are working on this, and really look forward to collaborating very closely with parliamentarians.</en>
      <fr>Nous travaillons actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6493">à</DiscourseConnective> ces points <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6506">et</DiscourseConnective> attendons avec impatience d'instaurer une étroite collaboration avec les députés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5830" docOffset="41">
      <en>We would like to congratulate Parliament on the very important work done.</en>
      <fr>Nous voudrions féliciter le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6629">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail très important réalisé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5904" id="201" name="Marie Panayotopoulos-Cassiotou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5904" docOffset="42">
      <en>(EL) Mr President, I should like to comment that, in this report which was adopted with an absolute majority in the Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality, there is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6078" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> an alternative motion tabled by certain Members.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais indiquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6718">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans ce rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6739">que</DiscourseConnective> la commission des droits de la femme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6780">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'égalité des genres a adopté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6816">à</DiscourseConnective> la majorité absolue, figure une autre proposition soumise par certains députés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6132" docOffset="43">
      <en>We shall be called on tomorrow to vote by choosing between this motion and the motion tabled by a parliamentary committee.</en>
      <fr>Demain, nous sommes invités à voter et à nous prononcer en faveur de cette proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6985">ou</DiscourseConnective> de la proposition présentée par une commission parlementaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6255" docOffset="44">
      <en>One demolishes the other.</en>
      <fr>La seconde sape la première.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6281" docOffset="45">
      <en>We cannot talk about this alternative motion in plenary, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6338" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">nor</DiscourseConnective> can we hear the Members who tabled it <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6380" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6384" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">nor</DiscourseConnective> can we express an opinion on it.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pouvons ni discuter en plénière de la proposition des députés, ni même entendre ceux qui l'ont soumise ni exprimer une opinion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6421" docOffset="46">
      <en>It is a defect in the new rules which you need to bear in mind.</en>
      <fr>C'est une des failles des nouvelles règles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7258">que</DiscourseConnective> vous devez prendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7281">en</DiscourseConnective> considération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6485" id="202" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6485" docOffset="47">
      <en>- Yes, Mrs Panayotopoulos-Cassiotou, what I said earlier to Mrs Doyle <Alignment alignment="26234" annotation_id="6555">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6555" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> applies here.</en>
      <fr>Oui, chère collègue, <Alignment alignment="14935" annotation_id="7320">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7320" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">même</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remarque <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7334">que</DiscourseConnective> précédemment avec Mme Doyle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6574" docOffset="48">
      <en>We are applying Rule 45 which, <Alignment alignment="17307" annotation_id="6605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6605" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, provides a very strict framework for our speaking time, <Alignment alignment="7469" annotation_id="6670">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6670" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> only the rapporteur can take the floor.</en>
      <fr>Nous appliquons l'article 45 qui, <Alignment alignment="11939" annotation_id="7401">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7401" sense="Expansion.Restatement">effectivement</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, donne un cadre très strict <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7443">pour</DiscourseConnective> nos temps de parole, <Alignment alignment="6670" annotation_id="7469">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7469" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> seul le rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7496">s'</DiscourseConnective>exprime.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6716" docOffset="49">
      <en>We take our lead from the Conference of Presidents, which decided that this subject came under that particular Rule.</en>
      <fr>Nous dépendons de la Conférence des présidents, qui a décidé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7568">que</DiscourseConnective> ce thème était traité sous cet article-là.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6833" docOffset="50">
      <en>Our Rules of Procedure certainly ought to be developed to allow for greater flexibility and richer debates, <Alignment alignment="7722" annotation_id="6941">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6941" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6946" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> you will understand, it is not up to me to amend these Rules of Procedure this evening.</en>
      <fr>Notre règlement devrait certainement évoluer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7660">pour</DiscourseConnective> permettre plus de flexibilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7695">et</DiscourseConnective> des débats plus riches, <Alignment alignment="6941" annotation_id="7722">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7722" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il ne m'appartient pas, vous le comprendrez, de modifier ce soir ce règlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7037" docOffset="51">
      <en>That being said, your comment is obviously noted.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7806">Cela dit</DiscourseConnective>, votre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7822">remarque</DiscourseConnective> figurera au procès-verbal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7087" docOffset="52">
      <en>The item is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le point est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7107" docOffset="53">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7142" docOffset="54">
      <en>Written statements (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclarations écrites (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7172" id="203" language="RO" name="Corina Creţu ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7172" docOffset="55">
      <en>Discrimination based on gender is still a reality, unfortunately, even in the European Union Member States.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (EN ) Les discriminations motivées par le genre restent, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8008">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, une réalité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8038">même</DiscourseConnective> dans les États membres de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7280" docOffset="56">
      <en>This fact is not only valid in the private sector, where men account for nine-tenths of the members of boards of directors in large companies, but also in the public sector where women are <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7469" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> underrepresented.</en>
      <fr>C'est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8100">pour</DiscourseConnective> le secteur privé où, dans les grosses sociétés, neuf personnes sur dix au sein du conseil d'administration sont des hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8228">mais</DiscourseConnective> cela vaut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8243">aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8249">pour</DiscourseConnective> le secteur public où les femmes sont sous-représentées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7492" docOffset="57">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17617" annotation_id="7492">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7492" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Lisbon Strategy aims to ensure that 60% of women able to work are in employment.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10095" annotation_id="8310">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8310" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la stratégie de Lisbonne vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8351">à</DiscourseConnective> garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8362">que</DiscourseConnective> 60 % des femmes qui peuvent travailler aient un emploi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7586" docOffset="58">
      <en>Apart from this, we must not forget that one of the biggest challenges in Europe in the medium- and long-term is the demographic situation.</en>
      <fr>Mais, en dehors de cela, n'oublions pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8462">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un des plus grands défis de l'Europe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8503">à</DiscourseConnective> moyen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8511">et</DiscourseConnective> à long terme, est celui de la situation démographique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7726" docOffset="59">
      <en>The European Union is facing a bigger rise in the average age of its population than other regions of the world, along with a population growth of just 0.4%, which means that the European Union will need, at the same time, to face up to a fall in the population able to work and an ageing population.</en>
      <fr>L'âge moyen de la population croît actuellement plus fortement dans l'Union européenne que dans le monde <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8674">alors que</DiscourseConnective> sa croissance démographique, elle, n'est que de 0,4 %. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8739">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>, l'Europe va devoir faire face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8789">simultanément</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8803">à</DiscourseConnective> une baisse de la population active <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8840">et</DiscourseConnective> à une population vieillissante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8027" docOffset="60">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28137" annotation_id="8027">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8027" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Consequently</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the choice between having a career and raising a family must not be definitive or mandatory <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8133" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it must be possible to balance these two aspects of life.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1527" annotation_id="8875">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8875" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le choix entre une carrière professionnelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8935">et</DiscourseConnective> l'éducation d'une famille ne doit être ni définitif ni obligatoire. Il faut qu'un équilibra existe entre ces deux facettes de la vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8195" id="204" language="RO" name="Daniel Petru Funeriu ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8195" docOffset="61">
      <en>One of the European Union's key values is to eliminate any form of discrimination.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (RO) L'une des valeurs fondamentales de l'Union européenne est l'élimination de toutes les formes de discrimination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8278" docOffset="62">
      <en>Apart from eliminating discrimination, which <Alignment alignment="848" annotation_id="8323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8323" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> means between men and women, we have the responsibility to implement proactive measures to encourage professional careers for women.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons supprimer les discriminations, c.-à-d. <Alignment alignment="12023" annotation_id="9253">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9253" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les discrimination entre hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9291">et</DiscourseConnective> femmes et encourager activement les femmes à se lancer dans une carrière professionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8461" docOffset="63">
      <en>One of the fields in which women are hugely underrepresented is scientific research.</en>
      <fr>L'un des domaines dans lesquels la gente féminine est largement sous-représentée est la recherche scientifique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8546" docOffset="64">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8546" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>, they are not only underrepresented in numerical terms, but also within the management hierarchy: the higher the level in the hierarchy, the lower the proportion of women.</en>
      <fr>Cette faible représentation n'est pas uniquement quantitative; elle s'observe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9574">aussi</DiscourseConnective> au sein de la hiérarchie dirigeante puisque, plus on gravit les échelons, plus la proportion de femmes est faible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8730" docOffset="65">
      <en>In this way, society is depriving itself of the creative potential of an important section of the population.</en>
      <fr>La société se prive ainsi du potentiel créatif d'une large frange de la population.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8840" docOffset="66">
      <en>The highly competitive nature of research, the inherent geographical mobility associated with scientific work, along with establishing a career at a relatively late age all make this activity difficult to combine with family life.</en>
      <fr>La nature hautement compétitive de la recherche, la mobilité géographique inhérente au travail scientifique et le démarrage relativement tardif d'une carrière sont des facteurs qui expliquent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9971">que</DiscourseConnective> cette activité est difficile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10004">à</DiscourseConnective> concilier avec une vie de famille.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9071" docOffset="67">
      <en>I am taking advantage of the discussion of this topic to highlight the need to introduce specific policies aimed at achieving equality between men and women in the academic profession.</en>
      <fr>Je profite de la discussion sur ce point <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10082">pour</DiscourseConnective> souligner la nécessité d'élaborer des mesures particulières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10147">dans le but de</DiscourseConnective> mettre les hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10180">et</DiscourseConnective> les femmes sur un même pied face aux carrières universitaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9256" docOffset="68">
      <en>These policies must take into account a set of good practices at European level, such as facilitating dual careers, encouraging universities and research institutes to invest in childcare centres, as well as fast-track access to academic posts for women.</en>
      <fr>Ces mesures doivent reposer sur un socle de bonnes pratiques européennes telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10326">que</DiscourseConnective> celles qui consistent à faciliter les doubles carrières, à encourager les universités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10416">et</DiscourseConnective> instituts de recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10442">à</DiscourseConnective> investir dans des structures d'accueil pour enfants ou à assurer aux femmes un accès plus rapide aux postes universitaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9511" id="205" language="HU" name="Zita Gurmai ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9511" docOffset="69">
      <en>The Member States of the European Union must support demographic renewal, incorporating their action into the renewed Lisbon Strategy for Growth and Jobs, in line with the policy of equality between men and women.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (HU) Les États membres de l'Union européenne doivent stimuler le renouvellement démographique en inscrivant leurs actes dans la nouvelle stratégie de Lisbonne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10740">pour</DiscourseConnective> la croissance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10759">et</DiscourseConnective> l'emploi, dans le respect de la politique d'égalité entre hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10827">et</DiscourseConnective> femmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9725" docOffset="70">
      <en>A balance in European societies depends on the sum total of solidarity relations between the generations, which are more complex than ever before: young people continue to live in their parents' home for longer periods, <Alignment alignment="36508" annotation_id="9945">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9945" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is increasingly common for those parents to have to look after their aging relatives as well.</en>
      <fr>Dans les sociétés européennes, l'équilibre est défini par la somme totale des liens de solidarité entre les générations, plus complexes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10974">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à n'importe quelle autre époque. En effet, les jeunes vivent plus longtemps chez leurs parents <Alignment alignment="9359" annotation_id="11072">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11072" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans un même temps, les parents doivent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11123">de plus</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11131">en plus</DiscourseConnective> fréquemment s'occuper de proches vieillissants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10048" docOffset="71">
      <en>The burden that this represents rests primarily on the young and middle-aged generation, and especially on women.</en>
      <fr>Cette charge repose principalement sur les épaules des jeunes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11249">et</DiscourseConnective> de la génération d'âge moyen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11282">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11286">plus particulièrement</DiscourseConnective> sur celles des femmes de ces générations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10162" docOffset="72">
      <en>For this reason, equality between women and men, that is to say, equal opportunities in the broader sense, would seem to be a fundamental condition for bringing about new forms of inter-generational solidarity.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle l'égalité entre femmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11403">et</DiscourseConnective> hommes, et l'égalité des chances plus généralement, semblent être une condition essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11498">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avènement de nouvelles formes de solidarité entre les générations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10373" docOffset="73">
      <en>With regard to family obligations, that is, the reconciliation of family life and work, the question of equality between men and women is clearly very important <Alignment alignment="11727" annotation_id="10534">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10534" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> European families are to gain new impetus.</en>
      <fr>Au rang des obligations familiales (le fait de concilier vie familiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11640">et</DiscourseConnective> vie professionnelle), l'égalité entre hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11688">et</DiscourseConnective> femmes est évidemment indispensable <Alignment alignment="10534" annotation_id="11727">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11727" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'on veut que la famille européenne trouver un nouveau souffle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10580" docOffset="74">
      <en>It is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10586" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> of critical importance to guarantee the opportunity for childcare of appropriate quality and quantity for those who would like to take up paid employment alongside childrearing.</en>
      <fr>Et, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11798">pour</DiscourseConnective> ceux qui souhaiteraient avoir un emploi rémunéré tout en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11860">s'</DiscourseConnective>occupant de leurs enfants, il faut absolument prévoir suffisamment de services de garde <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11950">et</DiscourseConnective> des services de qualité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10769" docOffset="75">
      <en>The Socialist Group in the European Parliament is doing everything it can to ensure that the goals of Barcelona Process are met, and notes with disappointment that this objective is visibly absent from the Czech Presidency's programme.</en>
      <fr>Le Groupe socialiste au Parlement tente de s'assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12031">que</DiscourseConnective> les objectifs qui accompagnent le processus de Barcelone soient effectivement atteints <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12122">et</DiscourseConnective> regrette <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12134">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils ne figurent pas au programme de la présidence tchèque.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11005" id="206" language="ET" name="Siiri Oviir ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11005" docOffset="76">
      <en>Today's Europe is faced with unprecedented demographic changes.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (ET) L'Europe connaît actuellement des changements démographiques inédits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11069" docOffset="77">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11069" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective> Europe wishes to change the trend towards population reduction, we must, through the policy of the EU and the Member States, support families in all possible ways, and permit women and men to combine family life and work, <Alignment alignment="3896" annotation_id="11294">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11294" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> such that obligations connected with home and family are equally divided between men and women.</en>
      <fr>Pour inverser la tendance à la décroissance démographique, nous devons offrir aux familles toutes les formes de soutien possibles par le biais de politiques communautaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12456">et</DiscourseConnective> nationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12470">et</DiscourseConnective> permettre aux femmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12494">et</DiscourseConnective> aux hommes de concilier vie familiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12535">et</DiscourseConnective> vie professionnelle. <Alignment alignment="11294" annotation_id="12559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12559" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, cela doit se faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12589">de telle façon que</DiscourseConnective> les obligations domestiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12636">et</DiscourseConnective> familiales soient réparties équitablement au sein du ménage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11394" docOffset="78">
      <en>I wholeheartedly support the alternative motion for a European Parliament resolution on non-discrimination based on gender and inter-generational solidarity, which is more realistic than the preceding report.</en>
      <fr>Je souscris pleinement à la proposition de résolution du Parlement européen relative à la non-discrimination sur la base du genre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12830">et</DiscourseConnective> à la solidarité entre les générations. Elle est plus réaliste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12895">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapport précédent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11603" docOffset="79">
      <en>I must particularly emphasise the objective of creating a care policy that is balanced between the genders.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais insister <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12942">surtout</DiscourseConnective> sur l'objectif d'une politique de garde garantissant un équilibre entre l'homme et la femme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11711" docOffset="80">
      <en>Inequality in the performance of caring is often caused by the absence of affordable, available and high-quality services in Member States, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11851" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> women are faced with the inevitability of sacrificing their opportunities to participate in social, economic and political life.</en>
      <fr>Ces inégalités face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13063">à</DiscourseConnective> la garde des enfants naissent souvent de l'absence de services abordables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13139">et</DiscourseConnective> de qualité dans les États membres. Les femmes se trouvent alors confrontée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13217">à</DiscourseConnective> une décision inévitable: renoncer aux occasions qu'elles auraient de participer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13299">à</DiscourseConnective> la vie sociale, économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13328">et</DiscourseConnective> politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11984" docOffset="81">
      <en>All of this preserves the inequality in the distribution of obligations connected with home and family between men and women, which generally forces women to choose a more flexible organisation of labour or give up working, which <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12214" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">in turn</DiscourseConnective> influences their career, the continuing disparity between the wages earned by women and men, and pension rights.</en>
      <fr>Tous ces facteurs nourrissent les inégalités dans la répartition des obligations domestiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13435">et</DiscourseConnective> familiales entre l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13463">et</DiscourseConnective> la femme, obligeant en général la femme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13506">à</DiscourseConnective> opter pour une organisation plus souple du travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13559">ou</DiscourseConnective> à arrêter de travailler. Leur carrière s'en ressent et cette situation entretient les disparités dans les niveaux de salaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13688">et</DiscourseConnective> les droits de retraite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12335" docOffset="82">
      <en>I am cautious of the recommendation of the Czech Presidency to make childcare 'a fully valid alternative to a professional career'.</en>
      <fr>J'exprime des réserves <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13738">quant à</DiscourseConnective> la recommandation de la présidence tchèque de faire de l'éducation des enfants une "alternative tout à fait valable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13862">à</DiscourseConnective> la carrière professionnelle".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12467" docOffset="83">
      <en>I am convinced that the implementation of this recommendation would perpetuate the traditional division of labour between men and women.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13913">que</DiscourseConnective> la concrétisation d'une telle recommandation perpétuerait le modèle traditionnel de répartition du travail entre l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14038">et</DiscourseConnective> la femme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12604" docOffset="84">
      <en>The measures planned in the framework of the Lisbon Strategy play an important role in establishing equality in the division of labour between women and men; their objective, in addition to increasing employment, promoting innovation and raising productivity, must <Alignment alignment="14326" annotation_id="12869">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12869" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be to eliminate in the EU the gender discrimination that has developed over time.</en>
      <fr>Les mesures fixées dans la stratégie de Lisbonne participent largement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14122">à</DiscourseConnective> l'instauration d'un équilibre dans la répartition du travail entre femmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14198">et</DiscourseConnective> hommes. Outre l'augmentation de l'emploi, la promotion de l'innovation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14272">et</DiscourseConnective> une hausse de la productivité, ces mesures doivent <Alignment alignment="12869" annotation_id="14326">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14326" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aider <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14342">à</DiscourseConnective> éliminer les discriminations motivées par le genre qui se sont imposées au fil du temps dans l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12956" id="990" language="SK" name="Zita Pleštinská ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12956" docOffset="85">
      <en>Caring has been the domain of women for centuries.</en>
      <fr>Pendant des siècles, l'éducation a été l'apanage des femmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13007" docOffset="86">
      <en>Ideal mothers who spent their youth caring for their children represent today the majority of the elderly female population <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13131" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it is this childcare and homecare that is not reflected in their pensions.</en>
      <fr>La majorité des femmes plus âgées ont été des mères idéales qui ont consacré leur jeunesse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14595">à</DiscourseConnective> élever leurs enfants. Or, ces tâches éducatives et domestiques ne sont pas prises en considération dans le calcul de leur pension.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13210" docOffset="87">
      <en>Many of them do not receive an appropriate pension for this socially valuable work during their active life <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13318" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this exposes them to a greater risk of poverty.</en>
      <fr>Bon nombre d'entre elles perçoivent une pension inappropriée en retour de ce précieux travail social auquel elles ont dédié leur vie active. Elles sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14880">dès lors</DiscourseConnective> plus susceptibles de connaître la pauvreté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13370" docOffset="88">
      <en>This is <Alignment alignment="5015" annotation_id="13378">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13378" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a reason why young women are postponing motherhood and giving priority to a professional career.</en>
      <fr>C'est <Alignment alignment="13378" annotation_id="14939">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14939" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une des raisons pour lesquelles les femmes jeunes reportent le projet de maternité au profit de leur carrière professionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13480" docOffset="89">
      <en>During my many speeches in the House, I have constantly emphasised that mothers and fathers who freely choose to bring up their children or to care for elderly or dependent family members must not suffer discrimination.</en>
      <fr>Au fil de mes nombreuses interventions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15116">en</DiscourseConnective> cette Assemblée, j'ai systématiquement répété <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15165">qu'</DiscourseConnective>on ne peut discriminer une mère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15200">ou</DiscourseConnective> un père qui choisit délibérément d'élever ses enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15257">ou</DiscourseConnective> de s'occuper de membres de sa famille plus âgés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15308">ou</DiscourseConnective> dépendants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13700" docOffset="90">
      <en>I know many families who have disabled relatives and carry out this demanding work with great courage despite the obstacles they constantly have to overcome.</en>
      <fr>Je connais beaucoup de familles dont un des membres est handicapé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15389">et</DiscourseConnective> qui font ce travail exigeant avec énormément de courage, malgré les obstacles qui se présentent continuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15504">à</DiscourseConnective> elles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13858" docOffset="91">
      <en>In this speech, I should like to praise the proposals made by the rapporteur Mrs Anna Záborská, which recommend recognition not only of traditional forms of gainful employment but also of the manifold forms of non-gainful employment carried out in families as part of inter-generational solidarity.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaiterais complimenter la rapporteure, Mme Anna Záborská, qui propose que soient reconnues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15610">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> les formes traditionnelles de travail rémunéré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15671">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15676">également</DiscourseConnective> les nombreuses tâches non rémunérés assumées au sein des familles, au nom de la solidarité entre les générations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14157" docOffset="92">
      <en>This work is reflected in the GDP <Alignment alignment="15800" annotation_id="14191">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14191" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a family employs someone. <Alignment alignment="15895" annotation_id="14220">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14220" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is not the case <Alignment alignment="3145" annotation_id="14248">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14248" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> one of the parents carries out this work.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14191" annotation_id="15800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15800" sense="Contingency.Condition">Lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>une famille engage quelqu'un pour assumer ces tâches, ce travail est repris dans le PIB <Alignment alignment="14220" annotation_id="15895">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15895" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15910">s'</DiscourseConnective>y reflétera pas <Alignment alignment="8020" annotation_id="15928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15928" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est quelqu'un de la famille qui l'effectue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14293" docOffset="93">
      <en>I believe that the report will inspire Member States to adopt measures to improve family policy within the EU.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15986">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapport encouragera les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16031">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre les mesures nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16065">pour</DiscourseConnective> améliorer les politiques familiales au sein de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14404" id="207" language="RO" name="Rovana Plumb ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14404" docOffset="94">
      <en>At a time <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14414" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> Europe is facing a deep economic crisis whose final magnitude may be difficult to estimate, it is only to be expected that the birth rate will feel the negative repercussions of the turmoil on the labour market, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14631" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> many women will tend not to have children <Alignment alignment="16390" annotation_id="14676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14676" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are terrified of the possibility of losing their job and of the reduction in the material resources required to care for and bring up their children.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (RO) Alors que l'Europe traverse une profonde crise économique dont il est peut-être encore difficile d'évaluer l'amplitude, il faut s'attendre à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16285">que</DiscourseConnective> le taux de natalité réagisse sous l'influence négative du désarroi qui frappe le marché de l'emploi. <Alignment alignment="6015" annotation_id="16390">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16390" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">En effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, terrorisées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16412">à</DiscourseConnective> l'idée de perdre leur emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16443">et</DiscourseConnective> de voir diminuer les ressources matérielles nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16502">pour</DiscourseConnective> soigner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16515">et</DiscourseConnective> élever des enfants bien des femmes décideront probablement de ne pas en avoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14839" docOffset="95">
      <en>Against this background, it is the duty of every Member State to promote multigenerational activities, such as 'bridge-between-generation' centres, where older adults are paid to take care of and bring up children.</en>
      <fr>Dès lors, chaque État membre doit promouvoir des initiatives intergénérationnelles telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16687">que</DiscourseConnective> les centres "passerelles entre les générations" qui engagent des personnes âgées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16772">pour</DiscourseConnective> s'occuper d'enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16797">et</DiscourseConnective> les élever, contre rémunération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15054" docOffset="96">
      <en>These 'bridge-between-generation' centres, which operate successfully in some Member States, would allow women who have had a child to return to work quite soon, <Alignment alignment="38286" annotation_id="15216">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15216" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15222" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> making it easier for elderly retired people to return to employment.</en>
      <fr>Grâce à ces centres qui connaissent un certain succès dans plusieurs États membres, les femmes qui viennent d'avoir un enfant ont la possibilité de reprendre le travail assez rapidement <Alignment alignment="1306" annotation_id="17019">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17019" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> donnant à des retraités la possibilité de recommencer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17081">à</DiscourseConnective> travailler.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15296" id="208" language="BG" name="Dushana Zdravkova ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15296" docOffset="97">
      <en>In the last few decades the population in the Member States of the European Union has increasingly aged.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (BG) Au cours des dernières décennies, le vieillissement des populations européennes s'est accentué.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15401" docOffset="98">
      <en>Successfully balancing professional and personal life is starting to become a strenuous task for women.</en>
      <fr>Les femmes trouvent plus difficilement un équilibre satisfaisant entre vie professionnelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17300">et</DiscourseConnective> vie privée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15505" docOffset="99">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="5970" annotation_id="15511">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15511" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> now even more important for Member States to promote the birth rate and to pay proper attention to families.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="15511" annotation_id="17315">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17315" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17349">encore</DiscourseConnective> beaucoup plus important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17380">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres promeuvent la natalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17425">et</DiscourseConnective> accordent aux familles l'attention qu'elles méritent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15630" docOffset="100">
      <en>In this area the EU could indirectly contribute and help Member States to modernise their policies.</en>
      <fr>L'UE pourrait intervenir indirectement en aidant les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17549">à</DiscourseConnective> moderniser leurs politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15730" docOffset="101">
      <en>I consider that recognition of 'unseen labour' is one of the important steps which could be taken in this field.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17589">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il conviendrait, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17609">en</DiscourseConnective> la matière, de reconnaître le "travail invisible".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15843" docOffset="102">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="16878" annotation_id="15846">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15846" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cannot ignore the fact that ever more people of active age are looking after children and close elderly relatives at the same time, leaving them in a precarious position.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="15846" annotation_id="17663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17663" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous ne pouvons ignorer le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17709">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un nombre croissant de personnes en âge de travailler doivent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17774">en même temps</DiscourseConnective> s'occuper de leurs enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17815">et</DiscourseConnective> de proches parents âgés. Elles sont, dès lors, en situation précaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16022" docOffset="103">
      <en>This is why it is particularly important for the Commission to introduce practical initiatives for the official recognition of skills gained from activities connected with looking after children and dependent people, and household management, <Alignment alignment="32923" annotation_id="16265">
          <Alignment alignment="6347" annotation_id="16265">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16265" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> these skills are taken into account <Alignment alignment="18217" annotation_id="16309">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16309" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> rejoining the labour market.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle la Commission doit prendre des dispositions pratiques <Alignment alignment="16265" annotation_id="17972">
          <Alignment alignment="9990" annotation_id="17972">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17972" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> soient reconnues officiellement des compétences acquises au fil d'activités liées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18063">à</DiscourseConnective> l'éducation des enfants, au soin des personnes dépendantes et à la gestion des tâches domestiques. Ces compétences pourront alors être prises en compte <Alignment alignment="16309" annotation_id="18217">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18217" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces personnes réintègrent le marché de l'emploi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16343" docOffset="104">
      <en>Today we need to think about the future of all these mothers who look after children, who are the future of Europe, and protect them from the risk of one day receiving small pensions and being in an unequal position compared with other members of society.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons aujourd'hui songer à l'avenir de toutes les femmes qui élèvent leurs enfants ; ces enfants qui sont l'avenir de l'Europe. Il faut protéger les mères afin qu'elles ne finissent pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18466">un jour</DiscourseConnective> avec une maigre pension <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18498">et</DiscourseConnective> se trouvent, alors, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18521">en</DiscourseConnective> position d'inégalité par rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18557">à</DiscourseConnective> d'autres membres de la société.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
