<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>One-minute speeches on matters of political importance</en>
    <fr>Interventions d'une minute sur des questions politiques importantes</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="55" id="019" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="55" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle les interventions d'une minute sur des questions politiques importantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="132" id="020" name="Ádám Kósa">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="132" docOffset="2">
      <en>(HU) Ladies and gentlemen, I would like to draw your attention to the Charter of Fundamental Rights relating to people with disabilities within the Treaty of Lisbon.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="179">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="202">à</DiscourseConnective> attirer votre attention sur la charte des droits fondamentaux relativement aux personnes handicapées dans le traité de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="298" docOffset="3">
      <en>The Council of Europe is currently working on a new draft anti-discrimination regulation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="387" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I would like to highlight three aspects.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil de l'Europe œuvre actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="375">à</DiscourseConnective> un nouveau projet de règlement anti-discrimination. Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="438">à</DiscourseConnective> souligner trois points à cet égard.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="432" docOffset="4">
      <en>Firstly, according to the charter, no one can be discriminated against directly or indirectly <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="526" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> they have a child or family member with disabilities.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="476">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, selon la charte, personne ne peut faire l'objet d'une discrimination directe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="567">ou</DiscourseConnective> indirecte en raison du handicap de l'un de ses enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="625">ou</DiscourseConnective> d'un membre de sa famille.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="588" docOffset="5">
      <en>Secondly, from now on, insurers cannot refuse to issue insurance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="653" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> someone has a genetic disorder or disability.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="655">Deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, désormais les assureurs ne peuvent refuser la souscription d'une assurance à une personne souffrant d'un trouble génétique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="792">ou</DiscourseConnective> d'un handicap.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="707" docOffset="6">
      <en>Thirdly, the rights promoted by the European Union's institutions and Christian Democracy attach a great deal of importance to respect for the quality of life of people with disabilities.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="810">Troisièmement</DiscourseConnective>, les droits promus par les institutions de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="886">et</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie chrétienne attachent beaucoup d'importance au respect de la qualité de vie des personnes handicapées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="895" docOffset="7">
      <en>I would like to draw my fellow Members' attention to all these points <Alignment alignment="1083" annotation_id="965">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="965" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would like to ask you to support the creation of the Disability Intergroup this week.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1014">à</DiscourseConnective> attirer l'attention de mes collègues sur l'ensemble de ces points, <Alignment alignment="187" annotation_id="1083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1083" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je vous invite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1102">à</DiscourseConnective> soutenir la création de l'intergroupe "Personnes handicapées" cette semaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1061" id="021" name="Jarosław Kalinowski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1061" docOffset="8">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, the European Union, in which one in seven citizens belongs to a national minority, can be proud of its extensive guarantee to respect their rights.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, l'Union européenne, où un citoyen sur sept fait partie d'une minorité nationale, peut être fière de sa garantie extensive du respect de leurs droits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1228" docOffset="9">
      <en>The significance of the European Union's motto - unity in diversity - is worth stressing here.</en>
      <fr>La signification de la devise de l'Union européenne, "L'unité dans la diversité", mérite que l'on s'y attache.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1323" docOffset="10">
      <en>All of us in this Chamber know that a true democracy can be recognised by the way it treats its minorities.</en>
      <fr>Chaque membre de cette Assemblée sait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1508">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on reconnaît une véritable démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1552">à</DiscourseConnective> sa façon de traiter ses minorités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1431" docOffset="11">
      <en>The Lisbon Treaty unambiguously imposes an obligation to respect the rights of people who belong to minorities, <Alignment alignment="9219" annotation_id="1543">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1543" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Charter of Fundamental Rights forbids any discrimination based on the grounds of ethnic origin or membership of a national minority.</en>
      <fr>Le traité de Lisbonne impose sans équivoque une obligation de respecter les droits des personnes qui appartiennent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1704">à</DiscourseConnective> des minorités, <Alignment alignment="1543" annotation_id="1721">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1721" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la charte des droits fondamentaux interdit toute forme de discrimination fondée sur l'origine ethnique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1835">ou</DiscourseConnective> l'appartenance à une minorité nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1684" docOffset="12">
      <en>Unfortunately, there are still countries in the EU which, despite their adoption of international legal obligations in this area, are moving towards the assimilation and outright deprivation of the national identity of their minorities by deliberate policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1879">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, il subsiste des pays de l'Union européenne qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1944">même s'</DiscourseConnective>ils ont adopté les obligations légales internationales dans ce domaine, tendent vers l'assimilation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2051">et</DiscourseConnective> la privation pure et simple de l'identité nationale de leurs minorités au moyen d'une politique délibérée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1942" docOffset="13">
      <en>Lithuania, for it is this country to which I refer, has, for over 20 years, been discriminating against its citizens in different areas of life.</en>
      <fr>La Lituanie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2174">puisque</DiscourseConnective> c'est le pays auquel je fais allusion, adopte une attitude discriminatoire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2257">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 20 ans à l'égard de ses citoyens dans différents domaines de la vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2087" docOffset="14">
      <en>Not only has this been done in a planned way but, since its accession to the European Union, these practices have even increased. The ruling of the Lithuanian Constitutional Court on the spelling of Polish surnames only in Lithuanian transcription is an example.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2333">Non seulement</DiscourseConnective> cette approche s'est effectuée de manière planifiée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2400">mais</DiscourseConnective> de surcroît, ces pratiques vont crescendo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2447">depuis</DiscourseConnective> l'adhésion du pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2473">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne, comme en témoigne l'arrêt de la Cour constitutionnelle lituanienne concernant la transcription des prénoms polonais uniquement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2622">en</DiscourseConnective> lituanien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2350" id="022" name="Jarosław Leszek Wałęsa">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2350" docOffset="15">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, on 14 October, the European Commission announced its annual enlargement strategy.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, le 14 octobre, la Commission européenne a communiqué sa stratégie annuelle d'élargissement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2451" docOffset="16">
      <en>In this document, the Commission presents an evaluation of the progress made by the Western Balkans and Turkey at a time of world economic crisis, and the most important problems which those countries will have to face up to in the near future.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce document, elle présente une évaluation des progrès réalisés par les Balkans occidentaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2852">et</DiscourseConnective> la Turquie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2866">à</DiscourseConnective> l'heure de la crise économique mondiale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2909">et</DiscourseConnective> des principales difficultés auxquelles ces pays seront confrontés dans un proche avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2696" docOffset="17">
      <en>In my short speech, speaking as a member of the European Parliament delegation to the EU-Turkey Joint Parliamentary Committee, I would like to encourage Turkey to continue the efforts it has undertaken for reform, the objective of which is full democratisation of the country and rapid resolution of conflicts with neighbouring countries.</en>
      <fr>Dans ma brève intervention, en m'exprimant en qualité de membre de la délégation du Parlement européen de la Commission parlementaire mixte UE-Turquie, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3162">à</DiscourseConnective> encourager la Turquie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3186">à</DiscourseConnective> poursuivre ses efforts dans la voie de la réforme, dont l'objectif est la démocratisation complète du pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3295">et</DiscourseConnective> la rapide résolution des conflits avec les pays limitrophes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3035" docOffset="18">
      <en>Accession negotiations have reached an advanced stage and require Turkey to make yet greater efforts at meeting the criteria for membership.</en>
      <fr>Les négociations d'adhésion ont atteint un stade avancé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3415">et</DiscourseConnective> nécessitent désormais que la Turquie intensifie ses efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3478">pour</DiscourseConnective> remplir les critères d'adhésion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3176" docOffset="19">
      <en>The perspective of accession to the EU should be an incentive to strengthen democracy and observe human rights, and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3292" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> to further modernisation of the country and the achievement of European Union standards.</en>
      <fr>La perspective d'une adhésion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3546">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne devrait inciter la Turquie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3594">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3620">et</DiscourseConnective> à respecter les droits de l'homme, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3658">tout en</DiscourseConnective> poursuivant la modernisation du pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3703">et</DiscourseConnective> l'instauration des normes de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3386" id="023" name="Marc Tarabella">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3386" docOffset="20">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, every six seconds, a child dies of hunger somewhere in the world, <Alignment alignment="35127" annotation_id="3493">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3493" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the number of people suffering from malnutrition has just reached the one billion mark.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3787">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, chers collègues, toutes les six secondes un enfant meurt de faim dans le monde, <Alignment alignment="3493" annotation_id="3881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3881" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous venons de passer le cap du milliard de personnes qui souffrent de malnutrition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3585" docOffset="21">
      <en>This very serious situation was condemned at the G20 Summit in Pittsburgh in September.</en>
      <fr>Cette situation gravissime a été dénoncée lors du sommet du G20, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4034">à</DiscourseConnective> Pittsburgh, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4048">en</DiscourseConnective> septembre dernier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3673" docOffset="22">
      <en>At that summit, it was announced that USD 20 billion would be given to support agriculture in developing countries.</en>
      <fr>Lors de ce sommet, 20 milliards de dollars avaient été annoncés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4134">pour</DiscourseConnective> aider l'agriculture des pays en voie de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3789" docOffset="23">
      <en>Incidentally, the same thing was said at the G8 Summit in L'Aquila.</en>
      <fr>Ce fut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4201">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4212">également</DiscourseConnective> fait au sommet du G8, à L'Aquila.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3857" docOffset="24">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14234" annotation_id="3857">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3857" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, at the World Summit on Food Security held on 16 November in Rome, under the auspices of the Food and Agriculture Organisation, the situation was entirely different: snubbed by almost all of the G8 leaders, it did not end in the ratification of the measures previously anticipated.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3857" annotation_id="4256">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4256" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le sommet réuni à Rome la semaine dernière, le 16 novembre, sous l'égide de la FAO, a montré une réalité tout autre: snobé par la quasi-totalité des dirigeants du G8, il n'a pas abouti <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4452">à</DiscourseConnective> la ratification des mesures escomptées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4147" docOffset="25">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="33622" annotation_id="4153">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4153" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hardly surprising that no precise figure appears in the text numbering forty or so articles, not even the USD 44 billion that the FAO says are needed annually in order to sustain the agricultural systems of the poorest countries.</en>
      <fr>Il n'est <Alignment alignment="1334" annotation_id="4503">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4503" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas étonnant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4521">qu'</DiscourseConnective>aucun engagement chiffré ne figure dans le texte d'une quarantaine d'articles, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4603">notamment</DiscourseConnective> les 44 milliards de dollars annuels jugés nécessaires par la FAO <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4678">pour</DiscourseConnective> soutenir l'agriculture des pays les plus pauvres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4393" docOffset="26">
      <en>The authors of the final declaration have merely paid lip service to the promise made by the G8 members - that is, those at L'Aquila - on this matter.</en>
      <fr>Les auteurs de la déclaration finale se sont contentés de saluer la promesse des membres du G8 - justement de L'Aquila - sur ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4544" docOffset="27">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="9882" annotation_id="4546">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4546" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> deplore these double standards and question whether the G20 will be capable of implementing these measures.</en>
      <fr>Je déplore <Alignment alignment="4546" annotation_id="4879">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4879" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce double discours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4903">et</DiscourseConnective> je mets en doute la capacité du G20 à mettre en application ces mesures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4664" docOffset="28">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11703" annotation_id="4664">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4664" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the famous French comedian Pierre Dac used to say, 'Infinite patience is required to wait eternally for what never comes'.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8105" annotation_id="4979">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4979" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le disait le célèbre humoriste français Pierre Dac: "Il faut une infinie patience <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5067">pour</DiscourseConnective> attendre toujours ce qui n'arrive jamais".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4790" id="024" name="Antonio Masip Hidalgo">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4790" docOffset="29">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, the situation in the Western Sahara is very serious.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, la situation du Sahara occidental est très préoccupante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4862" docOffset="30">
      <en>The alerts from the Human Rights Observatory in Asturias - my region - and from many other organisations deserve to be taken seriously.</en>
      <fr>Les avertissements émis par l'Observatoire des droits de l'homme des Asturies, ma région, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5290">et</DiscourseConnective> par beaucoup d'autres organisations, méritent toute notre attention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4998" docOffset="31">
      <en>There are seven prisoners awaiting military trials for having visited their families in Tindouf, there are political prisoners, there is torture, people have disappeared, <Alignment alignment="22334" annotation_id="5169">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5169" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a peaceful heroine and candidate for the Sakharov prize, Aminatou Haidar, the Saharan Gandhi, has been expelled by the territory's occupying power.</en>
      <fr>À l'heure actuelle, sept prisonniers attendent un jugement militaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5431">pour</DiscourseConnective> avoir rendu visite à leur famille <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5470">à</DiscourseConnective> Tindouf. Il y a des prisonniers politiques, on pratique la torture, des gens ont disparu <Alignment alignment="5169" annotation_id="5561">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5561" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une héroïne pacifique candidate au prix Sakharov, Aminatou Haidar, la Gandhi saharienne, a été expulsée par la puissance occupante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5321" docOffset="32">
      <en>This is something unprecedented in international law.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5699">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'une situation sans précédent dans le droit international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5375" docOffset="33">
      <en>Mrs Malmström, Members of the European Commission, new leaders in the Council: the European Union should get involved to support this extremely repressed population.</en>
      <fr>Madame Malmström, Mesdames et Messieurs les membres de la Commission européenne, Mesdames et Messieurs les nouveaux dirigeants du Conseil: L'Union européenne devrait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5932">s'</DiscourseConnective>engager <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5942">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur de cette population gravement opprimée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5541" docOffset="34">
      <en>On the 20th anniversary of the fall of the Berlin Wall, there is another wall very close to us acting as a barrier to freedom.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5992">À l'heure où</DiscourseConnective> nous fêtons le 20e anniversaire de la chute du mur de Berlin, il existe un autre mur, très près de nous, qui constitue un obstacle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6136">à</DiscourseConnective> la liberté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5668" docOffset="35">
      <en>Listen to Aminatou!</en>
      <fr>Écoutez Aminatou!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5688" docOffset="36">
      <en>Save her life!</en>
      <fr>Sauvez-lui la vie!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5703" id="025" name="Carl Haglund">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5703" docOffset="37">
      <en>(SV) Mr President, in recent weeks, we have once again received reports about the poor state of health of the Baltic Sea.</en>
      <fr>(SV) Monsieur le Président, au cours des dernières semaines, nous avons à nouveau reçu des rapports alarmants concernant la mer Baltique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5825" docOffset="38">
      <en>I really must, <Alignment alignment="25970" annotation_id="5840">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5840" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, say a few words about this today, too, <Alignment alignment="6346" annotation_id="5890">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5890" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="10443" annotation_id="5895">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5895" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we had conciliation between the Council and Parliament last week on the budget for 2010.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6718" annotation_id="6325">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6325" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je me dois <Alignment alignment="5890" annotation_id="6346">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6346" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de m'exprimer brièvement sur ce sujet aujourd'hui, <Alignment alignment="6289" annotation_id="6407">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6407" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la semaine dernière était organisée une conciliation entre le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6481">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement sur le budget 2010.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5992" docOffset="39">
      <en>The budget includes the additional EUR 20 million that Parliament wanted to be allocated to the Baltic Sea Strategy, which is gratifying.</en>
      <fr>Le budget englobe les 20 millions d'euros supplémentaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6575">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement désirait allouer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6609">à</DiscourseConnective> la stratégie pour la région de la mer Baltique, ce qui est satisfaisant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6130" docOffset="40">
      <en>I will <Alignment alignment="6693" annotation_id="6137">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6137" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be sure to remind the Commission, <Alignment alignment="8494" annotation_id="6181">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6181" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is represented here, that we need a legal basis for the Baltic Sea Strategy in order for us to actually be able to put it into practice and for the funds that have now been reserved to actually be put to use.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <Alignment alignment="13284" annotation_id="6693">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6693" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6698">à</DiscourseConnective> rappeler à la Commission, <Alignment alignment="13327" annotation_id="6726">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6726" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elle est représentée ici, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6759">que</DiscourseConnective> la stratégie pour la région de la mer Baltique nécessite une base juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6839">afin que</DiscourseConnective> nous soyons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6860">en</DiscourseConnective> mesure de la mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6883">en</DiscourseConnective> œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6892">et</DiscourseConnective> d'utiliser les fonds prévus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6923">à</DiscourseConnective> cette fin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6398" docOffset="41">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19383" annotation_id="6398">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6398" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> already mentioned, the reports that we have received over the last few weeks indicate that action is urgently required.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6398" annotation_id="6936">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6936" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6942">déjà</DiscourseConnective> indiqué, les rapports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6969">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons reçus au cours des dernières semaines indiquent la nécessité d'agir de toute urgence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6521" docOffset="42">
      <en>Various things need to happen - <Alignment alignment="34316" annotation_id="6553">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6553" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> quickly.</en>
      <fr>Plusieurs mesures doivent être prises, <Alignment alignment="6553" annotation_id="7109">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7109" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6566" docOffset="43">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="1217" annotation_id="6568">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6568" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hope that we will all roll up our sleeves and start to actually do something very soon.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2309" annotation_id="7118">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7118" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7137">que</DiscourseConnective> nous allons tous retrousser nos manches <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7181">et</DiscourseConnective> commencer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7194">à</DiscourseConnective> agir vraiment concrètement très <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7228">bientôt</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6666" docOffset="44">
      <en>Action is needed, not only by us, but also on the part of the Commission, the Council and the parties affected.</en>
      <fr>Il est urgent d'agir, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7259">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7273">à</DiscourseConnective> notre niveau, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7289">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7300">à</DiscourseConnective> celui de la Commission, du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7337">et</DiscourseConnective> des parties concernées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6778" id="026" name="Hélène Flautre">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6778" docOffset="45">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, on Thursday, I was in Tunis for the trial of the poet and writer Taoufik Ben Brik, indicted in Tunisia on obscure common-law charges that fool no one.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, jeudi j'étais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7401">à</DiscourseConnective> Tunis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7409">pour</DiscourseConnective> le procès du poète <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7433">et</DiscourseConnective> écrivain Taoufik Ben Brik, inculpé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7471">en</DiscourseConnective> Tunisie sur la base d'obscures accusations de droit commun qui ne trompent personne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6948" docOffset="46">
      <en>Since the 'elections' in Tunisia, held on 25 October, those who defend human rights have been subjected to an outburst of violence and harassment on such a scale <Alignment alignment="37047" annotation_id="7110">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7110" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I have never before witnessed, familiar <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7153" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective> I am with that country.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7559">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> les "élections" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7582">en</DiscourseConnective> Tunisie le 25 octobre, c'est le déchaînement des violences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7644">et</DiscourseConnective> du harcèlement des défenseurs des droits de l'homme, dans des proportions, pour bien connaître ce pays, <Alignment alignment="7110" annotation_id="7751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7751" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je n'ai jamais vues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7184" docOffset="47">
      <en>On 25 October, President Ben Ali no doubt realised the full extent of the Tunisian people's disaffection with their leader; <Alignment alignment="24399" annotation_id="7308">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7308" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the embassies and the European Commission, which unfortunately does not have the political visa to attend this kind of trial, have displayed a general lack of interest in the issue that is unfolding.</en>
      <fr>Probablement, M. Ben Ali, le 25 octobre, a pris la mesure de la désaffection <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7853">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il subit auprès de la population en Tunisie <Alignment alignment="7308" annotation_id="7900">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7900" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ceci se fait et se déroule dans l'indifférence générale des ambassades <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7974">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission européenne qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8010">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, n'a pas le visa politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8053">pour</DiscourseConnective> assister à ce type de procès.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7512" docOffset="48">
      <en>I think we must be very clear today.</en>
      <fr>Je crois qu'il faut être très clair aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7549" docOffset="49">
      <en>We are guilty of failing in our legal duty to rescue.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes coupables de non-assistance à personne en danger.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7603" docOffset="50">
      <en>What is stopping the embassies and the European Commission from rigorously questioning Mr Ben Ali - in the name of our binding agreements and mutual commitments with Tunisia - about his actions, which are entirely contrary to those commitments?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8199">Qu'</DiscourseConnective>est-ce qu'on attend dans les ambassades <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8242">et</DiscourseConnective> à la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8272">pour</DiscourseConnective> interpeller de la manière la plus vive M. Ben Ali - au nom des accords qui nous lient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8363">et</DiscourseConnective> de nos engagements réciproques avec la Tunisie - sur ces agissements qui sont absolument contraires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8466">à</DiscourseConnective> nos engagements?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7848" id="027" name="João Ferreira">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7848" docOffset="51">
      <en>(PT) The trade agreement signed on 4 November between the European Union <Alignment alignment="8555" annotation_id="7921">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7921" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Israel, which is aimed at liberalising trade in agricultural products, processed agricultural products and fish and fishery products, is unacceptable for various reasons which we will point out here.</en>
      <fr>(PT) L'accord commercial signé le 4 novembre entre l'Union européenne <Alignment alignment="5630" annotation_id="8555">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8555" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Israël, qui vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8575">à</DiscourseConnective> libéraliser le commerce des produits agricoles, des produits agricoles transformés, du poisson <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8672">et</DiscourseConnective> des produits de la pêche, est inacceptable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8718">pour</DiscourseConnective> de multiples raisons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8125" docOffset="52">
      <en>In the first place, it is unacceptable <Alignment alignment="23830" annotation_id="8164">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8164" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is aligned with neo-liberal policies that exacerbate the current economic and social crisis, especially in agriculture and fishing, <Alignment alignment="10429" annotation_id="8307">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8307" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this fact becomes particularly serious <Alignment alignment="8965" annotation_id="8350">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8350" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these policies are promoted through an agreement with a country that is violating international law and the most basic rights of the Palestinian people; a country which does not respect its obligations as agreed in the roadmap for peace, keeping Gaza under siege, building more settlements, continuing to build the wall and expelling Palestinians from Jerusalem.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8745">Tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="8164" annotation_id="8759">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8759" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il s'aligne sur les politiques néolibérales qui exacerbent la crise économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8847">et</DiscourseConnective> sociale actuelle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8868">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> dans les domaines agricole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8910">et</DiscourseConnective> piscicole. <Alignment alignment="1266" annotation_id="8924">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8924" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce fait devient d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8947">autant</DiscourseConnective> plus grave <Alignment alignment="10909" annotation_id="8965">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8965" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces politiques sont encouragées par un accord conclu avec un pays qui viole le droit international <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9072">et</DiscourseConnective> les droits les plus fondamentaux de la population palestinienne; un pays qui ne respecte pas ses obligations conformément à la feuille de route <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9219">pour</DiscourseConnective> la paix, qui assiège de Gaza, intensifie sa colonisation, poursuit la construction du mur et expulse les Palestiniens de Jérusalem.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8718" docOffset="53">
      <en>This is a country that is continuing to escalate the violation of human rights and international humanitarian laws.</en>
      <fr>Ce pays continue son escalade de la violation des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9424">et</DiscourseConnective> du droit humanitaire international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8834" docOffset="54">
      <en>We denounce and condemn the signing of this agreement, which will include the trade of products from Israeli settlements in Palestinian territories, highlighting the European Union's undeniable and unacceptable complicity with Israel in the face of the serious violations I have just described.</en>
      <fr>Nous dénonçons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9478">et</DiscourseConnective> condamnons la signature de cet accord, qui portera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9532">notamment</DiscourseConnective> sur le commerce de produits issus des colonies israéliennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9602">en</DiscourseConnective> territoire palestinien, ce qui illustre la complicité indéniable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9670">et</DiscourseConnective> intolérable de l'Union européenne avec Israël face aux graves violations que je viens de décrire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9129" docOffset="55">
      <en>We wish to voice our complete solidarity with the Palestinian people here, and stand up for their right to build a free, independent and sovereign state.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons exprimer notre totale solidarité avec le peuple palestinien, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9848">et</DiscourseConnective> défendons son droit de bâtir un État libre, indépendant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9907">et</DiscourseConnective> souverain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9283" id="028" name="Gerard Batten">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9283" docOffset="56">
      <en>Mr President, Russian exile Pavel Stroilov recently published revelations about the collaboration between the British Labour Party and the Soviet Union during the Cold War.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, le citoyen russe exilé Pavel Stroilov a récemment publié des révélations sur la collaboration entre le parti travailliste britannique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10083">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Union soviétique pendant la guerre froide.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9456" docOffset="57">
      <en>Soviet archival documents state that, in the 1980s, Neil Kinnock, as Leader of the Opposition, approached Mikhail Gorbachev through secret envoys to see how the Kremlin would respond <Alignment alignment="15938" annotation_id="9639">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9639" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a Labour Government stopped the implementation of the Trident nuclear missile programme.</en>
      <fr>Les documents d'archives soviétiques indiquent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10178">que</DiscourseConnective> dans les années 1980, Neil Kinnock, chef de l'opposition, a été en contact avec Mikhail Gorbachev par le biais d'agents secrets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10310">pour</DiscourseConnective> connaître la réaction du Kremlin <Alignment alignment="9639" annotation_id="10348">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10348" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un gouvernement travailliste mettait fin à la mise en œuvre du programme de missiles nucléaires Trident.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9731" docOffset="58">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19695" annotation_id="9731">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9731" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the report given to Mr Gorbachev is true, it means that Lord Kinnock approached one of Britain's enemies in order to seek approval regarding his party's defence policy and, <Alignment alignment="16218" annotation_id="9907">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9907" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elected, Britain's defence policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17204" annotation_id="10456">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10456" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce rapport confié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10477">à</DiscourseConnective> M. Gorbachev est authentique, ceci signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10523">que</DiscourseConnective> Lord Kinnock a contacté l'un des ennemis de la Grande-Bretagne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10590">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>obtenir son aval concernant la politique de défense de son parti <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10662">et</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="7510" annotation_id="10666">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10666" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il remportait les élections, de la Grande-Bretagne elle-même.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9945" docOffset="59">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10730" annotation_id="9945">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9945" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this report is true, then Lord Kinnock would be guilty of treason.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="16733" annotation_id="10730">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10730" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce rapport est authentique, Lord Kinnock serait coupable de trahison.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10015" docOffset="60">
      <en>The documents now available must be investigated at the highest possible level by the British authorities and Lord Kinnock given the opportunity to answer the Soviet evidence.</en>
      <fr>Les documents disponibles aujourd'hui doivent être examinés au plus haut niveau par les autorités britanniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10914">et</DiscourseConnective> Lord Kinnock doit avoir la possibilité de répondre aux preuves soviétiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10191" id="029" name="Csaba Sógor">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10191" docOffset="61">
      <en>(HU) It is a sad fact that a policy justifying the collective disenfranchisement of minorities can still provide an obstacle even today to the next wave of the integration process.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Il est déplorable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11016">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une politique justifiant l'incapacité collective des minorités puisse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11089">encore</DiscourseConnective> constituer un obstacle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11120">même</DiscourseConnective> à l'heure actuelle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11145">à</DiscourseConnective> la prochaine vague du processus d'intégration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10372" docOffset="62">
      <en>I would like to thank the President for what he did in order to restore normality in Slovakia.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11203">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier le Président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11228">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce qu'il a fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11249">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur du retour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11269">à</DiscourseConnective> la normale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11282">en</DiscourseConnective> Slovaquie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10467" docOffset="63">
      <en>The language law is just one such sad, small chapter.</en>
      <fr>La loi sur la langue officielle représente juste un chapitre triste et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11367">bref</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10521" docOffset="64">
      <en>The Czech case was another example.</en>
      <fr>L'affaire tchèque n'est qu'un exemple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10557" docOffset="65">
      <en>The Czech Head of State must know, even without the Treaty of Lisbon, that the Beneš Decrees came about through the enforcement of the principle of collective guilt and are not made unlawful with the enactment of the Charter of Fundamental Rights; they are, <Alignment alignment="17221" annotation_id="10815">
          <Alignment alignment="6974" annotation_id="10815">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10815" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, still in conflict with more than six European documents.</en>
      <fr>Le chef de l'État tchèque doit savoir que, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11455">même</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11460">sans</DiscourseConnective> le traité de Lisbonne, les décrets Beneš ont été adoptés sur la base du principe de la culpabilité collective <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11575">et</DiscourseConnective> n'ont pas été rendus illégaux par la promulgation de la charte des droits fondamentaux; <Alignment alignment="10815" annotation_id="11666">
          <Alignment alignment="11891" annotation_id="11666">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11666" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en réalité</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, ils sont toujours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11696">en</DiscourseConnective> conflit avec plus de six documents européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10881" docOffset="66">
      <en>We are confident that the future of the Treaty of Lisbon and the EU will be defined not by the rekindling of collective disenfranchisement from the Second World War, but by safeguarding the rights of minorities according to the customary European practice of guaranteeing autonomy in cultural life.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes convaincus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11768">que</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir du traité de Lisbonne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11803">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'Union européenne ne sera pas déterminé par le retour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11864">à</DiscourseConnective> l'incapacité collective née de la Seconde Guerre mondiale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11925">mais</DiscourseConnective> par la protection des droits des minorités conformément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11986">à</DiscourseConnective> la pratique européenne habituelle qui consiste à garantir l'autonomie dans la vie culturelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11180" id="030" name="Anna Záborská">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11180" docOffset="67">
      <en>(SK) 20 November marked the 20th anniversary of the UN's adoption of the Convention on the Rights of the Child.</en>
      <fr>(SK) Le 20 novembre a marqué le 20e anniversaire de l'adoption de la Convention relative aux droits de l'enfant par les Nations unies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11292" docOffset="68">
      <en>The anniversary <Alignment alignment="19680" annotation_id="11308">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11308" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> marks the creation of the Intergroup on Family and the Protection of Childhood.</en>
      <fr>Cet anniversaire marque <Alignment alignment="9420" annotation_id="12241">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12241" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la création de l'intergroupe "famille <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12289">et</DiscourseConnective> protection de l'enfance".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11393" docOffset="69">
      <en>The challenges facing the EU - such as demography, work-life balance, care for persons reliant on assistance, social inclusion, combating poverty among families and children and the policy for intergenerational solidarity - require the expertise of family organisations dedicated to protecting the interests of children.</en>
      <fr>Les défis auxquels est confrontée l'Union européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12372">comme</DiscourseConnective> la démographie, l'équilibre entre vie professionnelle et vie privée, les soins aux personnes dépendantes, l'inclusion sociale, la lutte contre la pauvreté des familles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12546">et</DiscourseConnective> des enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12561">et</DiscourseConnective> la politique de solidarité intergénérationnelle nécessitent l'expérience des organisations familiales vouées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12673">à</DiscourseConnective> la protection des intérêts des enfants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11714" docOffset="70">
      <en>The Convention on the Rights of the Child states that, for the harmonious development of personality, children need to grow up in a family environment based on happiness, love and understanding.</en>
      <fr>La Convention relative aux droits de l'enfant dispose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12769">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12774">en</DiscourseConnective> vue du développement harmonieux de leur personnalité, les enfants doivent grandir dans un environnement familial fondé sur le bonheur, l'amour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12920">et</DiscourseConnective> la compréhension.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11909" docOffset="71">
      <en>The Intergroup on Family and the Protection of Childhood works in Parliament as a platform for the pluralistic views of Members of all political groups.</en>
      <fr>L'intergroupe "famille <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12964">et</DiscourseConnective> protection de l'enfance" œuvre au sein du Parlement en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13022">tant que</DiscourseConnective> plateforme regroupant les visions multiples des députés de tous les groupes politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12062" docOffset="72">
      <en>I invite all Members to support this group in their political parties.</en>
      <fr>J'invite tous mes collègues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13147">à</DiscourseConnective> soutenir ce groupe dans leurs partis politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12133" docOffset="73">
      <en>They will enable the continuation of an important and useful role of this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Ils permettront la poursuite d'un rôle essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13247">et</DiscourseConnective> utile de cette Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12219" id="031" name="Daciana Octavia Sârbu">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12219" docOffset="74">
      <en>(RO) The situation of the Romanian community in Italy is a cause of ever-growing concern.</en>
      <fr>(RO) La situation de la communauté roumaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13320">en</DiscourseConnective> Italie est une source de préoccupation croissante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12309" docOffset="75">
      <en>The whole of Europe is already familiar with the way in which attempts have been made to blame a whole community on account of the actions of a few offenders.</en>
      <fr>Toute l'Europe connaît <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13397">déjà</DiscourseConnective> les tentatives visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13424">à</DiscourseConnective> blâmer une communauté tout entière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13461">pour</DiscourseConnective> les actions commises par une poignée de délinquants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12468" docOffset="76">
      <en>Romanians are facing ever-increasing problems on a daily basis, along with growing intimidation and fear.</en>
      <fr>Les Roumains sont confrontés au quotidien à des difficultés croissantes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13592">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à l'augmentation des manœuvres d'intimidation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12574" docOffset="77">
      <en>Let me give you just a few examples.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de vous donner quelques exemples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12611" docOffset="78">
      <en>There was a recent report in the press about a blatant case of discrimination.</en>
      <fr>Un rapport publié récemment dans la presse illustre un cas manifeste de discrimination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12690" docOffset="79">
      <en>The director of an Italian company providing telephone, cable and internet services advised his employees not to sign contracts with Romanian citizens.</en>
      <fr>Le directeur d'une société italienne fournissant des services de téléphone, câble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13866">et</DiscourseConnective> internet a recommandé à ses salariés de ne pas signer de contrats avec des citoyens roumains.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12842" docOffset="80">
      <en>In another example, a child, who was a Romanian national of Roma ethnic origin, suffered an injury, <Alignment alignment="18925" annotation_id="12942">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12942" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> none of the hospitals in the city of Messina wanted to admit him.</en>
      <fr>Un autre cas concerne un enfant roumain d'origine rom victime d'une blessure et <Alignment alignment="12942" annotation_id="14043">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14043" sense="Comparison.Contrast">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>aucun des hôpitaux de la ville de Messine n'a voulu accueillir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13012" docOffset="81">
      <en>He died on the way to Catania.</en>
      <fr>Il est décédé sur la route de Catane.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13043" docOffset="82">
      <en>These are just a few specific incidents. <Alignment alignment="20829" annotation_id="13084">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13084" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Romanians in Italy are facing similar censure almost every day.</en>
      <fr>Il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14154">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14161">que</DiscourseConnective> de quelques incidents isolés, <Alignment alignment="12399" annotation_id="14195">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14195" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les Roumains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14213">en</DiscourseConnective> Italie sont effectivement confrontés à une discrimination similaire chaque jour ou presque.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13157" docOffset="83">
      <en>I believe that clear notice must be given to the Italian Government at European level to halt the acts of discrimination against Romanian immigrants.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14317">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe doit envoyer un message clair au gouvernement italien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14384">pour qu'</DiscourseConnective>il mette fin à ces actes de discrimination à l'encontre des immigrés roumains.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13307" id="032" name="Derek Vaughan">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13307" docOffset="84">
      <en>Mr President, I was going to speak on the importance of European structural funds for regions like Wales post-2013, <Alignment alignment="14635" annotation_id="13423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13423" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I must respond to the comments made by Mr Batten earlier about a distinguished British politician and former Commissioner in the European Commission.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, j'avais l'intention de m'exprimer sur l'importance des Fonds structurels européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14582">pour</DiscourseConnective> les régions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14599">comme</DiscourseConnective> le pays de Galles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14623">après</DiscourseConnective> 2013, <Alignment alignment="10429" annotation_id="14635">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14635" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je me dois de répondre aux propos formulés précédemment par M. Batten concernant un homme politique distingué, ancien commissaire européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13577" docOffset="85">
      <en>To accuse such a person of treason is, I believe, to say the least, unparliamentary language, <Alignment alignment="14887" annotation_id="13671">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13671" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he should be ashamed of himself.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14780">À</DiscourseConnective> mes yeux, accuser une telle personne de trahison constitue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14841">pour</DiscourseConnective> le moins une attitude antiparlementaire, <Alignment alignment="7981" annotation_id="14887">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14887" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il devrait avoir honte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13708" docOffset="86">
      <en>I would ask him to withdraw those remarks, <Alignment alignment="14950" annotation_id="13751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13751" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13756" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> he will not, I think you, Mr President, should ask him to do so.</en>
      <fr>Je l'invite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14926">à</DiscourseConnective> retirer ces remarques <Alignment alignment="4510" annotation_id="14950">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14950" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans le cas contraire, je pense que vous, Monsieur le Président, devriez l'inviter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15037">à</DiscourseConnective> le faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13824" id="033" name="Ivo Vajgl">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13824" docOffset="87">
      <en>(SL) In this House, we will soon have the opportunity to hear from the candidate for the post of High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy.</en>
      <fr>(SL) Nous aurons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15066">bientôt</DiscourseConnective> l'occasion d'entendre dans cette Assemblée le candidat au poste de haut représentant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15159">pour</DiscourseConnective> les affaires étrangères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15188">et</DiscourseConnective> la politique de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13982" docOffset="88">
      <en>This will <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13992" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> be a kind of test for us and an indication of the influence which Europe can bring to bear on the peace process in the Middle East, as well as an answer to the question of whether the European Union can play an active role in resolving these problems at all.</en>
      <fr>Cette rencontre aura valeur de test <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15253">et</DiscourseConnective> nous donnera une idée l'influence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15290">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe est capable d'exercer pour soutenir le processus de paix au Moyen-Orient, et apportera une réponse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15402">à</DiscourseConnective> la question de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15426">si</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne peut jouer un rôle actif dans la résolution de ces problèmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14256" docOffset="89">
      <en>We have not had much success to date <Alignment alignment="7681" annotation_id="14293">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14293" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> my fellow Member who spoke previously has illustrated that in greater detail.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'avons guère été efficaces dans ce domaine jusqu'ici, <Alignment alignment="8655" annotation_id="15570">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15570" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'a illustré plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15594">en</DiscourseConnective> détail mon collègue qui s'est exprimé précédemment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14375" docOffset="90">
      <en>In recent days, the vicious circle of violence in the Middle East has continued.</en>
      <fr>Ces derniers jours, l'escalade de la violence s'est poursuivie au Moyen-Orient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14456" docOffset="91">
      <en>First, Hamas terrorists fired rockets, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14495" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> Israel retaliated disproportionately, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14538" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> once again it is difficult to distinguish between civilian and military casualties.</en>
      <fr>Des terroristes du Hamas ont commencé par tirer des roquettes, ce à quoi Israël a réagi de manière disproportionnée. Une fois de plus, il est difficile d'établir une distinction entre les victimes civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15934">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14626" docOffset="92">
      <en>I take the view that we must not, even for a moment, relax the efforts which we have to devote to the peace process in the Middle East.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15958">que</DiscourseConnective> nous ne devons pas relâcher, ne serait-ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16004">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un instant, les efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16031">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons déployer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16056">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur du processus de paix au Moyen-Orient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14762" id="034" name="Chris Davies">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14762" docOffset="93">
      <en>Mr President, soldiers from the United Kingdom and many other European nations are fighting and dying in Afghanistan. We are told that the reasons are to keep our country safe by preventing the return of al-Qaeda, or to protect democracy, or to fight drugs, or to support Pakistan, or to uphold the rights of women.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, des soldats du Royaume-Uni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16159">et</DiscourseConnective> de nombreuses autres nations européennes se battent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16214">et</DiscourseConnective> meurent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16225">en</DiscourseConnective> Afghanistan, soi-disant pour veiller <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16265">à</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité de notre pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16293">en</DiscourseConnective> empêchant le retour d'Al-Qaïda, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16328">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16331">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger la démocratie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16360">pour</DiscourseConnective> lutter contre la drogue, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16390">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16393">pour</DiscourseConnective> soutenir le Pakistan, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16420">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16423">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire respecter les droits des femmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15078" docOffset="94">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="33418" annotation_id="15078">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15078" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am no longer convinced by any of these explanations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="15078" annotation_id="16467">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16467" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je ne suis plus convaincu par aucune de ces explications.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15137" docOffset="95">
      <en>There is no clear political strategy, <Alignment alignment="11102" annotation_id="15175">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15175" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I do not know what the death of our soldiers is supposed to achieve.</en>
      <fr>Il n'existe aucune stratégie politique claire, <Alignment alignment="15175" annotation_id="16583">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16583" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ignore à quoi peut bien servir la mort de nos soldats.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15248" docOffset="96">
      <en>Far from bringing us security, I fear our presence is increasing the dangers, allowing us to be portrayed by Islamist extremists as foreign invaders supporting a government of warlords and drug barons in a civil war.</en>
      <fr>Au lieu de nous apporter la sécurité, je crains que notre présence n'accroisse les dangers, qu'elle permette aux extrémistes islamistes de nous dépeindre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16797">comme</DiscourseConnective> des envahisseurs étrangers soutenant un gouvernement de seigneurs de guerre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16879">et</DiscourseConnective> de barons de la drogue dans une guerre civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15465" docOffset="97">
      <en>Our actions foster the growth of radical, anti-Western Islamic beliefs.</en>
      <fr>Nos actions favorisent la croissance de croyances islamiques radicales antioccidentales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15537" docOffset="98">
      <en>We need a diplomatic strategy; we must talk with the Taliban, we must promote reconciliation and seek to broaden the composition of the current government <Alignment alignment="421" annotation_id="15692">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15692" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must be prepared to withdraw our soldiers from Afghan soil.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons besoin d'une stratégie diplomatique; nous devons discuter avec les talibans, promouvoir la réconciliation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17135">et</DiscourseConnective> tenter d'élargir la composition du gouvernement actuel. <Alignment alignment="14910" annotation_id="17194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17194" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons nous préparer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17223">à</DiscourseConnective> retirer nos soldats du sol afghan.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15759" id="035" name="Isabelle Durant">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15759" docOffset="99">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15778" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> you are aware, an agreement between the Belgian State and GDF Suez was reached in October 2009.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, vous le savez, un accord entre l'État belge <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17327">et</DiscourseConnective> GDF Suez a été conclu au mois d'octobre 2009.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15877" docOffset="100">
      <en>It extends and consolidates the monopoly held by GDF Suez until 2025.</en>
      <fr>Il prolonge <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17388">et</DiscourseConnective> il bétonne le monopole de GDF Suez jusque 2025.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15947" docOffset="101">
      <en>This goes entirely against liberalisation policies.</en>
      <fr>Ceci est tout à fait contraire aux politiques de libéralisation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15999" docOffset="102">
      <en>It <Alignment alignment="17159" annotation_id="16002">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16002" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> constitutes a decision that will confirm the monopoly of nuclear energy, which is going to make plans for renewable energies and related jobs considerably more challenging.</en>
      <fr>C'est <Alignment alignment="6788" annotation_id="17510">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17510" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une décision qui va confirmer le monopole du nucléaire, ce qui va rendre beaucoup plus difficiles les projets d'énergies renouvelables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17651">et</DiscourseConnective> tous les emplois qui y sont liés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16180" docOffset="103">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17688" annotation_id="16180">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16180" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we hear that the regulator, instead of being independent, is ultimately going to relinquish market surveillance and pricing to a follow-up committee on which GDF Suez is to sit, then I really do start to wonder.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="16180" annotation_id="17688">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17688" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on sait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17702">que</DiscourseConnective> le régulateur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17721">au lieu d'</DiscourseConnective>être un régulateur indépendant, va <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17766">finalement</DiscourseConnective> céder la surveillance du marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17809">et</DiscourseConnective> la fixation des prix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17833">à</DiscourseConnective> un comité de suivi dans lequel GDF Suez va siéger, je me pose vraiment des questions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16397" docOffset="104">
      <en>I hope the Commission is going to act in response and put its finger on a situation in which we find both judge and judged, monitor and monitored.</en>
      <fr>J'espère que la Commission aura une réaction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17966">et</DiscourseConnective> pourra mettre le doigt sur une situation où le juge est partie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18032">et</DiscourseConnective> est à la fois le surveillant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18064">et</DiscourseConnective> le surveillé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16544" docOffset="105">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="18090" annotation_id="16546">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16546" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hope that the Commission will respond, particularly on the eve of the Copenhagen Summit where energy issues - especially renewable energies - will, of course, be fundamental.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <Alignment alignment="16889" annotation_id="18090">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18090" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18095">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission réagira, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18122">surtout</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18130">à</DiscourseConnective> la veille du sommet de Copenhague, où les questions d'énergie - et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18199">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> d'énergies renouvelables - seront évidemment centrales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16731" docOffset="106">
      <en>I hope the Commission will make sure that Belgium does not see a so-called pax electrica, whose chief aim is to strengthen the monopoly held by Electrabel GDF Suez.</en>
      <fr>J'espère que la Commission sera attentive à ne pas laisser se faire en Belgique une soi-disant pax electrica, qui a surtout pour but de confirmer le monopole d'Electrabel GDF Suez.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16896" id="036" name="Joe Higgins">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16896" docOffset="107">
      <en>Mr President, tomorrow, tens of thousands of public sector workers in Ireland take national strike action.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, demain, des dizaines de milliers de travailleurs du secteur public <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18546">en</DiscourseConnective> Irlande se mettront en grève dans tout le pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17003" docOffset="108">
      <en>Low paid civil servants, nurses, teachers and local authority workers are sick of being scapegoated for a crisis in Irish and world capitalism and being forced to pay for that crisis, for which they are not responsible.</en>
      <fr>Les fonctionnaires des services publics, les infirmières, les enseignants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18671">et</DiscourseConnective> les travailleurs des autorités locales mal payés sont las d'être les boucs émissaires de la crise du capitalisme irlandais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18797">et</DiscourseConnective> mondial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18808">et</DiscourseConnective> d'être contraints de payer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18838">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette crise dont ils ne sont pas responsables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17223" docOffset="109">
      <en>I want, from this European Parliament, to send the warmest support to those workers on strike tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>J'invite ce Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18921">à</DiscourseConnective> manifester son soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18946">total</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18952">à</DiscourseConnective> ces travailleurs qui seront en grève demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17327" docOffset="110">
      <en>This Irish Government has no democratic mandate for its savage programme of cuts.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement irlandais ne possède aucun mandat démocratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19062">pour</DiscourseConnective> appliquer sa politique sauvage de restrictions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17409" docOffset="111">
      <en>I urge workers in Ireland to extend the action, to bring down this undemocratic government and force a general election, and let the people decide.</en>
      <fr>J'encourage les travailleurs d'Irlande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19154">à</DiscourseConnective> étendre leur action, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19177">à</DiscourseConnective> renverser ce gouvernement non démocratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19222">et</DiscourseConnective> à imposer des élections générales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19260">pour que</DiscourseConnective> se soit le peuple qui décide.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17557" docOffset="112">
      <en>The EU Council and Commission are <Alignment alignment="49561" annotation_id="17591">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17591" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> culpable in demanding savage cuts in Ireland.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19310">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sont <Alignment alignment="5463" annotation_id="19332">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19332" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> coupables, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19353">en ce sens qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils incitent l'Irlande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19390">à</DiscourseConnective> procéder à des restrictions sauvages.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17642" docOffset="113">
      <en>These institutions have even less credibility this week after another cynical deal between the EPP and the Social Democrats for the Presidency, and for appointing as High Representative for Foreign Affairs a lady who was never elected to a public assembly but derived the new position by being placed in a chamber of feudal fossils, as a result of being a Labour Party British trustee.</en>
      <fr>Or, la crédibilité de ces institutions a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19471">encore</DiscourseConnective> diminué cette semaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19500">après</DiscourseConnective> le nouvel accord cynique intervenu entre le PPE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19554">et</DiscourseConnective> les socio-démocrates <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19578">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Présidence, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19598">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19601">pour</DiscourseConnective> avoir désigné au poste de haut représentant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19650">pour</DiscourseConnective> les affaires étrangères une femme qui n'a jamais été élue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19713">à</DiscourseConnective> une assemblée publique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19739">mais</DiscourseConnective> a accédé à ce nouveau poste parce qu'elle faisait partie d'une chambre de fossiles féodaux et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19838">en</DiscourseConnective> raison de son appartenance au parti travailliste britannique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18028" docOffset="114">
      <en>Clearly, workers all over Europe have to stand up and fight, themselves, rather than depend on this neo-liberal majority in this Chamber.</en>
      <fr>À l'évidence, les travailleurs de toute l'Europe doivent se lever <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19969">et</DiscourseConnective> combattre eux-mêmes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19993">au lieu de</DiscourseConnective> compter sur la majorité néolibérale de cette Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18166" id="037" name="Andreas Mölzer">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18166" docOffset="115">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, one in seven Europeans belongs to an ethnic minority.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, un Européen sur sept appartient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20120">à</DiscourseConnective> une minorité ethnique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18239" docOffset="116">
      <en>In spite of this fact, protection for autochthonous minorities in Europe is not seen as a priority.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20145">En</DiscourseConnective> dépit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20154">de ce fait</DiscourseConnective>, la protection des minorités locales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20202">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe n'est pas considérée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20233">comme</DiscourseConnective> une priorité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18339" docOffset="117">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11248" annotation_id="18339">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18339" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Brussels never tires of taking all kinds of competences away from the Member States, the Commission, stating that it does not wish to interfere in internal affairs, has declared conflicts between minorities a matter for the states concerned.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9531" annotation_id="20253">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20253" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Bruxelles ne se lasse jamais de retirer des compétences en tout genre aux États membres, la Commission, manifestant sa décision de ne pas interférer dans les affaires intérieures, a déclaré que les conflits entre minorités relève de la compétence des pays concernés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18587" docOffset="118">
      <en>There is no unified approach in Europe.</en>
      <fr>Il n'existe aucune approche unifiée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20559">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18627" docOffset="119">
      <en>International law provisions are applied quite differently in different states.</en>
      <fr>Les dispositions de la législation internationale sont appliquées de manière très différente dans les différents États.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18707" docOffset="120">
      <en>France, <Alignment alignment="19623" annotation_id="18715">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18715" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, does not recognise any ethnic minorities and in Slovenia, the AVNOJ decisions still infringe international law.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3752" annotation_id="20690">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20690" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">À</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> titre d'exemple, la France ne reconnaît pas la moindre minorité ethnique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20765">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20768">en</DiscourseConnective> Slovénie, les décisions de l'AVNOJ enfreignent toujours le droit international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18840" docOffset="121">
      <en>In Austria, <Alignment alignment="6747" annotation_id="18852">
          <Alignment alignment="50381" annotation_id="18852">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18852" sense="Comparison.Contrast">on the other hand</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the Slovenian minority enjoys a full range of opportunities for development.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20851">En</DiscourseConnective> Autriche, <Alignment alignment="11063" annotation_id="20864">
          <Alignment alignment="13429" annotation_id="20864">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20864" sense="Comparison.Contrast">en revanche</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, la minorité slovène bénéficie d'un large éventail de possibilités en termes de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18948" docOffset="122">
      <en>In my view, these obvious discrepancies reflect a need for a European law on ethnic groups.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20971">À</DiscourseConnective> mes yeux, ces disparités évidentes illustrent la nécessité d'un droit européen sur les groupes ethniques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19040" docOffset="123">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="42521" annotation_id="19040">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19040" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europe wants to protect the ethnic diversity it has developed throughout history, it is vital to draw up an internationally binding European law on ethnic groups which covers autochthonous minorities.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7302" annotation_id="21079">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21079" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Europe souhaite protéger la diversité ethnique qu'elle a acquise au fil de son histoire, il importe d'établir un droit européen mondialement contraignant des groupes ethniques et qui couvrirait les minorités locales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19244" docOffset="124">
      <en>This would be an opportunity for the EU to prove that it pays more than just lip service to the protection of national diversity within Europe.</en>
      <fr>Ceci permettrait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21318">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne de prouver <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21350">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle ne formule pas que des vœux pieux en matière de protection de la diversité nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21443">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19388" id="038" name="Czesław Adam Siekierski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19388" docOffset="125">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, the ceremonies which took place on 9 November this year in Berlin on the 20th anniversary of the demolition of the Berlin Wall commemorated the unification of Germany.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, les cérémonies qui ont eu lieu le 9 novembre dernier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21535">à</DiscourseConnective> Berlin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21544">à</DiscourseConnective> l'occasion du 20e anniversaire de la chute du mur de Berlin ont commémoré l'unification de l'Allemagne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19575" docOffset="126">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="35469" annotation_id="19575">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19575" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, they <Alignment alignment="30057" annotation_id="19590">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19590" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> showed the route taken by Central and Eastern Europe to freedom and democracy, and to the end of the division, not only of Germany, but of the whole of Europe.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19575" annotation_id="21650">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21650" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, elles ont <Alignment alignment="403" annotation_id="21670">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21670" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mis en évidence la voie empruntée par l'Europe centrale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21736">et</DiscourseConnective> orientale vers la liberté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21765">et</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21783">et</DiscourseConnective> vers la fin de la division, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21814">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> de l'Allemagne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21844">mais</DiscourseConnective> de toute l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19755" docOffset="127">
      <en>Demolition of Berlin's wall of division was the end of that road, <Alignment alignment="25476" annotation_id="19821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19821" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the process of transformation in Central and Eastern Europe began with events on the Polish coast and the formation of Solidarity under the leadership of Lech Wałęsa in August 1980.</en>
      <fr>La chute du mur de la division à Berlin a marqué la fin de ce parcours, <Alignment alignment="6766" annotation_id="21940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21940" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le processus de transformation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21976">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe centrale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21995">et</DiscourseConnective> orientale a commencé avec des événements sur la côte polonaise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22061">et</DiscourseConnective> la formation de Solidarité sous l'égide de Lech Wałęsa <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22119">en</DiscourseConnective> août 1980.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20007" docOffset="128">
      <en>Let us <Alignment alignment="37544" annotation_id="20014">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20014" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remember the demonstrations for freedom in Hungary in 1956 and the June protests in Poznań, the events of 1968 in Czechoslovakia and the fallen shipyard workers in Gdańsk in 1970.</en>
      <fr>Rappelons-nous <Alignment alignment="12500" annotation_id="22148">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22148" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les manifestations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22177">pour</DiscourseConnective> la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22190">en</DiscourseConnective> Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22201">en</DiscourseConnective> 1956 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22209">et</DiscourseConnective> les protestations de juin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22238">à</DiscourseConnective> Poznań, les événements de 1968 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22271">en</DiscourseConnective> Tchécoslovaquie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22290">et</DiscourseConnective> les travailleurs des chantiers navals tombés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22338">à</DiscourseConnective> Gdańsk <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22347">en</DiscourseConnective> 1970.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20199" docOffset="129">
      <en>Many people were committed to the opposition in different countries, <Alignment alignment="36429" annotation_id="20268">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20268" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they fought for freedom and honour.</en>
      <fr>De nombreuses personnes se sont engagées dans l'opposition dans différents pays, <Alignment alignment="8908" annotation_id="22437">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22437" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elles ont lutté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22456">pour</DiscourseConnective> la liberté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22472">et</DiscourseConnective> l'honneur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20308" docOffset="130">
      <en>Some of them gave their lives.</en>
      <fr>Certaines ont donné leur vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20339" docOffset="131">
      <en>Let us revere and honour them.</en>
      <fr>Respectons-les <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22531">et</DiscourseConnective> honorons-les.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20370" docOffset="132">
      <en>Let us <Alignment alignment="13175" annotation_id="20377">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20377" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remember the politicians who displayed great imagination and determination in building freedom, democracy and a market economy.</en>
      <fr>Souvenons-nous <Alignment alignment="11663" annotation_id="22563">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22563" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des hommes politiques qui ont redoublé d'imagination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22626">et</DiscourseConnective> de détermination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22646">pour</DiscourseConnective> bâtir la liberté, la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22683">et</DiscourseConnective> l'économie de marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20510" id="039" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20510" docOffset="133">
      <en>Colleagues, I interrupt the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance in order to make an announcement.</en>
      <fr>Chers collègues, j'interromps les interventions d'une minute sur des questions politiques importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22810">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire une annonce.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
