<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>1.</en>
    <fr>1.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Adaption of Title IV of the EC Treaty - Court of Justice (vote)</en>
    <fr>Adaptation des dispositions du titre IV du traité CE relatives aux compétences de la Cour de justice des Communautés européennes (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="67" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Szájer report</en>
    <fr>- Rapport Szájer</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="83" docOffset="3">
    <en>- Before the vote</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="158">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="101" id="102" name="József Szájer ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="101" docOffset="4">
      <en>rapporteur. - (HU) The European Parliament is duty bound to provide for European citizens' legal protection.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (HU) Le Parlement européen a le devoir de garantir la protection juridique aux citoyens européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="210" docOffset="5">
      <en>Here in the EP, there is widespread support for the Treaty establishing a Constitution for Europe, which would be a great step forward from the point of view of the Court's jurisdiction.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen soutient largement le traité établissant une constitution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="365">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe, qui constituerait un grand pas en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="414">avant</DiscourseConnective> du point de vue des compétences de la Cour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="397" docOffset="6">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="464" annotation_id="397">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="397" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we are in the fortunate position of not having to wait in this matter for the birth of the Constitutional Treaty, <Alignment alignment="578" annotation_id="525">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="525" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Treaty of Amsterdam provides for a transition, a 'passerelle'.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="397" annotation_id="464">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="464" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous avons la chance dans ce domaine de ne pas devoir attendre la naissance du traité constitutionnel, <Alignment alignment="403" annotation_id="578">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="578" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le traité d'Amsterdam prévoit une transition, une passerelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="595" docOffset="7">
      <en>The report I have tabled clearly advocates implementing the transition, or 'passerelle', extending <Alignment alignment="757" annotation_id="694">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="694" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice to matters concerning the European visa, as well as to refugee and immigration policies.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport que j'ai déposé plaide clairement pour la mise en œuvre de la transition, la passerelle, étendant <Alignment alignment="694" annotation_id="757">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="757" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les compétences de la Cour de justice des communautés européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="829">à</DiscourseConnective> des domaines concernant le visa européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="872">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'aux politiques relatives aux réfugiés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="919">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'immigration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="841" docOffset="8">
      <en>This guarantees total legal protection for European citizens.</en>
      <fr>Cela garantit une protection juridique complète aux citoyens européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="903" docOffset="9">
      <en>My proposal would <Alignment alignment="1038" annotation_id="921">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="921" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> make it possible to strengthen European legal safeguards with regard to fundamental rights.</en>
      <fr>Ma proposition permettrait <Alignment alignment="921" annotation_id="1038">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1038" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de renforcer les protections juridiques européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1095">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les droits fondamentaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1018" docOffset="10">
      <en>In this way I wish to facilitate the uniform interpretation and application of Community rules and laws, and the creation of a unified system of legal safeguards.</en>
      <fr>De cette manière, je souhaite faciliter l'interprétation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1196">et</DiscourseConnective> l'application uniformes des règles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1234">et</DiscourseConnective> des législations communautaires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1270">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la création d'un système unifié de protections juridiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1181" docOffset="11">
      <en>This is not the first time Parliament calls upon the Council to speed up the adoption of this transitional clause, the 'passerelle', in order to remove the limitations on the Court's competence with regard to Article 4 of the Treaty.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est pas la première fois que le Parlement demande au Conseil d'accélérer l'adoption de cette clause transitoire, la passerelle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1472">afin de</DiscourseConnective> lever les limites aux compétences de la Cour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1525">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne l'article 4 du Traité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1415" docOffset="12">
      <en>I ask Parliament to support my proposal.</en>
      <fr>Je demande au Parlement de soutenir ma proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
