<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Single European Sky (debate)</en>
    <fr>Ciel unique européen (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="29" id="219" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="29" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the oral question to the Commission on building the single European sky through functional airspace blocks final) by Paolo Costa, on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism - B6-0135/2007).</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle la question orale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="71">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur la création de blocs d'espace aérien fonctionnels pour l'établissement du ciel unique européen final) de Paolo Costa, au nom de la commission des transports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="248">et</DiscourseConnective> du tourisme - B6-0135/2007).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="245" id="220" name="Gilles Savary ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="245" docOffset="2">
      <en>author. - (FR) Mr President, I must first render the things that are SESAR's unto SESAR, or to another Italian, Paolo Costa, who is actually the author of this written question and has asked me to stand in for him and put it to you in his absence.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - Monsieur le Président, il faut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="321">d'abord</DiscourseConnective> rendre à César ce qui lui appartient, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="367">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="370">à</DiscourseConnective> un autre Italien, c'est-à-dire à Paolo Costa, qui est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="426">en réalité</DiscourseConnective> le véritable auteur de cette question écrite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="482">et</DiscourseConnective> qui m'a demandé de bien vouloir me substituer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="531">à</DiscourseConnective> lui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="537">en</DiscourseConnective> son absence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="552">et</DiscourseConnective> devant vous pour la poser.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="493" docOffset="3">
      <en>This is an oral question to the Commission with debate on the creation of functional airspace blocks for building the Single European Sky, <Alignment alignment="768" annotation_id="632">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="632" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the intentions of the Commission regarding the implementation, or progress to date in the implementation of the package of texts which were the subject of conciliation in December 2003, 'the Single Sky package'</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="585">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'une question orale avec débat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="624">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur l'état des lieux en matière de création de blocs d'espace aérien fonctionnels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="722">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'établissement du ciel unique européen, <Alignment alignment="22536" annotation_id="768">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="768" sense="Expansion.Restatement">autrement dit</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, sur les intentions de la Commission eu égard à la mise en œuvre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="848">ou</DiscourseConnective> à l'état d'avancement de la mise en œuvre tel que l'on peut le constater aujourd'hui, du paquet de textes qui avait donné lieu à une conciliation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="997">en</DiscourseConnective> décembre 2003 et que l'on a appelé "le paquet ciel unique".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="859" docOffset="4">
      <en>One of the texts provided for the creation of functional airspace blocks, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="933" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective> airline routes at the various airspace levels, in order to optimise consumption, reduce greenhouse gases and if possible reduce congestion at the busiest airports, not forgetting the possibility of bringing down air transport costs.</en>
      <fr>Un de ces textes prévoyait le réagencement des blocs d'espace fonctionnels, c'est-à-dire des routes des avions de ligne aux différents étages de l'espace aérien, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1222">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>optimiser la consommation, de réduire les gaz à effet de serre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1292">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1296">si</DiscourseConnective> possible, de réduire l'encombrement des aéroports les plus sollicités, sans oublier la possibilité de faire baisser le coût du transport aérien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1181" docOffset="5">
      <en>This is a particularly sensitive issue, with reservations on the part of the Member States, which have always reaffirmed their sovereignty over their airspace.</en>
      <fr>Le dossier est particulièrement sensible, avec des réticences des États membres qui ont toujours réaffirmé leur souveraineté sur leur espace aérien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1341" docOffset="6">
      <en>That is especially true of the Member States - and I know of one that is dear to me, my own country - which have large military forces and military airspace blocks reserved in a virtually discretionary fashion.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1599">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> le cas des États membres - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1641">et</DiscourseConnective> j'en connais un qui m'est cher, celui dont je suis originaire - qui disposent d'une force militaire importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1755">et</DiscourseConnective> de blocs d'espace militaire réservés de façon quasi discrétionnaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1552" docOffset="7">
      <en>Mr Costa is concerned that, <Alignment alignment="1982" annotation_id="1580">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1580" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we might have feared, no progress has been made, as far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1639" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> he can see, on that text on the creation of airspace blocks, one of the four on the Single Sky, <Alignment alignment="39925" annotation_id="1738">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1738" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it has met with strong resistance from the Member States.</en>
      <fr>La préoccupation de Paolo Costa est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1863">que</DiscourseConnective> ce texte - un des quatre sur le ciel unique - sur le réagencement des blocs d'espace n'a, semble-t-il, pas avancé, <Alignment alignment="1580" annotation_id="1982">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1982" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que l'on pouvait le craindre, <Alignment alignment="1738" annotation_id="2018">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2018" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'il a fait l'objet de très grandes résistances de la part des États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1800" docOffset="8">
      <en>Mr Costa is <Alignment alignment="2120" annotation_id="1812">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1812" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> putting the following question to the Commission.</en>
      <fr>La question qui est <Alignment alignment="9175" annotation_id="2120">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2120" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> posée par Paolo Costa <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2147">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission est la suivante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1872" docOffset="9">
      <en>The Commission has just produced a communication making it clear that the cost of not having functional airspace blocks for building a Single European Sky is about EUR 1 billion.</en>
      <fr>Une communication vient d'être produite par la Commission qui avoue clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2259">que</DiscourseConnective> le coût de l'absence de blocs d'espace aérien fonctionnels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2322">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'établissement du ciel unique européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2367">s'</DiscourseConnective>élève environ à 1 milliard d'euros.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2051" docOffset="10">
      <en>Mr Costa has put an initial question: is the Commission satisfied with that situation and does it believe that the introduction of Regulation (EC) No 551/2004 on airspace organisation is progressing satisfactorily?</en>
      <fr>Paolo Costa pose une première question: la Commission peut-elle se satisfaire d'une telle situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2505">et</DiscourseConnective> considère-t-elle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2525">que</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place du règlement (CE) n° 551/2004, relatif à l'organisation de l'espace aérien, se déroule de manière satisfaisante?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2266" docOffset="11">
      <en>How does the Commission account for the fact that no new functional airspace blocks have become operational <Alignment alignment="2775" annotation_id="2374">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2374" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Regulation came into force?</en>
      <fr>Comment la Commission explique-t-elle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2697">qu'</DiscourseConnective>aucun nouveau bloc d'espace aérien fonctionnel ne soit devenu opérationnel <Alignment alignment="2374" annotation_id="2775">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2775" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">depuis</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2791">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur de ce règlement?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2412" docOffset="12">
      <en>Article 10 of the Regulation provides for an extension of airspace organisation to lower airspace and requires the Commission to determine any other steps that might be necessary 'in the light of progress achieved'.</en>
      <fr>L'article 10 de ce règlement prévoit que l'organisation de l'espace aérien soit étendue à l'espace aérien inférieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2935">et</DiscourseConnective> demande à la Commission de prévoir toute autre mesure appropriée "compte tenu des progrès accomplis".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2628" docOffset="13">
      <en>In view of that, what changes does the Commission think should be made to existing legislation?</en>
      <fr>Sur cette base, quelles sont les modifications que la Commission juge opportunes d'apporter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3132">à</DiscourseConnective> la législation actuelle?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2724" docOffset="14">
      <en>Finally, does the Commission agree that it should not wait until the end of 2008 <Alignment alignment="12641" annotation_id="2805">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2805" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> bringing forward a proposal to that effect?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3159">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, la Commission serait-elle d'accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3201">pour</DiscourseConnective> ne pas attendre la fin de 2008 <Alignment alignment="2805" annotation_id="3237">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3237" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> proposer une proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3267">en</DiscourseConnective> ce sens?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2856" docOffset="15">
      <en>Finally - there is more than one question in the oral question - Mr Costa is asking whether the Commission agrees that the 'bottom up' approach, whereby the initiative to create functional airspace blocks is left to the Member States, has failed <Alignment alignment="7117" annotation_id="3102">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3102" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that a more proactive approach by the European Union is now required?</en>
      <fr>Dernière question de Paolo Costa - il y a donc plusieurs questions dans une: la Commission convient-elle de l'échec de l'approche ascendante qui a laissé aux États membres le soin de créer entre eux des blocs d'espace aérien fonctionnels <Alignment alignment="13536" annotation_id="3517">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3517" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ne pense-t-elle pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3540">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est nécessaire désormais d'adopter une approche plus volontariste de la part de l'Union européenne?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3176" docOffset="16">
      <en>I think, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3185" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I hope I have remained true to its spirit, that that is the question Mr Costa is putting to the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Voilà, mes chers collègues, je crois, sans en avoir trahi l'esprit, la question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3726">que</DiscourseConnective> pose Paolo Costa <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3747">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3297" id="221" name="Jacques Barrot">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3297" docOffset="17">
      <en>Vice-President of the Commission. - (FR) Mr Savary, I thank you and, through you, Mr Costa, <Alignment alignment="3890" annotation_id="3389">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3389" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I think this question has been very well put and the problem it raises is a real one.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - Monsieur Savary, je vous remercie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3844">et</DiscourseConnective> je remercie aussi à travers vous M. Costa, <Alignment alignment="3389" annotation_id="3890">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3890" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je trouve que cette question est très bien posée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3943">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'elle correspond à un vrai problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3483" docOffset="18">
      <en>The reform in March 2004 was intended to organise air traffic in line with operational requirements, not national borders.</en>
      <fr>La réforme de mars 2004 visait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4016">à</DiscourseConnective> organiser le trafic aérien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4045">en</DiscourseConnective> fonction des besoins opérationnels et non pas en fonction des frontières nationales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3606" docOffset="19">
      <en>It is a way of shortening flights and avoiding aircraft flying around unnecessarily.</en>
      <fr>C'est le moyen de raccourcir les trajets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4174">et</DiscourseConnective> d'éviter que les avions tournent dans le ciel inutilement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3691" docOffset="20">
      <en>I shall answer each of the questions.</en>
      <fr>Je vais répondre aux différentes questions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3729" docOffset="21">
      <en>The first concerns the cost of air traffic management and the repercussions for the Single Sky.</en>
      <fr>La première porte sur le coût de la gestion du trafic aérien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4341">et</DiscourseConnective> le bilan du ciel unique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3825" docOffset="22">
      <en>You and Mr Costa have just quoted the key figure of EUR 1 billion <Alignment alignment="4447" annotation_id="3891">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3891" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Single Sky is not implemented, <Alignment alignment="5451" annotation_id="3929">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3929" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I might add that, according to Eurocontrol, the potential savings are even greater, <Alignment alignment="4588" annotation_id="4017">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4017" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> EUR 3 billion could be saved.</en>
      <fr>M. Costa et vous-même venez de rappeler le chiffre-clé de un milliard d'euros <Alignment alignment="7578" annotation_id="4447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4447" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le ciel unique ne devient pas une réalité, <Alignment alignment="12641" annotation_id="4493">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4493" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ajouterais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4509">que</DiscourseConnective> les économies potentielles sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4545">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus importantes selon Eurocontrol, <Alignment alignment="4017" annotation_id="4588">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4588" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> trois milliards d'euros pourraient être économisés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4053" docOffset="23">
      <en>In addition to the reduction in airline costs, a saving of two billion would be achieved through the improved efficiency of aviation services.</en>
      <fr>Outre la réduction des coûts pour les compagnies aériennes, deux milliards seraient liés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4737">à</DiscourseConnective> l'amélioration de l'efficacité des services de navigation aérienne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4196" docOffset="24">
      <en>It is true that, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4213" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> Mr Savary says, completion of the Single European Sky is not progressing quickly enough, given the importance of the objectives: competitiveness, sustainable development, combating climate change and promoting safety in the air.</en>
      <fr>Il est vrai, Monsieur Savary, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4837">que</DiscourseConnective> la réalisation du ciel unique européen ne progresse pas suffisamment vite compte tenu de l'importance des objectifs: objectifs de compétitivité, de développement durable, de lutte contre le changement climatique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5053">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité aérienne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4445" docOffset="25">
      <en>Should we, for that reason, stand there with our arms folded and do nothing?</en>
      <fr>Devons-nous, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5091">pour autant</DiscourseConnective>, rester les bras croisés, à ne rien faire?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4522" docOffset="26">
      <en>No.</en>
      <fr>Non.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4526" docOffset="27">
      <en>For the first time, the adoption of basic rules on the Single Sky has given the Community real powers in this area.</en>
      <fr>L'adoption des règlements de base sur le ciel unique a doté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5211">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois la Communauté de véritables pouvoirs dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4642" docOffset="28">
      <en>The 2004 reform has been implemented: separation between regulation and the provision of services, certification of providers in accordance with European rules, air traffic controllers' licences and a range of technical measures adopted by comitology.</en>
      <fr>La réforme de 2004 a été mise en œuvre: séparation entre la réglementation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5362">et</DiscourseConnective> la prestation des services, certification des prestataires selon les règles européennes, licence de contrôleur aérien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5483">et</DiscourseConnective> nombreuses mesures techniques adoptées par comitologie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4894" docOffset="29">
      <en>Lastly, there has been the launch of the SESAR industrial project, a real addition to the Single Sky.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5542">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, lancement du projet industriel CESAR, véritable complément du ciel unique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4996" docOffset="30">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5624" annotation_id="4996">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4996" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we need to move faster.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4996" annotation_id="5624">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5624" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il faut accélérer le mouvement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5024" docOffset="31">
      <en>The Commission must take stock of what has been done.</en>
      <fr>La Commission doit dresser un bilan de ce qui a été fait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5078" docOffset="32">
      <en>Back in December 2006, I consulted a group of high-level experts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5143" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this July they presented their report to me on the reforms that are imperative.</en>
      <fr>Dès décembre 2006, j'ai saisi un groupe d'experts à haut niveau qui vient de me rendre son rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5818">en</DiscourseConnective> juillet sur les réformes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5846">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut absolument mettre en œuvre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5227" docOffset="33">
      <en>The Commission will be submitting a communication based on that this autumn.</en>
      <fr>La Commission présentera cet automne une communication sur cette base.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5304" docOffset="34">
      <en>The second question relates to functional airspace blocks.</en>
      <fr>La deuxième question porte sur les blocs d'espace fonctionnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5363" docOffset="35">
      <en>It is true that in the 2004 reform the Council opted for a bottom-up approach, with action by the national governments on the creation of the blocks.</en>
      <fr>Il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6031">que</DiscourseConnective> dans le cadre de la réforme de 2004, le Conseil a choisi une approche bottom-up, c'est-à-dire du bas vers le haut, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6150">à</DiscourseConnective> travers l'action des administrations nationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6200">pour</DiscourseConnective> la constitution de ces blocs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5513" docOffset="36">
      <en>Frankly, that was not an entirely satisfactory approach, <Alignment alignment="6299" annotation_id="5570">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5570" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it limited the possibilities for the Commission and the Community institutions to ensure that the blocks were actually created <Alignment alignment="6421" annotation_id="5705">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5705" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that work at local level did not become bogged down.</en>
      <fr>Franchement, cette approche n'est pas pleinement satisfaisante, <Alignment alignment="5570" annotation_id="6299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6299" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle réduit la capacité de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6344">et</DiscourseConnective> des institutions communautaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6379">pour que</DiscourseConnective> les blocs deviennent une réalité <Alignment alignment="5705" annotation_id="6421">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6421" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6424">que</DiscourseConnective> les efforts au niveau local ne s'enlisent pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5762" docOffset="37">
      <en>Another part of the problem is that insufficient stress was placed on improving the economic efficiency of the service provided.</en>
      <fr>Une autre partie du problème est l'accent insuffisant mis sur l'amélioration de l'efficacité économique du service fourni.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5891" docOffset="38">
      <en>We are going to try and introduce a performance-based approach by the first half of 2008.</en>
      <fr>Nous allons essayer d'introduire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6632">pour</DiscourseConnective> le premier semestre 2008, une approche basée sur la performance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5981" docOffset="39">
      <en>That would set specific performance targets for service providers and provide for incentives and intervention mechanisms in the event of non-completion.</en>
      <fr>Cette approche devrait fixer des objectifs spécifiques de performance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6772">pour</DiscourseConnective> les prestataires de services <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6806">et</DiscourseConnective> prévoir des incitations, des mécanismes d'intervention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6864">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de non-réalisation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6134" docOffset="40">
      <en>I believe that that performance-based approach will speed up the creation of functional blocks, <Alignment alignment="7004" annotation_id="6230">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6230" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they will be essential to the achievement of the performance targets.</en>
      <fr>Je considère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6904">que</DiscourseConnective> cette approche basée sur la performance permettra d'accélérer la création de blocs fonctionnels <Alignment alignment="6230" annotation_id="7004">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7004" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils seront indispensables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7034">pour</DiscourseConnective> atteindre des objectifs de performance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6308" docOffset="41">
      <en>We are working on the idea of a performance review body and a coordinator responsible for developing the projects more quickly.</en>
      <fr>Nous travaillons sur l'idée d'un groupe de surveillance de la performance, un performance review body, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7182">et</DiscourseConnective> d'un coordinateur chargé de développer plus rapidement ces projets.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6436" docOffset="42">
      <en>I personally think that a coordinator of the kind we have for the trans-European networks would be very useful in speeding up the creation of these functional blocks that we need.</en>
      <fr>Je crois personnellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7278">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un coordinateur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7298">comme</DiscourseConnective> nous en avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7318">pour</DiscourseConnective> les réseaux transeuropéens, serait très utile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7369">pour</DiscourseConnective> activer la constitution de ces blocs fonctionnels dont nous avons besoin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6616" docOffset="43">
      <en>We shall not, of course, be waiting until 2009 to accelerate the creation and efficiency of the functional blocks.</en>
      <fr>Bien sûr, nous n'attendrons pas 2009 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7485">pour</DiscourseConnective> accélérer la création <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7512">et</DiscourseConnective> l'efficacité des blocs fonctionnels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6731" docOffset="44">
      <en>I would hope to present you with an initiative by the middle of 2008.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais vous présenter une initiative mi-2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6801" docOffset="45">
      <en>It is generally agreed that the blocks can only be effective <Alignment alignment="7675" annotation_id="6862">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6862" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> upper and lower airspace are regarded as indivisible.</en>
      <fr>Il y a un consensus sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7635">que</DiscourseConnective> ces blocs ne peuvent être efficaces <Alignment alignment="6862" annotation_id="7675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7675" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'espace aérien supérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7708">et</DiscourseConnective> l'espace aérien inférieur sont considérés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7753">comme</DiscourseConnective> indivisibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6919" docOffset="46">
      <en>Lastly, the fourth question, the bottom-up approach of the Member States, which, it must be admitted, has in some ways been a failure.</en>
      <fr>Quatrième question, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7793">enfin</DiscourseConnective>, celle de l'approche bottom-up des États membres qui a, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7855">en</DiscourseConnective> partie, échoué, il faut bien le reconnaître.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7054" docOffset="47">
      <en>In that case, should we adopt exactly the opposite approach?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7903">Pour autant</DiscourseConnective>, devons-nous complètement prendre l'approche inverse?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7115" docOffset="48">
      <en>I am not sure.</en>
      <fr>Je n'en suis pas sûr.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7130" docOffset="49">
      <en>I think we still have to try and make the best of the bottom-up approach, <Alignment alignment="25891" annotation_id="7204">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7204" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in order to develop a Single Sky we need to move on to a second stage, based on performance, on mechanisms.</en>
      <fr>Je crois qu'il faut essayer de continuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8032">à</DiscourseConnective> tirer parti de cette approche bottom-up <Alignment alignment="7204" annotation_id="8074">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8074" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il faut passer à une deuxième étape axée sur la performance, sur les mécanismes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8160">pour</DiscourseConnective> développer le ciel unique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7316" docOffset="50">
      <en>We have to cooperate actively with the Member States to encourage political commitment and exercise pressure from above to develop functional airspace blocks.</en>
      <fr>Il faut travailler activement avec les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8245">pour</DiscourseConnective> augmenter l'engagement politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8283">et</DiscourseConnective> exercer une pression de haut en bas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8322">pour</DiscourseConnective> le développement des blocs fonctionnels d'espace aérien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7475" docOffset="51">
      <en>That is why this question was so welcome. It has given me an opportunity to explain the main initiatives we shall be taking, which are in line with the very pertinent comments made by Mr Savary.</en>
      <fr>Voilà pourquoi je pense, Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, que cette question était la bienvenue, qu'elle me permet d'indiquer les principales initiatives que nous allons prendre dans le droit fil de ce que vient d'exposer, à mon avis fort justement, M. Savary.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7670" id="222" name="Georg Jarzembowski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7670" docOffset="52">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (DE) Mr President, Mr Vice-President of the Commission, we have no problems at all with what you have achieved in terms of improving efficiency in airspace, <Alignment alignment="8881" annotation_id="7860">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7860" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> your reply was quite clear.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (DE) M. le Président, M. le Vice-président de la Commission, nous n'avons aucune objection s'agissant de tout ce que vous avez accompli <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8833">pour</DiscourseConnective> améliorer l'efficacité de l'espace aérien, <Alignment alignment="7860" annotation_id="8881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8881" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> votre réponse était assez claire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7892" docOffset="53">
      <en>That reply was to the effect that Member States have not done their homework.</en>
      <fr>Celle-ci indiquait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8939">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres n'ont pas rempli leur tâche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7970" docOffset="54">
      <en>Member States have not met the obligation that has existed since 2004 rapidly to create functional airspace blocks.</en>
      <fr>Ils n'ont pas respecté leur obligation de 2004 qui leur demandait de créer rapidement des blocs d'espace aérien fonctionnels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8086" docOffset="55">
      <en>On the one hand that results in the costs you referred to of up to EUR 3 billion, and <Alignment alignment="9215" annotation_id="8172">
          <Alignment alignment="9215" annotation_id="8172">
            <Alignment alignment="13050" annotation_id="8172">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8172" sense="Comparison.Contrast">on the other hand</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> it <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8193" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> leads to environmental pollution.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9116">D'une part</DiscourseConnective>, cela se ressent dans les coûts que vous indiquiez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9178">à</DiscourseConnective> hauteur de 3 milliards d'euros, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9212">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="8172" annotation_id="9215">
          <Alignment alignment="8172" annotation_id="9215">
            <Alignment alignment="8172" annotation_id="9215">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9215" sense="Comparison.Contrast">d'autre part</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, cela entraîne une pollution environnementale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8232" docOffset="56">
      <en>At the moment, we are discussing the introduction of emission trading in air transport, talking about 3% of air transport emissions.</en>
      <fr>Nous débattons actuellement de l'introduction de l'échange de quotas d'émissions dans le transport aérien, environ 3 % des émissions du transport aérien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8365" docOffset="57">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9429" annotation_id="8365">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8365" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we had sensible, rapid and efficient air transport management we could reduce fuel consumption by up to 12%, which would substantially reduce CO2 emissions.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8365" annotation_id="9429">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9429" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous disposions d'une gestion du transport aérien sensée, rapide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9497">et</DiscourseConnective> efficace, nous pourrions réduire la consommation de 12 %, ce qui réduirait sensiblement les émissions de CO2.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8525" docOffset="58">
      <en>Mr Vice-President, you are a gentleman, <Alignment alignment="9656" annotation_id="8565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8565" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> let us get to the crux of the matter: the Member States are not doing their homework.</en>
      <fr>M. le Vice-président, vous êtes un gentleman, <Alignment alignment="8565" annotation_id="9656">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9656" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> entrons dans le vif du sujet: les États membres ne remplissent pas leurs obligations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8655" docOffset="59">
      <en>That is why we - you as the Commission and we as Parliament - must all tell the Member States: detention time!</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9747">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> - vous en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9772">tant que</DiscourseConnective> Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9792">et</DiscourseConnective> nous en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9803">tant que</DiscourseConnective> Parlement - nous devons tous dire aux États membres: punition!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8766" docOffset="60">
      <en>You have to catch up quickly now <Alignment alignment="9915" annotation_id="8799">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8799" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> falling so far behind.</en>
      <fr>Vous devez remonter la pente rapidement <Alignment alignment="8799" annotation_id="9915">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9915" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être tombés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9933">si</DiscourseConnective> bas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8828" docOffset="61">
      <en>Yet that may not be enough.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9941">Et</DiscourseConnective> cela risque encore de ne pas suffire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8856" docOffset="62">
      <en>We must <Alignment alignment="32418" annotation_id="8864">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8864" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> threaten them with changing the bottom-up-, bottom-down approach.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="24182" annotation_id="9994">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9994" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les menacer de changer la démarche "de bas en haut", "de bas en bas".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8935" docOffset="63">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10074" annotation_id="8935">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8935" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Member States cannot manage to make progress on the truly vital question of air safety, air efficiency, the impact of air transport on the climate, then we expect that in 2008 the Commission will not just present a report saying that the Member States are improving in terms of creating airspace blocks, <Alignment alignment="10453" annotation_id="9242">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9242" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that it will threaten the Member States.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8935" annotation_id="10074">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10074" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les États membres ne parviennent pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10114">à</DiscourseConnective> progresser sur cette question véritablement essentielle de la sécurité aérienne, de l'efficacité aérienne, de l'impact du transport aérien sur le climat, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10270">alors</DiscourseConnective> nous prévoyons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10291">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> 2008, la Commission ne présentera pas seulement un rapport indiquant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10366">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10388">s'</DiscourseConnective>améliorent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10401">s'</DiscourseConnective>agissant de la création de blocs d'espace aérien, <Alignment alignment="9242" annotation_id="10453">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10453" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10458">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle menacera les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9287" docOffset="64">
      <en>You can rely on our help.</en>
      <fr>Vous pouvez compter sur notre aide.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9313" docOffset="65">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10543" annotation_id="9313">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9313" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will have to change the system and create the airspace blocks at European level.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrons <Alignment alignment="9313" annotation_id="10543">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10543" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> modifier le système <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10571">et</DiscourseConnective> créer des blocs d'espace aérien au niveau européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9402" docOffset="66">
      <en>That is the stick we need in order to persuade Member States rapidly to create efficient, functional airspace blocks.</en>
      <fr>C'est la menace qu'il nous faut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10658">pour</DiscourseConnective> persuader les États membres de créer rapidement des blocs d'espace aérien fonctionnels efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9520" docOffset="67">
      <en>I know how difficult that is, <Alignment alignment="10794" annotation_id="9550">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9550" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> kind words will get us nowhere.</en>
      <fr>Je sais combien c'est difficile, <Alignment alignment="12922" annotation_id="10794">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10794" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de belles paroles ne nous mèneront nulle part.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9586" docOffset="68">
      <en>We must slowly begin to wave the big stick.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons commencer doucement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10878">à</DiscourseConnective> agiter le bâton.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9630" id="223" name="Brian Simpson">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9630" docOffset="69">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - Mr President, I am so long in this Parliament that I recall the occasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9733" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> Commissioner de Palacio first proposed the Single European Sky and the term 'functional airspace blocks' first entered EU vocabulary.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, cela fait tellement longtemps que je siège dans ce Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11010">que</DiscourseConnective> je me souviens de la fois où le commissaire de Palacio a proposé pour la première fois le ciel unique européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11125">et</DiscourseConnective> le terme "bloc d'espace fonctionnel aérien" qui a été le premier à entrer dans le vocabulaire européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9872" docOffset="70">
      <en>Well, after a painful birth, progress was made in 2004 with the regulation that enacted these airspace blocks, <Alignment alignment="11371" annotation_id="9983">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9983" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I have to say that since then progress has been painfully slow, particularly in regard to the extension of those airspace blocks and specifically as regards lower airspace.</en>
      <fr>Eh bien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11240">après</DiscourseConnective> une naissance douloureuse, des progrès ont été faits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11299">en</DiscourseConnective> 2004 avec la réglementation qui a adopté ces blocs d'espace aériens, <Alignment alignment="9983" annotation_id="11371">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11371" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je dois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11384">dire que</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11393">depuis</DiscourseConnective>, les progrès ont été terriblement lents, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11441">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11456">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne l'extension de ces blocs aériens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11508">et</DiscourseConnective> l'espace aérien inférieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10160" docOffset="71">
      <en>I appreciate, Commissioner, that it was the Commission's intention to work with Member States and no doubt some Member States have proved to be less willing to pursue this policy at the pace that we would like or, indeed, had envisaged, <Alignment alignment="11830" annotation_id="10397">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10397" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> surely the time is now right to find the accelerator pedal and for the Commission now to come forward with a directive as soon as possible.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, j'apprécie le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11582">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est la Commission qui envisageait de travailler avec les États membres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11660">et</DiscourseConnective> il fait aucun doute que certains États membres se sont montrés moins disposés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11741">à</DiscourseConnective> poursuivre cette politique au rythme auquel nous voudrions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11802">ou</DiscourseConnective> que nous avions envisagé <Alignment alignment="10397" annotation_id="11830">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11830" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est certainement le bon moment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11868">pour</DiscourseConnective> trouver la pédale d'accélérateur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11906">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11909">pour que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission propose une directive le plus tôt possible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10541" docOffset="72">
      <en>Since 2004, no new airspace blocks have been created <Alignment alignment="12037" annotation_id="10594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10594" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="12041" annotation_id="10599">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10599" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have heard from previous speakers, the cost of that in our failure to create a Single European Sky is estimated to be at EUR 1 billion.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11976">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> 2004, aucun nouveau bloc d'espace aérien n'a été créé <Alignment alignment="10594" annotation_id="12037">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12037" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="10599" annotation_id="12041">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12041" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12047">que</DiscourseConnective> les intervenants précédents l'ont dit, le coût de notre échec dans la non-création d'un Ciel Unique européen est estimé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12171">à</DiscourseConnective> 1 milliard EUR.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10741" docOffset="73">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12189" annotation_id="10741">
          <Alignment alignment="12189" annotation_id="10741">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10741" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the existing legislation is in need of updating and the travelling public are still faced on a daily basis with air traffic delays, due to the antiquated attitudes of Member States and what appears to be inactivity by the Commission.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10741" annotation_id="12189">
          <Alignment alignment="10741" annotation_id="12189">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12189" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, la législation en vigueur doit être mise à jour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12246">et</DiscourseConnective> le public-voyageurs sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12274">encore</DiscourseConnective> quotidiennement confrontés à des retards dans le trafic aérien dus aux attitudes vieillottes des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12392">et</DiscourseConnective> à ce qui semble être de l'inactivité de la part de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10988" docOffset="74">
      <en>Patience is running out, <Alignment alignment="12487" annotation_id="11013">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11013" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> action is needed urgently.</en>
      <fr>La patience a des limites <Alignment alignment="11013" annotation_id="12487">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12487" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des mesures sont nécessaires dans les plus brefs délais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11044" docOffset="75">
      <en>Failure to act is not an option, which is why my Group will support the oral question placed before Parliament by Mr Costa, on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism.</en>
      <fr>Le défaut d'agir n'est pas une option, et c'est la raison pour laquelle mon groupe apportera son soutien à la question orale posée devant le Parlement par Monsieur Costa, au nom de la commission des transports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12757">et</DiscourseConnective> du tourisme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11221" docOffset="76">
      <en>Commissioner, we are all growing older <Alignment alignment="12825" annotation_id="11260">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11260" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we would like to see the Single European Sky in our lifetime.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, nous prenons tous de l'âge <Alignment alignment="11260" annotation_id="12825">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12825" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous aimerions bien voir le ciel unique européen de notre vivant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11326" id="224" name="Seán Ó Neachtain">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11326" docOffset="77">
      <en>on behalf of the UEN Group. - (GA) Mr President, I should like to ask whether this aviation liberalisation policy can be considered in any way to be helping certain regions and regional airports.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe UEN. - (GA) M. le Président, j'aimerais demander <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12960">si</DiscourseConnective> la politique de libéralisation du transport aérien peut être considérée comme une aide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13050">pour</DiscourseConnective> certaines régions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13073">et</DiscourseConnective> aéroports régionaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11522" docOffset="78">
      <en>Look, <Alignment alignment="37423" annotation_id="11528">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11528" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, at what is happening at Shannon Airport in my own constituency in the west of Ireland.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11528" annotation_id="13097">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13097" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">Par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, regardez ce qui se passe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13135">à</DiscourseConnective> l'aéroport de Shannon dans ma circonscription dans l'Ouest de l'Irlande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11628" docOffset="79">
      <en>Aer Lingus's decision to discontinue flights to London has adversely affected the region, not least economically.</en>
      <fr>La décision d'Aer Lingus de suspendre les vols vers Londres a entraîné des conséquences néfastes pour la région, et pas seulement en termes économiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11742" docOffset="80">
      <en>It is totally contrary to Irish government policy.</en>
      <fr>C'est tout à fait contraire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13391">à</DiscourseConnective> la politique du gouvernement irlandais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11793" docOffset="81">
      <en>To my mind, then, as far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11818" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> Europe's regions are concerned, this freedom in aviation matters will help strong areas to progress, but weaken those which are not so strong.</en>
      <fr>Selon moi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13444">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les régions d'Europe, cette libéralisation du transport aérien permettra aux régions fortes de progresser, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13570">mais</DiscourseConnective> affaiblira les moins robustes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11964" docOffset="82">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="13617" annotation_id="11972">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11972" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ask the Commission to look at the case of, say, Shannon Airport, and consider how this policy can be pursued alongside regional development policy in such areas.</en>
      <fr>Je demande <Alignment alignment="11972" annotation_id="13617">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13617" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à la Commission de se pencher sur le cas de l'aéroport de Shannon, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13689">et</DiscourseConnective> d'examiner comment cette politique peut se poursuivre aux côtés de la politique de développement régional dans ces régions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12144" id="225" name="Vladimír Remek">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12144" docOffset="83">
      <en>on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group. - (CS) Mr Chairman, ladies and gentlemen, the 'Single European Sky' initiative confirms my experience as a private pilot that aviation is a textbook example of an area that calls for supranational cooperation irrespective of state borders.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. - (CS) M. le Président, mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13875">et</DiscourseConnective> messieurs, l'initiative du "Ciel unique européen" confirme mon expérience en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13955">tant que</DiscourseConnective> pilote privé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13977">que</DiscourseConnective> le transport aérien est le parfait exemple d'un domaine qui appelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14049">à</DiscourseConnective> une coopération supranationale indépendante des frontières nationales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12416" docOffset="84">
      <en>For that reason, and in view of the need to ensure maximum air traffic safety, maximum effectiveness and minimum flight delays, we support the creation of functional blocks and, <Alignment alignment="14330" annotation_id="12594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12594" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">consequently</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Single European Sky.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14122">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>, concernant la nécessité de garantir au maximum la sécurité du trafic aérien, une efficacité maximum <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14238">et</DiscourseConnective> un minimum de retards dans les vols, nous soutenons la création de blocs fonctionnels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14327">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="12594" annotation_id="14330">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14330" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> du Ciel unique européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12633" docOffset="85">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21109" annotation_id="12633">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12633" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, let us not forget that <Alignment alignment="14386" annotation_id="12665">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12665" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> fragmentation is expensive, defragmentation costs money too.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12633" annotation_id="14360">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14360" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, n'oublions pas <Alignment alignment="12665" annotation_id="14386">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14386" sense="Comparison.Contrast">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la fragmentation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14410">s'</DiscourseConnective>avère onéreuse, la défragmentation coûte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14453">également</DiscourseConnective> de l'argent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12732" docOffset="86">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14476" annotation_id="12732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12732" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is a complex system, I support, in the interest of continuity, the gradual establishment of a single operations management system in a common airspace.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12732" annotation_id="14476">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14476" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14485">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un système complexe, je soutiens la mise en place progressive d'un système unique de gestion des opérations dans un espace aérien commun, dans l'intérêt de la continuité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12895" docOffset="87">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14665" annotation_id="12895">
          <Alignment alignment="14665" annotation_id="12895">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12895" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the unification of European skies where 27 national operating systems exist today will jeopardise the jobs of air traffic controllers and other specialists in this field.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12895" annotation_id="14665">
          <Alignment alignment="12895" annotation_id="14665">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14665" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, l'unification des cieux européens où 27 systèmes d'exploitation nationaux existent actuellement mettra en danger les emplois des contrôleurs aériens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14824">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres spécialistes dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13079" docOffset="88">
      <en>As far <Alignment alignment="22616" annotation_id="13086">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13086" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am aware, a rather successful long-term social dialogue has been conducted on these issues <Alignment alignment="39115" annotation_id="13182">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13182" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in my opinion, it is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13208" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> necessary to reconcile seemingly contradictory procedures.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14866">Pour</DiscourseConnective> ce <Alignment alignment="13086" annotation_id="14874">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14874" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je sais, un dialogue social à long terme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14919">plutôt</DiscourseConnective> fructueux a été mené <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14947">en</DiscourseConnective> l'espèce <Alignment alignment="13182" annotation_id="14959">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14959" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, selon moi, il est nécessaire de réconcilier des procédures qui semblent contradictoires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13272" docOffset="89">
      <en>We want our flights to be safer and more effective; we want minimal flight delays and maximum elimination of the dangers of unusual air traffic events.</en>
      <fr>Nous voulons que nos vols soient plus sûrs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15095">et</DiscourseConnective> plus efficaces; nous voulons le moins de retards possibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15157">et</DiscourseConnective> éliminer au maximum les risques d'événements inhabituels dans le trafic aérien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13424" docOffset="90">
      <en>Human lives are at stake: the lives of those who fly and also the lives and fates of those who manage the air traffic.</en>
      <fr>Des vies humaines sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15263">en</DiscourseConnective> jeu: les vies des personnes qui prennent l'avion, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15316">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> les vies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15336">et</DiscourseConnective> les destins de ceux qui gèrent le trafic aérien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13543" id="226" name="Kathy Sinnott">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13543" docOffset="91">
      <en>on behalf of the IND/DEM Group. - Mr President, I am disturbed by the suggestion that the process of establishing open skies be accelerated.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe IND/DEM. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la proposition d'accélérer le processus de création d'espaces aériens m'inquiète.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13684" docOffset="92">
      <en>There seems to be no recognition of the problems that open skies have visited on regional airports in Europe, even in their preparatory stage.</en>
      <fr>Il semble n'y avoir aucune reconnaissance des problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15582">que</DiscourseConnective> les espaces aériens ont rencontré dans les aéroports régionaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15649">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15660">même</DiscourseConnective> au cours de leur préparation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13827" docOffset="93">
      <en>In creating a single European sky we will see the emergence of two major hubs - Heathrow, definitely, and either Frankfurt or Charles de Gaulle - flanked by a network of sub-hubs.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15695">En</DiscourseConnective> créant un ciel unique européen, nous assisterons à l'émergence de deux principales plates-formes de correspondances - Heathrow, de façon certaine, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15845">et</DiscourseConnective> Frankfort <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15858">ou</DiscourseConnective> Charles de Gaulle - flanquées d'un réseau de sous-plates-formes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14007" docOffset="94">
      <en>The competition among airports to be the first or second level in the open skies hierarchy is proving cut-throat in my country.</en>
      <fr>La concurrence entre les aéroports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15961">pour</DiscourseConnective> être au premier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15982">ou</DiscourseConnective> au second niveau dans la hiérarchie du ciel ouvert se révèle acharnée dans mon pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14135" docOffset="95">
      <en>Shannon Airport - a hub in its own right - and regional airports like Cork are being starved of routes, <Alignment alignment="16209" annotation_id="14239">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14239" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Dublin Airport is chronically overcrowded.</en>
      <fr>L'aéroport de Shannon - une plateforme de correspondances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16128">à</DiscourseConnective> part entière - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16145">et</DiscourseConnective> des aéroports régionaux tels que Cork, sont privés de routes <Alignment alignment="2778" annotation_id="16209">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16209" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'aéroport de Dublin est chroniquement surchargé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14288" docOffset="96">
      <en>My government stands by and does nothing <Alignment alignment="16312" annotation_id="14329">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14329" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the logic of open skies is to let the market decide, <Alignment alignment="16380" annotation_id="14390">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14390" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the market, not social responsibility or common sense around regional and rural development, is deciding in a way that increases profits but does not serve people.</en>
      <fr>Mon gouvernement reste là <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16296">à</DiscourseConnective> ne rien faire <Alignment alignment="14329" annotation_id="16312">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16312" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la logique du ciel ouvert consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16351">à</DiscourseConnective> laisser le marché décider, <Alignment alignment="14390" annotation_id="16380">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16380" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le marché, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16394">et</DiscourseConnective> non pas la responsabilité sociale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16431">ou</DiscourseConnective> le sens commun autour du développement régional <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16482">et</DiscourseConnective> rural, décide, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16500">en</DiscourseConnective> quelque sorte, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16518">que</DiscourseConnective> les développements profitent aux personnes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16565">mais</DiscourseConnective> ne les servent pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14558" docOffset="97">
      <en>Rather than rush open skies, let us, even at this late hour, take whatever time is necessary to do serious assessment on the impact of the policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16590">Plutôt qu'</DiscourseConnective>un ciel ouvert encombré, prenons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16633">le temps qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16654">même</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16659">à</DiscourseConnective> cette heure tardive, de procéder à une évaluation sérieuse sur les effets de la politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14705" docOffset="98">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14705" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Then</DiscourseConnective> let us take whatever measures are needed to ensure that whole areas of Europe, like the west and south of Ireland, are not cut off from a viable, economic future by open skies.</en>
      <fr>Prenons ensuite les mesures nécessaires afin de garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16809">que</DiscourseConnective> toutes les zones de l'Europe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16843">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'ouest <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16857">et</DiscourseConnective> le sud de l'Irlande, ne sont pas amputées d'un avenir viable et économique par un ciel ouvert.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14887" id="228" name="Reinhard Rack">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14887" docOffset="99">
      <en>(DE) Madam President, we all share the same concern regarding European transport policy.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Madame la Présidente, nous partageons tous la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17006">même</DiscourseConnective> inquiétude s'agissant de la politique européenne des transports.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14976" docOffset="100">
      <en>We want to improve the efficiency of all modes of transport, and especially air transport, without at the same time increasing environmental pollution.</en>
      <fr>Nous voulons améliorer l'efficacité de tous les moyens de transport, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17145">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17148">notamment</DiscourseConnective> du transport aérien, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17179">sans</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17184">pour autant</DiscourseConnective> accroître la pollution de l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15128" docOffset="101">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17239" annotation_id="15128">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15128" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> possible, we even want to improve the environmental balance of flying.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="15128" annotation_id="17239">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17239" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> possible, nous souhaitons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17268">même</DiscourseConnective> améliorer l'équilibre environnemental de l'aviation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15202" docOffset="102">
      <en>We have had many ideas on the subject in Europe, such as emission trading.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons de nombreuses idées sur la question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17373">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17384">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'échange de quotas d'émissions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15277" docOffset="103">
      <en>We hope to achieve our aims by, <Alignment alignment="17463" annotation_id="15309">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15309" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, possibly taxing aircraft fuel and suchlike.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons atteindre notre objectif, <Alignment alignment="15309" annotation_id="17463">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17463" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, en taxant éventuellement le carburant des appareils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17528">ou</DiscourseConnective> autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15366" docOffset="104">
      <en>That may not be the wrong approach, <Alignment alignment="17584" annotation_id="15402">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15402" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the way to achieve our aim is a different one.</en>
      <fr>Cette approche n'est peut-être pas mauvaise, <Alignment alignment="15402" annotation_id="17584">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17584" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce n'est pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17602">comme ça</DiscourseConnective> qu'on atteindra notre objectif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15453" docOffset="105">
      <en>As in the case of road transport, we should seek more intelligent solutions.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17643">Comme pour</DiscourseConnective> le transport par route, nous devons rechercher des solutions plus intelligentes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15530" docOffset="106">
      <en>The idea of an open European sky and a Single European Sky is the right approach, <Alignment alignment="34981" annotation_id="15612">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15612" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> of course it needs to be implemented.</en>
      <fr>L'idée d'un ciel européen ouvert <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17768">et</DiscourseConnective> d'un ciel européen unique est la bonne approche, <Alignment alignment="12926" annotation_id="17820">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17820" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il faut encore la mettre en œuvre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15659" docOffset="107">
      <en>SESAR is a step on the way <Alignment alignment="17904" annotation_id="15686">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15686" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must do more in this respect.</en>
      <fr>Le SESAR représente une étape <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17892">en ce sens</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="15686" annotation_id="17904">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17904" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons faire davantage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15723" docOffset="108">
      <en>Let me address a final point <Alignment alignment="17982" annotation_id="15752">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15752" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will be voting on the subject this week.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de soulever un dernier point, <Alignment alignment="15752" annotation_id="17982">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17982" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voterons la question cette semaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15804" docOffset="109">
      <en>Congestion is found not just in the sky, but on the ground too, especially in airports.</en>
      <fr>Le ciel n'est pas le seul <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18053">à</DiscourseConnective> souffrir de la congestion, elle frappe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18094">également</DiscourseConnective> au sol, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18112">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans les aéroports.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15892" docOffset="110">
      <en>Let us, <Alignment alignment="18160" annotation_id="15900">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15900" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, get rid of the senseless, bureaucratic rules on carrying fluids at airports.</en>
      <fr>Débarrassons-nous <Alignment alignment="15900" annotation_id="18160">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18160" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des règles bureaucratiques absurdes sur le transport de liquides dans les aéroports.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15988" docOffset="111">
      <en>That would save a lot of money and a lot more trouble.</en>
      <fr>Cela permettra de faire des économies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18288">et</DiscourseConnective> d'éviter des problèmes supplémentaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16043" id="229" name="Ulrich Stockmann">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16043" docOffset="112">
      <en>(DE) Madam President, Commissioner, we regard the Single European Sky as the most important project for the future of air transport.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Madame la Présidente, M. le commissaire, nous considérons le ciel unique européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18418">comme</DiscourseConnective> le projet le plus important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18452">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir du transport aérien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16176" docOffset="113">
      <en>The Commission always emphasised its importance under your predecessor <Alignment alignment="18582" annotation_id="16247">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16247" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I <Alignment alignment="18594" annotation_id="16253">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16253" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> believe it to be the case.</en>
      <fr>La Commission insistait sans cesse sur son importance sous la présidence de votre prédécesseur <Alignment alignment="16247" annotation_id="18582">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18582" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense <Alignment alignment="3020" annotation_id="18594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18594" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que c'est le cas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16285" docOffset="114">
      <en>We adopted the 2004 package of regulations.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons adopté le paquet de règlements 2004.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16329" docOffset="115">
      <en>We still have a kind of patchwork in the sky, with 58 national airspace blocks, even <Alignment alignment="18753" annotation_id="16414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16414" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we know we would really only need one, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16460" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective> to be generous perhaps three to six.</en>
      <fr>Notre ciel ressemble toujours à un patchwork, avec 58 blocs d'espace aérien nationaux, <Alignment alignment="16414" annotation_id="18753">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18753" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous savons que nous n'en avons besoin que d'un seul, voire de trois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18830">à</DiscourseConnective> six <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18836">pour</DiscourseConnective> être généreux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16500" docOffset="116">
      <en>We know that this patchwork - the figures were given earlier - has adverse effects on safety, and of course <Alignment alignment="19004" annotation_id="16608">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16608" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on the economy and consumers.</en>
      <fr>Nous savons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18868">que</DiscourseConnective> ce patchwork - les statistiques ont été indiquées précédemment - entraînent des conséquences néfastes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18974">pour</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18992">et</DiscourseConnective> bien sûr <Alignment alignment="16608" annotation_id="19004">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19004" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sur l'économie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19025">et</DiscourseConnective> les consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16643" docOffset="117">
      <en>We know about the stacking and congestion in the skies <Alignment alignment="19121" annotation_id="16698">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16698" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nowadays we are putting far more emphasis on emissions.</en>
      <fr>Nous connaissons l'entassement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19078">et</DiscourseConnective> la congestion dans les différents ciels <Alignment alignment="16698" annotation_id="19121">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19121" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, aujourd'hui, nous mettons davantage l'accent sur les émissions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16758" docOffset="118">
      <en>We have realised that we can take a big step forward here.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons réalisé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19208">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pouvions faire un grand pas en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19248">avant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16817" docOffset="119">
      <en>In its progress report, the Commission showed how slowly the Member States are moving, even <Alignment alignment="1123" annotation_id="16909">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16909" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are some initiatives, and proposed a few ways of exerting pressure.</en>
      <fr>Dans son rapport d'évaluation, la Commission a montré avec quelle lenteur les États membres évoluaient, <Alignment alignment="16909" annotation_id="19359">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19359" sense="Contingency.Condition">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'on observe quelques initiatives, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19402">et</DiscourseConnective> elle a proposé certains moyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19436">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire pression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16986" docOffset="120">
      <en>Now I am not saying that is meaningless, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17027" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">nor</DiscourseConnective> 'I told you so', <Alignment alignment="19541" annotation_id="17048">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17048" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> as early as 2003 we said the bottom-up approach would not work, <Alignment alignment="17823" annotation_id="17116">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17116" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> even at that time we suspected that Member States would get embroiled in discussions about areas of sovereignty in regard to service provision <Alignment alignment="19789" annotation_id="17267">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17267" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that such crucial matters need to be regulated by top-down legislative rules.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, je ne dis pas que cela n'a pas de sens, ni "Je vous l'avais bien dit", <Alignment alignment="24488" annotation_id="19541">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19541" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dès 2003, nous disions déjà que l'approche "de bas en haut" ne fonctionnerait pas, <Alignment alignment="17116" annotation_id="19629">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19629" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19633">même</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19638">à</DiscourseConnective> l'époque, nous craignions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19666">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres s'embourbent dans des discussions sur les zones de souveraineté au sujet de la prestation de service <Alignment alignment="5077" annotation_id="19789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19789" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19792">que</DiscourseConnective> des questions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19810">aussi</DiscourseConnective> sensibles ne doivent être réglementées par des règles législatives de haut en bas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17349" docOffset="121">
      <en>At the time we thought perhaps Eurocontrol could propose rules and make a proposal based simply on the substance, on functionality, which the Member States could <Alignment alignment="20112" annotation_id="17511">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17511" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> quarrel about, rather than waiting <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17551" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">until</DiscourseConnective> they themselves had created another kind of patchwork, in a bottom-up approach.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19899">À ce moment-là</DiscourseConnective>, nous pensions qu'Eurocontrol aurait peut-être pu proposer des règles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19984">et</DiscourseConnective> avancer une proposition fondée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20018">simplement</DiscourseConnective> sur la substance, sur la fonctionnalité, sur laquelle les États membres pourraient <Alignment alignment="17511" annotation_id="20112">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20112" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> se chamailler, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20135">au lieu d'</DiscourseConnective>attendre qu'ils ne créent eux-mêmes un autre genre de patchwork, dans une démarche de bas en haut.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17637" docOffset="122">
      <en>What is important now is seriously to consider whether we need to review the legal framework.</en>
      <fr>Ce qui compte aujourd'hui, c'est d'envisager sérieusement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20302">si</DiscourseConnective> nous devons réexaminer le cadre juridique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17731" docOffset="123">
      <en>That would be the only way to exert real pressure and bring about the necessary changes.</en>
      <fr>C'est la seule manière d'exercer une véritable pression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20404">et</DiscourseConnective> d'apporter les modifications nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17820" id="230" name="Mieczysław Edmund Janowski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17820" docOffset="124">
      <en>(PL) Madam President, Commissioner, in the spring of 2004, <Alignment alignment="20514" annotation_id="17879">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17879" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Union was adopting the relevant legislation, there was talk of the benefits that civil aviation would obtain from the reorganisation of air traffic rules and military cooperation with the civil sector in this regard.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Madame la Présidente, M. le Commissaire, au printemps 2004, <Alignment alignment="17879" annotation_id="20514">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20514" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne a adopté la législation pertinente, on discutait des avantages <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20604">que</DiscourseConnective> l'aviation civile tirerait de la réorganisation des règles du trafic aérien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20684">et</DiscourseConnective> de la coopération militaire avec le secteur civil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20737">en ce sens</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18114" docOffset="125">
      <en>The European system at that time was very fragmented, which resulted in there being narrow airspace corridors.</en>
      <fr>Le système européen de l'époque était très fragmenté, ce qui a entraîné des corridors d'espace aérien très étroits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18225" docOffset="126">
      <en>As a result there was a worsening in the safety of flights, <Alignment alignment="20942" annotation_id="18285">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18285" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> about 20% of aircraft were delayed, more fuel was being used, which had a negative ecological impact.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20865">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>, nous avons observé une détérioration de la sécurité des vols <Alignment alignment="18285" annotation_id="20942">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20942" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> quelque 20 % des appareils avaient du retard, cela consommait davantage de carburant, ce qui entraîne un impact écologique néfaste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18391" docOffset="127">
      <en>Is the situation any better today, Commissioner?</en>
      <fr>La situation est-elle meilleure aujourd'hui, M. le Commissaire?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18440" docOffset="128">
      <en>Why have the so-called 'functional airspace blocks' not begun to function?</en>
      <fr>Pourquoi les blocs d'espace aérien fonctionnels ne commencent-ils pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21211">à</DiscourseConnective> fonctionner?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18515" docOffset="129">
      <en>Is this just the fault of individual Member States?</en>
      <fr>La situation n'a-t-elle pas commencé à s'améliorer? Est-ce juste la faute des États membres?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18567" docOffset="130">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21319" annotation_id="18567">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18567" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> perhaps our laws did not meet actual requirements?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18567" annotation_id="21319">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21319" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> est-il possible que nos lois ne satisfassent pas aux exigences réelles?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18621" docOffset="131">
      <en>It would be good to have a prompt response to these questions and to take remedial steps now, and not wait to the end of 2008.</en>
      <fr>Il serait bon de répondre rapidement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21431">à</DiscourseConnective> ces questions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21447">et</DiscourseConnective> de prendre les mesures qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21477">s'</DiscourseConnective>imposent, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21489">sans</DiscourseConnective> attendre la fin 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18748" docOffset="132">
      <en>Growth in air traffic is phenomenal.</en>
      <fr>La croissance du trafic aérien est phénoménale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18785" docOffset="133">
      <en>What are needed <Alignment alignment="21572" annotation_id="18801">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18801" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> are appropriate legal regulations, but regulations that do not just remain empty words.</en>
      <fr>Il faut <Alignment alignment="25394" annotation_id="21572">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21572" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des règlements juridiques appropriés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21615">mais</DiscourseConnective> des règlements qui ne restent pas de vaines paroles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18899" docOffset="134">
      <en>What is <Alignment alignment="21681" annotation_id="18907">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18907" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> required is appropriate staff training.</en>
      <fr>Il faut <Alignment alignment="18907" annotation_id="21681">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21681" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une formation du personnel appropriée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18952" docOffset="135">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21726" annotation_id="18952">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18952" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">And</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="21729" annotation_id="18956">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18956" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">finally</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, how do you see this issue in the context of the EU's neighbours, Commissioner?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4446" annotation_id="21726">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21726" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="18956" annotation_id="21729">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21729" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">enfin</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, comment envisagez-vous la question dans le cadre des voisins de l'UE, M. le Commissaire?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19044" id="231" name="Saïd El Khadraoui">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19044" docOffset="136">
      <en>(NL) Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I agree with what other speakers have already said and I would add that the Single European Sky needs to be completed as a matter of urgency.</en>
      <fr>(NL) Madame la Présidente, M. le Commissaire, mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21880">et</DiscourseConnective> messieurs, j'approuve ce que les autres orateurs ont déclaré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21944">et</DiscourseConnective> j'ajouterais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21960">que</DiscourseConnective> le ciel unique européen doit être complété d'urgence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19244" docOffset="137">
      <en>It is clear that the softly-softly approach of Regulation 551/2004, designed to encourage Member States to make optimum use of these more functional airspace blocks, has not worked.</en>
      <fr>Il est clair <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22031">que</DiscourseConnective> l'approche en douceur du règlement 551/2004, destinée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22089">à</DiscourseConnective> encourager les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22120">à</DiscourseConnective> exploiter au maximum ces blocs d'espace aérien plus fonctionnels, n'a pas fonctionné.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19426" docOffset="138">
      <en>I understand too that this is largely <Alignment alignment="22254" annotation_id="19464">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19464" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> many Member States are holding back, they prefer not to be involved, stress their sovereignty, and so forth, <Alignment alignment="22375" annotation_id="19581">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19581" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must not allow them to get away with that.</en>
      <fr>Je comprends <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22221">aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22227">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est en grande partie <Alignment alignment="884" annotation_id="22254">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22254" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des nombreux États membres se retiennent, ils préfèrent ne pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22327">s'</DiscourseConnective>impliquer, souligner leur souveraineté, etc., <Alignment alignment="7498" annotation_id="22375">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22375" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne devons pas leur permettre de s'en tirer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22428">comme ça</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19631" docOffset="139">
      <en>Aviation is very much a sector which needs to be dealt with in every particular at the European level, in the interests of the industry, consumers, safety and the environment.</en>
      <fr>Le transport aérien est un secteur qui doit véritablement être traité au niveau européen, dans l'intérêt de l'industrie, des consommateurs, de la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22593">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19807" docOffset="140">
      <en>At a time <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19817" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> climate change is so high on the political agenda, Commissioner, we cannot have aircraft making unnecessary detours, wasting huge amounts of aviation fuel, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19978" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> so on.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22616">À</DiscourseConnective> une époque où le changement climatique est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22661">si</DiscourseConnective> important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22674">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'agenda politique, M. le Commissaire, nous ne pouvons permettre que les appareils effectuent des détours inutilement, gaspillant ainsi des quantités de carburant considérables, etc.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19989" docOffset="141">
      <en>We simply must push ahead with this dossier, along with other instruments - SESAR, the emissions trading system, and so forth. We cannot go on allowing tens of millions of euros to be wasted due to inefficient management of our airspace by a whole lot of unnecessary air traffic control centres.</en>
      <fr>Nous appuyons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22876">simplement</DiscourseConnective> ce dossier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22899">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que d'autres instruments - le SESAR, le système d'échange de quotas d'émissions, etc. Nous ne pouvons continuer de gaspiller des dizaines de millions d'euros <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23063">à</DiscourseConnective> cause d'une mauvaise gestion de notre espace aérien de la part d'un tas de centres de contrôle du trafic aérien inutiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20285" docOffset="142">
      <en>There is plenty of scope for trimming and pruning here <Alignment alignment="23241" annotation_id="20340">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20340" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is what we want.</en>
      <fr>Il y a vraiment de quoi rogner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23218">et</DiscourseConnective> élaguer en l'espèce <Alignment alignment="27267" annotation_id="23241">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23241" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est ce que nous voulons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20366" docOffset="143">
      <en>It is likely, <Alignment alignment="23271" annotation_id="20380">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20380" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, that we shall soon reach the limits of capacity thanks to the sector's rapid expansion.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="20380" annotation_id="23271">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23271" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous allons probablement atteindre prochainement les limites de capacité grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23360">à</DiscourseConnective> l'expansion rapide du secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20478" docOffset="144">
      <en>Existing bilateral contacts aimed at forming functional airspace blocks have achieved hardly anything, <Alignment alignment="23514" annotation_id="20581">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20581" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we really do need to pull our finger out.</en>
      <fr>Les relations bilatérales existantes destinées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23440">à</DiscourseConnective> former des blocs d'espace aérien fonctionnels n'ont presque rien donné, <Alignment alignment="20581" annotation_id="23514">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23514" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il faut vraiment retrousser nos manches.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20626" docOffset="145">
      <en>Appointing a coordinator and a performance review body would seem to be a step in the right direction, <Alignment alignment="23680" annotation_id="20729">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20729" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> at the same time, Commissioner, I fear that this bottom-up approach will not be enough; we have taken it as far <Alignment alignment="23810" annotation_id="20845">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20845" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we can <Alignment alignment="23823" annotation_id="20855">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20855" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must now look to take new legislative initiatives.</en>
      <fr>Désigner un coordinateur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23586">et</DiscourseConnective> un organe indépendant d'évaluation des performances serait un pas dans la bonne direction, <Alignment alignment="20729" annotation_id="23680">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23680" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23685">en même temps</DiscourseConnective>, M. le commissaire, je crains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23729">que</DiscourseConnective> cette démarche de bas en haut ne suffise pas; nous l'avons portée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23799">aussi</DiscourseConnective> loin <Alignment alignment="20845" annotation_id="23810">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23810" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> possible <Alignment alignment="20855" annotation_id="23823">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23823" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons à présent envisager de prendre de nouvelles initiatives législatives.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20913" id="232" name="Silvia-Adriana Ţicău">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20913" docOffset="146">
      <en>(RO) Madam President, in 2006, low-cost companies opened 225 new European airways routes, meaning 1 800 new flights per week.</en>
      <fr>(RO) Madame la Présidente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23935">en</DiscourseConnective> 2006, les compagnies low-cost ont ouvert 225 nouvelles routes aériennes en Europe, ce qui signifie 1 800 nouveaux vols par semaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21039" docOffset="147">
      <en>The fragmentation of airspace at national level, with specific operational rules and procedures, may have negative effects on the safety of transport capability, on the introduction of new technologies and on costs.</en>
      <fr>La fragmentation de l'espace aérien au niveau national, avec des règles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24142">et</DiscourseConnective> des procédures opérationnelles spécifiques, peut entraîner des effets néfastes sur la sécurité de la capacité de transport, sur l'introduction de nouvelles technologies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24314">et</DiscourseConnective> sur les coûts.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21255" docOffset="148">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24332" annotation_id="21255">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21255" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> passing from one air sector to another, pilots change frequency and contact the next air traffic controller.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="21255" annotation_id="24332">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24332" sense="Comparison.Contrast">En</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> passant d'un secteur aérien vers un autre, les pilotes changent de fréquence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24412">et</DiscourseConnective> contactent le contrôleur aérien suivant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21370" docOffset="149">
      <en>Air traffic control has become a critical element.</en>
      <fr>Le contrôle du trafic aérien est devenu un élément essentiel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21421" docOffset="150">
      <en>It is important that new functional blocks be implemented following consultation of all the relevant parties, <Alignment alignment="45579" annotation_id="21531">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21531" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Member States take effective actions in order to achieve an integrated management system.</en>
      <fr>Il est important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24535">que</DiscourseConnective> de nouveaux blocs fonctionnels soient mis en œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24590">après</DiscourseConnective> la consultation de toutes les parties concernées, <Alignment alignment="21531" annotation_id="24646">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24646" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que les États membres prennent des mesures efficaces <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24702">pour</DiscourseConnective> réaliser un système de gestion intégré.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21625" docOffset="151">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24747" annotation_id="21625">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21625" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Meanwhile</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, investments should be made in more efficient aircrafts and airport infrastructure.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="21625" annotation_id="24747">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24747" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">En attendant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il faut investir dans des appareils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24797">et</DiscourseConnective> des infrastructures aéroportuaires plus efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21719" docOffset="152">
      <en>Romania and Bulgaria's accession to the EU adds new functional blocks for the Community airspace, with relevance both for the Black Sea region and for cooperation in the Balkans.</en>
      <fr>L'adhésion de la Roumanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24877">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Bulgarie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24895">à</DiscourseConnective> l'UE ajoute de nouveaux blocs fonctionnels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24940">à</DiscourseConnective> l'espace aérien communautaire, avec un intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24989">pour</DiscourseConnective> la région de la mer Noire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25020">et</DiscourseConnective> la coopération dans les Balkans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="21898" id="233" name="Jacques Barrot">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="21898" docOffset="153">
      <en>Vice-President of the Commission. - (FR) Madam President, I appreciate and share the impatience expressed by Parliament.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - Monsieur le Président, je comprends <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25127">et</DiscourseConnective> je partage l'impatience du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22019" docOffset="154">
      <en>I shall give you a very precise but very concise answer. Ladies and gentlemen, you will have a report in October 2007 and a second package of legislation by the middle of 2008, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22196" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective> it certainly cannot be said that we are not doing anything!</en>
      <fr>Je réponds d'une manière très concise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25206">mais</DiscourseConnective> très précise: vous aurez, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25246">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs les députés, un rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25283">en</DiscourseConnective> octobre 2007 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25299">et</DiscourseConnective> vous aurez, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25314">à</DiscourseConnective> la mi-2008, un deuxième paquet législatif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22259" docOffset="155">
      <en>We are <Alignment alignment="62525" annotation_id="22266">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22266" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> going to answer this question in detail together.</en>
      <fr>Il n'est donc pas question d'en rester là! Nous allons <Alignment alignment="22266" annotation_id="25414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25414" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, sur ce point, répondre ensemble, de manière précise, à ce problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22326" docOffset="156">
      <en>The second point: I have probably spoken to you about a coordinator, a senior political figure who will promote the introduction of these operational blocks between the Member States.</en>
      <fr>Deuxième disposition: je vous ai probablement parlé d'un coordinateur, figure politique de haut niveau qui facilitera la mise en œuvre de ces blocs opérationnels entre les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22510" docOffset="157">
      <en>I must say that the results achieved in the trans-European networks indicate to me that this would be a useful way of stepping up our action in this area.</en>
      <fr>Je dois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25693">dire que</DiscourseConnective> les résultats obtenus au niveau des réseaux transeuropéens me font penser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25776">que</DiscourseConnective> cette méthode sera aussi utile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25811">pour</DiscourseConnective> renforcer notre action dans le domaine qui nous préoccupe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22665" docOffset="158">
      <en>I shall reply to the third question by referring to Sesar, <Alignment alignment="25928" annotation_id="22724">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22724" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Sesar exists, it is already a joint enterprise that brings together all the participants.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25875">À</DiscourseConnective> la troisième question, je veux répondre par Cesar, <Alignment alignment="22555" annotation_id="25928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25928" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Cesar existe, c'est désormais une entreprise commune.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22822" docOffset="159">
      <en>I believe that the introduction of Sesar will overturn all the bad habits that were keeping us confined to airspaces defined by national borders, which are no longer sensible.</en>
      <fr>Cette entreprise commune réunit tous les acteurs, tous les opérateurs et je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26074">que</DiscourseConnective> l'arrivée de Cesar va bousculer toutes ces mauvaises habitudes qui nous enfermaient dans des espaces aériens délimités par des frontières nationales qui n'ont plus de sens aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22998" docOffset="160">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="26263" annotation_id="22998">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22998" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am giving a very positive reply to the question put by Mr Costa and discussed by Mr Savary and have listened carefully to what Parliament wants.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="22998" annotation_id="26263">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26263" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Monsieur le Président, je réponds très positivement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26321">à</DiscourseConnective> la question posée par M. Costa <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26354">et</DiscourseConnective> développée par M. Savary <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26382">et</DiscourseConnective> j'ai écouté avec attention les demandes du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23150" docOffset="161">
      <en>I am ready to do all I can to respond.</en>
      <fr>Je suis prêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26452">à</DiscourseConnective> tout mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26466">en</DiscourseConnective> œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26475">pour</DiscourseConnective> y répondre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="23189" id="234" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="23189" docOffset="162">
      <en>The debate is now closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23215" docOffset="163">
      <en>Written statement (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclaration écrite (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="23244" id="235" name="Zuzana Roithová ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="23244" docOffset="164">
      <en>in writing. - (CS) The Member States agreed to set up common airspace blocks to control a single sky, irrespective of national borders.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (CS) Les États membres ont approuvé la création de blocs d'espace aérien communs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26638">pour</DiscourseConnective> contrôler un ciel unique, indépendamment des frontières nationales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23380" docOffset="165">
      <en>Prior to that two planes collided over Germany <Alignment alignment="26776" annotation_id="23427">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23427" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> 71 people perished.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26711">Avant</DiscourseConnective> cela, deux avions se sont heurtés au-dessus de l'Allemagne <Alignment alignment="23427" annotation_id="26776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26776" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> 71 personnes ont trouvé la mort.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23451" docOffset="166">
      <en>The arguments for a single sky are growing stronger: we have 57 control points for 28 000 daily flights; the US has two.</en>
      <fr>Les arguments en faveur d'un ciel unique européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26862">s'</DiscourseConnective>intensifient: nous comptons 57 points de contrôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26914">pour</DiscourseConnective> 28 000 vols quotidiens; les États-Unis en comptent deux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23572" docOffset="167">
      <en>Three years later we are no further on.</en>
      <fr>Trois ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26986">plus tard</DiscourseConnective>, nous ne sommes pas plus avancés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23612" docOffset="168">
      <en>The EU has not put all of the Regulations from 2004 into practice.</en>
      <fr>L'UE n'a pas mis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27047">en</DiscourseConnective> pratique l'ensemble des règlements de 2004.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23679" docOffset="169">
      <en>These Regulations were supposed to integrate airspace in the internal services market and provide a basis for an effective operating system with emphasis on safety, the environment and increased flying capacity.</en>
      <fr>Ces règlements sont censés intégrer l'espace aérien dans le marché des services internes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27183">et</DiscourseConnective> jeter les bases d'un système d'exploitation efficace en mettant l'accent sur la sécurité, l'environnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27292">et</DiscourseConnective> une capacité de vol accrue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23891" docOffset="170">
      <en>We currently have 65 radar centres with 31 systems using 22 computer networks, <Alignment alignment="27418" annotation_id="23970">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23970" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we expect that the number of flights over Europe will double in 10 years' time.</en>
      <fr>Nous comptons actuellement 65 centres radar où 31 systèmes utilisent 22 réseaux informatiques, <Alignment alignment="23970" annotation_id="27418">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27418" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous prévoyons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27436">que</DiscourseConnective> le nombre de vols <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27458">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe doublera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27477">en</DiscourseConnective> l'espace de 10 ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24054" docOffset="171">
      <en>Do the citizens know that their governments and parliaments are ignoring the benefits of common Europe to their disadvantage?</en>
      <fr>Les citoyens savent-ils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27524">que</DiscourseConnective> leurs gouvernements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27548">et</DiscourseConnective> leurs parlements ignorent les avantages d'une Europe commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27612">à</DiscourseConnective> leur détriment?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24180" docOffset="172">
      <en>Why does the process of creating a shared operating airspace for both civilian and military flights over a united Europe take such a long time?</en>
      <fr>Pourquoi le processus de création d'un espace européen opérationnel partagé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27706">pour</DiscourseConnective> les vols civils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27727">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires dans une Europe unie prend-il tant de temps?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24324" docOffset="173">
      <en>Is it to appease local economic interests?</en>
      <fr>Est-ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27793">pour</DiscourseConnective> apaiser les intérêts économiques locaux?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24367" docOffset="174">
      <en>Is it to protect national sovereignty, to the detriment of transport safety and at high prices?</en>
      <fr>Est-ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27846">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger la souveraineté nationale au détriment de la sécurité des transports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27929">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27932">à</DiscourseConnective> des prix élevés?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24463" docOffset="175">
      <en>Today we want to know how <Alignment alignment="27992" annotation_id="24489">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24489" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="27995" annotation_id="24493">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24493" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are going to integrate the classification of the upper airspace <Alignment alignment="28065" annotation_id="24565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24565" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> how are we going to jointly operate the lower airspace in the future.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, nous voulons savoir comment <Alignment alignment="24489" annotation_id="27992">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27992" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="13761" annotation_id="27995">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27995" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous intégrerons la classification de l'espace aérien supérieur <Alignment alignment="24565" annotation_id="28065">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28065" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> comment nous allons exploiter conjointement l'espace aérien inférieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28138">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24639" docOffset="176">
      <en>Can obstacles to the creation of functional blocks over European territory be identified openly?</en>
      <fr>Les obstacles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28164">à</DiscourseConnective> la création de blocs fonctionnels sur le territoire européen peuvent-ils être identifiés ouvertement?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24736" docOffset="177">
      <en>Is it possible to shed light on the political will of Member States to fulfil their obligations?</en>
      <fr>Est-il possible de mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28294">en</DiscourseConnective> lumière la volonté politique des États membres de respecter leurs obligations?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24833" docOffset="178">
      <en>We are <Alignment alignment="28397" annotation_id="24840">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24840" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> worried about the failure of the bottom-up approach <Alignment alignment="28449" annotation_id="24897">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24897" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in three years the Member States have not developed the functional blocks needed for more efficient control of the sky.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous inquiétons <Alignment alignment="24840" annotation_id="28397">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28397" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de l'échec de la démarche de bas en haut, <Alignment alignment="2780" annotation_id="28449">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28449" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28454">en</DiscourseConnective> trois ans, les États membres n'ont pas développé les blocs fonctionnels indispensables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28544">à</DiscourseConnective> un contrôle du ciel plus efficace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
