<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Award of the Sakharov Prize (Formal sitting)</en>
    <fr>Remise du Prix Sakharov (séance solennelle)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="45" id="133" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="45" docOffset="1">
      <en>Honourable Members, ladies and gentlemen, for almost two decades the European Parliament has been awarding the Sakharov Prize for Freedom of Thought to men and women from all parts of the world who campaign for human rights, freedom of speech and freedom of expression.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Honorables membres, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="78">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="92">depuis</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="99">bientôt</DiscourseConnective> deux décennies, le Parlement européen remet le Prix Sakharov <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="168">pour</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de pensée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="194">à</DiscourseConnective> des hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="207">et</DiscourseConnective> des femmes des quatre coins du monde qui luttent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="259">pour</DiscourseConnective> les droits de l'homme, la liberté de parole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="308">et</DiscourseConnective> la liberté d'expression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="315" docOffset="2">
      <en>I am delighted to bid a very warm welcome today, here in the European Parliament, to the winner of the Sakharov Prize for 2007, Salih Mahmoud Osman.</en>
      <fr>J'ai aujourd'hui le grand plaisir d'accueillir chaleureusement au sein du Parlement européen le lauréat du Prix Sakharov 2007, Monsieur Salih Mahmoud Osman.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="464" docOffset="3">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="475" docOffset="4">
      <en>It <Alignment alignment="537" annotation_id="478">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="478" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> gives me great pleasure to extend my warmest greetings to his wife, Salwa Ahmed Faragalla Ali, who has always stood by his side at difficult times in his life.</en>
      <fr>Cette occasion me permet <Alignment alignment="478" annotation_id="537">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="537" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de saluer très cordialement son épouse, Madame Salwa Ahmed Faragalla Ali, qui a toujours été <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="640">à</DiscourseConnective> ses côtés dans les moments les plus difficiles de sa vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="643" docOffset="5">
      <en>We welcome you among us.</en>
      <fr>Bienvenue parmi nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="668" docOffset="6">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="679" docOffset="7">
      <en>The decision to award the 2007 Sakharov Prize to Salih Mahmoud Osman was taken unanimously by the Conference of Presidents, which comprises the chairs of the political groups, on the basis of a proposal adopted by a large number of Members of the European Parliament from various groups.</en>
      <fr>La décision de décerner le Prix Sakharov 2007 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="787">à</DiscourseConnective> Salih Mahmoud Osman a été prise à l'unanimité par la Conférence des présidents, qui se compose des présidents des groupes politiques. Cette décision a été prise sur la base d'une proposition adoptée par une large majorité des membres du Parlement européen de divers groupes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="967" docOffset="8">
      <en>The European Parliament has <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="995" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective> reaffirmed its solidarity with the people in Darfur and its conviction that a sustainable solution for that region can only be achieved through justice, democracy and respect for human rights.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen a de la sorte réaffirmé sa solidarité avec le peuple du Darfour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1150">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que sa conviction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1174">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une solution durable ne pourra être trouvée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1221">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette région que par la justice, la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1273">et</DiscourseConnective> le respect des droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1196" docOffset="9">
      <en>The conflict that has plagued Darfur since 2003 is exacerbating the plight of a country devastated by more than twenty years of civil war.</en>
      <fr>Le conflit qui ravage le Darfour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1343">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 2003 exacerbe la situation déjà difficile d'un pays dévasté par plus de vingt années de guerre civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1335" docOffset="10">
      <en>As with most conflicts, it is the civilian population who have suffered most from militia raids, the destruction of villages, scorched-earth policies and forcible displacements.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1453">Comme</DiscourseConnective> dans la plupart des conflits, c'est la population civile qui souffre le plus des attaques des milices, de la destruction de villages, de la politique de la terre brûlée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1628">et</DiscourseConnective> des déplacements forcés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1513" docOffset="11">
      <en>The conflict has claimed at least 400 000 lives and has been responsible for more than two and a half million displaced persons and refugees, notwithstanding the signing of the peace agreement in Darfur in 2006.</en>
      <fr>Ce conflit est responsable d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1685">au moins</DiscourseConnective> 400 000 morts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1708">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1711">de plus</DiscourseConnective> de deux millions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1736">et</DiscourseConnective> demi de personnes déplacées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1767">et</DiscourseConnective> réfugiées, malgré la signature de l'accord de paix au Darfour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1832">en</DiscourseConnective> 2006.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1725" docOffset="12">
      <en>Just like the European Parliament, the winner of the 2007 Sakharov Prize does not simply accept this unjust situation but protests against the impunity of those who caused it.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1841">Tout comme</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen, le lauréat du Prix Sakharov 2007 rejette tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1921">simplement</DiscourseConnective> cette situation injuste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1956">et</DiscourseConnective> proteste contre l'impunité de ceux qui l'ont causée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1901" docOffset="13">
      <en>For years Salih Mahmoud Osman has been defending the rights of victims of the conflict in Darfur.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2012">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> des années, Salih Mahmoud Osman défend les droits des victimes du conflit au Darfour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1999" docOffset="14">
      <en>Thousands of people who have been imprisoned without trial, tortured and exposed to death threats, who have been driven from their homes, displaced or subjected to sexual violence are familiar with the name of Salih Mahmoud Osman.</en>
      <fr>Des milliers de personnes qui ont été emprisonnées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2156">sans</DiscourseConnective> procès, torturées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2179">et</DiscourseConnective> menacées de mort, arrachées à leur foyer, déplacées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2234">ou</DiscourseConnective> victimes de violence sexuelle connaissent bien le nom de Salih Mahmoud Osman.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2230" docOffset="15">
      <en>His commitment is remarkable in several respects.</en>
      <fr>Son engagement est remarquable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2346">à</DiscourseConnective> plusieurs égards.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2280" docOffset="16">
      <en>In a country where violence is constantly on the increase, Salih Osman risks his life on a daily basis in the cause of human dignity and justice.</en>
      <fr>Dans un pays où la violence ne cesse d'augmenter, Salih Osman risque sa vie chaque jour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2454">pour</DiscourseConnective> la cause de la dignité humaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2490">et</DiscourseConnective> de la justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2426" docOffset="17">
      <en>In the name of human dignity, Salih Osman reassures those destitute, defenceless and intimidated men and women who have sunk into oblivion that the world is aware of their suffering, that they have not been forgotten <Alignment alignment="2741" annotation_id="2643">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2643" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that they have reason to hope for a return to a perfectly normal and simply human life.</en>
      <fr>Au nom de la dignité humaine, Salih Osman rassure ces hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2569">et</DiscourseConnective> ces femmes pauvres, sans défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2605">et</DiscourseConnective> intimidés qui sont tombés dans l'oubli, en leur disant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2663">que</DiscourseConnective> le monde est conscient de leurs souffrances, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2712">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils n'ont pas été oubliés <Alignment alignment="2643" annotation_id="2741">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2741" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2744">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils ont des raisons d'espérer le retour d'une vie parfaitement normale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2818">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2821">simplement</DiscourseConnective> humaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2735" docOffset="18">
      <en>Since 2004, Salih Osman has been committing himself to the establishment and administration of the Amal Centre in Nyala, amal being Arabic for 'hope', for the rehabilitation of victims of violence and sexual abuse.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2841">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> 2004, Salih Osman s'est engagé dans la tâche de mettre en place <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2912">et</DiscourseConnective> d'administrer le Centre Amal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2944">à</DiscourseConnective> Nyala - amal signifie "espoir" en arabe - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2988">pour</DiscourseConnective> la réhabilitation des victimes de violences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3037">et</DiscourseConnective> d'abus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2950" docOffset="19">
      <en>In a predominantly Muslim country, Salih Osman is one of the few men who campaign actively in support of women's rights and especially for recognition of the right to compensation for victims of sexual violence.</en>
      <fr>Dans un pays à prédominance musulmane, Salih Osman est l'un des rares hommes qui militent de façon active <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3154">pour</DiscourseConnective> défendre les droits des femmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3190">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3193">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3208">pour</DiscourseConnective> obtenir la reconnaissance du droit au dédommagement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3265">pour</DiscourseConnective> les victimes de violence sexuelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3162" docOffset="20">
      <en>In the name of justice, Salih Osman strives, day after day, to ensure that those responsible for war crimes are held to account both nationally and internationally.</en>
      <fr>Au nom de la justice, Salih Osman se bat, jour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3352">après</DiscourseConnective> jour, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3364">pour que</DiscourseConnective> les auteurs de crimes de guerre soient jugés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3418">pour</DiscourseConnective> leurs actes, cela au niveau tant national <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3465">qu'</DiscourseConnective>international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3327" docOffset="21">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3327" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective> the Sudanese judicial system still has many defects that make it unable to put an end to the prevailing climate of lawlessness within the country, international jurisdiction seems to offer an alternative.</en>
      <fr>Les nombreux dysfonctionnements du système judiciaire soudanais le rendent incapable de mettre fin au climat anarchique qui règne dans le pays, mais la justice internationale semble constituer une alternative.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3538" docOffset="22">
      <en>The fact that the Sudanese authorities are refusing to hand over alleged war criminals to the International Criminal Court, <Alignment alignment="3693" annotation_id="3662">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3662" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, highlights the limits of international justice and shows how much progress is still needed before the rule of law can be established in Darfur and throughout Sudan.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3662" annotation_id="3693">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3693" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3712">que</DiscourseConnective> les autorités soudanaises refusent de livrer les présumés criminels de guerre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3794">à</DiscourseConnective> la Cour pénale internationale met en évidence les limites de la justice internationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3883">et</DiscourseConnective> montre tous les progrès qui restent à accomplir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3934">avant que</DiscourseConnective> l'État de droit puisse être établi au Darfour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3990">et</DiscourseConnective> dans l'ensemble du Soudan.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3836" docOffset="23">
      <en>That is why Salih Osman's work is not confined to the legal aid he gives the victims.</en>
      <fr>C'est pour cette raison que le travail de Salih Osman ne se limite pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4091">à</DiscourseConnective> l'assistance juridique aux victimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3922" docOffset="24">
      <en>As a member of the Opposition in the Sudanese Parliament since 2005, he does not hesitate to affirm his convictions in the Sudanese political arena and to engage in efforts to bring about genuine reform of the legal system.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4133">tant que</DiscourseConnective> membre de l'opposition au Parlement soudanais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4188">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 2005, il n'hésite pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4217">à</DiscourseConnective> affirmer ses convictions sur la scène politique soudanaise ni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4281">à</DiscourseConnective> s'engager dans des efforts visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4317">à</DiscourseConnective> mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4326">en</DiscourseConnective> marche une véritable réforme du système judiciaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4146" docOffset="25">
      <en>At the meeting between the European Parliament and the Pan-African Parliament on the eve of last weekend's EU-Africa Summit in Lisbon, I had the opportunity and the great pleasure to meet Salih Osman.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4381">À</DiscourseConnective> Lisbonne, lors de la réunion entre le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4440">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement panafricain, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4469">à</DiscourseConnective> la veille du sommet UE-Afrique du week-end passé, j'ai eu l'occasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4540">et</DiscourseConnective> le grand plaisir de rencontrer Salih Osman.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4347" docOffset="26">
      <en>I was immediately impressed by his strong personality <Alignment alignment="4649" annotation_id="4401">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4401" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> his unbending will to fight for human rights in spite of all the persecution and hostility to which he and his family have been subjected.</en>
      <fr>J'ai été tout de suite impressionné par sa forte personnalité <Alignment alignment="2352" annotation_id="4649">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4649" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sa volonté inflexible de lutter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4684">pour</DiscourseConnective> les droits de l'homme malgré les persécutions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4735">et</DiscourseConnective> l'hostilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4750">que</DiscourseConnective> lui-même <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4763">et</DiscourseConnective> sa famille ont subis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4544" docOffset="27">
      <en>I learned a short while ago that Ali and you have three children, who are <Alignment alignment="18445" annotation_id="4618">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4618" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> very much in our thoughts today.</en>
      <fr>J'ai appris voici peu de temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4819">qu'</DiscourseConnective>Ali <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4826">et</DiscourseConnective> vous avez trois enfants; toutes nos pensées les accompagnent <Alignment alignment="4618" annotation_id="4890">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4890" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4656" docOffset="28">
      <en>In 2004 Salih Osman himself was imprisoned for seven months without being charged, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4739" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it was only <Alignment alignment="5031" annotation_id="4755">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4755" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he went on hunger strike that he was released.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4901">En</DiscourseConnective> 2004, Salih Osman a été emprisonné pendant sept mois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4957">sans qu'</DiscourseConnective>aucune charge n'ait été retenue contre lui. Il n'a été relâché qu'<Alignment alignment="4755" annotation_id="5031">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5031" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avoir entamé une grève de la faim.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4807" docOffset="29">
      <en>Members of his family have been tortured and murdered or have had their houses set on fire by the militias.</en>
      <fr>Les milices ont torturé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5096">et</DiscourseConnective> assassiné des membres de sa famille <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5135">ou</DiscourseConnective> incendié leurs maisons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4915" docOffset="30">
      <en>The great German writer Johann Wolfgang von Goethe once wrote, 'Knowing is not enough; we must apply.</en>
      <fr>Le grand écrivain allemand Johann Wolfgang von Goethe a écrit: "Savoir ne suffit pas; nous devons aussi pratiquer ce que nous savons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5017" docOffset="31">
      <en>Willing is not enough; we must do'.</en>
      <fr>Vouloir ne suffit pas; nous devons aussi agir".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5053" docOffset="32">
      <en>Salih Osman embodies that kind of will and determination, showing his courage in his daily struggle on behalf of his fellow human beings.</en>
      <fr>Salih Osman incarne ce genre de volonté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5384">et</DiscourseConnective> de détermination: son courage se manifeste dans la lutte quotidienne qu'il mène <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5467">pour</DiscourseConnective> ses frères les êtres humains.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5191" docOffset="33">
      <en>He is an exemplary campaigner for greater respect for the rule of law in his region.</en>
      <fr>Il est un militant exemplaire pour la cause d'un plus grand respect de l'État de droit dans sa région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5276" docOffset="34">
      <en>Salih Mahmoud Osman, you have our firm support and our warm acclaim.</en>
      <fr>Salih Mahmoud Osman, nous vous donnons notre soutien inconditionnel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5673">et</DiscourseConnective> vous acclamons chaleureusement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5345" docOffset="35">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5345" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> you know, the European Parliament has always been particularly receptive to the suffering of the African peoples.</en>
      <fr>Vous n'êtes pas sans savoir que le Parlement européen, a toujours été sensible aux souffrances des peuples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5462" docOffset="36">
      <en>Salih Osman is one of a number of African prizewinners to whom Parliament has given its support in past years <Alignment alignment="5905" annotation_id="5572">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5572" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whom it continues to support.</en>
      <fr>Salih Osman figure parmi les lauréats africains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5864">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement a soutenus précédemment <Alignment alignment="5572" annotation_id="5905">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5905" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et encore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5606" docOffset="37">
      <en>Nelson Mandela was awarded the Sakharov Prize in 1988, Salima Ghezali in 1997, Dom Zacarias Kamwenho in 2001 and Hauwa Ibrahim in 2005.</en>
      <fr>Ainsi, Nelson Mandela s'est vu décerner le Prix Sakharov <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5985">en</DiscourseConnective> 1988, Salima Ghezali <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6009">en</DiscourseConnective> 1997, Dom Zacarias Kamwenho <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6040">en</DiscourseConnective> 2001 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6048">et</DiscourseConnective> Hauwa Ibrahim <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6065">en</DiscourseConnective> 2005.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5742" docOffset="38">
      <en>Salih Osman, we congratulate you on your untiring work in this cause, in this spirit, <Alignment alignment="6180" annotation_id="5828">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5828" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we hope that the recognition this prize brings might grant you strength and protection from year to year for <Alignment alignment="22644" annotation_id="5941">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5941" sense="Contingency.Condition">as long as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> your struggle continues.</en>
      <fr>Salih Osman, nous vous félicitons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6108">pour</DiscourseConnective> votre travail infatigable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6139">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur de cette cause, de cet esprit, <Alignment alignment="19" annotation_id="6180">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6180" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6192">que</DiscourseConnective> la reconnaissance symbolisée par ce prix pourra vous accorder force <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6264">et</DiscourseConnective> protection au fil des ans, <Alignment alignment="5941" annotation_id="6294">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6294" sense="Contingency.Condition">tant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> continuera votre combat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5977" docOffset="39">
      <en>We are at your side.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6340">à</DiscourseConnective> vos côtés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5998" docOffset="40">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6009" id="134" name="Salih Mahmoud Osman">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6009" docOffset="41">
      <en>Sudanese lawyer acting for the victims of the war in Darfur. - Mr President, thank you for this tremendous honour.</en>
      <fr>avocat soudanais qui milite en faveur des victimes de la guerre au Darfour. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, merci <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6484">pour</DiscourseConnective> cet immense honneur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6124" docOffset="42">
      <en>This prize is awarded as a unanimous vote of the European Parliament - a fact which gives me great satisfaction, but more importantly one which gives me the opportunity to speak to you today.</en>
      <fr>Cette récompense est décernée par un vote unanime du Parlement européen, un fait qui me remplit de satisfaction, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6623">mais</DiscourseConnective> qui me donne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6641">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout l'occasion de m'exprimer devant vous aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6316" docOffset="43">
      <en>I am a native of Darfur, born in Jebel Marra, which is a mountainous region located in the centre of Darfur State.</en>
      <fr>Je suis né au Darfour, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6725">à</DiscourseConnective> Jebel Marra, une région montagneuse au centre de l'État du Darfour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6431" docOffset="44">
      <en>I have worked as a lawyer in Darfur in Sudan for many years.</en>
      <fr>Je travaille en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6811">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>avocat au Darfour, au Soudan, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6849">depuis</DiscourseConnective> de longues années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6492" docOffset="45">
      <en>I have been a victim of detention and torture because of my work.</en>
      <fr>J'ai été victime de détention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6905">et</DiscourseConnective> de torture à cause de mon travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6558" docOffset="46">
      <en>Members of my own family have been tortured and displaced by the militia in Darfur.</en>
      <fr>Des membres de ma propre famille ont été torturés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6993">et</DiscourseConnective> déplacés par la milice au Darfour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6642" docOffset="47">
      <en>For many years, in my work, I have represented thousands of people who needed my help in front of the Courts.</en>
      <fr>Pendant bien des années, dans mon travail, j'ai représenté des milliers de gens qui avaient besoin de mon aide devant les tribunaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6752" docOffset="48">
      <en>I have seen thousands of people who have been tortured; I have seen hundreds of women and young girls who have been victims of sexual abuse; I have seen the four million who have been forcibly displaced from their homes and those two and a half million who are confined, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7023" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> we speak now, in the camps around the cities of Darfur: Nyala, Al Fashir, Zalingi and Al Geneina.</en>
      <fr>J'ai vu des milliers de gens torturés; j'ai vu des centaines de femmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7235">et</DiscourseConnective> de jeunes filles victimes d'abus sexuels; j'ai vu les quatre millions de gens déplacés de force loin de leur foyer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7353">et</DiscourseConnective> ces deux millions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7374">et</DiscourseConnective> demi de personnes confinées, au moment où nous parlons, dans des camps autour des villes du Darfour: Nyala, Al Fashir, Zalingi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7504">et</DiscourseConnective> Al Geneina.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7124" docOffset="49">
      <en>The UN Security Council has adopted several resolutions related to the situation in Darfur.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil de sécurité de l'ONU a adopté plusieurs résolutions relatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7592">à</DiscourseConnective> la situation au Darfour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7216" docOffset="50">
      <en>Unfortunately, none of these has been implemented effectively.</en>
      <fr>Hélas, aucune d'entre elles n'a été appliquée de manière effective.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7279" docOffset="51">
      <en>The victims feel disappointed.</en>
      <fr>Les victimes sont déçues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7310" docOffset="52">
      <en>They are waiting to hear from you; from the people of Europe.</en>
      <fr>Elles attendent un geste de votre part, de la part du peuple européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7372" docOffset="53">
      <en>Your leaders have been talking tough about the policies of the Sudanese Government in Darfur.</en>
      <fr>Vos dirigeants ont eu des mots durs à l'égard de la politique du gouvernement soudanais au Darfour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7466" docOffset="54">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7884" annotation_id="7466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7466" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> so far we have not seen any concrete steps to address the situation in a strong and targeted manner.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7466" annotation_id="7884">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7884" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> jusqu'ici, nous n'avons vu aucune action concrète <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7939">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire face à la situation de manière intensive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7991">et</DiscourseConnective> ciblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7571" docOffset="55">
      <en>As a representative of the victims of the conflict, today I have an unprecedented opportunity to speak directly to the leaders of Europe.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8005">tant que</DiscourseConnective> représentant des victimes du conflit, j'ai aujourd'hui une opportunité sans précédent de m'adresser directement aux dirigeants européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7709" docOffset="56">
      <en>The people of Darfur need the European Union to show a strong, united position regarding protection of innocent civilians.</en>
      <fr>Le peuple du Darfour a besoin que l'Union européenne adopte une position forte et unie concernant la protection de civils innocents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7832" docOffset="57">
      <en>The people of Darfur ask you to protect them from the violence, killings and abuse they are forced to face on a daily basis.</en>
      <fr>Le peuple du Darfour vous demande de le protéger de la violence, des meurtres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8363">et</DiscourseConnective> des abus auxquels il est confronté quotidiennement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7957" docOffset="58">
      <en>The people of Darfur want you to protect their children and women from acts of rape and sexual violence, which are being used as 'weapons of war'.</en>
      <fr>Le peuple du Darfour veut que vous protégiez ses enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8475">et</DiscourseConnective> ses femmes des viols <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8499">et</DiscourseConnective> des violences sexuelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8526">qu'</DiscourseConnective>on utilise sur eux en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8551">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>"armes de guerre".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8104" docOffset="59">
      <en>This protection can be made possible through the deployment of the UN-AU hybrid force.</en>
      <fr>Cette protection peut être rendue possible par le biais d'un déploiement d'une force hybride ONU-UA.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8191" docOffset="60">
      <en>The involvement of international, and especially European, forces is imperative, even <Alignment alignment="8767" annotation_id="8277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8277" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Government of Sudan may be unwilling to accept that at the present moment.</en>
      <fr>L'engagement de forces internationales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8719">et</DiscourseConnective> particulièrement européennes, est impératif, <Alignment alignment="8277" annotation_id="8767">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8767" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le gouvernement soudanais n'est pas disposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8819">à</DiscourseConnective> l'accepter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8832">à</DiscourseConnective> l'heure actuelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8363" docOffset="61">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8852" annotation_id="8363">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8363" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europe has a role to play in putting more pressure on the Government of Sudan to facilitate the deployment of these troops and the protection of the people of Darfur.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8363" annotation_id="8852">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8852" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Europe a un rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8876">à</DiscourseConnective> jouer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8884">en</DiscourseConnective> mettant plus de pression sur le gouvernement soudanais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8942">afin de</DiscourseConnective> faciliter le déploiement de ces troupes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8990">et</DiscourseConnective> la protection du peuple du Darfour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8534" docOffset="62">
      <en>Now, in Darfur, and in Sudan, I tell you there will be no peace without justice and without protection.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, au Darfour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9053">et</DiscourseConnective> au Soudan, je vous le dis, il n'y aura pas de paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9107">sans</DiscourseConnective> justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9120">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9123">sans</DiscourseConnective> protection.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8638" docOffset="63">
      <en>Peace can <Alignment alignment="9153" annotation_id="8648">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8648" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be facilitated by Europe.</en>
      <fr>La paix peut <Alignment alignment="8648" annotation_id="9153">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9153" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être facilitée par l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8679" docOffset="64">
      <en>The European Union has a great responsibility to promote peace internationally.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne a la lourde responsabilité de promouvoir la paix dans le monde entier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8759" docOffset="65">
      <en>The leaders of Europe have the ability to lead the peace process <Alignment alignment="9359" annotation_id="8824">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8824" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in Sudan.</en>
      <fr>Les dirigeants européens ont la capacité de mener le processus de paix au Soudan <Alignment alignment="8824" annotation_id="9359">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9359" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8839" docOffset="66">
      <en>I ask you to increase your efforts in bringing the rebel groups and the Government of Sudan to the table of peace negotiations as a matter of urgency.</en>
      <fr>Je vous demande de redoubler d'efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9405">pour</DiscourseConnective> amener les rebelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9430">et</DiscourseConnective> le gouvernement soudanais autour de la table des négociations pour la paix, et ce dans le cadre d'une action d'urgence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8990" docOffset="67">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9553" annotation_id="8990">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8990" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the fact is that rebel groups are splitting among themselves, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9056" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this does not help the situation in Darfur.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3007" annotation_id="9553">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9553" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9558">le fait est que</DiscourseConnective> les groupements rebelles se divisent entre eux, ce qui nuit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9634">à</DiscourseConnective> la situation au Darfour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9104" docOffset="68">
      <en>I want you to think about taking on board other stakeholders: the millions of victims who are voiceless in the camps and other, directly affected people of Darfur.</en>
      <fr>Je veux que vous songiez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9686">à</DiscourseConnective> impliquer d'autres acteurs: les millions de victimes sans voix dans les camps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9766">et</DiscourseConnective> les autres citoyens du Darfour directement touchés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9268" docOffset="69">
      <en>Take on board <Alignment alignment="9831" annotation_id="9282">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9282" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the civil society movement, NGOs and community leaders.</en>
      <fr>Impliquez <Alignment alignment="6793" annotation_id="9831">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9831" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le mouvement de la société civile, les ONG <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9880">et</DiscourseConnective> les chefs de communautés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9343" docOffset="70">
      <en>That would help the situation in Darfur.</en>
      <fr>Cela ferait avancer la situation au Darfour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9384" docOffset="71">
      <en>Even <Alignment alignment="9954" annotation_id="9389">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9389" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we can provide protection and promote peace in Darfur, justice and accountability must not be compromised by any political deal.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9389" annotation_id="9954">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9954" sense="Contingency.Condition">Même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous pouvons fournir une protection <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9998">et</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir la paix au Darfour, la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10043">et</DiscourseConnective> la responsabilité ne doivent pas être compromises par un accord politique quel qu'il soit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9521" docOffset="72">
      <en>Presently, none of the victims can return to their houses or homes, because of the absence or lack of security.</en>
      <fr>Actuellement, aucune des victimes ne peut rejoindre sa maison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10199">ou</DiscourseConnective> son foyer, à cause de l'absence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10234">ou</DiscourseConnective> du manque de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9633" docOffset="73">
      <en>Not only are our communities being attacked by militias, <Alignment alignment="10322" annotation_id="9690">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9690" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> even helicopter gunships of the Government of Sudan are destroying our villages in aerial bombardments.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10260">Non seulement</DiscourseConnective> nos communautés sont attaquées par les milices, <Alignment alignment="9690" annotation_id="10322">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10322" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10327">même</DiscourseConnective> les hélicoptères armés du gouvernement soudanais détruisent nos villages lors de bombardements aériens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9798" docOffset="74">
      <en>Despite these serious violations of human rights and international humanitarian law, none of the perpetrators has been brought to justice, <Alignment alignment="10574" annotation_id="9937">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9937" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Sudanese judicial system is incapable, incompetent and unwilling to provide justice.</en>
      <fr>Malgré ces violations aggravées des droits humains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10487">et</DiscourseConnective> du droit humanitaire international, aucun des criminels n'a été traduit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10562">en</DiscourseConnective> justice, <Alignment alignment="9937" annotation_id="10574">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10574" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le système judiciaire soudanais est incapable, incompétent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10643">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'il n'est pas disposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10670">à</DiscourseConnective> rendre justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10034" docOffset="75">
      <en>All the perpetrators are beyond the reach of our domestic justice.</en>
      <fr>Tous les criminels sont hors de portée de notre justice nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10101" docOffset="76">
      <en>This conflict is one which is marked by a culture of total impunity.</en>
      <fr>Ce conflit compte parmi ceux qui sont marqués par une culture de totale impunité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10170" docOffset="77">
      <en>As a lawyer, and a native of Darfur, I know that there can never be a lasting peace in the region without justice.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10837">En</DiscourseConnective> tant qu'avocat né au Darfour, je sais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10878">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne pourra jamais y avoir de paix durable dans la région <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10940">sans</DiscourseConnective> justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10285" docOffset="78">
      <en>The International Criminal Court (ICC) has made some important and significant steps in promoting accountability.</en>
      <fr>La Cour pénale internationale (CPI) a pris plusieurs mesures importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11027">et</DiscourseConnective> significatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11045">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir la responsabilité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10399" docOffset="79">
      <en>Yet, the cycle of impunity has not yet been broken.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11085">Pourtant</DiscourseConnective>, le cycle de l'impunité n'a pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11126">encore</DiscourseConnective> été brisé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10451" docOffset="80">
      <en>The people of Darfur ask you to support the work of the ICC.</en>
      <fr>Le peuple du Darfour vous demande de soutenir le travail de la CPI.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10512" docOffset="81">
      <en>The ICC is the most competent international criminal tribunal which can make the many notorious perpetrators of war crimes and crimes against humanity accountable for their actions.</en>
      <fr>Elle constitue le tribunal international pénal le plus compétent, elle peut rendre responsables de leurs actes les nombreux auteurs notoires de crimes de guerre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11373">et</DiscourseConnective> de crimes contre l'humanité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10694" docOffset="82">
      <en>Right now, the two identified suspects Kosheib and Haroun are still beyond the reach of justice.</en>
      <fr>En ce moment même, les deux suspects identifiés Kosheib <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11461">et</DiscourseConnective> Haroun sont toujours hors de portée de la justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10791" docOffset="83">
      <en>The Government of Sudan is insisting that it will never hand them over to the ICC.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement soudanais insiste encore sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11568">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne les livrera jamais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11596">à</DiscourseConnective> la CPI.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10874" docOffset="84">
      <en>Darfur is not the only region of Sudan which suffers from abuses of human rights.</en>
      <fr>Le Darfour n'est pas la seule région du Soudan touchée par les violations des droits humains.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10956" docOffset="85">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11700" annotation_id="10956">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10956" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Indeed</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, citizens from every part of Sudan face daily restrictions on their freedom of expression, freedom of association and other basic rights that many people in Europe take for granted.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10956" annotation_id="11700">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11700" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, les citoyens des quatre coins du Soudan subissent des restrictions de leur liberté d'expression, d'association <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11821">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres droits fondamentaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11853">que</DiscourseConnective> bien des gens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11871">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe considèrent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11893">comme</DiscourseConnective> acquis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11145" docOffset="86">
      <en>I urge you, <Alignment alignment="11923" annotation_id="11157">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11157" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, to encourage and promote the rule of law in my country, <Alignment alignment="11989" annotation_id="11219">
          <Alignment alignment="11989" annotation_id="11219">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11219" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> all citizens of Sudan can enjoy their individual and collective rights.</en>
      <fr>Je vous demande <Alignment alignment="11157" annotation_id="11923">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11923" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'encourager la promotion de l'État de droit dans mon pays, <Alignment alignment="11219" annotation_id="11989">
          <Alignment alignment="11219" annotation_id="11989">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11989" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> tous les Soudanais puissent jouir de leurs droits individuels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12060">et</DiscourseConnective> collectifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11299" docOffset="87">
      <en>In the light of the upcoming elections in 2009, we must ensure that free and fair elections take place, <Alignment alignment="12179" annotation_id="11403">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11403" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that a free and fair result will be respected by all sides.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12075">À</DiscourseConnective> la lumière des élections à venir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12110">en</DiscourseConnective> 2009, nous devons garantir la tenue d'élections libres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12168">et</DiscourseConnective> justes, <Alignment alignment="11403" annotation_id="12179">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12179" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12185">que</DiscourseConnective> le respect par toutes les parties de résultats libres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12243">et</DiscourseConnective> justes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11467" docOffset="88">
      <en>Lastly, I would like to thank you, the Members of the European Parliament, who came to Sudan in June of this year to see with your own eyes what I have described.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12254">Pour terminer</DiscourseConnective>, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12278">à</DiscourseConnective> vous remercier, députés du Parlement européen qui êtes venus au Soudan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12351">en</DiscourseConnective> juin de cette année <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12374">pour</DiscourseConnective> constater de visu ce que je viens de vous décrire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11630" docOffset="89">
      <en>This was a visit coordinated by the office of the European Commission in Khartoum.</en>
      <fr>Cette visite a été coordonnée par le bureau de la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12502">à</DiscourseConnective> Khartoum.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11713" docOffset="90">
      <en>The office of the European Commission has been a source of great support and a partner to me in my work for many years now.</en>
      <fr>Le bureau de la Commission européenne est une source de grand soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12584">et</DiscourseConnective> un partenaire dans mon travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12618">depuis</DiscourseConnective> bien des années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11837" docOffset="91">
      <en>The recognition of the European Commission and of you, the European Parliament, for the work of human rights defenders in Sudan gives us the courage and determination to continue to speak for the victims, and relieve some of their suffering.</en>
      <fr>La reconnaissance par la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12689">et</DiscourseConnective> vous, le Parlement européen, du travail des défenseurs des droits humains au Soudan nous donne le courage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12798">et</DiscourseConnective> la détermination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12818">pour</DiscourseConnective> continuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12833">à</DiscourseConnective> parler au nom des victimes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12863">pour</DiscourseConnective> alléger un peu leurs souffrances.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12079" docOffset="92">
      <en>In conclusion, I am proud to accept this honour on behalf of the other candidates to this prize: the Russian journalist assassinated last year, Anna Politkovskaya; the Chinese dissidents, Zeng Jinyan and Hu Jia; and the Afghani MP and women's rights activist, Joya Malalai, and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12357" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> on behalf of so many Sudanese who believe - <Alignment alignment="13241" annotation_id="12406">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12406" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I do - in human dignity and the pursuit of justice.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12902">En</DiscourseConnective> conclusion, je suis fier d'accepter cet honneur au nom de tous les autres candidats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12989">à</DiscourseConnective> ce prix: la journaliste russe assassinée l'année dernière, Anna Politkovskaya, les dissidents chinois, Zeng Jinyan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13106">et</DiscourseConnective> Hu Jia, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13117">et</DiscourseConnective> la députée afghane <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13139">et</DiscourseConnective> activiste des droits de la femme, Joya Malalai, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13190">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'au nom de tant de Soudanais qui croient - <Alignment alignment="12406" annotation_id="13241">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13241" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> moi - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13253">à</DiscourseConnective> la dignité humaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13274">et</DiscourseConnective> à la poursuite de la justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12461" docOffset="93">
      <en>Thank you so much.</en>
      <fr>Merci beaucoup.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12480" docOffset="94">
      <en>(The House rose and accorded the speaker a standing ovation)</en>
      <fr>(L'Assemblée, debout, applaudit l'orateur)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12541" id="135" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12541" docOffset="95">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, may I ask you to stand, or remain standing, for the European anthem in honour of Salih Osman.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13380">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13394">puis</DiscourseConnective>-je vous demander de vous lever, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13431">ou</DiscourseConnective> de rester debout, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13452">pour</DiscourseConnective> écouter l'hymne national qui va être joué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13499">en</DiscourseConnective> l'honneur de Salih Osman.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
