<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Welcome</en>
    <fr>Souhaits de bienvenue</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="098" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I am delighted to be able to inform you that a delegation from Australia's House of Representatives and Senate has taken its place in the public gallery.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, j'ai le plaisir de vous informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="83">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une délégation de la Chambre des Représentants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="133">et</DiscourseConnective> du Sénat d'Australie a pris place dans l'hémicycle parmi le public.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="184" docOffset="2">
      <en>I wish a very warm welcome to you all.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="216">à</DiscourseConnective> tous une très chaleureuse bienvenue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="223" docOffset="3">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="234" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is taking part in the 31st EP-Australia interparliamentary meeting, which is being held here in the European Parliament on 9 and 10 April.</en>
      <fr>La délégation participe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="298">à</DiscourseConnective> la 31e réunion interparlementaire qui se tient ici au Parlement européen les 9 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="379">et</DiscourseConnective> 10 avril.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="376" docOffset="5">
      <en>The delegation consists of Members of the Senate and the House of Representatives, and is led by Senator Alan Ferguson, President of the Australian Senate.</en>
      <fr>La délégation comprend des membres du Sénat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="436">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Chambre des Représentants. Elle est emmenée par la sénateur Alan Ferguson, président du Sénat australien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="532" docOffset="6">
      <en>The European Parliament and the Australian Parliament began their direct and wide-ranging political dialogue in 1981.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="573">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement australien ont entamé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="611">en</DiscourseConnective> 1981 leur dialogue politique direct <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="650">et</DiscourseConnective> de vaste portée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="650" docOffset="7">
      <en>We very much look forward to strengthening and expanding this cooperation even further.</en>
      <fr>Nous anticipons avec intérêt le renforcement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="715">et</DiscourseConnective> l'expansion de cette coopération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="738" docOffset="8">
      <en>I wish the delegation every success for the remainder of its stay and a safe journey home <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="828" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> the time comes.</en>
      <fr>Tous mes vœux de réussite accompagnent la délégation pendant son séjour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="824">et</DiscourseConnective>, le moment venu, lors de son voyage retour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="849" docOffset="9">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
