<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Membership of Parliament</en>
    <fr>Composition du Parlement</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="25" id="009" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="25" docOffset="1">
      <en>The 35 Romanian Members will be the voice of the Romanian people, representing their interests in the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Les 35 députés roumains exprimeront la voix du peuple roumain, et représenteront leurs intérêts au sein du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="148" docOffset="2">
      <en>As President of the European Parliament, I wish our new fellow Members - many of whom we already know from their work to date - every success in the forthcoming 18 months of their mandate.</en>
      <fr>En ma qualité de Président du Parlement européen, je souhaite un franc succès à nos nouveaux collègues au cours des 18 prochains mois de leur mandat. Nous connaissons d'ailleurs déjà certains de ces collègues par le travail qu'ils ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="392">déjà</DiscourseConnective> réalisé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="405">à</DiscourseConnective> ce jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="337" docOffset="3">
      <en>On this occasion I should <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="363" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> like once again to thank all the members of the Romanian Parliament, who have been observers since September 2005 and Members of the European Parliament since 1 January this year.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="416">À</DiscourseConnective> cette occasion, j'aimerais à nouveau remercier l'ensemble des députés roumains, qui ont assuré le rôle d'observateurs à partir de septembre 2005 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="563">et</DiscourseConnective> sont aujourd'hui députés européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="601">depuis</DiscourseConnective> le 1er janvier de cette année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="548" docOffset="4">
      <en>I thank you for you tireless work and your commitment to European unity.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="656">pour</DiscourseConnective> votre travail acharné <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="683">et</DiscourseConnective> votre dévouement envers l'unité européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="621" docOffset="5">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="632" docOffset="6">
      <en>A total of 13 of the first MEPs were re-elected <Alignment alignment="798" annotation_id="680">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="680" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I hope that they will assist their new fellow Members in their full and very quick integration into the work of Parliament <Alignment alignment="914" annotation_id="807">
          <Alignment alignment="575" annotation_id="807">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="807" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> together they contribute to the success of the European unification project for the benefit of their electors.</en>
      <fr>13 des premiers députés européens ont été réélus <Alignment alignment="680" annotation_id="798">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="798" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="810">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils aideront leurs nouveaux collègues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="851">à</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="853">s'</DiscourseConnective>intégrer pleinement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="875">et</DiscourseConnective> rapidement aux travaux du Parlement <Alignment alignment="3" annotation_id="914">
          <Alignment alignment="807" annotation_id="914">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="914" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de sorte qu'</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>ensemble, ils contribuent au succès du projet d'unification européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="998">pour</DiscourseConnective> le bien de leurs électeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="926" docOffset="7">
      <en>A list of these Members is published in the Minutes of today's sitting.</en>
      <fr>La liste de ces députés est publiée au procès-verbal de la session d'aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="998" docOffset="8">
      <en>Once again, a very warm welcome to our fellow Members from Romania.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de souhaiter à nouveau chaleureusement la bienvenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1179">à</DiscourseConnective> nos collègues roumains.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
