<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>European Space Policy: How to bring space down to earth (debate)</en>
    <fr>Politique spatiale européenne: l'Europe et l'espace (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="65" id="228" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="65" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the debate on:</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="97" docOffset="2">
      <en>the oral question to the Council (B6-0482/2008) by Mr Pribetich, on behalf of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy, on the European space policy: How to bring space down to earth, and</en>
      <fr>la question orale au Conseil sur la politique spatiale européenne: l'Europe et l'espace de Pierre Pribetich, au nom de la commission de l'industrie, de la recherche et de l'énergie - B6-0482/2008), <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="296">et</DiscourseConnective>
      </fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="291" docOffset="3">
      <en>the oral question to the Commission (B6-0483/2008) by Mr Pribetich, on behalf of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy, on the European space policy: How to bring space down to earth.</en>
      <fr>la question orale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="317">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur la politique spatiale européenne: l'Europe et l'espace de Pierre Pribetich, au nom de la commission de l'industrie, de la recherche et de l'énergie - B6-0483/2008).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="484" docOffset="4">
      <en>As a native of Toulouse, I am delighted to chair this debate.</en>
      <fr>Le Toulousain que je suis est ravi de présider ce débat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="546" id="229" name="Pierre Pribetich">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="546" docOffset="5">
      <en>author. - (FR) Mr President, Mr Vice-President, Minister, 'it is high time to rekindle the stars'.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Vice-président, Monsieur le Ministre, "il est grand temps de rallumer les étoiles".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="645" docOffset="6">
      <en>I wanted to begin my speech with this line from a Guillaume Apollinaire poem, to emphasise the importance for the European Parliament of relaunching its space policy.</en>
      <fr>Je voulais débuter mon propos par ce vers d'un poème de Guillaume Apollinaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="767">pour</DiscourseConnective> signifier l'importance, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="796">pour</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen, de relancer la politique spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="812" docOffset="7">
      <en>For more than thirty years, the European Union and its Member States have worked together in financing, drawing up and developing space policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="859">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> plus de trente ans, l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="905">et</DiscourseConnective> ses États membres concourent au financement, à l'élaboration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="969">et</DiscourseConnective> au développement de la politique spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="956" docOffset="8">
      <en>Alas, this policy has progressively lost its luminescence and radiance.</en>
      <fr>Hélas, progressivement, cette politique a perdu de sa luminescence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1082">et</DiscourseConnective> de son rayonnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1028" docOffset="9">
      <en>It is true that in 2003, the foundations of a European space policy were set out by the EC-ESA framework agreement.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1105">Certes</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1113">en</DiscourseConnective> 2003, les fondements d'une politique spatiale européenne furent élaborés par l'accord-cadre CE - ESA.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1144" docOffset="10">
      <en>It is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1150" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> true that the 'Space' Council of 22 May 2007 was in line with the political continuum of this framework agreement.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1218">Certes</DiscourseConnective>, le Conseil "Espace" du 22 mai 2007 s'inscrivait dans le continuum politique de cet accord-cadre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1270" docOffset="11">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7347" annotation_id="1270">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1270" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the light emitted by this star remains insufficient.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1270" annotation_id="1323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1323" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la lumière émise par cette étoile demeure insuffisante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1332" docOffset="12">
      <en>For Europe's independence, its role on the international stage, its security and prosperity all come together to make this major policy an incomparable trump card for an industrial policy that creates both jobs and stimulates growth; an ambitious policy for cultural, economic and scientific influence that is reinforced on the international stage and is an essential vehicle for society to acquire the knowledge that we wish to gain.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1384">Pour autant</DiscourseConnective>, l'indépendance de l'Europe, son rôle sur la scène internationale, la sécurité, sa prospérité, tout converge <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1505">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire de cette politique majeure un atout incomparable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1565">pour</DiscourseConnective> une politique industrielle créatrice d'emplois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1617">et</DiscourseConnective> de croissance, ambitieuse, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1647">pour</DiscourseConnective> une influence culturelle, économique, scientifique renforcée sur la scène internationale, vecteur essentiel de la société de la connaissance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1793">que</DiscourseConnective> nous appelons de nos vœux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1767" docOffset="13">
      <en>In the institutional triangle of the Union, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1811" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> to ensure that this does not turn into a Bermuda triangle, the European Parliament, on behalf of European citizens, must play an important and increased role in the drawing up and definition of this policy.</en>
      <fr>Dans le triangle institutionnel de l'Union, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1868">pour qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne se transforme pas en triangle des Bermudes, le Parlement représentant les citoyens européens doit jouer un rôle important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2004">et</DiscourseConnective> accru dans l'élaboration, la définition de cette politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2022" docOffset="14">
      <en>It is high time to rekindle the stars.</en>
      <fr>Il est grand temps de rallumer les étoiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2061" docOffset="15">
      <en>On 26 September 2008, the Council participated in this act <Alignment alignment="24007" annotation_id="2120">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2120" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want to make our mark on this policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2111">En</DiscourseConnective> s'engageant, le 26 septembre 2008, le Conseil participe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2170">à</DiscourseConnective> cet acte <Alignment alignment="2120" annotation_id="2181">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2181" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous, nous voulons apporter notre pierre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2225">à</DiscourseConnective> cet édifice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2165" docOffset="16">
      <en>Of course, this address here and now on behalf of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy is made in this same spirit.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2240">Certes</DiscourseConnective>, cette adresse aujourd'hui, ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2279">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2282">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, au nom de la commission industrie, recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2339">et</DiscourseConnective> énergie relève de cette <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2366">même</DiscourseConnective> disposition d'esprit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2291" docOffset="17">
      <en>To follow the correct route, it seems to me essential to remember the fundamental elements in the creation of this space policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2393">Pour</DiscourseConnective> suivre cette bonne étoile, il me paraît essentiel de rappeler les éléments fondamentaux dans l'élaboration de cette politique spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2420" docOffset="18">
      <en>Firstly, there is the question of the budget.</en>
      <fr>La question du budget, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2557">d'abord</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2466" docOffset="19">
      <en>We call for, from this point onwards, the creation of a specific budget line to reflect and demonstrate our commitment to European space policy.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons, dès à présent, la création d'une ligne budgétaire spécifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2643">pour</DiscourseConnective> refléter, pour démontrer comme il se doit notre engagement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2707">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard de la politique spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2611" docOffset="20">
      <en>The space industries need sufficient public support to increase their research and development capacity and, quite simply, to remain profitable.</en>
      <fr>Les industries spatiales ont besoin d'un soutien public suffisant, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2821">pour</DiscourseConnective> augmenter leur capacité en recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2863">et</DiscourseConnective> développement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2881">pour</DiscourseConnective> rester tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2898">simplement</DiscourseConnective> rentables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2756" docOffset="21">
      <en>International competition is hard and fierce.</en>
      <fr>La concurrence internationale est rude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2959">et</DiscourseConnective> âpre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2802" docOffset="22">
      <en>Whilst the United States, Russia, Japan and even India are significantly increasing their budget dedicated to the space industry, <Alignment alignment="3112" annotation_id="2932">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2932" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> multiplying public orders, us Europeans are still searching for the appropriate funding to achieve our ambitious aims like others search for lost time.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2968">Tandis que</DiscourseConnective> les États-Unis, la Russie, le Japon <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3015">ou encore</DiscourseConnective> l'Inde augmentent de manière significative leur budget consacré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3089">à</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie spatiale <Alignment alignment="2829" annotation_id="3112">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3112" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> multiplient les commandes publiques, nous, Européens, nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3181">encore</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3188">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche de financements appropriés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3230">pour</DiscourseConnective> atteindre nos objectifs ambitieux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3270">comme</DiscourseConnective> d'autres recherchent le temps perdu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3088" docOffset="23">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="68068" annotation_id="3088">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3088" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Consequently</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, what initiatives can the Commission take to improve the contribution to the European space sector, and be not just an actor, but the major actor responding to this growing, global demand, across all aspects of space policy from beginning to end?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17809" annotation_id="3313">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3313" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">En conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, quelles initiatives propres la Commission compte-t-elle prendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3393">pour</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la contribution du secteur spatial européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3453">pour</DiscourseConnective> être un acteur, l'acteur majeur répondant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3500">à</DiscourseConnective> cette demande croissante, mondiale, sur tous les aspects de la politique spatiale, du lanceur au service?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3348" docOffset="24">
      <en>The second point is the issue of strategic options for those applications linked, on the one hand, to Galileo and EGNOS and, on the other, to GMES, through the prism of governance to create an efficient structure generating a clear governance for a reinforced efficiency across all European space programmes.</en>
      <fr>Deuxième volet. L'enjeu des options stratégiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3657">pour</DiscourseConnective> les applications liées, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3686">d'une part</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3698">à</DiscourseConnective> Galileo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3708">et</DiscourseConnective> Egnos <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3717">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3721">d'autre part</DiscourseConnective>, au GEMS, à travers le prisme de la gouvernance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3782">pour</DiscourseConnective> créer une structure efficiente, générant une gouvernance claire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3851">pour</DiscourseConnective> une efficacité renforcée de tous les programmes spatiaux européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3657" docOffset="25">
      <en>The final issue is the exploration of space.</en>
      <fr>Dernier enjeu, l'exploration de l'espace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3702" docOffset="26">
      <en>What is the long-term vision for our European space policy, and for what ends does it exist?</en>
      <fr>Quelle vision à long terme de notre politique spatiale européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4033">pour</DiscourseConnective> quels objectifs?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3795" docOffset="27">
      <en>Embarking on the long-distance conquest of space is a project for several decades and requires both long-term vision and ambition</en>
      <fr>Partir à la conquête de l'espace lointain est l'affaire de décennies, d'une vision à long terme, d'une ambition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3925" docOffset="28">
      <en>At this point, I see an echo of the speech made by President Kennedy, focusing the American people on a new uncrossed frontier.</en>
      <fr>J'ai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4173">à</DiscourseConnective> cet instant en écho le discours du président Kennedy, fixant au peuple américain une nouvelle frontière dépassable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4053" docOffset="29">
      <en>Made sacred on 21 July 1969, this step was, without a doubt, in the technological history of our civilisation, the most fabulous catalyst for progress for all space-related and even everyday industries.</en>
      <fr>Sacraliser le 21 juillet 1969: cette démarche fut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4341">sans</DiscourseConnective> doute, dans l'histoire technologique de notre civilisation, l'accélérateur de progrès le plus fabuleux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4449">pour</DiscourseConnective> toutes les industries relevant du spatial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4496">et même</DiscourseConnective> du quotidien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4256" docOffset="30">
      <en>Give us, in this concert of nations, this long term vision.</en>
      <fr>Donnez-nous cette vision à long terme dans ce concert des nations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4316" docOffset="31">
      <en>Here we find ourselves at a milestone on this long journey.</en>
      <fr>Nous voilà donc <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4601">au point d'</DiscourseConnective>étape de cette longue marche, à un point d'étape.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4376" docOffset="32">
      <en>Europe is at a crossroads with regard to space policy.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4675">à</DiscourseConnective> la croisée des chemins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4700">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de politique spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4431" docOffset="33">
      <en>Space has, from now on, multiplied its spheres of action and application.</en>
      <fr>L'espace a désormais multiplié ses champs d'action <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4785">et</DiscourseConnective> d'application.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4505" docOffset="34">
      <en>From scientific to defence activities, space covers sectors of activity as vast and as varied as environmental protection or the development of SMEs.</en>
      <fr>Des activités scientifiques aux activités de défense, l'espace couvre des secteurs d'activité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4897">aussi</DiscourseConnective> vastes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4910">et</DiscourseConnective> variés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4920">que</DiscourseConnective> la protection environnementale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4955">ou</DiscourseConnective> le développement des PME.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4655" docOffset="35">
      <en>Let us get closer to users and increase the viability and quality of the collected data.</en>
      <fr>Rapprochons-nous des utilisateurs, augmentons la fiabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5043">et</DiscourseConnective> la qualité des données récoltées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4744" docOffset="36">
      <en>Let us become the leaders in the space market.</en>
      <fr>Devenons les leaders du marché spatial.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4791" docOffset="37">
      <en>It is a duty that we owe to future generations to fortify this European space policy and make the vital choices to place into orbit an avant-garde and futuristic Europe for subsequent generations to live in.</en>
      <fr>C'est un devoir vis-à-vis des générations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5162">à</DiscourseConnective> venir que de fortifier cette politique européenne de l'espace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5226">et</DiscourseConnective> de faire les choix capitaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5257">pour</DiscourseConnective> mettre en orbite les générations futures, qu'elles puissent vivre dans une Europe avant-gardiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5359">et</DiscourseConnective> futuriste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4999" docOffset="38">
      <en>Space is our new European frontier.</en>
      <fr>L'espace est notre nouvelle frontière de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5035" docOffset="39">
      <en>The great history book lies open with its dizzying array of blank pages.</en>
      <fr>Le grand livre de l'histoire est ouvert maintenant avec son vertige de pages blanches.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5108" docOffset="40">
      <en>Europe must not only play a part in it, <Alignment alignment="47876" annotation_id="5148">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5148" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be the major actor.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe ne doit pas seulement en faire partie, <Alignment alignment="6445" annotation_id="5559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5559" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5564">en</DiscourseConnective> être l'acteur majeur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5172" docOffset="41">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2431" annotation_id="5172">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5172" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is high time to rekindle the stars.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="2046" annotation_id="5596">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5596" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> bien grand temps de rallumer les étoiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5222" id="230" language="FR" name="Jean-Pierre Jouyet">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5222" docOffset="42">
      <en>Mr President, Mr Vice-President of the Commission, Mr Verheugen, honourable Members, your speech, Mr Pribetich, and questioning are particularly pertinent <Alignment alignment="5920" annotation_id="5377">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5377" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> given the élan with which you have posed and supported them, your speech will be particularly difficult to follow.</en>
      <fr>président en exercice du Conseil. - Cher Monsieur le Président Onesta, Monsieur le Vice-président de la Commission européenne, Monsieur Verheugen, Mesdames et Messieurs les Députés, Monsieur Pribetich, votre intervention et vos interrogations sont particulièrement pertinentes <Alignment alignment="13662" annotation_id="5920">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5920" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, compte tenu de l'élan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5946">que</DiscourseConnective> vous avez mis à les soutenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5979">et</DiscourseConnective> à les poser, il me sera particulièrement difficile d'intervenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6046">après</DiscourseConnective> vous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5496" docOffset="43">
      <en>They are pertinent, <Alignment alignment="6071" annotation_id="5516">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5516" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> space has become, <Alignment alignment="60689" annotation_id="5542">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5542" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you have pointed out, an essential tool for all European countries.</en>
      <fr>Pertinentes, <Alignment alignment="26593" annotation_id="6071">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6071" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'espace est devenu, <Alignment alignment="27367" annotation_id="6102">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6102" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous l'avez souligné, un outil essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6149">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous les pays européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5613" docOffset="44">
      <en>These missions contribute to our acquisition of knowledge, whether this concerns the observation of the earth or oceanography or meteorology by satellite.</en>
      <fr>Ses missions contribuent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6204">à</DiscourseConnective> l'accroissement de nos connaissances, tant en ce qui concerne l'observation de la terre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6294">ou</DiscourseConnective> l'océanographie que la météorologie par satellite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5768" docOffset="45">
      <en>It <Alignment alignment="6362" annotation_id="5771">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5771" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> corresponds to the growth of our economies through satellite telecommunications and navigation.</en>
      <fr>Il correspond <Alignment alignment="13411" annotation_id="6362">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6362" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6368">à</DiscourseConnective> la croissance de nos économies à travers les télécommunications <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6434">et</DiscourseConnective> la navigation par satellite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5872" docOffset="46">
      <en>It has become, in a discrete yet essential way, an integral instrument for modern life.</en>
      <fr>C'est devenu, tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6485">à</DiscourseConnective> fait discrètement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6506">mais</DiscourseConnective> de manière essentielle, un instrument consubstantiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6564">à</DiscourseConnective> la vie moderne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5960" docOffset="47">
      <en>Space is <Alignment alignment="6595" annotation_id="5969">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5969" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a tool, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5982" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> you have indicated, that allows Europe to be united around a common ambition and to develop a European identity.</en>
      <fr>L'espace est <Alignment alignment="22469" annotation_id="6595">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6595" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un outil, vous l'avez indiqué, qui permet de fédérer l'Europe autour d'une <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6676">même</DiscourseConnective> ambition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6690">et</DiscourseConnective> qui permet de développer l'identité européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6098" docOffset="48">
      <en>It is in this spirit, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6120" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>, that the French Presidency organised, last July, with Valérie Pécresse, the first informal meeting of European space ministers at Kourou which, <Alignment alignment="32716" annotation_id="6275">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6275" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you know, is the European spaceport.</en>
      <fr>Et c'est dans cet esprit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6766">que</DiscourseConnective> la présidence française a organisé, en juillet dernier, avec Valérie Pécresse, la première réunion informelle des ministres européens chargés de l'espace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6924">à</DiscourseConnective> Kourou, qui est, <Alignment alignment="6275" annotation_id="6943">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6943" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez, le port spatial de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6315" docOffset="49">
      <en>I know that the European Parliament was represented by Mr Rovsing at this event, <Alignment alignment="7097" annotation_id="6396">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6396" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I thank him for that.</en>
      <fr>Je sais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7001">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen était représenté par M. Rovsing dans le cadre de cette manifestation, <Alignment alignment="18974" annotation_id="7097">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7097" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'en remercie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6422" docOffset="50">
      <en>This meeting allowed us to set out a common vision for Europe in space built around the three principal actors of European space policy: the Union, the European Space Agency, and the Member States - <Alignment alignment="40912" annotation_id="6621">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6621" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> recognising the Union's increased responsibilities.</en>
      <fr>Cette réunion a permis de dégager une vision commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7171">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe dans l'espace autour des trois acteurs principaux de la politique spatiale européenne: l'Union, l'Agence spatiale européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7310">et</DiscourseConnective> les États membres, <Alignment alignment="5162" annotation_id="7332">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7332" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> reconnaissant à l'Union des responsabilités accrues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6679" docOffset="51">
      <en>Together, these three actors will make Europe one of the main space powers on the international stage, of that we are certain.</en>
      <fr>Ces trois acteurs feront, ensemble, de l'Europe une des principales puissances spatiales sur la scène internationale, soyez-en certains.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6806" docOffset="52">
      <en>To develop a European space policy of benefit to all Europeans, first of all we need to guarantee open and equal access for all Member States of the Union to the advantages that are brought by space activities. Secondly, we must reinforce existing coordination mechanisms in the space sector, European expertise and investments financed by both the Community and by intergovernmental and national sources.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7530">Pour</DiscourseConnective> développer une politique spatiale européenne qui bénéficie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7594">à</DiscourseConnective> tous les Européens, il convient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7628">premièrement</DiscourseConnective> de garantir l'accès libre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7667">et</DiscourseConnective> équitable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7680">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble des États membres de l'Union aux avantages <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7739">que</DiscourseConnective> représentent les activités spatiales; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7781">deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, de renforcer les mécanismes existants de coordination dans le domaine spatial, l'expertise européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7897">et</DiscourseConnective> les investissements financés par la Communauté, par des sources intergouvernementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7986">et</DiscourseConnective> nationales; enfin, il nous faut aussi améliorer les synergies entre les programmes spatiaux civils et de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7212" docOffset="53">Finally, it is necessary to improve the synergy between civil and defence space programmes.</ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7304" docOffset="54">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8104" annotation_id="7304">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7304" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Union, the European Space Agency and the Member States will ensure that we benefit from an access to space that is autonomous, viable and at the best price, which is necessary with regard to our biggest partners.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8282" annotation_id="8104">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8104" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, c'est ainsi que l'Union, l'Agence spatiale européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8164">et</DiscourseConnective> les États membres feront en sorte de bénéficier d'un accès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8226">à</DiscourseConnective> l'espace qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8241">soit</DiscourseConnective> autonome, fiable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8263">et</DiscourseConnective> au meilleur coût, ce qui est nécessaire par rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8318">à</DiscourseConnective> nos grands partenaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7531" docOffset="55">
      <en>Of course, this requires a reinforcing of the role of the European Union in the sphere of European space policy.</en>
      <fr>Bien sûr, cela nécessite un renforcement du rôle de l'Union européenne dans la politique spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7644" docOffset="56">
      <en>It is for the Union to unite demand for space applications, to take stock of users' requirements, to establish priorities and to look after the continuity of services.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8460">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union qu'il convient de fédérer la demande en matière d'applications spatiales, de recenser les exigences des utilisateurs, d'établir les priorités, de veiller à la continuité des services.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7812" docOffset="57">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8665" annotation_id="7812">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7812" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, at Union level, we have developed instruments and Community financial schemes to take into account the characteristics of the space sector with respect, in particular, to forthcoming financial perspectives.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="20458" annotation_id="8665">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8665" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, au niveau de l'Union, développé des instruments <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8724">et</DiscourseConnective> des schémas financiers communautaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8765">pour</DiscourseConnective> prendre en compte les spécificités du secteur spatial dans le cadre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8839">notamment</DiscourseConnective>, des prochaines perspectives financières.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8025" docOffset="58">
      <en>The 'Space' Council that took place on 26 September made it possible to send into orbit, <Alignment alignment="22352" annotation_id="8114">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8114" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I dare say, and to confirm the importance of the two flagship programmes, Galileo EGNOS and GMES.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil "Espace" qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8915">s'</DiscourseConnective>est tenu le 26 septembre dernier a permis de mettre en orbite, <Alignment alignment="11084" annotation_id="8980">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8980" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'ose dire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8995">et</DiscourseConnective> de confirmer l'importance des deux programmes phares que sont Galileo EGNOS <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9074">et</DiscourseConnective> le programme GMES.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8215" docOffset="59">
      <en>With regard to Galileo EGNOS, the European Union can congratulate itself on having signed a significant number of cooperation agreements with third countries such as the United States, China, Israel, South Korea, Ukraine and Morocco.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9096">À propos</DiscourseConnective> de Galileo EGNOS, l'Union européenne peut se féliciter d'avoir signé un nombre important d'accords de coopération avec des États tiers, tels les États-Unis, la Chine, Israël, la Corée du Sud, l'Ukraine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9307">et</DiscourseConnective> le Maroc.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8449" docOffset="60">
      <en>This same Council of 26 September underlined the importance of increasing the coordination between the Commission, the European Space Agency and the Member States in the sphere of research and development, notably for satellite navigation systems.</en>
      <fr>Ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9323">même</DiscourseConnective> Conseil du 26 septembre a souligné l'importance d'accroître la coordination entre la Commission, l'ESA <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9431">et</DiscourseConnective> les États membres dans le domaine de la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9484">et</DiscourseConnective> du développement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9505">notamment</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9515">pour</DiscourseConnective> les systèmes de navigation par satellite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8697" docOffset="61">
      <en>With regard to the GMES programme, the forthcoming Councils on 1 and 2 December are expected to set out the applicable lines and define the terms of the partnership between the Union and the Member States and to lay down legislative proposals formalising the programme before the end of 2009. I can already inform you that the Council believes that an approach based on the public good must be maintained for this programme to develop successfully.</en>
      <fr>Concernant le programme GMES, les Conseils à venir des 1er <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9621">et</DiscourseConnective> 2 décembre prochains devraient fixer les lignes applicables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9684">et</DiscourseConnective> définir le terme du partenariat entre l'Union <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9733">et</DiscourseConnective> les États membres, faire des propositions législatives qui formalisent le programme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9820">avant</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'année 2009, et je peux d'ores et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9871">déjà</DiscourseConnective> vous indiquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9890">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil considère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9915">que</DiscourseConnective> l'approche basée sur le bien public est celle qui doit être retenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9987">pour</DiscourseConnective> le bon développement de ce programme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9146" docOffset="62">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9146" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>, a data policy must <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9178" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> be put into place swiftly.</en>
      <fr>Une politique des données, également, doit être mise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10083">en</DiscourseConnective> place rapidement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9210" docOffset="63">Finally, there must be four priorities that have <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9259" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> been cited by Mr Pribetich: the first concerns space and climate change, inasmuch as the contribution of space applications is unique in this sphere.</ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9414" docOffset="64">The second is the contribution of space activities to the Lisbon strategy.</ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9489" docOffset="65">
      <en>The third covers space and security with respect to having monitoring and surveillance of European space infrastructures and space debris at European level. Finally, the fourth priority remains space exploration, this is a political and planetary policy <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9743" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> Europe should act within the framework of a worldwide programme.</en>
      <fr>Enfin, il doit y avoir quatre priorités, qui ont d'ailleurs été reprises par M. Pribetich: la première, c'est l'espace et le changement climatique, tant la contribution des applications spatiales est unique en ce domaine; la seconde, c'est la contribution des activités spatiales à la stratégie de Lisbonne; la troisième, c'est tout ce qui a trait à l'espace et à la sécurité de façon à ce que nous puissions avoir, au niveau européen, un suivi et une surveillance des infrastructures spatiales européennes et des débris spatiaux; enfin, la quatrième priorité reste l'exploration spatiale, c'est une entreprise politique et planétaire et l'Europe devrait agir dans le cadre d'un programme mondial.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9812" docOffset="66">
      <en>In this respect, Europe must develop a common vision and a long-term strategic plan and must <Alignment alignment="10911" annotation_id="9905">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9905" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have the necessary political dialogue with other states within an enlarged framework of international cooperation <Alignment alignment="11037" annotation_id="10024">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10024" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in this respect, the Council is very pleased that the Commission has announced that it will be organising a high level political conference in 2009 concerning the long-term worldwide vision for space exploration.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10804">Pour</DiscourseConnective> cela, l'Europe doit élaborer une vision commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10857">et</DiscourseConnective> une planification stratégique à long terme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10903">et</DiscourseConnective> doit <Alignment alignment="13659" annotation_id="10911">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10911" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avoir le dialogue politique nécessaire avec les autres États dans le cadre d'une coopération internationale élargie <Alignment alignment="15919" annotation_id="11037">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11037" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, de ce point de vue, le Conseil se félicite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11084">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission ait annoncé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11114">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle organiserait, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11136">en</DiscourseConnective> 2009, une conférence politique de haut niveau sur la vision mondiale à long terme en matière d'exploration spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10242" docOffset="67">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10242" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">And</DiscourseConnective> so, Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, this renewed vision of European space policy demonstrates a new commitment from the Member States, a commitment that, in the interests of unprecedented European ambition, I have no doubt will resonate across your House.</en>
      <fr>Voilà, Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11295">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs les Députés, cette vision renouvelée de la politique spatiale européenne marque un nouvel engagement des États membres, un engagement qui, au service d'une ambition européenne exceptionnelle, je n'en doute pas, trouvera un écho dans votre Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10506" id="231" language="DE" name="Günter Verheugen">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10506" docOffset="68">
      <en>Mr President, Mr President-in-Office of the Council, ladies and gentlemen, I am very grateful to Mr Pribetich for giving me the opportunity to begin a speech on a highly technical subject with a line from a poem by my favourite French poet Guillaume Apollinaire: 'Il est grand temps de rallumer les étoiles.'</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11643">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11676">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je remercie M. Pribetich de m'avoir donné la possibilité d'entamer mon allocution consacrée à un sujet hautement technique sur un vers de mon poète français favori, Guillaume Apollinaire: "Il est grand temps de rallumer les étoiles."</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10815" docOffset="69">
      <en>I believe that the French Presidency has already taken considerable steps towards giving European space policy the importance which it genuinely deserves.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11933">que</DiscourseConnective> la présidence française a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11963">déjà</DiscourseConnective> largement contribué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11988">à</DiscourseConnective> rendre à la politique spatiale européenne l'importance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12045">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle mérite réellement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10970" docOffset="70">
      <en>We have made major progress in recent years <Alignment alignment="12138" annotation_id="11014">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11014" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, for the first time, we have a European space policy, which we have never had before.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons réalisé des progrès considérables ces dernières années <Alignment alignment="11014" annotation_id="12138">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12138" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12142">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois dans l'histoire, nous avons une politique spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11104" docOffset="71">
      <en>We have a framework for a common European policy in which the Commission plays a coordinating role.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons mis en place le cadre d'une politique européenne dans laquelle la Commission joue un rôle de coordination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11204" docOffset="72">
      <en>We have achieved a high level of agreement on the strategic, environmental and economic importance of the space policy for Europe.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes parvenus à un large consensus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12387">quant à</DiscourseConnective> l'importance stratégique, environnementale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12438">et</DiscourseConnective> économique de la politique spatiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12477">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11335" docOffset="73">
      <en>No one opposes this.</en>
      <fr>Personne ne s'y oppose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11356" docOffset="74">
      <en>I would like to highlight specifically the meeting of the European Space Council at the end of July at the Kourou Space Centre in French Guiana, where, for the first time, it became clear that Europe is ready for this new departure into space.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais mettre en exergue tout particulièrement la réunion du Conseil "Espace" fin juillet au Centre spatial de Kourou <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12639">en</DiscourseConnective> Guinée française. Ce Conseil a montré clairement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12692">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12715">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe était prête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12740">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre un nouveau départ vers l'espace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11600" docOffset="75">
      <en>We have <Alignment alignment="12794" annotation_id="11608">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11608" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> been able to demonstrate that the European space industry is highly competitive.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="11608" annotation_id="12794">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12794" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> apporté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12812">la preuve</DiscourseConnective> de la grande compétitivité de l'industrie aérospatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11694" docOffset="76">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="54804" annotation_id="11694">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11694" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we compare the money which Europe can spend on activities in space with that which our American friends spend, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11810" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>, we are in a good position.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11694" annotation_id="12889">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12889" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on compare le budget <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12916">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe peut consacrer à l'espace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12955">à</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12960">que</DiscourseConnective> dépensent nos amis américains, nous sommes bien placés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11850" docOffset="77">
      <en>Europe plays a leading role in satellite technology and in carrier rocket technology.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe joue un rôle moteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13049">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de satellites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13074">et</DiscourseConnective> de technologie des fusées porteuses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11936" docOffset="78">
      <en>We have the best carrier rocket systems in the world.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons les meilleures fusées porteuses du monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11990" docOffset="79">
      <en>In Kourou, we have an infrastructure which is not to be found anywhere else in the world.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13167">À</DiscourseConnective> Kourou, nous possédons une infrastructure inégalée dans le monde entier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12080" docOffset="80">
      <en>Our contribution to the International Space Station in the form of the space laboratory demonstrates the high level of European space technology.</en>
      <fr>Le laboratoire spatial que nous avons développé pour la Station spatiale internationale démontre le haut niveau de la technologie spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12226" docOffset="81">
      <en>I am <Alignment alignment="13407" annotation_id="12231">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12231" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> very pleased that the ESA has carried out a whole series of successful research expeditions within our solar system which other countries have not been able to achieve.</en>
      <fr>Je me réjouis <Alignment alignment="17382" annotation_id="13407">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13407" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13417">que</DiscourseConnective> l'ESA ait mené une série d'expéditions de recherche réussies à travers notre système solaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13514">que</DiscourseConnective> d'autres pays n'ont pas été en mesure d'accomplir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12405" docOffset="82">
      <en>As Europeans, we have absolutely no reason for hiding behind others.</en>
      <fr>Les Européens n'ont aucune raison de se cacher derrière d'autres acteurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12474" docOffset="83">
      <en>The collaboration between the European Commission and the ESA is excellent <Alignment alignment="13715" annotation_id="12549">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12549" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the division of work is functioning smoothly.</en>
      <fr>La collaboration entre la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13691">et</DiscourseConnective> l'ESA est excellente <Alignment alignment="23051" annotation_id="13715">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13715" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la division des tâches fonctionne sans accrocs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12599" docOffset="84">
      <en>Against the background of this effective cooperation, there is not the slightest reason to consider changing the structures in this area.</en>
      <fr>Au vu de cette coopération efficace, il n'y a pas la moindre raison d'envisager de modifier les structures dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12737" docOffset="85">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13899" annotation_id="12737">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12737" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, there are problems which we still have to solve.</en>
      <fr>Il reste <Alignment alignment="27918" annotation_id="13899">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13899" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13923">à</DiscourseConnective> résoudre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12795" docOffset="86">
      <en>As Europeans, we have no independent access to space.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13938">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>Européens, nous n'avons pas d'accès indépendant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13994">à</DiscourseConnective> l'espace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12849" docOffset="87">
      <en>We cannot send people into space or bring them back again.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne sommes pas capables d'envoyer des êtres humains dans l'espace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14076">et</DiscourseConnective> de les ramener.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12908" docOffset="88">
      <en>We have to decide whether <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12934" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective> not we want to be dependent on others in the long term.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons décider si nous voulons dépendre d'autres pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14154">à</DiscourseConnective> long terme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12993" docOffset="89">
      <en>I do not want to hide my own opinion from you.</en>
      <fr>Je ne veux pas vous taire mon opinion personnelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14218">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13040" docOffset="90">
      <en>Europe needs an independent and secure means of access to space.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe a besoin d'un accès indépendant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14271">et</DiscourseConnective> sûr <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14278">à</DiscourseConnective> l'espace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13105" docOffset="91">
      <en>We will <Alignment alignment="14302" annotation_id="13113">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13113" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have to consider what form the next major missions to research the solar system should take.</en>
      <fr>Nous allons <Alignment alignment="2229" annotation_id="14302">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14302" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> devoir réfléchir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14329">à</DiscourseConnective> la forme que devront prendre les prochaines grandes missions d'exploration du système solaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13211" docOffset="92">
      <en>In my opinion, the next large-scale missions can only be regarded <Alignment alignment="14507" annotation_id="13277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13277" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tasks carried out on behalf of the whole of the human race.</en>
      <fr>Je pense que les prochaines grandes missions devront absolument être considérées <Alignment alignment="16302" annotation_id="14507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14507" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des activités au nom de l'humanité tout entière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13340" docOffset="93">
      <en>We should avoid all types of national or regional competition.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons éviter toute forme de concurrente nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14618">ou</DiscourseConnective> régionale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13403" docOffset="94">
      <en>In any case, our policy aims to achieve the highest possible level of cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Notre politique a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14650">de toute façon</DiscourseConnective> pour but de parvenir à un degré de collaboration aussi élevé que possible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13486" docOffset="95">
      <en>This will be the subject of the conference which Mr Jouyet has just been speaking about <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13574" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> which the Commission is organising next year.</en>
      <fr>Tel sera le thème de la conférence organisée l'année prochaine par la Commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14822">que</DiscourseConnective> M. Jouyet vient de mentionner.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13624" docOffset="96">
      <en>To ensure that it is clear to everyone, we want to discuss what will be the next major mission that goes beyond the pure technical application of space-based technologies.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14857">Que</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14864">soit</DiscourseConnective> bien clair <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14880">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous: nous voulons discuter de ce que sera la prochaine grande mission au-delà de la pure application technique des technologies spatiales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13796" docOffset="97">
      <en>What is the next large-scale mission, the next major objective which will satisfy the human urge to explore space?</en>
      <fr>Quelle est la prochaine grande mission, le prochain objectif majeur qui pourra satisfaire l'enthousiasme de l'homme pour la recherche spatiale?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13911" docOffset="98">
      <en>Space-based technology is completely indispensable to our civilisation, our security and our economy.</en>
      <fr>La technologie spatiale est absolument indispensable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15222">pour</DiscourseConnective> notre civilisation, notre sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15262">et</DiscourseConnective> notre économie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14013" docOffset="99">
      <en>You only need to think of all our communication technology or the financial markets, which would not function at all without satellites.</en>
      <fr>Il suffit de penser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15301">à</DiscourseConnective> notre technologie des télécommunications <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15344">ou</DiscourseConnective> aux marchés financiers, qui ne fonctionneraient pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15399">sans</DiscourseConnective> satellites.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14150" docOffset="100">
      <en>It is right that there should be a strong security component to this policy.</en>
      <fr>Cette politique doit donc comporter un élément de sécurité important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14227" docOffset="101">
      <en>We are not trying to ignore that.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'essayons pas de l'ignorer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14261" docOffset="102">
      <en>We have been able to establish a regular and structured dialogue between the Council and the Commission, which includes the European Defence Agency and the EU Satellite Centre.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons pu instaurer un dialogue régulier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15565">et</DiscourseConnective> structuré entre le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15595">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission, qui inclut l'Agence européenne de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15655">et</DiscourseConnective> le Centre satellitaire de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14438" docOffset="103">
      <en>This dialogue is intended to result in improved coordination between civilian, security and defence-related space activities.</en>
      <fr>Ce dialogue vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15721">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la coordination des activités civiles et des activités liées à la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15808">et</DiscourseConnective> à la défense dans l'espace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14564" docOffset="104">
      <en>From the perspective of the environment, the GMES (Global Monitoring for Environment and Security) system, which is currently under development, represents the European response to the global environmental crisis.</en>
      <fr>Du point de vue de l'environnement, le système GMES (Global Monitoring for Environment and Security, surveillance mondiale pour l'environnement et la sécurité), actuellement en cours de développement, constitue la réponse européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16072">à</DiscourseConnective> la crise environnementale mondiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14778" docOffset="105">
      <en>This system will provide us with the data and information we need to act and react with foresight <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14876" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> disasters occur.</en>
      <fr>Ce système nous fournira les données <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16147">et</DiscourseConnective> les informations dont nous avons besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16190">pour</DiscourseConnective> agir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16200">et</DiscourseConnective> réagir de façon prévoyante en cas de catastrophe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14898" docOffset="106">
      <en>Of course, our two flagship projects - GMES and Galileo - are making an important contribution to the implementation of the Lisbon Strategy by ensuring that there is a strong industrial and technological basis in Europe for space-based applications.</en>
      <fr>Bien sûr, nos deux projets principaux, GMES <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16297">et</DiscourseConnective> Galileo, contribuent de façon significative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16344">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en œuvre de la stratégie de Lisbonne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16391">en</DiscourseConnective> dotant l'Europe d'une base industrielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16434">et</DiscourseConnective> technologique solide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16458">pour</DiscourseConnective> les applications spatiales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15148" docOffset="107">
      <en>As far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15155" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> GMES is concerned, I am very pleased to be able to tell you that, only a few days ago, the Commission accepted a communication at my suggestion which relates to the organisation of the funding and the questions of cooperation with GMES.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16491">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne GMES, je suis heureux de pouvoir vous indiquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16557">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il y a quelques jours à peine, la Commission a accepté une communication que j'avais suggérée concernant l'organisation du financement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16695">et</DiscourseConnective> les questions de coopération avec GMES.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15395" docOffset="108">
      <en>The Competitiveness Council will be looking at this in a few days.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil "Compétitivité" se penchera sur ces thèmes dans quelques jours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15462" docOffset="109">
      <en>It is true to say that GMES is on the right track.</en>
      <fr>On peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16821">dire que</DiscourseConnective> GMES est sur la bonne voie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15513" docOffset="110">
      <en>The first demonstration projects have started <Alignment alignment="16907" annotation_id="15559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15559" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, as far <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15571" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> I can see, we will be able to meet the schedule.</en>
      <fr>Les premiers projets de démonstration ont débuté <Alignment alignment="15559" annotation_id="16907">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16907" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16911">à</DiscourseConnective> ma connaissance, nous serons en mesure de respecter le calendrier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15623" docOffset="111">
      <en>We are in full agreement with the ESA about the space-based infrastructure of GMES.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16997">à</DiscourseConnective> fait d'accord avec l'ESA concernant l'infrastructure spatiale de GMES.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15707" docOffset="112">
      <en>The ESA has already made good progress on the development of the European satellites which we need for this system, so the prospects are good.</en>
      <fr>L'ESA a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17078">déjà</DiscourseConnective> accompli d'importants progrès dans le développement des satellites européens dont nous avons besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17183">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce système, les perspectives sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17222">donc</DiscourseConnective> excellentes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15850" docOffset="113">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10922" annotation_id="15850">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15850" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, one thing still needs to be resolved.</en>
      <fr>Il reste <Alignment alignment="23488" annotation_id="17249">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17249" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17271">à</DiscourseConnective> résoudre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15897" docOffset="114">
      <en>The Community budget only provides research funding for GMES.</en>
      <fr>Le budget communautaire prévoit uniquement le financement des activités de recherche sur GMES.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15959" docOffset="115">
      <en>We have no operational funds.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'avons pas de budget opérationnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15989" docOffset="116">
      <en>Next year, we will need a small amount of operational funding for the first time <Alignment alignment="17511" annotation_id="16070">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16070" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this has already been cleared with the budgetary authority.</en>
      <fr>L'année prochaine, nous aurons besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17457">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois d'un petit budget opérationnel, <Alignment alignment="13828" annotation_id="17511">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17511" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette question a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17531">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été résolue avec l'autorité budgétaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16134" docOffset="117">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17576" annotation_id="16134">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16134" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we need to find a long-term solution, <Alignment alignment="17629" annotation_id="16181">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16181" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is clear that GMES is not a system which will fund itself.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4998" annotation_id="17576">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17576" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons trouver des solutions à long terme, <Alignment alignment="16181" annotation_id="17629">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17629" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il est clair <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17651">que</DiscourseConnective> le système GMES ne va pas s'autofinancer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16251" docOffset="118">
      <en>It will generate an income, <Alignment alignment="10116" annotation_id="16279">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16279" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this will never cover the costs.</en>
      <fr>Il génèrera des revenus, <Alignment alignment="20312" annotation_id="17722">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17722" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ceux-ci ne couvriront jamais les coûts.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16316" docOffset="119">
      <en>GMES is a European infrastructure project <Alignment alignment="17813" annotation_id="16358">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16358" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is how we need to look at it in order to ensure that long-term funding is available.</en>
      <fr>GMES est un projet européen d'infrastructure, <Alignment alignment="16358" annotation_id="17813">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17813" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est sous cet angle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17837">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons l'envisager <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17865">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>assurer son financement à long terme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16452" docOffset="120">
      <en>Next year, we will draw up an accurate schedule and action plan for the future implementation of the GMES initiative.</en>
      <fr>L'année prochaine, nous établirons un calendrier précis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17966">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'un plan d'action <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17992">pour</DiscourseConnective> la future mise en œuvre de l'initiative GMES.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16570" docOffset="121">
      <en>In summary, in 2009 the Commission will present a proposal for financing the initial deployment of GMES in 2011 on the basis of a detailed impact assessment and cost-benefit analysis.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18043">En résumé</DiscourseConnective>, la Commission présentera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18079">en</DiscourseConnective> 2009 une proposition relative au financement du déploiement initial de GMES <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18158">en</DiscourseConnective> 2011 sur la base d'une analyse des incidences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18207">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une analyse coûts-bénéfices détaillée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16754" docOffset="122">
      <en>Galileo has already been discussed.</en>
      <fr>Galileo a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18261">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été abordé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16790" docOffset="123">
      <en>I simply want to say here that, as a result of the effective cooperation between the institutions, the Galileo and EGNOS programmes now have a solid legal basis and can be put into operation.</en>
      <fr>Je veux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18286">simplement</DiscourseConnective> vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18302">dire que</DiscourseConnective>, grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18318">à</DiscourseConnective> une coopération efficace entre les institutions, les programmes Galileo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18392">et</DiscourseConnective> EGNOS possèdent désormais une base juridique solide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18447">et</DiscourseConnective> peuvent être mis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18467">en</DiscourseConnective> route.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16982" docOffset="124">
      <en>The implementation of Galileo and EGNOS <Alignment alignment="18521" annotation_id="17022">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17022" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> forms part of the plan <Alignment alignment="43637" annotation_id="17050">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17050" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, of course, we need to find out whether the requirement in the GNSS Regulation to complete the Galileo system by 2013 can <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17176" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> be met by industry.</en>
      <fr>La mise en œuvre de Galileo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18505">et</DiscourseConnective> d'EGNOS fait <Alignment alignment="17022" annotation_id="18521">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18521" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> partie du plan, <Alignment alignment="17050" annotation_id="18543">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18543" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, évidemment, il reste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18570">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18579">si</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie sera en mesure de satisfaire l'exigence, imposée par le règlement GNSS, de terminer le système Galileo d'ici 2013.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17201" docOffset="125">
      <en>This will become clear in the course of the tendering procedure.</en>
      <fr>Nous en saurons plus dans le courant de la procédure d'attribution du marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17266" docOffset="126">
      <en>I would like to urge the European space industry to make use of the major opportunity presented by Galileo, to work together with us as closely as possible and to mobilise all of its resources.</en>
      <fr>J'invite l'industrie aérospatiale européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18832">à</DiscourseConnective> saisir l'occasion majeure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18860">que</DiscourseConnective> constitue Galileo, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18883">à</DiscourseConnective> collaborer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18896">aussi</DiscourseConnective> étroitement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18914">que</DiscourseConnective> possible avec nous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18937">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18940">à</DiscourseConnective> mobiliser toutes ses ressources.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17460" docOffset="127">
      <en>For us, Galileo is one of the most important, if not the most important, industrial policy projects <Alignment alignment="53157" annotation_id="17560">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17560" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must ensure that it runs smoothly.</en>
      <fr>Nous considérons Galileo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19000">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'un des projets les plus importants, voire le plus important de notre politique industrielle, <Alignment alignment="17560" annotation_id="19101">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19101" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons faire en sorte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19131">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il se déroule sans accrocs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17602" docOffset="128">
      <en>This involves issues raised by the resolution, such as the questions of competition which arise in relation to international business practices and public procurement markets.</en>
      <fr>Cela touche également à des questions soulevées par la résolution, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19229">par exemple</DiscourseConnective> celle de la concurrence dans le contexte des pratiques commerciales internationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19325">et</DiscourseConnective> des marchés publics.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17778" docOffset="129">
      <en>It is true that different international regulations govern the procurement practices in the space industry.</en>
      <fr>Il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19361">que</DiscourseConnective> les pratiques d'attribution des marchés dans le domaine aérospatial sont régies par différentes réglementations internationales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17886" docOffset="130">
      <en>These practices differ depending on whether services or goods are being procured <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17967" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>, above all, depending on which countries have signed the relevant agreements.</en>
      <fr>La pratique varie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19512">selon qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19524">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de fournir des services <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19555">ou</DiscourseConnective> des produits, mais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19577">surtout</DiscourseConnective> en fonction des pays qui ont signé les accords concernés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18049" docOffset="131">
      <en>During the process of awarding contracts for the Galileo deployment phase, the Commission has strictly applied the principle of reciprocity <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18189" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> we hope that this has given a boost to the negotiations with third countries on the mutual opening up of markets.</en>
      <fr>Tout au long de la procédure d'attribution des marchés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19698">pour</DiscourseConnective> la phase de déploiement de Galileo, la Commission a appliqué strictement le principe de la réciprocité. Nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19821">que</DiscourseConnective> cette approche a donné un coup de fouet aux négociations menées avec les pays tiers concernant l'ouverture réciproque des marchés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18307" docOffset="132">
      <en>One final point, and I am very grateful that Parliament has considered this, is the question of the involvement of small and medium-sized companies in European space activities.</en>
      <fr>Un dernier point que je voudrais mentionner, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20001">et</DiscourseConnective> je suis reconnaissant envers le Parlement d'y avoir réfléchi, concerne la participation des petites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20104">et</DiscourseConnective> moyennes entreprises aux activités spatiales de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18485" docOffset="133">
      <en>This is very important to me, <Alignment alignment="67730" annotation_id="18515">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18515" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are only a few large-scale European players in the space industry.</en>
      <fr>Cet aspect est très important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20195">pour</DiscourseConnective> moi, <Alignment alignment="24013" annotation_id="20205">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20205" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'industrie aérospatiale ne compte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20250">que</DiscourseConnective> quelques grands acteurs européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18596" docOffset="134">
      <en>There are only a handful of European countries which can really have a presence in space.</en>
      <fr>Seule une poignée de pays européens peuvent réellement avoir une présence dans l'espace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18686" docOffset="135">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="40647" annotation_id="18686">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18686" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, many others are making contributions <Alignment alignment="20423" annotation_id="18732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18732" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am very pleased to see that specialist space technology is increasingly being developed in a number of Member States, particularly the new Member States, by small and medium-sized companies which are providing often extremely complex and highly advanced products and services.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10189" annotation_id="20378">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20378" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, de nombreux autres y contribuent, <Alignment alignment="18732" annotation_id="20423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20423" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je me réjouis de constater le développement croissant de technologies spatiales spécialisées dans plusieurs États membres, et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20552">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans les nouveaux États membres. Ces technologies sont développées par des PME qui fournissent des produits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20670">et</DiscourseConnective> services souvent extrêmement complexes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19015" docOffset="136">
      <en>For this reason, it is important that we ensure that small and medium-sized companies are given an appropriate proportion of the orders on major projects.</en>
      <fr>Il est donc important, pour les grands projets, d'attribuer un pourcentage adéquat des marchés à des petites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20822">et</DiscourseConnective> moyennes entreprises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19170" docOffset="137">
      <en>This proportion is set at 40% <Alignment alignment="20879" annotation_id="19200">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19200" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commission will do everything in its power to make sure that the proportion is adhered to.</en>
      <fr>Ce pourcentage est fixé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20871">à</DiscourseConnective> 40 %, <Alignment alignment="19200" annotation_id="20879">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20879" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission fera tout ce qui est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20917">en</DiscourseConnective> son pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20932">pour qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20943">soit</DiscourseConnective> respecté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19299" docOffset="138">
      <en>This is not a purely economic issue, it is <Alignment alignment="4239" annotation_id="19342">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19342" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a political question, <Alignment alignment="21048" annotation_id="19369">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19369" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this will allow us to ensure that European space-related activities are not regarded simply as the privilege of a few large European countries, but are seen as something which all 27 countries are involved in and can benefit from.</en>
      <fr>Il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20964">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit pas d'une question strictement économique, elle est <Alignment alignment="1933" annotation_id="21023">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21023" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'ordre politique. <Alignment alignment="13260" annotation_id="21048">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21048" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">En effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous pourrons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21072">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> faire en sorte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21093">que</DiscourseConnective> les activités aérospatiales européennes ne soient pas perçues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21159">comme</DiscourseConnective> le domaine réservé de quelques grands pays européens, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21219">mais</DiscourseConnective> plutôt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21231">comme</DiscourseConnective> un secteur auquel participent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21267">et</DiscourseConnective> dont profitent les 27 pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19608" id="232" language="HU" name="Etelka Barsi-Pataky">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19608" docOffset="139">
      <en>Thank you for the floor, Mr President.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (HU) Monsieur le Président, merci de me donner la parole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19647" docOffset="140">
      <en>The title of our parliamentary decision is 'How to bring space down to earth'.</en>
      <fr>Le titre de notre résolution parlementaire est "L'Europe et l'espace".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19726" docOffset="141">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, the average citizen of Europe makes use of 50 satellites a day.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21463">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs chaque citoyen européen utilise en moyenne 50 satellites par jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19812" docOffset="142">
      <en>The utilisation of space has quite imperceptibly come to be part of daily life.</en>
      <fr>De façon presque imperceptible, l'utilisation de l'espace fait désormais partie de notre vie quotidienne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19892" docOffset="143">
      <en>The question is: can Europe cooperate in that process, can it actively shape the utilisation of space?</en>
      <fr>La question qui se pose est la suivante: l'Europe arrivera-t-elle à coopérer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21726">à</DiscourseConnective> ce processus, contribuera-t-elle activement à donner forme à l'utilisation de l'espace?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19995" docOffset="144">
      <en>A few remarks are in order.</en>
      <fr>Quelques remarques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21835">s'</DiscourseConnective>imposent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20023" docOffset="145">
      <en>Space is our common and global asset.</en>
      <fr>L'espace est un atout commun <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21876">et</DiscourseConnective> mondial.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20061" docOffset="146">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17806" annotation_id="20061">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20061" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, international cooperation is of paramount importance to Europe.</en>
      <fr>La coopération internationale est <Alignment alignment="7405" annotation_id="21922">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21922" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cruciale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21936">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20136" docOffset="147">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21951" annotation_id="20136">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20136" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Europe can participate meaningfully only <Alignment alignment="18648" annotation_id="20186">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20186" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it has established its autonomy in the political, technological and operational fields.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="33214" annotation_id="21951">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21951" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Europe ne peut participer utilement à ces projets <Alignment alignment="19777" annotation_id="22008">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22008" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle a acquis au préalable son autonomie politique, technologique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22081">et</DiscourseConnective> opérationnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20277" docOffset="148">
      <en>Hence, it has relevance for Parliament.</en>
      <fr>D'où la pertinence de cette question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22137">pour</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20317" docOffset="149">
      <en>In light of the global financial and already partly economic crisis, we now see clearly that high-technology initiatives such as space utilisation add a significant edge to our competitiveness.</en>
      <fr>Au vu de la crise financière mondiale, qui se transforme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22213">déjà</DiscourseConnective> en crise économique, nous constatons clairement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22266">que</DiscourseConnective> les initiatives en matière de haute technologie telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22325">que</DiscourseConnective> l'utilisation de l'espace contribuent de façon significative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22390">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer notre compétitivité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20511" docOffset="150">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="42249" annotation_id="20511">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20511" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, given the challenges we face and the related tasks to be tackled, we rely increasingly on space technology, <Alignment alignment="22606" annotation_id="20629">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20629" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, to understand and monitor climate change or achieve security by means of defence, the prevention of increasingly frequent catastrophes or the provision of ever broader communication and navigation services.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="29750" annotation_id="22423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22423" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, étant donné les défis auxquels nous sommes confrontés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22486">et</DiscourseConnective> les tâches connexes à accomplir, nous dépendons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22537">de plus</DiscourseConnective> en plus de la technologie aérospatiale. Nous en avons besoin <Alignment alignment="9405" annotation_id="22606">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22606" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22618">pour</DiscourseConnective> comprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22634">et</DiscourseConnective> observer le changement climatique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22671">ou</DiscourseConnective> pour assurer notre défense, pour prévenir des catastrophes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22733">de plus</DiscourseConnective> en plus fréquentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22760">ou</DiscourseConnective> pour fournir des services de communication <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22806">et</DiscourseConnective> de navigation encore plus étendus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20849" docOffset="151">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="35374" annotation_id="20849">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20849" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we are dealing with strategic questions here.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22847">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit <Alignment alignment="3446" annotation_id="22854">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22854" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de questions stratégiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20901" docOffset="152">
      <en>The European Parliament wishes to play a constructive part in this process, primarily by fostering a structured dialogue between the EU and government institutions.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen souhaite jouer un rôle constructif dans ce processus, principalement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22977">en</DiscourseConnective> encourageant un dialogue structuré entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23040">et</DiscourseConnective> les institutions gouvernementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21066" docOffset="153">
      <en>In our opinion, this will provide all Member States with the opportunity to participate and gain open and fair access.</en>
      <fr>Nous pensons que cela permettra à tous les États membres de participer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23149">et</DiscourseConnective> de bénéficier d'un accès libre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23183">et</DiscourseConnective> équitable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21185" docOffset="154">
      <en>Galileo, our joint European project, was a pioneer in many respects.</en>
      <fr>Galileo, notre projet européen commun, fut un pionnier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23252">à</DiscourseConnective> bien des égards.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21254" docOffset="155">
      <en>To name <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21262" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> a few: it set up the operational model of the Galileo Interinstitutional Panel to create closer cooperation, <Alignment alignment="45327" annotation_id="21375">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21375" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in the case of larger projects, we were able to secure joint funding built into the Community budget.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23271">Pour</DiscourseConnective> ne citer que quelques exemples: il a créé le modèle opérationnel du panel interinstitutionnel de Galileo visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23388">à</DiscourseConnective> instaurer une coopération plus étroite <Alignment alignment="7588" annotation_id="23429">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23429" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23433">pour</DiscourseConnective> des projets importants, nous sommes parvenus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23483">à</DiscourseConnective> intégrer le financement commun au budget communautaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21481" docOffset="156">
      <en>This is only the beginning, <Alignment alignment="23541" annotation_id="21509">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21509" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="21509" annotation_id="23541">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23541" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce n'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23555">encore que</DiscourseConnective> le début.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21518" docOffset="157">
      <en>The Galileo programme, <Alignment alignment="27416" annotation_id="21541">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21541" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Commissioner Verheugen mentioned, secured the participation of SMEs <Alignment alignment="56781" annotation_id="21612">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21612" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we know by <Alignment alignment="23717" annotation_id="21631">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21631" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">now that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> spin-off companies are the ones most capable of accomplishing great things in the high-tech world.</en>
      <fr>Le programme Galileo, <Alignment alignment="21541" annotation_id="23598">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23598" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'a mentionné le commissaire Verheugen, s'est assuré la participation des PME, <Alignment alignment="21612" annotation_id="23683">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23683" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous savons aujourd'hui <Alignment alignment="16259" annotation_id="23717">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23717" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les spin-offs sont les entreprises les mieux à même de réaliser de grandes choses dans le domaine de la haute technologie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21739" docOffset="158">
      <en>The European People's Party and European Democrats have made countless proposals, concerning, in part, our industrial policy where we still have a lot of catching up to do <Alignment alignment="24034" annotation_id="21911">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21911" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it might serve as a solid base.</en>
      <fr>Le Parti populaire européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23872">et</DiscourseConnective> des Démocrates européens a soumis d'innombrables propositions, relatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23948">notamment</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23958">à</DiscourseConnective> notre politique industrielle, qui a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23996">encore</DiscourseConnective> beaucoup de retard <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24022">à</DiscourseConnective> rattraper <Alignment alignment="12372" annotation_id="24034">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24034" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pouvoir constituer une base solide.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21950" docOffset="159">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21950" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>, we have to strengthen our role in research and development.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons également renforcer notre rôle dans le domaine de la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24154">et</DiscourseConnective> du développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22023" docOffset="160">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24185" annotation_id="22023">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22023" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Besides</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, these competencies are essential for defence and security policy as well.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agit <Alignment alignment="16146" annotation_id="24185">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24185" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">d'ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de compétences essentielles en matière de politique de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24259">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22106" docOffset="161">
      <en>In this way, the European space policy will come to be part of Europe's identity.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24275">C'est ainsi que</DiscourseConnective> la politique spatiale européenne deviendra une partie intégrante de l'identité européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22188" docOffset="162">
      <en>Thank you for the floor.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie de m'avoir donné la parole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="22213" id="233" language="RO" name="Silvia-Adriana Ţicău">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="22213" docOffset="163">
      <en>Satellite navigation systems and satellite-based telecommunication networks, services and applications are tools which the European Union needs to invest in.</en>
      <fr>Les systèmes de navigation par satellite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24468">et</DiscourseConnective> les réseaux, services <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24493">et</DiscourseConnective> applications de télécommunications satellitaires sont des outils dans lesquels l'Union européenne doit investir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22371" docOffset="164">
      <en>Research is one of the fundamental pillars on which the Lisbon Strategy is based.</en>
      <fr>La recherche est l'un des piliers de la stratégie de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22453" docOffset="165">
      <en>The GALILEO programme is one of the priority projects for European research in view of its potential use for managing traffic, monitoring the effects of climate change and for intervening in situations involving emergencies and natural disasters.</en>
      <fr>Le programme Galileo est l'un des projets prioritaires de la recherche européenne du fait de ses utilisations potentielles en matière de gestion du trafic, d'observation des effets du changement climatique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24878">et</DiscourseConnective> d'intervention dans les situations d'urgence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24926">et</DiscourseConnective> en cas de catastrophes naturelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22700" docOffset="166">
      <en>Last year, the European Parliament, along with the Commission and Council, managed to identify sources of funding for the GALILEO project, which was regarded as one of the Union's strategic projects.</en>
      <fr>L'année dernière, le Parlement européen, la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25019">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil ont identifié des sources de financement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25074">pour</DiscourseConnective> le projet Galileo, considéré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25108">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'un des projets stratégiques de l'Union.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22900" docOffset="167">
      <en>I would like to stress the importance of developing a space-related industrial policy.</en>
      <fr>J'insiste sur l'importance de développer une politique industrielle en matière spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22987" docOffset="168">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="25257" annotation_id="22995">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22995" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to remind you that the GALILEO Regulation sets a benchmark for the involvement of SMEs in European space-related industrial policy.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="29704" annotation_id="25257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25257" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25281">que</DiscourseConnective> le règlement Galileo fixe un seuil de référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25333">pour</DiscourseConnective> la participation des PME <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25363">à</DiscourseConnective> la politique industrielle européenne en matière spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23137" docOffset="169">
      <en>It is time for Europe to develop a common vision and strategic planning for space exploration.</en>
      <fr>Il est temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25436">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe développe une vision commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25478">et</DiscourseConnective> une planification stratégique en matière d'exploration spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="23232" id="234" language="FR" name="Anne Laperrouze">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="23232" docOffset="170">
      <en>Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, it seems that we are all in agreement here on the fact that space policy has become an essential component of the future of our society.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe ALDE. - Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, il semble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25646">que</DiscourseConnective> nous soyons tous d'accord ici sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25692">que</DiscourseConnective> la politique spatiale est devenue une composante essentielle de l'avenir de notre société.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23419" docOffset="171">
      <en>We could sum up three important strands to this: security and defence, protection against environmental crises and the supply of new services to human activities.</en>
      <fr>On pourrait résumer trois dimensions prioritaires: la sécurité-défense, la protection contre les crises environnementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25909">et</DiscourseConnective> la fourniture de nouveaux services aux activités humaines.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23582" docOffset="172">
      <en>Yes, ladies and gentlemen, we must, as Europeans, recognise that space is taking on a strategic defensive dimension.</en>
      <fr>Oui, chers collègues, il faut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26001">que</DiscourseConnective> nous, Européens, reconnaissions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26037">que</DiscourseConnective> l'espace revêt une dimension défensive stratégique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23699" docOffset="173">
      <en>I know that some of my fellow Members dispute this.</en>
      <fr>Je sais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26101">que</DiscourseConnective> ce point est contesté par certains de mes collègues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23751" docOffset="174">
      <en>Yes, the observation of the planet must be assured in the long term <Alignment alignment="26224" annotation_id="23819">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23819" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23822" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> to study its slow, dynamic variations and, in particular, those caused by the actions of man that affect the global climate, natural resources and biodiversity.</en>
      <fr>Oui, l'observation de la planète doit être assurée dans la durée, <Alignment alignment="664" annotation_id="26224">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26224" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>étudier ses variations dynamiques lentes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26273">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26276">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> celles induites par l'action de l'homme affectant le climat global, les ressources naturelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26385">et</DiscourseConnective> la biodiversité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23986" docOffset="175">
      <en>At the same time, a large number of public policy groups and economic activities need information and forecasts from observation systems based in space.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26405">En</DiscourseConnective> parallèle, un grand nombre de politiques publiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26459">et</DiscourseConnective> d'activités économiques ont besoin d'informations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26512">et</DiscourseConnective> de prévisions issues de systèmes d'observation depuis l'espace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24139" docOffset="176">
      <en>This, in particular, is the importance of Europe's GMES in the world GEO process.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26585">notamment</DiscourseConnective> l'enjeu du GMES de l'Europe inscrit dans le processus mondial du GEO.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24221" docOffset="177">
      <en>Yes, space policies are having a growing impact on scientific research, technological innovation and, beyond that, on the stimulation of imaginations.</en>
      <fr>Oui, les politiques spatiales ont un impact croissant sur la recherche scientifique, l'innovation technologique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26777">et</DiscourseConnective> au-delà, sur la dynamisation des imaginaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24372" docOffset="178">
      <en>In this respect, space and planetary exploration programmes have an essential role to play from now on.</en>
      <fr>Les programmes d'exploration de l'espace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26867">et</DiscourseConnective> des planètes jouent désormais un rôle essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26918">en ce sens</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24476" docOffset="179">
      <en>Telephony and television, GPS, but <Alignment alignment="56342" annotation_id="24511">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24511" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> weather forecasting or even long-distance medical care have dramatically changed our way of life.</en>
      <fr>Téléphone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26940">et</DiscourseConnective> télévision, GPS, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26960">mais</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="24511" annotation_id="26965">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26965" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> prévisions météo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26992">ou encore</DiscourseConnective> soins médicaux à distance, ont bouleversé nos modes de vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24614" docOffset="180">
      <en>We can no longer imagine what would happen <Alignment alignment="27116" annotation_id="24657">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24657" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> satellites stopped working.</en>
      <fr>Personne ne peut dès lors imaginer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27097">que</DiscourseConnective> les satellites <Alignment alignment="24657" annotation_id="27116">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27116" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>arrêtent de fonctionner.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24688" docOffset="181">
      <en>The experience acquired in space technologies - notably through the success of the Ariane rocket - in itself justifies implementing a real European space policy.</en>
      <fr>L'expérience acquise dans les technologies spatiales avec <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27201">notamment</DiscourseConnective> la réussite du lanceur Ariane justifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27250">à</DiscourseConnective> elle seule la mise en œuvre d'une réelle politique spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24850" docOffset="182">
      <en>To respond to our ambition of independence, it will be necessary to achieve not only good governance, but also, of course, good funding.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27324">Pour</DiscourseConnective> répondre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27338">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ambition de notre indépendance, il faudra trouver la bonne gouvernance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27413">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27416">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, bien sûr, les bons financements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24987" docOffset="183">
      <en>In conclusion, the space policy that Europe pursues will demonstrate its willingness, either to remain an influential actor on the world scene, but one that is more or less reduced to a partner role, or to be a strong Europe, a major player in world governance capable of resolving the key problems facing the future of humanity.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27456">En</DiscourseConnective> conclusion, la politique spatiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27493">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe entend mener témoignera de sa volonté, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27545">soit</DiscourseConnective> de demeurer un acteur qui compte sur la scène mondiale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27606">mais</DiscourseConnective> est plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27620">ou</DiscourseConnective> moins réduit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27636">à</DiscourseConnective> un rôle de partenaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27661">soit</DiscourseConnective> d'être une Europe forte, acteur majeur de la gouvernance mondiale capable de résoudre des problèmes clés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27771">pour</DiscourseConnective> le futur de l'humanité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="25317" id="235" language="FR" name="Patrick Louis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="25317" docOffset="184">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, in my former capacity as rapporteur for the Committee on Transport, I held a enthusiastic viewpoint on the Galileo project.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe IND/DEM. - Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27868">en</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27871">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>ex-rapporteur de la commission des transports, j'avais émis un avis enthousiaste sur le projet Galileo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25477" docOffset="185">
      <en>Today, we see that this central project was bogged down due to the omnipotence and technocratic inertia of our institutions.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, nous voyons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28008">que</DiscourseConnective> ce projet central s'est englué grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28049">à</DiscourseConnective> l'omnipotence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28065">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'inertie technocratique de nos institutions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25602" docOffset="186">
      <en>Every time that the Union refused free and variable cooperation between States, they sterilised private initiative, increased costs and impeded the emergence of rival, competent and coherent consortiums.</en>
      <fr>Chaque fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28128">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union a refusé les coopérations libres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28173">et</DiscourseConnective> à géométrie variable entre États, elle a stérilisé l'initiative privée, augmenté les coûts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28267">et</DiscourseConnective> freiné l'émergence de consortiums concurrents compétents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28327">et</DiscourseConnective> cohérents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25806" docOffset="187">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28341" annotation_id="25806">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25806" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Yet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on each occasion that states have united together freely, projects have succeeded.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="25806" annotation_id="28341">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28341" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, chaque fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28359">que</DiscourseConnective> les États se sont unis librement, les projets ont abouti.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25893" docOffset="188">
      <en>Hence, here, as elsewhere, the role of our institutions is to maintain a simple substitute role, wishing to be the manager of all, <Alignment alignment="49815" annotation_id="26024">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26024" sense="Comparison.Contrast">whereas</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we ought to be the guarantors of little. We should bear one thing in mind: <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26107" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> dealing with space matters, Europe must, first of all, keep its feet on the ground.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28421">Alors</DiscourseConnective>, ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28432">comme</DiscourseConnective> ailleurs, le rôle de nos institutions est de garder un simple rôle de suppléance; vouloir être les gérants de tout, <Alignment alignment="26024" annotation_id="28554">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28554" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devrions êtres les garants de peu, nous rappelle une chose: c'est qu'en matière spatiale, l'Europe doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28673">d'abord</DiscourseConnective> garder les pieds sur terre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="26196" id="236" name="Giles Chichester">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="26196" docOffset="189">
      <en>Mr President, I had a childhood ambition of being one of the pioneers in space - I daresay many other children had the same - <Alignment alignment="59470" annotation_id="26322">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26322" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="23372" annotation_id="26326">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26326" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I grew up, in 1969, I was inspired by those images that came back to us from the Lunar Landing Project, particularly the television image of the Earth from space.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, comme beaucoup d'enfants sans doute, je rêvais autrefois de devenir un pionnier de la conquête spatiale. <Alignment alignment="26322" annotation_id="28842">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28842" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="26326" annotation_id="28845">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28845" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> grandissant, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28861">en</DiscourseConnective> 1969, les images transmises depuis la lune, et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28911">surtout</DiscourseConnective> les images télévisées de la terre vue depuis l'espace, m'ont inspiré.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26494" docOffset="190">
      <en>Space is now less of a headline grabber, <Alignment alignment="29049" annotation_id="26535">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26535" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is extremely important for all the reasons that other colleagues have given <Alignment alignment="29139" annotation_id="26618">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26618" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I applaud the European Union commitment to a space policy.</en>
      <fr>L'espace attire moins l'attention des journaux aujourd'hui, <Alignment alignment="10403" annotation_id="29049">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29049" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il reste tout aussi important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29084">pour</DiscourseConnective> toutes les raisons mentionnées par mes collègues, <Alignment alignment="12344" annotation_id="29139">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29139" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'applaudis l'engagement de l'Union européenne en faveur d'une politique spatiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26681" docOffset="191">
      <en>I visited the NASA Goddard Center in Washington a year ago <Alignment alignment="29297" annotation_id="26740">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26740" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, very recently, ESA, the European Space Agency Centre in Rome, and to me the images they can show us of the work that they undertake make space as exciting as ever.</en>
      <fr>J'ai visité l'année dernière le Centre Goddard de la NASA <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29283">à</DiscourseConnective> Washington, <Alignment alignment="26740" annotation_id="29297">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29297" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> très récemment l'ESA, l'Agence spatiale européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29351">à</DiscourseConnective> Rome, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29359">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29363">pour</DiscourseConnective> moi, les images que ces organisations nous montrent de leur travail sont plus fascinantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29458">que</DiscourseConnective> jamais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26909" docOffset="192">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23854" annotation_id="26909">
          <Alignment alignment="54658" annotation_id="26909">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26909" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the more people see these images, the more perhaps we will bring space down to earth.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="22608" annotation_id="29470">
          <Alignment alignment="26909" annotation_id="29470">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29470" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, plus les gens verront ces images, plus nous parviendrons peut-être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29546">à</DiscourseConnective> ramener l'espace sur terre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27004" docOffset="193">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="29576" annotation_id="27004">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27004" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> what it <Alignment alignment="5972" annotation_id="27016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27016" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> showed me anew was the relevance to science, to research and to the economy of the use of space, and the importance of the satellites and their launchers.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="27004" annotation_id="29576">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29576" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces visites m'ont <Alignment alignment="27016" annotation_id="29599">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29599" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> rappelé l'importance de l'espace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29642">pour</DiscourseConnective> la science, la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29672">et</DiscourseConnective> l'économie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29687">tout comme</DiscourseConnective> l'importance des satellites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29726">et</DiscourseConnective> de leurs lanceurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27176" docOffset="194">
      <en>Commissioner, I have been made aware of concerns felt by satellite operators about the need to observe international agreements with regard to spectrum usage and satellite footprints.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, j'ai été informé des préoccupations des opérateurs de satellites concernant l'obligation de respecter les accords internationaux relatifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29911">à</DiscourseConnective> l'usage du spectre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29932">et</DiscourseConnective> aux zones couvertes par les satellites.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27360" docOffset="195">
      <en>There is a concern that <Alignment alignment="29989" annotation_id="27384">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27384" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> any breach of international arrangements is tolerated, other regions will breach them too.</en>
      <fr>Ils craignent <Alignment alignment="27384" annotation_id="29989">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29989" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la moindre violation des accords internationaux est tolérée, d'autres régions les violeront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30088">également</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27478" docOffset="196">
      <en>It seems to me that effective exploitation of space depends crucially on observing common agreed laws and principles, <Alignment alignment="30222" annotation_id="27596">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27596" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I hope the Commission can reassure us <Alignment alignment="33159" annotation_id="27637">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27637" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> them on that point.</en>
      <fr>Il me semble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30112">que</DiscourseConnective> l'exploitation efficace de l'espace dépend du respect absolu des actes législatifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30199">et</DiscourseConnective> principes convenus, <Alignment alignment="27596" annotation_id="30222">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30222" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'espère donc que la Commission pourra nous rassurer <Alignment alignment="27637" annotation_id="30278">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30278" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les rassurer sur ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27661" docOffset="197">
      <en>We have a good story to tell of achievements and prospects in space.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons une belle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30329">histoire de</DiscourseConnective> réussites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30351">et</DiscourseConnective> de perspectives dans l'espace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30384">à</DiscourseConnective> raconter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="27730" id="237" name="Teresa Riera Madurell">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27730" docOffset="198">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, Commissioner, Mr Pribetich, in my opinion your proposal is very comprehensive and balanced.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Monsieur Pribetich, votre proposition me semble complète <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30506">et</DiscourseConnective> équilibrée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27841" docOffset="199">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="15127" annotation_id="27843">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27843" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> want to congratulate you on shedding more light <Alignment alignment="30567" annotation_id="27901">
          <Alignment alignment="51511" annotation_id="27901">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27901" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> we can see the stars better.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie <Alignment alignment="3889" annotation_id="30538">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30538" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'avoir fait la lumière <Alignment alignment="27901" annotation_id="30567">
          <Alignment alignment="3990" annotation_id="30567">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30567" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin de</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> nous permettre de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30593">mieux</DiscourseConnective> voir les étoiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27938" docOffset="200">
      <en>The European Union must, without question, be responsible for defining Europe's political aspirations in terms of space, by using it for the European people and economy, and by guaranteeing independent and reliable access to it.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30641">sans</DiscourseConnective> nul doute se charger de définir les aspirations politiques européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30717">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne l'espace. Elle doit l'utiliser au profit des citoyens européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30800">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'économie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30817">et</DiscourseConnective> y garantir un accès indépendant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30852">et</DiscourseConnective> fiable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28167" docOffset="201">
      <en>I am <Alignment alignment="30877" annotation_id="28172">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28172" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pleased with the Council's conclusions from September which make a useful political commitment to develop the European Space Policy.</en>
      <fr>Je me réjouis <Alignment alignment="1863" annotation_id="30877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30877" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des conclusions du Conseil de septembre, qui font la promesse politique utile de développer la politique spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28310" docOffset="202">
      <en>The priorities must clearly be the timely application of the Galileo and EGNOS programmes and the Global Monitoring for Environment and Security programme which will assist in the assessment and implementation of European policies impacting on the environment.</en>
      <fr>De toute évidence, les priorités doivent être la mise en œuvre en temps utile des programmes Galileo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31114">et</DiscourseConnective> EGNOS <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31123">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que du programme de surveillance mondiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31171">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'environnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31192">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité, qui facilitera l'évaluation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31236">et</DiscourseConnective> l'application des politiques européennes en matière d'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28571" docOffset="203">
      <en>As regards financing, we must find instruments appropriate to the European Space Policy which, in addition to that specified in the Seventh Framework Programme, will enable medium- and long-term planning.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31308">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne le financement, nous devons trouver des instruments adaptés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31387">à</DiscourseConnective> la politique spatiale européenne et qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31430">en plus de</DiscourseConnective> ceux prévus dans le septième programme-cadre, permettront une planification à moyen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31525">et</DiscourseConnective> à long terme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28776" docOffset="204">
      <en>The possible inclusion in the budget of a specific chapter will show the European Union's commitment to this policy and increase its clarity and transparency in anticipation of the entry into force of the Lisbon Treaty provisions.</en>
      <fr>L'éventuelle inclusion d'un chapitre spécifique dans le budget montrera l'engagement de l'Union européenne en faveur de cette politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31678">et</DiscourseConnective> renforcera sa clarté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31702">et</DiscourseConnective> sa transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31721">en attendant</DiscourseConnective> l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31743">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur des dispositions du traité de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="29007" id="238" name="Janusz Onyszkiewicz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="29007" docOffset="205">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, I am very pleased that we are developing our space programme in cooperation with the Russians.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, je suis très heureux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31843">que</DiscourseConnective> nous développions notre programme spatial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31889">en</DiscourseConnective> collaboration avec la Russie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29121" docOffset="206">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="40939" annotation_id="29121">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29121" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we must remember that in the background there is another partner with which we need to establish cooperation - Ukraine.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="17466" annotation_id="31934">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31934" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31958">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à l'arrière-plan se trouve un autre partenaire avec lequel nous devons instaurer une coopération, à savoir l'Ukraine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29250" docOffset="207">
      <en>The best Soviet rockets were built in Ukraine.</en>
      <fr>Les meilleures fusées soviétiques ont été construites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32133">en</DiscourseConnective> Ukraine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29297" docOffset="208">
      <en>Its potential in this area is enormous.</en>
      <fr>Ce pays possède un potentiel énorme dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29337" docOffset="209">
      <en>I think that we need to recognise it and use it for our common good.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32207">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons le reconnaître <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32238">et</DiscourseConnective> l'utiliser dans notre intérêt commun.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29406" docOffset="210">
      <en>My other comment relates to the Galileo programme.</en>
      <fr>Mon autre commentaire concerne le programme Galileo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29457" docOffset="211">
      <en>We must remember that this programme can and should be extremely important to our military operations and our military missions as well.</en>
      <fr>Il ne faut pas oublier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32355">que</DiscourseConnective> ce programme peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32377">et</DiscourseConnective> doit revêtir une importance extrême <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32416">pour</DiscourseConnective> nos opérations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32436">et</DiscourseConnective> nos missions militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29594" docOffset="212">
      <en>The important thing is that the use of this system for military purposes must be adequately safeguarded, <Alignment alignment="32556" annotation_id="29699">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29699" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29702" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> to ensure that other programme participants - I am thinking of China above all - should not know how to and should not be able to block it.</en>
      <fr>L'essentiel est de protéger correctement l'utilisation de ce système <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32533">à</DiscourseConnective> des fins militaires, <Alignment alignment="6494" annotation_id="32556">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32556" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de façon à ce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les autres participants à ce programme - et je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32627">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32638">à</DiscourseConnective> la Chine - ne sachent pas comment bloquer cette utilisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32700">et</DiscourseConnective> ne soient pas en mesure de le faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="29845" id="239" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="29845" docOffset="213">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="32740" annotation_id="29845">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29845" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> handing over to the Council, may I bring to your attention ladies and gentlemen the fact that there are three Members of this House born on 5 August - that is to say, the birthday of Neil Armstrong.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="29845" annotation_id="32740">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32740" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> passer la parole au Conseil, je vous apprends peut-être, chers collègues, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32823">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il y a trois députés dans cette assemblée qui sont nés un 5 août, c'est-à-dire le jour de l'anniversaire de Neil Armstrong.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30051" docOffset="214">
      <en>I happen to be one of them, which is why I am aware of this.</en>
      <fr>Je suis l'un des trois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32974">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> je suis au courant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30112" docOffset="215">
      <en>I will leave you to reflect on this <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30148" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">while</DiscourseConnective> listening to the Council.</en>
      <fr>Je vous laisse méditer en écoutant le Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="30180" id="240" language="FR" name="Jean-Pierre Jouyet">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="30180" docOffset="216">
      <en>That does not surprise me, Mr President, <Alignment alignment="33145" annotation_id="30221">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30221" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am very happy for you, you are well worthy of it!</en>
      <fr>président en exercice du Conseil. - Cela ne m'étonne pas de vous, Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="30221" annotation_id="33145">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33145" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'en suis très heureux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33171">pour</DiscourseConnective> vous, vous en êtes digne!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30277" docOffset="217">
      <en>Mr President, Mr Vice-President of the Commission, honourable Members, I will be very brief <Alignment alignment="20670" annotation_id="30369">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30369" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> much has already been said.</en>
      <fr>Je serai extrêmement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33223">bref</DiscourseConnective>, Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Vice-président de la Commission, Mesdames et Messieurs les Députés, <Alignment alignment="30369" annotation_id="33332">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33332" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> beaucoup a été dit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30400" docOffset="218">
      <en>Firstly, your speeches and debates have shown the mobilisation of your House around the issue of European space policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33362">Premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, vos interventions, vos débats ont montré la mobilisation de votre Assemblée autour de la politique spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30520" docOffset="219">
      <en>We are in search of a unifying European project.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33508">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche d'un projet européen fédérateur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30569" docOffset="220">
      <en>We are in search of European projects that truly stimulate and ensure that new generations of Europeans can take part in this unique adventure.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33568">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche de projets européens qui, véritablement, stimulent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33634">et</DiscourseConnective> fassent en sorte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33654">que</DiscourseConnective> de nouvelles générations d'Européens puissent rejoindre cette aventure unique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30713" docOffset="221">
      <en>We are, as has been underlined, in search of projects targeted to improve the practical lives of our fellow citizens.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33750">comme</DiscourseConnective> cela a été souligné, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33777">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche de projets visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33810">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la vie concrète de nos concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30831" docOffset="222">
      <en>We are in search of projects with a real purpose to develop competitiveness, to associate different European industrial partners and to support activity during this period of depression.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33870">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche de projets qui ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33904">pour</DiscourseConnective> véritable vocation de développer la compétitivité, d'associer les différents partenaires industriels européens, de soutenir l'activité dans cette période de dépression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31018" docOffset="223">
      <en>We are in search of projects aimed at improving research, development and innovation.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34090">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche de projets visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34123">à</DiscourseConnective> faire en sorte que la recherche, le développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34175">et</DiscourseConnective> l'innovation soient renforcés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31104" docOffset="224">
      <en>We are in search of projects - to be truly comprehensive - that make Europe more visible, make it a global actor and influential in dealing with the global challenges that await us, whether they be the fight against climate change, or matters of development, or the strategic balances with our other partners.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34221">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche de projets - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34249">pour</DiscourseConnective> être tout à fait synthétique - qui font que l'Europe soit plus visible, devienne un acteur global <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34352">et</DiscourseConnective> pèse sur les défis globaux qui nous attendent, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34402">que</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34409">soit</DiscourseConnective> en matière de lutte contre le changement climatique, que ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34474">soit</DiscourseConnective> en matière de développement, que ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34515">soit</DiscourseConnective> également dans des équilibres stratégiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34563">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard de nos autres partenaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31414" docOffset="225">
      <en>I believe that your debate shows us clearly that we absolutely must not relax our efforts. <Alignment alignment="34707" annotation_id="31505">
          <Alignment alignment="59960" annotation_id="31505">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31505" sense="Comparison.Contrast">On the contrary</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, we must concentrate all of our means, all of our abilities of cooperation on that most symbolic of European projects: the European space policy.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34609">que</DiscourseConnective> votre débat montre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34632">bien que</DiscourseConnective> nous ne devons absolument pas relâcher l'effort, que nous devons, <Alignment alignment="31505" annotation_id="34707">
          <Alignment alignment="12126" annotation_id="34707">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34707" sense="Comparison.Contrast">au contraire</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, concentrer tous nos moyens, toutes nos facultés de coopération sur ce qui est le plus symbolique des projets européens, c'est-à-dire la politique spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="31667" id="241" language="DE" name="Günter Verheugen">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="31667" docOffset="226">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I am grateful for the broad support for European space policy demonstrated by this debate.</en>
      <fr>vice-président de la Commission. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34960">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je vous suis reconnaissant du large soutien en faveur de la politique spatiale européenne témoigné durant ce débat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31794" docOffset="227">
      <en>I would very much like this broad support to be shown during the process of creating the financial foundations for a permanent and lasting European presence in space.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais beaucoup que ce même soutien enthousiaste se manifeste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35156">quand</DiscourseConnective> il s'agira de jeter les bases financières d'une présence européenne permanente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35241">et</DiscourseConnective> durable dans l'espace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31961" docOffset="228">
      <en>I would like to draw your attention to the fact that our competitors are not sitting back and doing nothing.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais attirer votre attention sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35315">que</DiscourseConnective> nos concurrents ne restent pas les bras croisés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32070" docOffset="229">
      <en>Other regions in the world are already far ahead of us <Alignment alignment="35436" annotation_id="32125">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32125" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it comes to the vision of what should be done next.</en>
      <fr>D'autres régions du monde ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35398">déjà</DiscourseConnective> une vision nettement plus claire <Alignment alignment="4076" annotation_id="35436">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35436" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la nôtre de ce qu'elles souhaitent faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32182" docOffset="230">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="35482" annotation_id="32182">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32182" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we cannot identify new projects and develop new technologies, we will not be able to retain our leading position in the field of space-based applications, <Alignment alignment="55832" annotation_id="32340">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32340" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will simply not have the necessary foundations in science and research.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13980" annotation_id="35482">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35482" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne parvenons pas à identifier de nouveaux projets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35540">et</DiscourseConnective> à développer de nouvelles technologies, nous ne pourrons pas maintenir notre position pionnière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35639">en</DiscourseConnective> matière d'applications spatiales <Alignment alignment="1869" annotation_id="35675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35675" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne possèderons tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35710">simplement</DiscourseConnective> pas les bases nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35747">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de science <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35769">et</DiscourseConnective> de recherche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32423" docOffset="231">
      <en>For this reason, I would like to repeat that I was very grateful that all of this has been made clear today.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35786">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35811">à</DiscourseConnective> le répéter, je vous suis très reconnaissant d'avoir permis de clarifier tout cela aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32532" docOffset="232">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="35908" annotation_id="32532">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32532" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we can work together to raise awareness, we can tell all the citizens of Europe the story referred to by Mr Chichester, the story that European space projects can be the cause that brings us all together.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="32532" annotation_id="35908">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35908" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous parvenons à travailler ensemble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35948">pour</DiscourseConnective> sensibiliser l'opinion, nous pourrons raconter aux citoyens européens ce que nous a dit M. Chichester, leur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36061">dire que</DiscourseConnective> les projets spatiaux européens peuvent constituer un lien solide qui nous unira tous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="32740" id="242" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="32740" docOffset="233">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
