<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Consumer Markets Scoreboard (short presentation)</en>
    <fr>Tableau de bord des marchés de consommation (brève présentation)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="49" id="208" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="49" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Mrs Anna Hedh, on behalf of the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, on the Consumer Markets Scoreboard.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de Mme Anna Hedh, au nom de la commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="162">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs, sur le tableau de bord des marchés de consommation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="206" id="209" language="SV" name="Anna Hedh">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="206" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, The internal market is an extremely important part of the European cooperation, <Alignment alignment="4673" annotation_id="300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="300" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> for many consumers it is nothing more than a vague concept.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, le marché intérieur est souvent considéré comme la pièce maîtresse de l'intégration européenne, <Alignment alignment="2352" annotation_id="372">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="372" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la représentation que s'en font de nombreux consommateurs est plutôt vague.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="364" docOffset="3">
      <en>Irrespective of how well we recognise its importance, rules and provisions, we are all consumers and are all affected by how the internal market operates.</en>
      <fr>Chacun d'entre nous, quel que soit son degré de familiarité avec le sens de cette expression et les règles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="560">et</DiscourseConnective> règlements qui s'y rapportent, est un consommateur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="614">et</DiscourseConnective> chacun d'entre nous est affecté par le fonctionnement de ce marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="519" docOffset="4">
      <en>I have always maintained that <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="549" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> we have satisfied and confident European consumers, we will <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="612" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> have an internal market that operates efficiently and thrives.</en>
      <fr>J'ai toujours été d'avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="710">que</DiscourseConnective> la confiance du consommateur européen est une condition sine qua non au bon fonctionnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="805">et</DiscourseConnective> au développement du marché intérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="680" docOffset="5">
      <en>In order to win this trust, we must make the internal market more efficient and sensitive to citizens' expectations and problems.</en>
      <fr>Pour gagner cette confiance, nous devons rendre le marché intérieur plus efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="928">et</DiscourseConnective> faire en sorte qu'il réponde mieux aux attentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="979">et</DiscourseConnective> aux problèmes des citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="810" docOffset="6">
      <en>This does not necessarily mean more or stricter legislation and rules imposed by the EU.</en>
      <fr>Point n'est besoin pour cela d'étoffer la législation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1064">ou</DiscourseConnective> de la rendre plus rigoureuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="899" docOffset="7">
      <en>Information, education and self-regulation can often be a more appropriate and more effective solution.</en>
      <fr>Il peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1105">s'</DiscourseConnective>avérer plus judicieux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1129">et</DiscourseConnective> plus efficace d'informer, d'éduquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1168">ou</DiscourseConnective> d'autoréguler.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1003" docOffset="8">
      <en>Irrespective of how we solve the problems, the aim must always be to ensure that we safeguard consumers' rights <Alignment alignment="16003" annotation_id="1115">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1115" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they can make good and well-founded decisions.</en>
      <fr>Quelle que soit la façon de résoudre les problèmes, l'objectif doit être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1259">à</DiscourseConnective> tout moment de veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1289">que</DiscourseConnective> les droits des consommateurs soient garantis et de faire en sorte <Alignment alignment="1115" annotation_id="1359">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1359" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces derniers puissent faire des choix éclairés et fondés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1170" docOffset="9">
      <en>This is, of course, <Alignment alignment="10948" annotation_id="1190">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1190" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a good thing for the market itself.</en>
      <fr>Ceci est évidemment bon <Alignment alignment="1824" annotation_id="1445">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1445" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1455">pour</DiscourseConnective> le fonctionnement du marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1231" docOffset="10">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1541" annotation_id="1231">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1231" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Committee on Internal Market and Consumer Protection and I welcome the Consumer Markets Scoreboard that the Commission presented at the request of the Committee.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1231" annotation_id="1489">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1489" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1539">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1577">et</DiscourseConnective> moi-même saluons le tableau de bord des marchés de consommation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1644">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission a présenté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1673">à</DiscourseConnective> la demande de la commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1408" docOffset="11">
      <en>We believe that it could be an important tool for the future development of consumer policy.</en>
      <fr>Nous pensons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1717">que</DiscourseConnective> cet outil est appelé à jouer un rôle central dans l'évolution de la politique des consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1501" docOffset="12">
      <en>The internal market comprises around 500 million consumers and has a large supply of goods and services.</en>
      <fr>Le marché unique, c'est près de 500 millions de consommateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1880">et</DiscourseConnective> une multiplicité de marchandises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1916">et</DiscourseConnective> de services.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1606" docOffset="13">
      <en>It is, of course, impossible to examine in detail all aspects of the internal market. It is therefore important to use analytic resources where they are actually needed most.</en>
      <fr>Bien sûr, il est impossible de suivre tous les aspects du marché intérieur dans ses moindres détails, mais il est capital de se servir des ressources analytiques là où elles sont le plus nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1781" docOffset="14">
      <en>I welcome the five areas that the Commission has focused on, namely complaints, price levels, satisfaction, switching and safety.</en>
      <fr>J'approuve totalement les cinq domaines ciblés par la Commission, à savoir les plaintes, les niveaux de prix, la satisfaction, les changements de fournisseur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2290">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1911" docOffset="15">
      <en>These five main indicators are relevant and applicable, even <Alignment alignment="2403" annotation_id="1972">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1972" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there will, over time, be a need to further develop and improve them and maybe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2054" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> to include some new categories.</en>
      <fr>Au fil du temps, il faudra bien entendu étoffer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2354">et</DiscourseConnective> améliorer certains de ces indicateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2395">et même</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="1972" annotation_id="2403">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2403" sense="Contingency.Condition">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> formuler de nouveaux mais ces cinq grands indicateurs sont pertinents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2476">et</DiscourseConnective> utiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2091" docOffset="16">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="2499" annotation_id="2099">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2099" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to stress the importance of raising awareness of the Scoreboard amongst consumers themselves and the general public.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="2099" annotation_id="2499">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2499" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> souligner l'importance de mieux faire comprendre le tableau de bord par les consommateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2599">et</DiscourseConnective> le public en général.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2226" docOffset="17">
      <en>It is therefore important for it to be written in an easily accessible language.</en>
      <fr>Il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2631">donc</DiscourseConnective> important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2646">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2652">soit</DiscourseConnective> écrit dans un langage facilement accessible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2307" docOffset="18">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2702" annotation_id="2307">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2307" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Scoreboard should be visible on relevant websites.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2307" annotation_id="2702">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2702" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le tableau de bord doit être présent sur les sites web pertinents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2372" docOffset="19">
      <en>Finally, I would like to say that it will take time to develop the Scoreboard, partly <Alignment alignment="8534" annotation_id="2458">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2458" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have made very different degrees of progress in the different Member States with regard to consumer policy and consumer protection, but <Alignment alignment="2998" annotation_id="2605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2605" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="10169" annotation_id="2610">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2610" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are different, with different cultures and different traditions.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2778">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2797">dire que</DiscourseConnective> le développement du tableau de bord prendra du temps, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2860">d'une part</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="2458" annotation_id="2871">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2871" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le rythme des progrès en matière de politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2927">et</DiscourseConnective> de protection des consommateurs diffère d'un État membre à l'autre, <Alignment alignment="2605" annotation_id="2998">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2998" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="2610" annotation_id="3009">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3009" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous sommes tous différents, que les cultures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3065">et</DiscourseConnective> les traditions diffèrent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2686" docOffset="20">
      <en>We must be patient and give this Consumer Markets Scoreboard time.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons être patients <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3120">et</DiscourseConnective> donner du temps au tableau de bord des marchés de consommation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2753" docOffset="21">
      <en>I would <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2761" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> like to take the opportunity to thank Commissioner Kuneva and her secretariat, as well as my own secretariat, for their extremely constructive cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Je saisis cette occasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3212">pour</DiscourseConnective> remercier la commissaire Kuneva <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3249">et</DiscourseConnective> son secrétariat, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3269">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que mon propre secrétariat, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3303">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur coopération extrêmement constructive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2922" id="210" name="Danuta Hübner">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2922" docOffset="22">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the Scoreboard initiative came into existence less than a year ago <Alignment alignment="4482" annotation_id="3031">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3031" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> during that time the Commission has greatly appreciated Parliament's interest and support.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, l'initiative du tableau de bord est née il y a moins d'un an <Alignment alignment="2283" annotation_id="3467">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3467" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pendant cette période la Commission a grandement apprécié l'intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3538">et</DiscourseConnective> le soutien du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3126" docOffset="23">
      <en>The Scoreboard has been the subject of many debates in the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, <Alignment alignment="3383" annotation_id="3243">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3243" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have learnt a lot from these debates and from the suggestions made.</en>
      <fr>Le tableau de bord a fait l'objet de nombreux débats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3619">en</DiscourseConnective> commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3653">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs, <Alignment alignment="3243" annotation_id="3692">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3692" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de ces débats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3709">et</DiscourseConnective> des suggestions faites dans leur cadre nous avons tiré énormément d'enseignements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3318" docOffset="24">
      <en>Thank you very much for all that, but especially thanks to Ms Anna Hedh for the excellent report.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie tous vivement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3826">pour</DiscourseConnective> tout cela, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3842">et</DiscourseConnective> je remercie tout spécialement Mme Anna Hedh <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3889">pour</DiscourseConnective> son excellent rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3416" docOffset="25">
      <en>Let me reiterate briefly why the Consumer Market Scoreboard is so important for all of us.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de répéter brièvement pourquoi le tableau de bord des marchés de consommation est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4013">si</DiscourseConnective> important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4026">pour</DiscourseConnective> nous tous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3507" docOffset="26">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4042" annotation_id="3507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3507" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are to deliver to consumers, we need to be more responsive to their expectations and better understand the problems they are facing in their day-to-day lives.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3507" annotation_id="4042">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4042" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons être utiles aux consommateurs, nous devons être plus réactifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4120">à</DiscourseConnective> leurs attentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4137">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4140">mieux</DiscourseConnective> comprendre les problèmes qui se posent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4185">à</DiscourseConnective> eux dans la vie quotidienne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3672" docOffset="27">
      <en>To do so, we need an evidence base that shows how markets perform in terms of economic and social outcomes for consumers, <Alignment alignment="23027" annotation_id="3794">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3794" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> how consumers behave on the market.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4216">Pour ce faire</DiscourseConnective>, il nous faut une base fondée sur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4264">la preuve</DiscourseConnective> qui indique quelles sont les performances des marchés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4328">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de résultats économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4363">et</DiscourseConnective> sociaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4374">pour</DiscourseConnective> les consommateurs, <Alignment alignment="3794" annotation_id="4398">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4398" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> comment les consommateurs se comportent sur le marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3834" docOffset="28">
      <en>Sound policy-making requires accurate data, <Alignment alignment="4525" annotation_id="3878">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3878" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we fully share your view on this.</en>
      <fr>Pour faire une bonne politique, il faut disposer de données précises <Alignment alignment="3878" annotation_id="4525">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4525" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous partageons pleinement votre avis sur ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3916" docOffset="29">
      <en>The Scoreboard brings together evidence to identify markets that risk not delivering well for consumers and <Alignment alignment="4734" annotation_id="4024">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4024" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> need further attention.</en>
      <fr>Le tableau de bord rassemble des preuves permettant d'identifier les marchés qui risquent de ne pas servir au <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4690">mieux</DiscourseConnective> les consommateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4714">et</DiscourseConnective> qui nécessitent, <Alignment alignment="4024" annotation_id="4734">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4734" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, une attention supplémentaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4058" docOffset="30">
      <en>It <Alignment alignment="4790" annotation_id="4061">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4061" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> allows progress in retail market integration to be tracked, and helps to benchmark the consumer environment in Member States, particularly in terms of compliance with consumer legislation, enforcement, redress, and consumer empowerment.</en>
      <fr>Il permet <Alignment alignment="3848" annotation_id="4790">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4790" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de suivre les progrès de l'intégration du marché de détail, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4860">et</DiscourseConnective> facilite l'étalonnage de l'environnement des consommateurs dans les États membres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4946">notamment en</DiscourseConnective> termes de conformité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4980">à</DiscourseConnective> la législation sur la protection des consommateurs, d'application de la loi, de recours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5070">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autonomisation des consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4303" docOffset="31">
      <en>We share your views on which indicators to include in this Scoreboard, <Alignment alignment="14662" annotation_id="4374">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4374" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we believe that the establishment of a harmonised EU-wide database of consumer complaints will be an essential step forward.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes d'accord avec vous sur la sélection des indicateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5173">à</DiscourseConnective> inclure dans ce tableau de bord, <Alignment alignment="4374" annotation_id="5208">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5208" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous pensons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5224">que</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place d'une base de données des plaintes des consommateurs, harmonisée à l'échelle de l'UE, représentera une avancée décisive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4503" docOffset="32">
      <en>It will allow us to detect problems in consumer markets at an early stage and, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4582" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> necessary, to take appropriate action.</en>
      <fr>Elle nous permettra de détecter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5398">à</DiscourseConnective> un stade précoce les problèmes des marchés de consommation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5459">et</DiscourseConnective>, le cas échéant, de prendre les mesures appropriées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4624" docOffset="33">
      <en>The Commission firmly believes that it is important to include price data, <Alignment alignment="21250" annotation_id="4699">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4699" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> prices are one of consumers' principal concerns.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est convaincue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5544">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est important d'inclure des données sur les prix, <Alignment alignment="2724" annotation_id="5600">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5600" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les prix sont l'une des principales préoccupations des consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4754" docOffset="34">
      <en>The current political and economic climate further reinforces the need for good price data.</en>
      <fr>Considérant le contexte politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5712">et</DiscourseConnective> économique actuel, il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5741">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus nécessaire de disposer de bonnes données sur les prix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4846" docOffset="35">
      <en>We need to send a clear signal to our consumers that we are keeping an eye on how prices compare across the internal market.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons montrer clairement aux consommateurs européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5867">que</DiscourseConnective> nous surveillons et comparons les prix dans le marché intérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4971" docOffset="36">
      <en>The Commission can assure you that it is fully aware of the complexity of this issue, <Alignment alignment="8805" annotation_id="5057">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5057" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> will of course interpret this data carefully and make sure the data are put in the right context.</en>
      <fr>La Commission peut vous garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5969">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle est pleinement consciente de la complexité de cette question, <Alignment alignment="5057" annotation_id="6039">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6039" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'il va de soi qu'elle interprétera ces données avec précaution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6107">en</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6110">s'</DiscourseConnective>assurant que les données sont placées dans le bon contexte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5159" docOffset="37">
      <en>Prices may diverge across the internal market for sound economic reasons, but also because of market malfunctioning, <Alignment alignment="13689" annotation_id="5276">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5276" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our aim is to find ways to tell the difference.</en>
      <fr>Il peut se faire que les prix divergent dans le marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6237">pour</DiscourseConnective> des raisons économiques cohérentes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6278">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6283">également</DiscourseConnective> à cause d'un dysfonctionnement du marché, <Alignment alignment="2670" annotation_id="6335">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6335" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> notre but est de trouver des moyens d'expliquer la différence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5328" docOffset="38">
      <en>We share Ms Hedh's view on the importance of close cooperation with Member States.</en>
      <fr>Nous partageons l'avis de Mme Hedh sur l'importance de coopérer étroitement avec les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5411" docOffset="39">
      <en>This year, the Commission started to work together with national policy-makers, statistical offices, enforcement authorities and consumer organisations to further develop the Scoreboard indicators, <Alignment alignment="9361" annotation_id="5609">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5609" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will continue with this cooperation in the coming years.</en>
      <fr>Cette année, la Commission a commencé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6539">à</DiscourseConnective> travailler avec les responsables politiques nationaux, les instituts de statistiques, les services répressifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6651">et</DiscourseConnective> les organisations de consommateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6689">pour</DiscourseConnective> affiner les indicateurs du tableau de bord, <Alignment alignment="5609" annotation_id="6738">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6738" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous poursuivrons cette coopération dans les années à venir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5673" docOffset="40">
      <en>Ms Hedh has stressed that we should make this Scoreboard more accessible to a larger public <Alignment alignment="6912" annotation_id="5765">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5765" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that we should raise awareness.</en>
      <fr>Mme Hedh a insisté sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6833">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devrions rendre ce tableau de bord plus accessible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6893">à</DiscourseConnective> un vaste public, <Alignment alignment="5765" annotation_id="6912">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6912" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6915">aussi</DiscourseConnective> mieux faire connaître le tableau de bord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5801" docOffset="41">
      <en>The Commission accepts this point, and will step up efforts to do so.</en>
      <fr>La Commission accepte ce point, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6995">et</DiscourseConnective> nous augmenterons nos efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7028">en ce sens</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5871" docOffset="42">
      <en>I invite you to see the results in the second edition of the Scoreboard.</en>
      <fr>Je vous invite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7055">à</DiscourseConnective> constater les résultats lors de la deuxième édition du tableau de bord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5944" docOffset="43">
      <en>Finally, what the Commission wishes to take from Ms Hedh's report - <Alignment alignment="7199" annotation_id="6012">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6012" sense="Comparison.Concession">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I could quote many other points <Alignment alignment="7252" annotation_id="6053">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6053" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I had more time - is the wish for more empowerment indicators such as literacy and skills.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7129">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, ce que la Commission souhaite retenir du rapport de Mme Hedh - <Alignment alignment="3970" annotation_id="7199">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7199" sense="Comparison.Concession">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pourrais citer de nombreux autres points <Alignment alignment="6053" annotation_id="7252">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7252" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'en avais le temps - c'est le souhait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7294">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il comprenne davantage d'indicateurs d'autonomisation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7352">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'alphabétisation des adultes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7388">et</DiscourseConnective> les compétences.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6147" docOffset="44">
      <en>Within the framework of Eurostat's revised European Social Survey Programme, the Commission plans to run a module on consumer empowerment through which it wants to measure consumer skills, consumer information and awareness of rights and assertiveness.</en>
      <fr>Dans le cadre du programme révisé European Social Survey (enquête sociale européenne) d'Eurostat, la Commission prévoit de mettre en place un module sur l'autonomisation des consommateurs qui lui permettra de mesurer les compétences des consommateurs, les informations qu'ils possèdent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7694">et</DiscourseConnective> leur conscientisation en matière de droits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7740">et</DiscourseConnective> d'assertivité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6400" docOffset="45">
      <en>This would allow us to start drawing up a statistical snapshot of Europe's citizens in their capacity as consumers.</en>
      <fr>Ce module nous permettrait de commencer à dresser le tableau statistique des capacités des citoyens européens en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7871">tant que</DiscourseConnective> consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6516" docOffset="46">
      <en>We see this as the main subject of the pilot project proposed by the Parliament for 2009.</en>
      <fr>Nous considérons cette idée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7923">comme</DiscourseConnective> le principal sujet du projet pilote proposé par le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7990">pour</DiscourseConnective> 2009.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6606" docOffset="47">
      <en>Let me conclude by again thanking Ms Hedh for the interest and support, not least in financial terms.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de conclure en remerciant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8041">encore</DiscourseConnective> Mme Hedh <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8057">pour</DiscourseConnective> son intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8074">et</DiscourseConnective> son soutien, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8090">surtout</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8098">en</DiscourseConnective> termes financiers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6708" id="211" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6708" docOffset="48">
      <en>That concludes this item.</en>
      <fr>La présentation est close.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6734" docOffset="49">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow at 12 noon.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8172">à</DiscourseConnective> 12 heures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6780" docOffset="50">
      <en>Written statements (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclarations écrites (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6810" id="212" name="Slavi Binev ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6810" docOffset="51">
      <en>in writing. - (BG) I welcome Anna Hedh's report on the Consumer Markets Scoreboard <Alignment alignment="8321" annotation_id="6893">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6893" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> its aim of making the internal market more sensitive to the expectations and concerns of citizens.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (BG) Je salue le rapport d'Anna Hedh sur le tableau de bord des marchés de consommation <Alignment alignment="6893" annotation_id="8321">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8321" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'approuve son objectif de rendre le marché intérieur plus sensible aux attentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8405">et</DiscourseConnective> aux préoccupations des citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6996" docOffset="52">
      <en>Over the past 19 years of Bulgaria's so-called democratic transition, we have had our fill of various privatisation solutions put forward by the ruling authorities in Bulgaria.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8441">Après</DiscourseConnective> ces 19 dernières années de transition dite "démocratique" de la Bulgarie, nous en avons plus qu'assez des diverses solutions de privatisation mises en œuvre par le gouvernement bulgare.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7173" docOffset="53">
      <en>A striking case is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7192" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> proven thieves from the ČEZ Měření power company were allowed into the Bulgarian domestic market.</en>
      <fr>L'un des cas les plus scandaleux est celui des voleurs avérés de la compagnie d'électricité ČEZ Měření qui ont été autorisés à entrer sur le marché domestique bulgare.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7295" docOffset="54">
      <en>The gentlemen of ČEZ, whom we of ATAKA have long identified as blatant gangsters, have been indicted in their own country.</en>
      <fr>Ces Messieurs de ČEZ, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8823">que</DiscourseConnective> nous, les membres d'ATAKA, avons depuis longtemps identifiés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8888">comme</DiscourseConnective> de véritables gangsters, ont été formellement mis en accusation dans leur pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7418" docOffset="55">
      <en>32 of their employees have been arrested for blackmailing customers whom they accused of stealing electricity.</en>
      <fr>Trente-deux de leurs employés ont été arrêtés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9020">pour</DiscourseConnective> chantage auprès de clients <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9052">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils accusaient de voler de l'électricité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7529" docOffset="56">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4162" annotation_id="7529">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7529" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> obviously too busy with corruption, the tripartite coalition in Bulgaria did not consider this reason enough to throw these criminals out, <Alignment alignment="16012" annotation_id="7672">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7672" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the governments of Canada and Hungary did, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7718" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> so ČEZ continues to rob and blackmail the Bulgarian taxpayer under the guise of their neat little privatisation agreements.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7529" annotation_id="9097">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9097" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, manifestement trop occupé par le problème de la corruption, la coalition tripartite de Bulgarie ne considère pas cette raison suffisante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9240">pour</DiscourseConnective> jeter dehors ces criminels, <Alignment alignment="7672" annotation_id="9273">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9273" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'ont fait les gouvernements canadien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9317">et</DiscourseConnective> hongrois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9330">si bien que</DiscourseConnective> la ČEZ continue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9358">à</DiscourseConnective> gruger <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9367">et</DiscourseConnective> à faire chanter les contribuables bulgares sous le couvert de leurs petits accords de privatisation bien propres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7846" docOffset="57">
      <en>I believe that the adoption of the Consumer Markets Scoreboard will improve the tools for keeping tabs on sectors which need to be investigated for weaknesses and infringements, will involve the national consumer protection authorities in preserving the quality of social services, and will help to restore consumer confidence in the internal market.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9493">que</DiscourseConnective> l'adoption du tableau de bord des marchés de consommation améliorera les outils permettant d'avoir l'œil sur les secteurs nécessitant une enquête au sujet de leurs défaillances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9674">et</DiscourseConnective> des infractions qu'ils commettent, permettra aux autorités nationales de protection des consommateurs de jouer leur rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9798">en</DiscourseConnective> préservant la qualité des services sociaux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9845">et</DiscourseConnective> favorisera la restauration de la confiance des consommateurs dans le marché intérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8197" id="213" language="SK" name="Zita Pleštinská ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8197" docOffset="58">
      <en>The Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection of the European Parliament has the priority aim of improving the position of European consumers in the internal market.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (SK) La commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9987">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs du Parlement européen a pour priorité l'amélioration de la position des consommateurs européens dans le marché intérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8378" docOffset="59">
      <en>It is constantly calling on the Commission and the Member States to research what consumers think about the internal market <Alignment alignment="21189" annotation_id="8502">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8502" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> particularly what they need.</en>
      <fr>Elle appelle constamment la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10186">et</DiscourseConnective> les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10207">à</DiscourseConnective> étudier ce que les consommateurs pensent du marché intérieur <Alignment alignment="8502" annotation_id="10270">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10270" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10274">notamment</DiscourseConnective>, ce qu'ils en attendent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8535" docOffset="60">
      <en>The main precondition for an effective and well-functioning internal market is consumer confidence.</en>
      <fr>La toute première condition préalable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10347">à</DiscourseConnective> un fonctionnement efficace du marché intérieur, c'est la confiance des consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8635" docOffset="61">
      <en>Recognising the advantages of the evaluation table for the internal market which has been used since 1997, the committee has called on the Commission to submit a proposal for an evaluation table for consumer markets as an instrument for assessing the market from a consumer perspective as well.</en>
      <fr>Reconnaissant les avantages du tableau de bord du marché intérieur en usage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10511">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 1997, la commission a appelé la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10572">à</DiscourseConnective> présenter une proposition de tableau de bord des marchés de consommation, qui devrait servir d'instrument <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10680">pour</DiscourseConnective> évaluer le marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10703">également</DiscourseConnective> du point de vue des consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8930" docOffset="62">
      <en>Complaints, pricing levels, satisfaction, interfaces and security are the five main indicators used in the evaluation table.</en>
      <fr>Les plaintes, les niveaux de prix, la satisfaction, les changements de fournisseur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10831">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité: tels sont les cinq principaux indicateurs utilisés dans le tableau de bord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9055" docOffset="63">
      <en>The committee realises that <Alignment alignment="13010" annotation_id="9083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9083" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this will be the first ever evaluation table for consumer markets, some of these indicators will have to be replaced with new ones in the future.</en>
      <fr>La commission réalise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10945">que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="9083" annotation_id="10950">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10950" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">étant donné qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il s'agira du premier tableau de bord des marchés de consommation, certains de ces indicateurs devront être remplacés par de nouveaux indicateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11111">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9235" docOffset="64">
      <en>The indicator referring to pricing levels is particularly doubtful.</en>
      <fr>L'indicateur des niveaux de prix, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11157">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>, doit être remis en cause.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9303" docOffset="65">
      <en>I agree with the opinion of the rapporteur, Anna Hedh, that the table should be properly promoted through the media and placed on the relevant websites.</en>
      <fr>Je conviens avec la rapporteure, Anna Hedh, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11243">que</DiscourseConnective> le tableau de bord devrait être adéquatement promu par le biais des médias <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11322">et</DiscourseConnective> figurer sur les sites web pertinents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9456" docOffset="66">
      <en>My preference would be for the Commission to provide financial support for a public awareness campaign which would be carried out by the consumer organisations.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11374">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission alloue un soutien financier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11420">pour</DiscourseConnective> une campagne de sensibilisation du public qui serait menée par les organisations de consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9617" docOffset="67">
      <en>Due to their experience in the area of consumer policy, they will know the best way to get the table across to consumers.</en>
      <fr>Du fait de leur expérience dans le domaine de la politique des consommateurs, elles sont les <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11617">mieux</DiscourseConnective> placées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11631">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire connaître le tableau de bord auprès des consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9739" docOffset="68">
      <en>I firmly believe that the table will have to capture the interest of consumers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9818" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> it is to become an important instrument for the future development of consumer policy.</en>
      <fr>Je suis fermement convaincue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11726">que</DiscourseConnective> le tableau de bord saura attirer l'attention des consommateurs, pour autant qu'il devienne un important instrument du futur développement de la politique des consommateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
