<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Public contracts in the fields of defence and security (debate)</en>
    <fr>Marchés publics dans les domaines de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="64" id="269" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="64" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Mr Lambsdorff, on behalf of the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, on the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on the coordination of procedures for the award of certain public works contracts, public supply contracts and public service contracts in the fields of defence and security - C6-0467/2007 -.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de M. Lambsdorff, au nom de la commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="171">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs, sur la proposition de directive du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="264">et</DiscourseConnective> du Conseil relative à la coordination des procédures de passation de certains marchés publics de travaux, de fournitures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="388">et</DiscourseConnective> de services dans les domaines de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="435">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité - C6-0467/2007 -.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="455" id="270" language="DE" name="Alexander Graf Lambsdorff">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="455" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, worldwide there are currently 13 EU missions through which we are helping to bring peace and stability.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="522">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, à l'heure actuelle, treize missions européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="584">s'</DiscourseConnective>activent à travers le monde à promouvoir la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="635">et</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="595" docOffset="3">
      <en>Nine missions have already ended.</en>
      <fr>Neuf missions sont terminées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="629" docOffset="4">
      <en>In many of these operations, armed forces, often including police officers, from our Member States enter difficult environments.</en>
      <fr>Les forces armées de nos États membres, parmi lesquelles se trouvent bien souvent des officiers de police, qui participent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="805">à</DiscourseConnective> ces opérations sont couramment confrontées à des situations difficiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="758" docOffset="5">
      <en>At the same time, we all know that there are still many more trouble spots <Alignment alignment="989" annotation_id="833">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="833" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that demand for European intervention in international politics is more likely to increase than decrease, <Alignment alignment="1107" annotation_id="943">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="943" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, unfortunately, we <Alignment alignment="70470" annotation_id="966">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="966" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> know that we Europeans are often not in a position to carry out our missions in the way that we really ought to, with optimum equipment and in an interoperable and strategically redeployable manner.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="879">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>, nous sommes tous conscients <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="921">que</DiscourseConnective> le nombre de zones de conflit restantes est bien plus important <Alignment alignment="5352" annotation_id="989">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="989" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="992">que</DiscourseConnective> la demande d'intervention européenne dans la politique internationale risque plus d'augmenter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1090">que</DiscourseConnective> de diminuer. <Alignment alignment="32750" annotation_id="1107">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1107" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1111">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, nous savons <Alignment alignment="12809" annotation_id="1140">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1140" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1150">que</DiscourseConnective> nous, Européens, ne sommes généralement pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1198">en</DiscourseConnective> mesure de mener à bien nos missions exactement comme il le faudrait, avec le meilleur matériel possible, dans un cadre interopérable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1334">et</DiscourseConnective> avec la possibilité d'un redéploiement stratégique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1170" docOffset="6">
      <en>We must achieve this, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1192" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> we owe this to our soldiers and police officers involved in operations throughout the world.</en>
      <fr>Mais nous devons y parvenir, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1418">pour</DiscourseConnective> nos soldats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1435">et</DiscourseConnective> nos officiers de police impliqués dans des opérations de ce type à travers le monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1288" docOffset="7">
      <en>This goal is a long way off, <Alignment alignment="1535" annotation_id="1317">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1317" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <Alignment alignment="1317" annotation_id="1535">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1535" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> encore très loin d'avoir atteint cet objectif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1326" docOffset="8">
      <en>One of the reasons for this is our fragmented defence equipment market.</en>
      <fr>Cela est dû <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1604">en</DiscourseConnective> partie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1614">à</DiscourseConnective> la fragmentation de notre marché des équipements de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1398" docOffset="9">
      <en>Our 27 Member States indulge in 89 different, sometimes even duplicated, research programmes. The US has only 29.</en>
      <fr>Nos 27 États membres possèdent 89 programmes de recherche différents, dont certains font double emploi, alors que les États-Unis n'en ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1815">que</DiscourseConnective> 29.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1512" docOffset="10">
      <en>There is far too little cooperation between the Member States in connection with product development.</en>
      <fr>La coopération entre les États membres est beaucoup trop limitée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1888">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de développement de ces produits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1614" docOffset="11">
      <en>So-called traditional suppliers are preferred over non-traditional, but perhaps better suppliers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1711" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that is what we want to change.</en>
      <fr>Les fournisseurs dits traditionnels sont préférés aux non traditionnels, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2006">alors que</DiscourseConnective> ceux-ci sont peut-être meilleurs. Nous voulons que cela change.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1747" docOffset="12">
      <en>Goods and services to the value of around EUR 91 billion are acquired each year on the European defence equipment market.</en>
      <fr>Le marché européen des équipements de défense vend des biens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2141">et</DiscourseConnective> des services <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2157">pour</DiscourseConnective> quelque 91 milliards d'euros chaque année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1869" docOffset="13">
      <en>Of this, only 13% is, on average, put out to tender Europe-wide.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2205">En</DiscourseConnective> moyenne, treize pour cent seulement de ces ventes font l'objet d'appels d'offres européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1934" docOffset="14">
      <en>The sorry country bringing up the rear in this case, I might add, is Germany with only around 2%.</en>
      <fr>Et j'ajouterai que l'Allemagne fait triste figure dans ce domaine, occupant la dernière place avec un petit 2 %.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2032" docOffset="15">
      <en>The bottom line is that the internal market for defence-related products is not working.</en>
      <fr>Il en résulte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2427">que</DiscourseConnective> le marché intérieur des produits en matière de défense n'est pas fonctionnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2121" docOffset="16">
      <en>Many important innovations in this high-tech industry cannot be utilised, our armed forces do not get the best equipment <Alignment alignment="2667" annotation_id="2242">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2242" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> taxpayers' money is wasted.</en>
      <fr>Quantités d'innovations importantes dans cette industrie de pointe restent inexploitées, nos forces armées ne bénéficient pas du meilleur matériel disponible <Alignment alignment="16209" annotation_id="2667">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2667" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'argent des contribuables est utilisé à mauvais escient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2274" docOffset="17">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2728" annotation_id="2274">
          <Alignment alignment="2728" annotation_id="2274">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2274" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">As a result</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, highly developed defence-related products are becoming increasingly expensive, <Alignment alignment="2797" annotation_id="2366">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2366" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the defence budget remains the same or is even getting smaller.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17469" annotation_id="2728">
          <Alignment alignment="16388" annotation_id="2728">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2728" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, les produits de pointe sont de plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2780">en plus</DiscourseConnective> coûteux, <Alignment alignment="2366" annotation_id="2797">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2797" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le budget consacré à la défense reste identique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2856">quand</DiscourseConnective> il ne diminue pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2436" docOffset="18">
      <en>In this situation, it is clear what it is all about.</en>
      <fr>Dans pareille situation, la solution est très claire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2489" docOffset="19">
      <en>It is not about greater arms expenditure, but about spending the existing money more wisely.</en>
      <fr>Il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2941">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit pas d'accroître les dépenses en armements, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2991">mais</DiscourseConnective> de dépenser les fonds existants de manière plus judicieuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2582" docOffset="20">
      <en>That is what we need to do.</en>
      <fr>Voilà ce que nous devons faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2610" docOffset="21">
      <en>We owe it to our taxpayers.</en>
      <fr>Nous le devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3103">à</DiscourseConnective> nos contribuables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2638" docOffset="22">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2638" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>, in a report in 2005 this Parliament called on the Commission to submit a directive for this sector. It has done so, in agreement with both Parliament and the Council.</en>
      <fr>Dans cette optique, ce Parlement a rédigé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3166">en</DiscourseConnective> 2005 un rapport appelant la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3208">à</DiscourseConnective> présenter une directive relative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3243">à</DiscourseConnective> ce secteur, ce qu'elle a fait, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3276">en</DiscourseConnective> accord avec le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3304">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2816" docOffset="23">
      <en>It was important for us, and <Alignment alignment="1229" annotation_id="2845">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2845" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> for me as rapporteur, that President Sarkozy expressly mentioned the European defence equipment market in his speech about the priorities of the French Presidency.</en>
      <fr>Il nous a paru très significatif, <Alignment alignment="1146" annotation_id="3353">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3353" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3363">à</DiscourseConnective> moi-même en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3377">tant que</DiscourseConnective> rapporteur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3398">que</DiscourseConnective> le président Sarkozy mentionne expressément le marché européen des équipements de défense dans son discours sur les priorités de la présidence française.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3014" docOffset="24">
      <en>With that it was clear that Parliament, the Council and the Commission would work together on this in a united effort.</en>
      <fr>Il signalait ainsi sans ambages <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3588">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement, le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3617">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission travailleraient main dans la main dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3133" docOffset="25">
      <en>The agreement at first reading is a result of this common political will.</en>
      <fr>L'accord conclu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3701">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture découle de cette volonté politique commune.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3207" docOffset="26">
      <en>Tomorrow, we will - hopefully together - lay the foundation for a new European legal framework, which will ensure a genuine opening of the market and greater transparency and competition with regard to procurement.</en>
      <fr>Demain - ensemble espérons-le -, nous jetterons les fondements d'un nouveau cadre juridique européen, qui contribuera à une ouverture effective du marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3919">et</DiscourseConnective> à une transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3941">et</DiscourseConnective> une concurrence accrues dans le domaine de la passation de marchés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3422" docOffset="27">
      <en>We must <Alignment alignment="4023" annotation_id="3430">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3430" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> view this directive in context.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <Alignment alignment="3430" annotation_id="4023">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4023" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de replacer cette directive dans son contexte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3467" docOffset="28">
      <en>In December, we successfully adopted the Directive on the transfer of defence-related products within the Community.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4079">En</DiscourseConnective> décembre, nous avons adopté la directive sur les transferts de produits liés à la défense dans la Communauté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3584" docOffset="29">
      <en>The directive before us today is the second important building block in the European defence equipment package.</en>
      <fr>La directive que nous examinons aujourd'hui est le deuxième élément fondamental du paquet législatif sur le marché européen des équipements de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3696" docOffset="30">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4344" annotation_id="3696">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3696" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the two directives function independently in theory, in practice they need one another.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="20295" annotation_id="4344">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4344" sense="Comparison.Concession">Bien qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>en théorie, les deux directives fonctionnent indépendamment l'une <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4418">de l'autre</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4430">en</DiscourseConnective> pratique, elles sont interdépendantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3793" docOffset="31">
      <en>This is another reason why the completion tomorrow of our work on the defence equipment package is so important.</en>
      <fr>C'est pour cette raison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4496">également</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4506">que</DiscourseConnective> les travaux que nous achèverons demain sur ce paquet de mesures est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4578">si</DiscourseConnective> important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3906" docOffset="32">
      <en>It will not bring a revolution in the market overnight, that is clear, <Alignment alignment="53683" annotation_id="3977">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3977" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is an important step in the right direction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4028" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it is able to move European security and defence policy substantially further forward.</en>
      <fr>Non que le marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4610">en</DiscourseConnective> sera révolutionné du jour au lendemain - nous ne nous faisons aucune illusion à ce sujet -, <Alignment alignment="424" annotation_id="4705">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4705" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est un grand pas dans la bonne direction, susceptible de faire progresser considérablement la politique européenne en matière de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4849">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4119" docOffset="33">
      <en>I would like to offer my sincere thanks to my colleagues, the shadow rapporteurs Charlotte Cederschiöld, Barbara Weiler and Gisela Kallenbach for their ever fair, sometimes critical, but always constructive cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4874">à</DiscourseConnective> adresser mes sincères remerciements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4912">à</DiscourseConnective> mes collègues, les rapporteurs fictifs Charlotte Cederschiöld, Barbara Weiler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4992">et</DiscourseConnective> Gisela Kallenbach, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5014">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur collaboration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5038">sans</DiscourseConnective> failles, parfois critique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5070">mais</DiscourseConnective> toujours constructive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4339" docOffset="34">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="5110" annotation_id="4347">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4347" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to thank the Council and the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="5894" annotation_id="5110">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5110" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remercier le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5141">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4398" docOffset="35">
      <en>Everyone involved showed a wonderful mixture of political will, professionalism and a willingness to compromise.</en>
      <fr>Tous ceux qui ont pris part à cette aventure ont fait montre d'un mélange extraordinaire de volonté politique, de professionnalisme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5291">et</DiscourseConnective> d'acceptation du compromis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4511" docOffset="36">
      <en>We all owe it to our citizens to make constructive policy for Europe together.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons élaborer ensemble une politique constructive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5379">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe dans l'intérêt de nos concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4590" docOffset="37">
      <en>I hope that we will fulfil this obligation tomorrow for our sphere of competence with the adoption of this package.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5437">que</DiscourseConnective> nous remplirons cette obligation demain dans notre sphère de compétence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5513">en</DiscourseConnective> adoptant ce paquet de mesures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4706" docOffset="38">
      <en>Incidentally, we should be having this debate in Brussels and not in Strasbourg.</en>
      <fr>J'ajouterai que nous devrions mener ce débat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5592">à</DiscourseConnective> Bruxelles, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5605">et</DiscourseConnective> non <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5612">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4787" docOffset="39">
      <en>Thank you.</en>
      <fr>Merci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4798" id="271" name="Charlie McCreevy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4798" docOffset="40">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, let me first of all apologise for the weakness of my voice, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4900" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> I have a very heavy cold.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je tiens tout d'abord à m'excuser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5722">pour</DiscourseConnective> la faible portée de ma voix, je suis très enrhumé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4929" docOffset="41">
      <en>You are about to vote on the proposal for a directive on the procurement of defence and security equipment, which the Commission tabled in December 2007 as part of the so-called 'defence package'.</en>
      <fr>Vous êtes sur le point de voter sur la proposition relative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5838">à</DiscourseConnective> une directive sur la passation de marchés publics pour l'équipement dans le domaine de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5938">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité, présentée par la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5985">en</DiscourseConnective> décembre 2007 dans le cadre du "paquet défense".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5126" docOffset="42">
      <en>This proposal is a major step forward towards the establishment of a common European defence market, which, by itself, is an important contribution to the Union's security and defence policy.</en>
      <fr>Cette proposition constitue une avancée importante vers la création d'un marché commun européen de la défense qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6152">en</DiscourseConnective> soi, représente une contribution essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6200">à</DiscourseConnective> la politique de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6226">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité de l'Union.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5318" docOffset="43">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11870" annotation_id="5318">
          <Alignment alignment="6253" annotation_id="5318">
            <Alignment alignment="6253" annotation_id="5318">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5318" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, this directive is a politically highly important instrument which will help to strengthen Europe's defence capabilities, make public spending more efficient and enhance the security of our citizens.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14199" annotation_id="6253">
          <Alignment alignment="10052" annotation_id="6253">
            <Alignment alignment="4891" annotation_id="6253">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6253" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, cette directive est un instrument d'une importance politique capitale qui permettra un renforcement des capacités de défense de l'Europe, en rendant les dépenses publiques plus efficaces <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6460">et</DiscourseConnective> en améliorant la sécurité de nos citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5533" docOffset="44">
      <en>The negotiation process for the proposal has benefited from the close cooperation between Parliament, the Council and the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Le processus de négociation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6534">pour</DiscourseConnective> la proposition a bénéficié de l'étroite coopération entre le Parlement, le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6622">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5667" docOffset="45">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6649" annotation_id="5667">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5667" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I would like to warmly thank the rapporteur, Mr Lambsdorff, for his intensive and efficient work to achieve an agreement with the Council in first reading.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <Alignment alignment="6383" annotation_id="6649">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6649" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6654">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier vivement le rapporteur, M. Lambsdorff, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6705">pour</DiscourseConnective> son travail intensif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6731">et</DiscourseConnective> efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6743">afin de</DiscourseConnective> parvenir à un accord avec le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6788">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5834" docOffset="46">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="6821" annotation_id="5842">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5842" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to thank the shadow rapporteurs for their constructive cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="6821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6821" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remercier les rapporteurs fictifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6865">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur collaboration constructive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5920" docOffset="47">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="6915" annotation_id="5922">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5922" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> want to congratulate the French presidency, together with the Slovenian presidency, for the way they successfully spurred the negotiations in Council.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite <Alignment alignment="14266" annotation_id="6915">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6915" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> féliciter la présidence française, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6956">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la présidence slovène, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6989">pour</DiscourseConnective> la façon dont ils ont encouragé les négociations au Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6078" docOffset="48">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6078" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">And</DiscourseConnective> last but not least, I would like to thank the Czech presidency for its commitment in finalising this file.</en>
      <fr>Dernier point, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7070">mais</DiscourseConnective> non le moindre, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7100">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier la présidence tchèque <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7134">pour</DiscourseConnective> son engagement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7154">à</DiscourseConnective> finaliser ce dossier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6189" docOffset="49">
      <en>The Commission welcomes the text that we have now on the table.</en>
      <fr>La Commission salue le texte actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7220">en</DiscourseConnective> cours de négociation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6253" docOffset="50">
      <en>The new directive is tailor-made for defence and security procurement.</en>
      <fr>La nouvelle directive est spécialement conçue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7291">pour</DiscourseConnective> les marchés publics en matière de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7338">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6324" docOffset="51">
      <en>It will give contracting authorities the flexibility they need to negotiate contracts which are often particularly complex and sensitive.</en>
      <fr>Elle apportera la souplesse nécessaire aux autorités contractantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7421">pour</DiscourseConnective> négocier des contrats souvent particulièrement complexes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7483">et</DiscourseConnective> sensibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6462" docOffset="52">
      <en>It will <Alignment alignment="32291" annotation_id="6470">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6470" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> allow them to ask for specific security clauses to protect classified information and ensure their security of supply.</en>
      <fr>Elle leur permettra <Alignment alignment="16495" annotation_id="7517">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7517" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de demander des clauses spécifiques liées à la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7583">afin de</DiscourseConnective> protéger les informations classifiées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7629">et</DiscourseConnective> de garantir la sécurité des approvisionnements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6594" docOffset="53">
      <en>All this makes the directive an instrument which Member States can apply to most of their defence procurement without putting at risk their security interests.</en>
      <fr>Tous ces aspects font de la directive un instrument dont les États membres peuvent se servir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7773">pour</DiscourseConnective> la plupart de leurs marchés publics de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7825">sans</DiscourseConnective> nuire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7836">à</DiscourseConnective> leurs intérêts en matière de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6754" docOffset="54">
      <en>The new directive will <Alignment alignment="7908" annotation_id="6777">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6777" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> apply to sensitive procurements in the field of non-military security.</en>
      <fr>La nouvelle directive couvrira <Alignment alignment="14282" annotation_id="7908">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7908" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les marchés publics sensibles dans le domaine de la sécurité non militaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6853" docOffset="55">
      <en>This approach is in line with today's strategic environment, in which transnational threats and new technologies have blurred the dividing line between military and non-military, internal and external security.</en>
      <fr>Cette approche est conforme à l'environnement stratégique actuel, dans lequel les menaces transnationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8100">et</DiscourseConnective> les nouvelles technologies ont estompé la séparation entre la sécurité militaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8184">et</DiscourseConnective> non militaire, intérieure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8213">et</DiscourseConnective> extérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7064" docOffset="56">
      <en>Public procurement cannot ignore these developments: in cases where equipment for police forces, <Alignment alignment="8291" annotation_id="7161">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7161" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, has features similar to those of defence equipment, it is only logical to make the same procurement rules applicable.</en>
      <fr>La passation de marchés publics ne peut ignorer ces évolutions: <Alignment alignment="20090" annotation_id="8291">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8291" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans les cas où les équipements des forces de police ont des caractéristiques semblables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8393">à</DiscourseConnective> ceux de la défense, il est tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8427">simplement</DiscourseConnective> logique de faire appliquer les mêmes règles en matière de passation de marchés publics.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7292" docOffset="57">
      <en>All this will have major advantages: the new directive will make it possible for Member States to limit the use of the derogation under Article 296 of the EC Treaty to exceptional cases.</en>
      <fr>Tous ces aspects comporteront des avantages importants: la nouvelle directive permettra aux États membres de limiter le recours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8654">à</DiscourseConnective> la dérogation au titre de l'article 296 du traité CE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8709">à</DiscourseConnective> des cas exceptionnels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7479" docOffset="58">
      <en>Hence, the principles of the internal market will, at last, apply to important parts of defence and security markets in Europe.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8734">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>, les principes du marché intérieur couvriront, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8796">enfin</DiscourseConnective>, les parties importantes des marchés de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8853">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8871">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7607" docOffset="59">
      <en>Fair and transparent procurement rules will become applicable throughout the Union and allow companies to tender more easily in other Member States.</en>
      <fr>Des règles de passation de marchés publics équitables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8936">et</DiscourseConnective> transparentes deviendront applicables dans toute l'Union <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8996">et</DiscourseConnective> permettront aux entreprises de répondre plus facilement à des appels d'offres dans d'autres États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7756" docOffset="60">
      <en>European industries will get a much larger 'home' market with longer production runs and economies of scale. This, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7871" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">in turn</DiscourseConnective>, will reduce costs and lead to lower prices.</en>
      <fr>Les industries européennes disposeront d'un marché "national" beaucoup plus vaste avec de plus longues séries de fabrications <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9232">et</DiscourseConnective> des économies d'échelle, ce qui réduira les coûts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9285">et</DiscourseConnective> entraînera une baisse des prix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7924" docOffset="61">
      <en>At the end, we will achieve greater openness of markets to the benefit of all: industries will become more competitive, armed forces will get better value for money, <Alignment alignment="9535" annotation_id="8090">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8090" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> taxpayers will benefit from more efficiency in public spending.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9320">En</DiscourseConnective> fin de comptes, nous parviendrons à une plus grande ouverture des marchés au bénéfice de tous: les industries deviendront plus concurrentielles, les forces armées bénéficieront d'un meilleur rapport qualité/prix <Alignment alignment="26773" annotation_id="9535">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9535" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la meilleure efficacité des dépenses publiques profitera aux contribuables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8158" docOffset="62">
      <en>All this is <Alignment alignment="71602" annotation_id="8170">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8170" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the fruit of your work and your input.</en>
      <fr>Tout ceci est <Alignment alignment="8170" annotation_id="9628">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9628" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le fruit de votre travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9664">et</DiscourseConnective> de votre contribution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8214" docOffset="63">
      <en>Let me <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8221" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective> once again thank you and congratulate you on this.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite vous remercier une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9726">encore</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9733">et</DiscourseConnective> vous féliciter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9751">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail accompli.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8282" id="272" language="SV" name="Charlotte Cederschiöld">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8282" docOffset="64">
      <en>Mr President, a European market in defence-related products is not created overnight, <Alignment alignment="9923" annotation_id="8368">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8368" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the rapporteur has built up confident cooperation that has helped us, together with the Council, and <Alignment alignment="10046" annotation_id="8473">
          <Alignment alignment="6589" annotation_id="8473">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8473" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the Commission, to take a first, very important step.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE-DE. - (SV) Monsieur le Président, un marché européen des produits en matière de défense ne se crée pas du jour au lendemain. <Alignment alignment="8368" annotation_id="9923">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9923" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le rapporteur a instauré une coopération basée sur la confiance, qui nous aidés, de concert avec le Conseil, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10043">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="38012" annotation_id="10046">
          <Alignment alignment="8473" annotation_id="10046">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10046" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> avec la Commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10081">à</DiscourseConnective> faire un premier pas très important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8541" docOffset="65">
      <en>Now defence-related products will be clearly incorporated within the ground rules of the internal market, which should help to lower prices.</en>
      <fr>Désormais, les produits en matière de défense vont être clairement inclus dans les règles fondamentales qui régissent le marché intérieur, ce qui devrait contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10285">à</DiscourseConnective> faire baisser les prix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8682" docOffset="66">
      <en>Along with a more open market come increased European competitiveness and more efficient equipment production.</en>
      <fr>Un marché plus ouvert est gage d'une compétitivité européenne accrue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10380">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une production d'équipements plus efficace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8793" docOffset="67">
      <en>The French Government <Alignment alignment="10461" annotation_id="8815">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8815" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> deserves praise for its constructive role, <Alignment alignment="10516" annotation_id="8863">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8863" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the rapporteur, Mr Lambsdorff, has, of course, been the most important contributor.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement français mérite <Alignment alignment="8815" annotation_id="10461">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10461" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des félicitations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10489">pour</DiscourseConnective> son rôle constructif, <Alignment alignment="36707" annotation_id="10516">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10516" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le rôle principal revient bien évidemment au rapporteur, M. Lambsdorff.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8951" docOffset="68">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="6933" annotation_id="8959">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8959" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to thank the defence industry for its valuable contribution, which has increased flexibility.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="25190" annotation_id="10605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10605" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remercier l'industrie de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10650">pour</DiscourseConnective> sa précieuse contribution, qui nous a garanti une plus grande marge de manœuvre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9063" docOffset="69">
      <en>Many elements from the 2004 Procurement Directive have been retained here.</en>
      <fr>Bon nombre d'éléments de la directive de 2004 sur la passation de marchés ont été conservés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9138" docOffset="70">
      <en>At the same time, respect is shown for national security interests and special conditions for supply and the protection of information, <Alignment alignment="10918" annotation_id="9274">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9274" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10829">Parallèlement</DiscourseConnective>, les intérêts de sécurité nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10879">et</DiscourseConnective> les conditions spéciales en matière <Alignment alignment="16195" annotation_id="10918">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10918" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">notamment</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de fourniture <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10942">et</DiscourseConnective> de protection de l'information ont été respectés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9287" docOffset="71">
      <en>Application of Article 296 is retained as per the current legislation, <Alignment alignment="15896" annotation_id="9358">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9358" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> misuse is prevented.</en>
      <fr>L'application de l'article 296 n'a pas changé par rapport à la législation actuelle, <Alignment alignment="9358" annotation_id="11080">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11080" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des dispositions sont prises pour régler les cas de non-respect.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9383" docOffset="72">
      <en>This should <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9395" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> be welcomed by the industry, which will, of course, continue to be able to influence the implementation of the directive as well as the development of new practices.</en>
      <fr>Cette mesure devrait être accueillie favorablement par l'industrie, qui conservera naturellement la possibilité d'influencer la mise en œuvre de la directive, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11309">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la mise en place de nouvelles pratiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9566" docOffset="73">
      <en>We in Parliament are pleased that the Council has met us halfway with regard to the threshold values and transparency, to name just a couple of examples of the many successes of the European Parliament, the Committee on Internal Market and Consumer Protection and the rapporteur.</en>
      <fr>Au Parlement, nous nous réjouissons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11396">du fait que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil ait accepté de nous rencontrer à mi-chemin sur la question des valeurs limites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11498">et</DiscourseConnective> de la transparence, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11521">pour</DiscourseConnective> ne citer que quelques exemples des nombreux succès remportés par le Parlement, la commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11639">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11677">et</DiscourseConnective> le rapporteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9846" docOffset="74">
      <en>I, personally, am pleased that it has been possible to resolve the most controversial issues with regard to existing EC law.</en>
      <fr>À titre personnel, je me félicite de ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11735">que</DiscourseConnective> nous ayons pu résoudre les questions les plus controversées concernant le droit européen actuellement en vigueur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9971" docOffset="75">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11853" annotation_id="9971">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9971" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Parliament, <Alignment alignment="43603" annotation_id="9986">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9986" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I hope and believe, widely supports this report, then an important and logical step forward will have been taken.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9971" annotation_id="11853">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11853" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement, <Alignment alignment="9986" annotation_id="11870">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11870" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11888">et</DiscourseConnective> le suppose, soutient ce rapport à une large majorité, nous aurons accompli un pas en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11976">avant</DiscourseConnective> important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11992">et</DiscourseConnective> logique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10103" docOffset="76">
      <en>My sincere thanks go to all my fellow Members and other stakeholders who have helped to make this a constructive and exciting process.</en>
      <fr>J'adresse tous mes remerciements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12037">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble de mes collègues députés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12076">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à toutes les autres personnes grâce auxquelles nous avons pu mener un processus constructif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12177">et</DiscourseConnective> passionnant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10238" id="273" language="DE" name="Barbara Weiler">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10238" docOffset="77">
      <en>Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, at the end of last year there were some remarkable headlines proclaiming 'the world is rearming', 'trade in weapons is booming', 'defence equipment industry - expensive through lack of competition' and other cases of corruption in Germany as well as in other countries of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12279">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, fin de l'année passée, plusieurs titres chocs ont fait la une de journaux: "Le monde en phase de réarmement", "Le commerce des armes en plein essor", "L'industrie des équipements de défense - la flambée des prix par manque de concurrence", sans compter d'autres cas de corruption <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12573">en</DiscourseConnective> Allemagne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12586">et</DiscourseConnective> dans d'autres pays de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10580" docOffset="78">
      <en>We Social Democrats are absolutely clear in our opposition to this kind of arms race, this increase in weaponry, and also the laissez-faire attitude towards corruption.</en>
      <fr>Nous, sociaux-démocrates, sommes totalement opposés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12683">à</DiscourseConnective> cette course à l'armement, à cette prolifération des armes, à cette attitude de laisser-faire face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12784">à</DiscourseConnective> la corruption.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10749" docOffset="79">
      <en>We are in agreement with our national colleagues on this issue.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12813">en</DiscourseConnective> accord avec nos collègues nationaux sur ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10813" docOffset="80">
      <en>The aims of this legislative package, with these two directives on transfer and procurement that we are discussing here today, will ensure that it is not just a matter of competitiveness, but also of putting a stop to the wasting of taxpayers' money on the production of defence equipment and of preventing corruption.</en>
      <fr>Les objectifs liés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12885">à</DiscourseConnective> ce paquet législatif, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12909">à</DiscourseConnective> ces deux directives sur les transferts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12950">et</DiscourseConnective> la passation de marché dont nous débattons aujourd'hui, permettront de ne pas se focaliser sur la compétitivité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13066">mais</DiscourseConnective> de veiller <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13082">également</DiscourseConnective> à ne plus gâcher l'argent des contribuables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13136">à</DiscourseConnective> la production d'équipements de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13177">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13180">à</DiscourseConnective> empêcher la corruption.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11132" docOffset="81">
      <en>These are good enough reasons alone for the Social Democrats to accept the result.</en>
      <fr>Il n'en faut pas plus aux sociaux-démocrates <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13251">pour</DiscourseConnective> accepter le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13268">résultat</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11215" docOffset="82">
      <en>There will be a European legal framework for awarding contracts for goods and services in the area of defence and security, there will be more cooperation between the Member States, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11397" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective> no unnecessary overlaps and no deceiving of Member States by the arms companies, <Alignment alignment="13570" annotation_id="11493">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11493" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there will be more competition overall and fewer exceptions under Article 296.</en>
      <fr>Il y aura un cadre juridique européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13316">pour</DiscourseConnective> la passation de marchés de biens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13354">et</DiscourseConnective> de services dans les domaines de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13401">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité, il y aura plus de coopération entre les États membres - c'est-à-dire pas de double emploi ni tromperie des États membres par les fabricants d'armes - <Alignment alignment="11493" annotation_id="13570">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13570" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il y aura <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13583">globalement</DiscourseConnective> plus de concurrence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13615">et</DiscourseConnective> moins d'exceptions en vertu de l'article 296.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11576" docOffset="83">
      <en>For us Members - for all groups, I believe - it was important for us to have introduced the Remedies Directive, <Alignment alignment="13769" annotation_id="11688">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11688" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the directive prepared by Mr Fruteau.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13664">Pour</DiscourseConnective> nous, les députés - de tous les partis, je pense -, l'introduction de la directive sur les recours, <Alignment alignment="9388" annotation_id="13769">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13769" sense="Expansion.Restatement">à</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> savoir la directive préparée par M. Fruteau, était une chose importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11741" docOffset="84">
      <en>For the Council, it was not at all so clear cut.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13844">Pour</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil, les choses étaient loin d'être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13892">aussi</DiscourseConnective> claires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11790" docOffset="85">
      <en>For us it was important for there to be sanctions in the event of corruption, even down to exclusion from contracts.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13907">Pour</DiscourseConnective> nous, il était important de sanctionner les auteurs de corruption, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13979">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> les exclure des procédures de passation le cas échéant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11907" docOffset="86">
      <en>I think that is something new for this industry, which has been spoilt up to now.</en>
      <fr>Je pense que cette situation est nouvelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14085">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette industrie, qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14112">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> présent, jouissait d'une position privilégiée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11989" docOffset="87">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14167" annotation_id="11989">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11989" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it was <Alignment alignment="14192" annotation_id="12005">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12005" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> important to us that the results be viable for all 27 Member States.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11989" annotation_id="14167">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14167" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous voulions <Alignment alignment="13062" annotation_id="14192">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14192" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14202">que</DiscourseConnective> les résultats soient viables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14235">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble des 27 États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12079" docOffset="88">
      <en>Even <Alignment alignment="84890" annotation_id="12084">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12084" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> only six or seven Member States have their own production <Alignment alignment="14336" annotation_id="12145">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12145" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a few less get involved in trade, it is important to have 27 States behind us. We have succeeded in that.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9535" annotation_id="14273">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14273" sense="Contingency.Condition">Même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> six <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14285">ou</DiscourseConnective> sept pays seulement ont leur propre production, <Alignment alignment="27813" annotation_id="14336">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14336" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un peu moins participent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14364">à</DiscourseConnective> ce commerce, il est important de s'assurer le soutien des 27 États membres, et nous y sommes parvenus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12255" docOffset="89">
      <en>I am not sure whether everything will work the way we imagine it will <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12325" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="14531" annotation_id="12329">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12329" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have incorporated the fact that Parliament wishes to continue to have a certain amount of control.</en>
      <fr>Je ne sais pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14484">si</DiscourseConnective> tout se passera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14503">comme</DiscourseConnective> nous l'avons imaginé; <Alignment alignment="10337" annotation_id="14531">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14531" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons inclus le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14572">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement souhaite continuer d'exercer un certain contrôle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12441" docOffset="90">
      <en>We want to be informed, not just automatically by the Commission, <Alignment alignment="74173" annotation_id="12507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12507" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want to be informed of the results and about the transposition of this package of directives.</en>
      <fr>Nous voulons être informés, et pas uniquement de manière automatique par la Commission, <Alignment alignment="18003" annotation_id="14727">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14727" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14732">également</DiscourseConnective> des résultats obtenus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14764">et</DiscourseConnective> de la transposition de ce paquet de directives.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12608" docOffset="91">
      <en>In future, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12619" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> we will have an even stronger European internal market and will gain European powers, <Alignment alignment="84031" annotation_id="12710">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12710" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Mr Sarkozy has of course planned, then the European Parliament <Alignment alignment="15018" annotation_id="12776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12776" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an elected institution in Europe must be involved in genuine control, a control that we have in the national parliaments, but do not yet have in the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Lorsque, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14824">plus tard</DiscourseConnective>, le marché intérieur européen sera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14869">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus solidement établi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14899">et</DiscourseConnective> que nous acquerrons des compétences européennes, <Alignment alignment="13178" annotation_id="14951">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14951" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'a naturellement prévu M. Sarkozy, le Parlement européen en <Alignment alignment="14716" annotation_id="15018">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15018" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>institution élue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15043">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe devra jouer un authentique rôle de contrôle, rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15103">que</DiscourseConnective> nous jouons d'ores et déjà au sein des parlements nationaux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15168">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15177">encore</DiscourseConnective> au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12949" docOffset="92">
      <en>This, <Alignment alignment="15225" annotation_id="12955">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12955" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, is a task for the future.</en>
      <fr>Cette tâche n'est <Alignment alignment="14310" annotation_id="15225">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15225" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas encore <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15246">pour</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15251">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12990" docOffset="93">
      <en>In Germany, <Alignment alignment="15277" annotation_id="13002">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13002" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we have got our fingers burnt with the production of defence equipment and increased prices.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15263">En</DiscourseConnective> Allemagne, <Alignment alignment="10763" annotation_id="15277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15277" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous nous sommes brûlés les doigts avec la production des équipements de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15371">et</DiscourseConnective> avec la hausse des prix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13108" docOffset="94">
      <en>We have the Eurofighter - an excessively expensive, if not the most expensive, project - <Alignment alignment="100022" annotation_id="13197">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13197" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am sure that every Member State has similar experiences.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons l'Eurofighter - un projet extrêmement coûteux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15457">si</DiscourseConnective> pas le plus coûteux - <Alignment alignment="16735" annotation_id="15482">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15482" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis certaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15502">que</DiscourseConnective> tous les États membres peuvent rendre compte d'expériences similaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13260" docOffset="95">
      <en>Finally, I do not wish to express my thanks.</en>
      <fr>Je ne terminerai pas par des remerciements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13305" docOffset="96">
      <en>The cooperation was quite constructive <Alignment alignment="15668" annotation_id="13344">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13344" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the results are, above all, significant.</en>
      <fr>La coopération a été relativement constructive <Alignment alignment="21927" annotation_id="15668">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15668" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15672">surtout</DiscourseConnective>, les résultats sont notables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13389" docOffset="97">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="15710" annotation_id="13389">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13389" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I would like to say quite openly that the parliamentary procedure was intolerable.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="24781" annotation_id="15710">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15710" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> en toute franchise, la procédure parlementaire était intolérable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13481" docOffset="98">
      <en>Reaching compromises with the Council and the Commission at first reading simply should not be the work of this House.</en>
      <fr>Ce Parlement ne devrait pas avoir à se soucier de dégager des compromis avec le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15869">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15886">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13600" docOffset="99">
      <en>For this reason, this procedure must only be an absolute exception in future.</en>
      <fr>Cette procédure doit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15928">donc</DiscourseConnective> être l'exception absolue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15958">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13678" docOffset="100">
      <en>It was not, <Alignment alignment="20204" annotation_id="13690">
          <Alignment alignment="17198" annotation_id="13690">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13690" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, necessary for this legislative package.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="30818" annotation_id="15970">
          <Alignment alignment="33313" annotation_id="15970">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15970" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En réalité</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, elle n'était pas nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16010">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce paquet législatif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13739" docOffset="101">
      <en>We should stick to our guns and, immediately after the vote, do away with this type of procedure for non-parliamentary work.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne devons pas céder de terrain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16073">et</DiscourseConnective>, dès la fin du vote, nous devons supprimer ce type de procédure adaptée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16148">à</DiscourseConnective> des travaux non parlementaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13864" id="274" name="Cristian Silviu Buşoi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13864" docOffset="102">
      <en>on behalf of the ALDE Group. - Mr President, I wish to begin by congratulating my colleague, Mr Lambsdorff, on his excellent report.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe ALDE. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16244">à</DiscourseConnective> commencer par féliciter mon collègue, M. Lambsdorff, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16299">pour</DiscourseConnective> son excellent rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13997" docOffset="103">
      <en>I know he dedicated himself to this very important work.</en>
      <fr>Je sais combien il s'est engagé dans ce travail très important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14054" docOffset="104">
      <en>I consider it vital to create a common arms market and to establish a legal framework for this in order to further develop the European security and defence policy (ESDP).</en>
      <fr>J'estime qu'il est capital de créer un marché commun de l'armement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16458">et</DiscourseConnective> d'établir un cadre juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16490">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16501">pour</DiscourseConnective> continuer de développer la politique européenne de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16566">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense (PESD).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14226" docOffset="105">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="16597" annotation_id="14228">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14228" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcome the important achievement that the principles of the Treaty, in particular transparency, non-discrimination and openness, will <Alignment alignment="16721" annotation_id="14368">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14368" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be implemented in the defence and security market <Alignment alignment="16796" annotation_id="14423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14423" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, as has already been said, this will result in an improvement of the efficiency of defence spending.</en>
      <fr>Je salue <Alignment alignment="49" annotation_id="16597">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16597" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16615">que</DiscourseConnective> les principes du traité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16644">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> la transparence, la non-discrimination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16698">et</DiscourseConnective> l'ouverture, seront <Alignment alignment="24901" annotation_id="16721">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16721" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mis en œuvre dans le cadre du marché de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16778">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité <Alignment alignment="18741" annotation_id="16796">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16796" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16800">comme</DiscourseConnective> mentionné précédemment, que cette avancée considérable permettra d'améliorer l'efficacité des dépenses en matière de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14528" docOffset="106">
      <en>The Commission's proposal, as well as Mr Lambsdorff's report, managed to establish a set of rules concerning procurement contracts in the field of security and defence, which allow the proper functioning of the common arms market.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de la Commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16965">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que le rapport de M. Lambsdorff, ont permis de fixer une série de règles relatives aux marchés publics dans le domaine de la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17105">et</DiscourseConnective> de la défense, ce qui contribue au bon fonctionnement du marché commun de l'armement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14759" docOffset="107">
      <en>I want to refer to at least two major improvements for both suppliers and the contracting authorities which aim to protect the security of the EU and its Member States.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17203">à</DiscourseConnective> citer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17211">au moins</DiscourseConnective> deux améliorations importantes, non seulement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17266">pour</DiscourseConnective> les fournisseurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17289">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> pour les autorités contractantes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17334">afin de</DiscourseConnective> protéger la sécurité de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17371">et</DiscourseConnective> de ses États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14928" docOffset="108">
      <en>I would mention here the provisions relating to the security of supply, namely information about tenderers and subcontractors provided to the contracting authorities <Alignment alignment="17594" annotation_id="15094">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15094" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the commitments tenderers have to make to ensure security of supply.</en>
      <fr>Je citerais ici les dispositions relatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17439">à</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité de l'approvisionnement, à savoir les informations concernant les soumissionnaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17535">et</DiscourseConnective> les sous-traitants fournies aux autorités contractantes <Alignment alignment="8706" annotation_id="17594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17594" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que les engagements des soumissionnaires afin d'assurer la sécurité de l'approvisionnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15167" docOffset="109">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17692" annotation_id="15167">
          <Alignment alignment="17692" annotation_id="15167">
            <Alignment alignment="17692" annotation_id="15167">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15167" sense="Comparison.Contrast">On the other hand</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, tenderers are <Alignment alignment="17732" annotation_id="15200">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15200" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> protected by the introduction of the review procedure, which guarantees the awarding process is fair <Alignment alignment="17857" annotation_id="15306">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15306" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> no discrimination occurs.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="15167" annotation_id="17692">
          <Alignment alignment="42051" annotation_id="17692">
            <Alignment alignment="30100" annotation_id="17692">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17692" sense="Comparison.Contrast">D'autre part</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, les soumissionnaires sont <Alignment alignment="3939" annotation_id="17732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17732" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> protégés par l'introduction de la procédure de révision, qui garantit que le processus d'attribution est équitable <Alignment alignment="7034" annotation_id="17857">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17857" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> non discriminatoire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15336" docOffset="110">
      <en>The proposal increases the transparency in the work procedure, <Alignment alignment="17948" annotation_id="15399">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15399" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Member States should not at all be reluctant to it <Alignment alignment="18011" annotation_id="15454">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15454" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> their security interests are safeguarded, especially by maintaining the derogations from the disclosure of information <Alignment alignment="18167" annotation_id="15576">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15576" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> security interests are at stake.</en>
      <fr>La proposition accroît la transparence de la procédure de travail, <Alignment alignment="39824" annotation_id="17948">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17948" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les États membres de doivent pas tous y être réfractaires <Alignment alignment="1792" annotation_id="18011">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18011" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">dans la mesure où</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leurs intérêts en matière de sécurité sont sauvegardés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18085">notamment en</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18098">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> les dérogations relatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18135">à</DiscourseConnective> la divulgation d'informations <Alignment alignment="4927" annotation_id="18167">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18167" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les intérêts de sécurité sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18203">en</DiscourseConnective> jeu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15614" docOffset="111">
      <en>In conclusion, I should like to emphasise the fact that it is very important for us to have a common European market for defence.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18211">Pour conclure</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais insister sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18259">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est très important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18284">pour</DiscourseConnective> nous d'avoir un marché commun de la défense en Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15744" docOffset="112">
      <en>At the same time, <Alignment alignment="13931" annotation_id="15762">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15762" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are discussing this issue - the common European defence market - <Alignment alignment="18444" annotation_id="15835">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15835" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> perhaps <Alignment alignment="18457" annotation_id="15846">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15846" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we discuss more sensitive issues like offsets in the future, we should seriously take into consideration the strategic interests and the concrete situation of each and every Member State.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18344">Parallèlement</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="15762" annotation_id="18359">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18359" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous débattrons de cette question - le marché commun de la défense en Europe - <Alignment alignment="42291" annotation_id="18444">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18444" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> peut-être <Alignment alignment="8209" annotation_id="18457">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18457" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous abordons des questions plus sensibles telles que les compensations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18532">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir, nous devrons sérieusement tenir compte des intérêts stratégiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18609">et</DiscourseConnective> de la situation concrète de chaque État membre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16037" id="275" language="PL" name="Mieczysław Edmund Janowski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16037" docOffset="113">
      <en>Mr President, Commissioner, Mr Lambsdorff has done an excellent job.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe UEN. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, M. Lambsdorff a réalisé un excellent travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16106" docOffset="114">
      <en>Congratulations.</en>
      <fr>Félicitations!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16123" docOffset="115">
      <en>The spending of public money has always stirred up strong feelings.</en>
      <fr>L'utilisation des fonds publics a toujours déchaîné les passions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16191" docOffset="116">
      <en>This is especially true in the case of procurement for the army or defence forces.</en>
      <fr>C'est particulièrement vrai dans le cas de la passation de marchés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18931">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'armée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18944">ou</DiscourseConnective> les forces de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16274" docOffset="117">
      <en>Large sums of money are involved <Alignment alignment="19006" annotation_id="16307">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16307" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we need to select manufacturers and service-providers who provide the best service, rather than the cheapest solution.</en>
      <fr>Des sommes phénoménales sont en jeu <Alignment alignment="5318" annotation_id="19006">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19006" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devons sélectionner les fabricants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19049">et</DiscourseConnective> fournisseurs de services qui proposent les meilleurs services, et non choisir la solution la moins onéreuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16430" docOffset="118">
      <en>We need high quality at a reasonable price.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons opter pour la qualité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19195">à</DiscourseConnective> un prix raisonnable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16474" docOffset="119">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="19230" annotation_id="16477">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16477" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have to consider how thorough all the work will be and the quality of the materials used, as well as specific issues such as confidentiality, even secrecy, especially in relation to crucial issues.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="30843" annotation_id="19230">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19230" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> déterminer le degré de précision du travail réalisé, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19293">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la qualité des matériaux utilisés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19338">de même que</DiscourseConnective> certains point spécifiques tels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19382">que</DiscourseConnective> la confidentialité, voire le secret, tout particulièrement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19445">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les aspects cruciaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16680" docOffset="120">
      <en>These matters are <Alignment alignment="6954" annotation_id="16698">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16698" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> linked to the issues of offsetting and ensuring a return on investment.</en>
      <fr>Ces questions sont <Alignment alignment="23881" annotation_id="19505">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19505" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> liées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19524">à</DiscourseConnective> celles d'amortissement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19549">et</DiscourseConnective> de retour sur investissement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16775" docOffset="121">
      <en>I think that we will have to return to this subject.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19591">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devrons revenir sur ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16828" docOffset="122">
      <en>I believe that the position presented in the proposal for a directive is correct.</en>
      <fr>De mon point de vue, la position présentée dans la proposition de directive est correcte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16910" docOffset="123">
      <en>In my opinion, the proposed solutions will increase the efficiency of the European public tender system in the field of defence.</en>
      <fr>Je pense que les solutions proposées permettront d'améliorer le système d'adjudication européen dans le domaine de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17039" docOffset="124">
      <en>They deserve our acceptance.</en>
      <fr>Elles méritent d'être soutenues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17068" id="276" language="DE" name="Gisela Kallenbach">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17068" docOffset="125">
      <en>Mr President, I would like to thank the rapporteur for his constructive cooperation, because for all the justified criticism of the procedure at first reading, this cooperation was in actual fact the prerequisite for the voice of Parliament clearly being heard in the trialogue.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe des Verts/ALE. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19951">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier le rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19977">pour</DiscourseConnective> sa coopération constructive, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20011">car</DiscourseConnective>, en dépit de toutes les critiques légitimes formulées à l'encontre de la procédure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20098">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture, cette coopération était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20143">en réalité</DiscourseConnective> indispensable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20168">pour</DiscourseConnective> permettre au Parlement de faire entendre sa voix au sein du trilogue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17347" docOffset="126">
      <en>We are deciding today on a compromise with regard to an object of trade, the previous market for which was limited to just a few Member States.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons parvenir aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20276">à</DiscourseConnective> un compromis sur un article de commerce, dont le marché était précédemment limité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20360">à</DiscourseConnective> quelques États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17491" docOffset="127">
      <en>It has been a really interesting experience for me just to see fundamental advocates of the internal market and competition suddenly pulling out all the stops to continue to be able to utilise national decision-making and isolation mechanisms.</en>
      <fr>J'ai trouvé particulièrement intéressant de voir de fervents défenseurs du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20478">et</DiscourseConnective> de la concurrence freiner soudainement des quatre fers pour pouvoir continuer d'utiliser les mécanismes décisionnels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20598">et</DiscourseConnective> isolationnistes nationaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17735" docOffset="128">
      <en>They did not succeed <Alignment alignment="20647" annotation_id="17756">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17756" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is a good thing.</en>
      <fr>En vain toutefois, <Alignment alignment="8845" annotation_id="20647">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20647" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est une bonne chose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17782" docOffset="129">
      <en>Why was that?</en>
      <fr>Pour quelle raison?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17796" docOffset="130">
      <en>It was <Alignment alignment="20693" annotation_id="17803">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17803" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> more competition in the trade in defence equipment will hopefully in future result in a move away from the dictation of prices and in the chance that the public money designated for this purpose will be reduced and used more efficiently.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19398" annotation_id="20693">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20693" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>une concurrence accrue sur le marché des équipements de défense permettra ultérieurement, espérons-le, d'échapper au système de fixation des prix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20848">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20854">que</DiscourseConnective> de réduire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20869">et</DiscourseConnective> d'utiliser plus efficacement les deniers publics destinés à cette fin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18049" docOffset="131">
      <en>The same goes for reducing corruption. We owe this to our citizens.</en>
      <fr>Il en va <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20952">de même</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20960">pour</DiscourseConnective> la lutte contre la corruption, que nous devons mener dans l'intérêt de nos concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18117" docOffset="132">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="65805" annotation_id="18123">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18123" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> clear that unambiguous tendering conditions will now apply, which will lead to greater transparency in connection with the awarding of contracts and will at last <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18290" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> give SMEs a real chance of entering the market.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="18123" annotation_id="21060">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21060" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> évident <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21077">que</DiscourseConnective> des conditions de passation de marchés claires s'appliqueront désormais, garantissant une transparence accrue de la procédure de passation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21220">et</DiscourseConnective> offrant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21231">enfin</DiscourseConnective> une réelle possibilité aux PME d'intégrer le marché.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18343" docOffset="133">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21290" annotation_id="18343">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18343" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, all conceivable loopholes for avoiding the tendering process have <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18419" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> been reduced, <Alignment alignment="21405" annotation_id="18438">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18438" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> any envisaged deviations must be agreed in advance with the Commission.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11013" annotation_id="21290">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21290" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, tous les vides juridiques imaginables permettant de contourner la procédure de passation ont été réduits <Alignment alignment="18438" annotation_id="21405">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21405" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> toute déviation envisagée doit faire l'objet d'une approbation préalable de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18514" docOffset="134">
      <en>The bartering which up to now has <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18548" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">indeed</DiscourseConnective> been prohibited under law but has <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18589" sense="Comparison.Contrast">nevertheless</DiscourseConnective> been common practice has not been legalised by this directive.</en>
      <fr>Le troc, jusque là interdit par la loi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21538">mais</DiscourseConnective> monnaie courante dans la pratique, n'a pas été légalisé par cette directive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18665" docOffset="135">
      <en>Last but not least, legal remedy can now be utilised for the first time.</en>
      <fr>Dernière chose, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21636">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas des moindres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21659">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois, des voies de recours sont disponibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18738" docOffset="136">
      <en>I had hoped that we would Europeanise it further, reduce the threshold values and so gain greater transparency, <Alignment alignment="21867" annotation_id="18850">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18850" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is a major step in the right direction <Alignment alignment="16665" annotation_id="18898">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18898" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am looking forward to its transposition.</en>
      <fr>J'avais espéré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21736">que</DiscourseConnective> nous parviendrions à européaniser davantage le processus, à diminuer les valeurs seuils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21828">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21831">à</DiscourseConnective> gagner davantage en transparence, <Alignment alignment="18850" annotation_id="21867">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21867" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons malgré tout accompli un grand pas dans la bonne direction, <Alignment alignment="3639" annotation_id="21942">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21942" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'attends avec impatience sa transposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18945" id="277" language="DE" name="Tobias Pflüger">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18945" docOffset="137">
      <en>Mr President, this directive is part of the defence package, the context of which is, and I quote, 'the strategy for a stronger and more competitive European defence industry'. The principal guideline, as with so many things, is the free market for defence-related products too, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19224" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective> weapons, and weapons are for killing and waging war.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, cette directive fait partie du paquet sur la défense, qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22103">s'</DiscourseConnective>inscrit dans le cadre - je cite - de la "Stratégie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22156">pour</DiscourseConnective> une industrie européenne de la défense plus forte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22211">et</DiscourseConnective> plus compétitive", dont la ligne directrice est, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22263">comme pour</DiscourseConnective> tant d'autres choses, le libre-échange de produits en matière de défense, c'est-à-dire d'armes - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22371">et</DiscourseConnective> les armes servent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22392">à</DiscourseConnective> tuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22399">et</DiscourseConnective> faire la guerre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19292" docOffset="138">
      <en>The aim of the directive is to improve the efficiency and competitiveness of the arms industry in the EU.</en>
      <fr>La directive vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22437">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer l'efficacité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22462">et</DiscourseConnective> la compétitivité de l'industrie de l'armement dans l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19398" docOffset="139">
      <en>Mr Swoboda spoke plainly in the previous debate.</en>
      <fr>M. Swoboda a parlé sans fioriture lors du débat précédent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19447" docOffset="140">
      <en>He said that we need better initial conditions for the European arms industry in view of the competition, in particular from the United States.</en>
      <fr>Il a souligné <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22595">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avions besoin de meilleures conditions initiales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22653">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie européenne de l'armement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22695">afin de</DiscourseConnective> renforcer sa compétitivité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22731">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> vis-à-vis des États-Unis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19591" docOffset="141">
      <en>In 2005, the EU Member States jointly became for the first time the top arms exporter in the world.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22772">En</DiscourseConnective> 2005, les États membres de l'UE combinés sont devenus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22829">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois le premier exportateur d'armes au monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19691" docOffset="142">
      <en>Of these exports, 70% come from the four large nations of France, Germany, the United Kingdom and Italy.</en>
      <fr>De ces exportations, 70 % sont le fait des quatre grands pays que sont la France, l'Allemagne, le Royaume-Uni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23002">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Italie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19796" docOffset="143">
      <en>The main importer states are those of the Middle East.</en>
      <fr>Les principaux importateurs sont les États du Moyen-Orient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19851" docOffset="144">
      <en>Our concern should not be for a more efficient arms industry, but rather for disarmament, <Alignment alignment="57244" annotation_id="19941">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19941" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> unlike the efficiency of the arms industry, for this there is no directive.</en>
      <fr>Notre objectif devrait être, non pas un renforcement de notre industrie de l'armement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23162">mais</DiscourseConnective> le désarmement; <Alignment alignment="816" annotation_id="23183">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23183" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> s'il existe une directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23212">pour</DiscourseConnective> le renforcement de cette industrie, ce n'est pas le cas concernant le désarmement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20021" docOffset="145">
      <en>It is very clear what this is really all about.</en>
      <fr>Cela ne laisse aucun doute sur le véritable but poursuivi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20069" id="278" name="Andreas Schwab">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20069" docOffset="146">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20118" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> like to express my sincere thanks to the rapporteur from the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, but also to the Subcommittee on Security and Defence and its chairman and draftsman of the opinion on the Lambsdorff report, my friend Karl von Wogau.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23396">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23419">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier sincèrement le rapporteur de la commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23494">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection des consommateurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23533">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23538">également</DiscourseConnective> la sous-commission de la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23582">et</DiscourseConnective> de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23599">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que son président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23623">et</DiscourseConnective> rapporteur pour avis sur le rapport de M. Lambsdorff, mon ami Karl von Wogau.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20393" docOffset="147">
      <en>We are not talking here about the export of weapons to states outside the European internal market, only about the issue of how the sale and trade in weapons within the European internal market, that is in the 27 Member States of the European Union, can be made more cost-effective and more efficient.</en>
      <fr>Le débat de ce jour ne traite pas de l'exportation d'armes vers les États qui n'appartiennent pas au marché intérieur européen, mais uniquement de la façon dont nous pouvons améliorer la rentabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23903">et</DiscourseConnective> le rendement de la vente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23931">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'échange d'armes au sein même du marché intérieur, c'est-à-dire dans les 27 États membres de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20695" docOffset="148">
      <en>I very much welcome the fact that Parliament has taken up a common position here, <Alignment alignment="24135" annotation_id="20777">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20777" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20786" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">as a result</DiscourseConnective>, citizens will ultimately make considerable savings in a market of around EUR 70 billion per year, and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20901" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective> can in some way be paid a peace dividend.</en>
      <fr>Je suis très heureux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24072">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement ait adopté une position commune sur ce point, <Alignment alignment="39222" annotation_id="24135">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24135" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela permettra aux citoyens de réaliser des économies considérables dans un marché qui pèse quelque 70 milliards d'euros par an <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24273">et</DiscourseConnective> leur vaudra <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24288">en</DiscourseConnective> quelque sorte un dividende "Paix".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20953" docOffset="149">
      <en>This work and - it is a little disappointing that so few representatives of the Council are here today - this decision are extremely welcome in the light of an extremely difficult discussion between the Member States in the past.</en>
      <fr>Ce travail - il est dommage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24354">que</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24369">soit</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24374">si</DiscourseConnective> peu représenté aujourd'hui -, cette décision tombe à point nommé au vu des discussions extrêmement houleuses qui ont eu lieu entre les États membres par le passé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21183" docOffset="150">
      <en>As much as I agree with the opinion about the difficulties experienced in the trialogue, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21272" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> expressed by the Social Democrats, I have to say that one day we will achieve a milestone in European defence policy with this.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24540">Si</DiscourseConnective> je partage l'avis exprimé par les sociaux-démocrates concernant les difficultés rencontrées dans le cadre du trilogue, je me dois d'affirmer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24684">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24687">un jour</DiscourseConnective>, le travail que nous effectuons aujourd'hui permettra une réelle avancée dans la politique européenne de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21403" docOffset="151">
      <en>I am even more disappointed that so few fellow Members wish to be present for this decision.</en>
      <fr>Je suis d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24819">autant</DiscourseConnective> plus déçu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24836">que si</DiscourseConnective> peu de députés veuillent être présents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24882">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette décision.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21496" docOffset="152">
      <en>This morning we celebrated 10 years of the euro.</en>
      <fr>Ce matin, nous avons célébré le dixième anniversaire de l'euro.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21545" docOffset="153">
      <en>I hope that in a few years we will <Alignment alignment="25021" annotation_id="21580">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21580" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> look back on today, <Alignment alignment="25054" annotation_id="21605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21605" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is a milestone in European cooperation between Member States in the area of defence and of foreign and security policy, <Alignment alignment="17419" annotation_id="21733">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21733" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in future it will, in principle, be the case that whatever requirements we set in our own Member State, the same will <Alignment alignment="25322" annotation_id="21859">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21859" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> apply automatically in all the other Member States.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24976">que</DiscourseConnective>, d'ici quelques années, nous célèbrerons <Alignment alignment="34554" annotation_id="25021">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25021" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la date d'aujourd'hui, <Alignment alignment="35240" annotation_id="25054">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25054" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25066">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25075">un jour</DiscourseConnective> charnière dans la coopération européenne entre les États membres dans le domaine de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25178">et</DiscourseConnective> de la politique étrangère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25207">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité, <Alignment alignment="21733" annotation_id="25223">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25223" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>à l'avenir, toute exigence que nous mettrons en place dans notre État membre s'appliquera <Alignment alignment="21859" annotation_id="25322">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25322" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> automatiquement dans tous les autres États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21916" docOffset="154">
      <en>This involves a large credit of trust that the Member States have now become willing to give.</en>
      <fr>Cela demande une grande confiance, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25419">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres sont à présent disposés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25465">à</DiscourseConnective> donner.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22010" docOffset="155">
      <en>For this I am particularly grateful.</en>
      <fr>Et je leur en suis particulièrement reconnaissant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22047" docOffset="156">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22047" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>, I would <Alignment alignment="25538" annotation_id="22064">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22064" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to thank the Commission, which has worked with much vigour on this directive, which has overcome the opposition in the Member States <Alignment alignment="25700" annotation_id="22207">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22207" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which has tried constructively to help Parliament to find a way through the tangled undergrowth of public procurement law.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="14319" annotation_id="25538">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25538" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remercier la Commission, qui a travaillé avec beaucoup d'acharnement sur cette directive, qui a surmonté l'opposition rencontrée dans les États membres <Alignment alignment="41735" annotation_id="25700">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25700" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui s'est efforcée d'aider de manière constructive le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25767">à</DiscourseConnective> se sortir des arcanes du droit sur les marchés publics.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22334" docOffset="157">
      <en>The positive points have already been mentioned, including the improvements that will be made to procurement law <Alignment alignment="25940" annotation_id="22447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22447" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I do not wish to repeat these.</en>
      <fr>Les points positifs ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25849">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été mentionnés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25870">notamment</DiscourseConnective> les améliorations qui seront apportées à cette législation, <Alignment alignment="16668" annotation_id="25940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25940" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je ne les répéterai pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22482" docOffset="158">
      <en>With the second part of the package for creating this genuine European internal market for defence-related products we have indeed come another important mile along the road.</en>
      <fr>Grâce au deuxième volet du paquet destiné à la création effective de ce marché intérieur européen pour les produits en matière de défense, nous avons assurément posé un autre jalon important dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22657" docOffset="159">
      <en>This <Alignment alignment="26190" annotation_id="22662">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22662" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> strengthens the autonomous ability of the European Union to respond to international crises, work to which Mr von Wogau has devoted himself in particular in the Subcommittee on Security and Defence.</en>
      <fr>Cela renforce <Alignment alignment="22662" annotation_id="26190">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26190" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la capacité autonome de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26243">à</DiscourseConnective> répondre aux crises internationales, une tâche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26292">à</DiscourseConnective> laquelle s'est consacré M. von Wogau, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26332">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> au sein de la sous-commission de la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26392">et</DiscourseConnective> de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22866" docOffset="160">
      <en>If then, <Alignment alignment="20022" annotation_id="22875">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22875" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> recently described, an autonomous operation of the European Union in Africa under the leadership of an Irish General with a Polish deputy and troops comprising members from 15 different Member States is possible, then it shows how far the European Union has come in building a Europe of Defence.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26410">Si</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="33874" annotation_id="26414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26414" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mentionné plus tôt, il est possible de mettre en place une opération autonome de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26520">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique sous le commandement d'un général irlandais assisté d'un Polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26597">et</DiscourseConnective> à la tête d'une armée composée de membres issus de quinze États membres différents, cela montre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26696">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne a bien progressé dans l'instauration d'une Europe de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23174" docOffset="161">
      <en>We need to go further along this road.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons continuer sur cette voie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23213" docOffset="162">
      <en>Thank you very much.</en>
      <fr>Merci beaucoup.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="23234" id="279" name="Joel Hasse Ferreira">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="23234" docOffset="163">
      <en>(PT) Mr President, firstly I would like to acknowledge the rapporteur, Mr Lambsdorff, and the shadow rapporteurs, particularly Mrs Weiler.</en>
      <fr>(PT) Monsieur le Président, je souhaiterais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26882">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout saluer le travail du rapporteur M. Lambsdorff <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26939">et</DiscourseConnective> des rapporteurs fictifs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26967">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> Mme Weiler.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23373" docOffset="164">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I believe it to be essential that we move towards integration of national defence markets and even strategic coordination of their production.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27003">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27024">à</DiscourseConnective> mes yeux essentiel d'œuvrer à l'intégration des marchés nationaux de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27106">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27109">à</DiscourseConnective> la coordination stratégique de leur production.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23538" docOffset="165">
      <en>We must move forward, with all the necessary specificities and precautions, towards applying the basic rules of the internal market to the defence industries, increasing transparency in the tendering processes that are organised and the contracts that are awarded involving Member States of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons progresser, avec toutes les spécificités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27212">et</DiscourseConnective> précautions requises, vers l'application des règles fondamentales du marché intérieur aux industries de la défense, vers une transparence accrue dans les procédures d'adjudication <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27395">et</DiscourseConnective> les marchés impliquant des États membres de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23849" docOffset="166">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23849" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>, at the same time we must help to create the conditions that will make European equipment and products more competitive in world markets.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27462">Parallèlement</DiscourseConnective>, nous devons également contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27510">à</DiscourseConnective> créer les conditions nécessaires pour améliorer la compétitivité des équipements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27593">et</DiscourseConnective> produits européens sur les marchés mondiaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23995" docOffset="167">
      <en>It seems important to me, Commissioner McCreevy, that this directive be able to guarantee improvements in the legal framework for public contracts in the fields of defence and security.</en>
      <fr>Il me paraît important, Monsieur le Commissaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27690">que</DiscourseConnective> cette directive puisse garantir la mise en place d'un meilleur cadre juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27773">pour</DiscourseConnective> la passation de marchés publics dans les domaines de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27842">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24181" docOffset="168">
      <en>It must further the construction of the internal market <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24237" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">while</DiscourseConnective>, obviously, respecting the rights and interests of Member States, especially in the field of security; I refer specifically to those that manufacture arms, munitions and defence and security equipment, such as my own country, <Alignment alignment="28181" annotation_id="24469">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24469" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</en>
      <fr>Elle doit promouvoir la construction du marché intérieur tout en respectant, il va de soi, les droits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27963">et</DiscourseConnective> les intérêts des États membres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27998">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> dans le domaine de la sécurité. Je pense plus spécifiquement aux constructeurs d'armes, de munitions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28114">et</DiscourseConnective> d'équipements de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28142">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28158">comme</DiscourseConnective> mon propre pays, <Alignment alignment="3477" annotation_id="28181">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28181" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24482" docOffset="169">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="39656" annotation_id="24490">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24490" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Mr President, highlight the provisions that allow easier access to this market for small and medium-sized enterprises, specifically by improving the rules for subcontracting.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi <Alignment alignment="38265" annotation_id="28208">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28208" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Monsieur le Président, de mettre l'accent sur les dispositions garantissant un accès facilité des PME <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28321">à</DiscourseConnective> ce marché, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28334">notamment en</DiscourseConnective> améliorant les règles de sous-traitance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24671" docOffset="170">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="28403" annotation_id="24673">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24673" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> emphasise the prospect of making a greater and more profound impact on the industrial fabric, in order to create a true European market in the defence industries.</en>
      <fr>Je soulignerai <Alignment alignment="20684" annotation_id="28403">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28403" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la perspective de modifier plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28445">en</DiscourseConnective> profondeur le réseau industriel, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28481">afin de</DiscourseConnective> créer un véritable marché européen de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24841" docOffset="171">
      <en>That may <Alignment alignment="47352" annotation_id="24850">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24850" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> contribute to strengthening research and development, not just within these industries, but also in a section of European industry that feeds off their development.</en>
      <fr>Cela peut <Alignment alignment="24850" annotation_id="28549">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28549" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28566">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28591">et</DiscourseConnective> le développement, et pas uniquement dans ces industries, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28651">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28656">également</DiscourseConnective> dans une section de l'industrie européenne qui favorise leur développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25020" docOffset="172">
      <en>In conclusion, I believe reference could be made to the obvious link between the defence industries and the foreign policies of the Union.</en>
      <fr>Je conclurai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28755">en</DiscourseConnective> évoquant le lien évident qui existe entre les industries de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28829">et</DiscourseConnective> les politiques étrangères de l'Union.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25159" docOffset="173">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28870" annotation_id="25159">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25159" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in response to a recent speech, I would like to quote a classical Roman saying: 'if you want peace, prepare for war'.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12418" annotation_id="28870">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28870" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28881">en</DiscourseConnective> réponse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28892">à</DiscourseConnective> une intervention récente, je citerai un Romain de l'ère classique, qui a dit: "Qui veut la paix, prépare la guerre."</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25286" docOffset="174">
      <en>In the European Union, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25309" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> it is almost a pacifist superpower, we call these industries 'defence industries' and not 'war industries' <Alignment alignment="29166" annotation_id="25419">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25419" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want peace, not war.</en>
      <fr>Dans l'Union européenne, qui est pratiquement une super-puissance pacifique, nous parlons d'"industries de la défense" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29130">et</DiscourseConnective> non d'"industries de la guerre", <Alignment alignment="10819" annotation_id="29166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29166" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons la paix, pas la guerre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25451" docOffset="175">
      <en>That is <Alignment alignment="3969" annotation_id="25459">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25459" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> why we need defence industries.</en>
      <fr>C'est <Alignment alignment="32497" annotation_id="29219">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29219" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la raison pour laquelle nous avons besoin d'industries de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="25496" id="280" name="Janusz Onyszkiewicz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="25496" docOffset="176">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, the United States spends around USD 500 billion on defence. The European Union spends a little over 200 billion on the same.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, les États-Unis dépensent quelque 500 milliards de dollars <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29381">pour</DiscourseConnective> la défense, alors que l'Union européenne dépense un peu plus de 200 milliards dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25640" docOffset="177">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="29494" annotation_id="25640">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25640" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the question is whether, in return for this 200 billion, the military capabilities of the European Union Member States really reflect that investment, <Alignment alignment="29628" annotation_id="25800">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25800" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> is the case in the United States.</en>
      <fr>La question, <Alignment alignment="12409" annotation_id="29494">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29494" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, est de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29519">si</DiscourseConnective> les capacités militaires des États membres de l'Union européenne reflètent réellement cet investissement, <Alignment alignment="3017" annotation_id="29628">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29628" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est le cas aux États-Unis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25837" docOffset="178">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="29663" annotation_id="25837">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25837" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I was defence minister, I met industry representatives and told them that I was the minister responsible for national defence, and not industrial defence.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="25837" annotation_id="29663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29663" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'étais ministre de la défense, j'ai rencontré des représentants de cette industrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29755">et</DiscourseConnective> leur ai signalé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29774">que</DiscourseConnective> j'étais le ministre de la défense nationale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29823">et</DiscourseConnective> non de la défense industrielle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25997" docOffset="179">
      <en>I think that the sort of directive we are discussing today, <Alignment alignment="29917" annotation_id="26057">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26057" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> for which I would like to express my thanks and my gratitude to Mr Lambsdorff, will lead to the large sums that we spend on defence being used in a significantly more sensible and reasonable manner, <Alignment alignment="30142" annotation_id="26260">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26260" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the military capability of the European Union will reflect our level of spending on defence.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29867">que</DiscourseConnective> la directive dont nous débattons aujourd'hui, <Alignment alignment="10239" annotation_id="29917">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29917" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29920">pour</DiscourseConnective> laquelle je souhaiterais exprimer tous mes remerciements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29982">et</DiscourseConnective> toute ma gratitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30004">à</DiscourseConnective> M. Lambsdorff, permettra une utilisation beaucoup plus sensée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30068">et</DiscourseConnective> raisonnable des sommes phénoménales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30107">que</DiscourseConnective> nous dépensons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30126">pour</DiscourseConnective> la défense <Alignment alignment="9387" annotation_id="30142">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30142" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30145">que</DiscourseConnective> les capacités militaires de l'Union européenne reflèteront ce niveau de dépenses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="26362" id="281" name="Angelika Beer">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="26362" docOffset="180">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to point out once again that we are talking about a package: the resolution in December and this debate today.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30268">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, permettez-moi de rappeler une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30317">encore que</DiscourseConnective> nous discutons d'un paquet de mesures: la résolution de décembre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30393">et</DiscourseConnective> le débat d'aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26527" docOffset="181">
      <en>Only <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26532" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> we view both together - the regulation on transfers of defence-related products within the Community and now the procurement directive - do they make sense.</en>
      <fr>Ces deux éléments - le règlement sur les transferts de produits en matière de défense dans la Communauté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30525">et</DiscourseConnective>, à présent, la directive sur les marchés publics - n'ont de sens que s'ils sont considérés ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26694" docOffset="182">
      <en>I have prepared the opinion of the Committee on Foreign Affairs.</en>
      <fr>J'ai rédigé l'avis de la commission des affaires étrangères.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26759" docOffset="183">
      <en>We had a core political objective, namely that with the harmonisation of the European arms industry and the liberalisation within the EU, tougher means of control with regard to the issue of exports outside the EU should at the same time be implemented.</en>
      <fr>Nous poursuivions un objectif politique fondamental, à savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30752">qu'</DiscourseConnective>avec l'harmonisation de l'industrie européenne de l'armement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30816">et</DiscourseConnective> la libéralisation au sein de l'UE, nous mettions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30868">également</DiscourseConnective> en place des moyens de contrôle plus rigoureux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30925">en</DiscourseConnective> matière d'exportations hors de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27013" docOffset="184">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="30965" annotation_id="27013">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27013" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are going to mention the negative headlines, we should mention the good ones as well.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9992" annotation_id="30965">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30965" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous mentionnons les points négatifs, nous devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31018">également</DiscourseConnective> mentionner les points positifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27105" docOffset="185">
      <en>At its last meeting at the end of last year, the Council, under the French Presidency, adopted the Code of Conduct as a legally binding instrument.</en>
      <fr>Lors de sa dernière réunion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31088">en</DiscourseConnective> fin d'année passée, le Conseil, alors sous présidence française, a adopté le code de conduite en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31188">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>instrument contraignant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27253" docOffset="186">
      <en>That is a good thing <Alignment alignment="31243" annotation_id="27274">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27274" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is what this Parliament has always called for.</en>
      <fr>C'est une bonne chose <Alignment alignment="10573" annotation_id="31243">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31243" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est ce que le Parlement a toujours voulu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27328" docOffset="187">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="31290" annotation_id="27336">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27336" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to point out once again that this harmonisation that we consider to be right - and not only the harmonisation, but also the development of a sanction mechanism that is to be used <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27530" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> this directive is contravened - is now <Alignment alignment="31544" annotation_id="27572">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27572" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> under the control of the nation states and the Members.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12751" annotation_id="31290">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31290" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je voudrais souligner une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31337">encore que</DiscourseConnective> cette harmonisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31368">que</DiscourseConnective> nous estimons adéquate - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31397">et</DiscourseConnective> pas uniquement l'harmonisation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31432">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place d'un mécanisme de sanctions applicable en cas de violation de cette directive - est <Alignment alignment="7363" annotation_id="31544">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31544" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> soumise au contrôle des États-nations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31592">et</DiscourseConnective> des parlementaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27633" docOffset="188">
      <en>We will follow this process, and not only the harmonisation, with great interest.</en>
      <fr>Nous surveillerons ce processus, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31648">et</DiscourseConnective> pas uniquement l'harmonisation, avec grand intérêt.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="27715" id="282" name="Jacques Toubon">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27715" docOffset="189">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, I would like to add my support to the line taken by Mr Schwab a few moments ago.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je voudrais m'inscrire exactement dans la ligne qui a été celle de mon collègue Schwab, il y a quelques instants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27815" docOffset="190">
      <en>I would say that adopting this directive today is a major decision <Alignment alignment="19872" annotation_id="27882">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27882" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we owe it to the very remarkable efforts of our rapporteur, Mr Lambsdorff, our shadow rapporteur, Charlotte Cederschiöld, whom I thank <Alignment alignment="18843" annotation_id="28021">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28021" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> naturally, the French Presidency who, at the end of last year, made great efforts to achieve a compromise.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31852">dire que</DiscourseConnective> l'adoption, aujourd'hui, de cette directive est une décision importante <Alignment alignment="7757" annotation_id="31933">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31933" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous la devons aux efforts très remarquables de notre rapporteur, M. Lambsdorff, de notre rapporteure fictive, Charlotte Cederschiöld, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32071">que</DiscourseConnective> je remercie <Alignment alignment="9952" annotation_id="32087">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32087" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> naturellement de la Présidence française qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32136">à</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'année dernière, a fait de très grands efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32196">pour qu'</DiscourseConnective>on aboutisse à un compromis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28132" docOffset="191">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24948" annotation_id="28132">
          <Alignment alignment="87921" annotation_id="28132">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28132" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, what we are doing today is to finish a cycle which has been remarkably fast, that is to say a few months, which includes both the directive on the internal market in defence products, adopted in December, the Code of Conduct for exports, which became law at the same time and, finally, this directive reconciling Article 296 of the Treaty with the common rules on public contracts.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="33530" annotation_id="32233">
          <Alignment alignment="37641" annotation_id="32233">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32233" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, ce que nous sommes en train de faire aujourd'hui, c'est d'achever un cycle qui a été remarquablement rapide, c'est-à-dire, quelques mois, qui comporte à la fois la directive sur le marché intérieur des produits de défense, adoptée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32473">en</DiscourseConnective> décembre, le code de conduite sur les exportations, qui est devenu du droit positif au <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32563">même</DiscourseConnective> moment, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32576">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32580">enfin</DiscourseConnective>, cette directive qui consiste à concilier l'article 296 du traité avec les règles communes des marchés publics.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28523" docOffset="192">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="37482" annotation_id="28523">
          <Alignment alignment="32698" annotation_id="28523">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28523" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, this whole set, so to speak, commits us to what I will call 'communitisation' of the defence economy. This might, of course, appear to be inimical to the desire for sovereignty or even to the very characteristics of defence policies.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="22747" annotation_id="32698">
          <Alignment alignment="18437" annotation_id="32698">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32698" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, tout cet ensemble - je me permets de le dire - nous engage dans ce que j'appellerai "la communautarisation" de l'économie de la défense, ce qui évidemment peut paraître hérétique par rapport au souci de souveraineté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32923">ou</DiscourseConnective> aux caractéristiques mêmes des politiques de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28766" docOffset="193">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="26091" annotation_id="28766">
          <Alignment alignment="32980" annotation_id="28766">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28766" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, this translates a desire for integration of state sovereignties.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="28766" annotation_id="32980">
          <Alignment alignment="2335" annotation_id="32980">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32980" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, ceci traduit une volonté d'intégration par rapport aux souverainetés étatiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28840" docOffset="194">
      <en>The same thing will be noted in the field of justice.</en>
      <fr>On constate d'ailleurs la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33095">même</DiscourseConnective> chose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33106">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28894" docOffset="195">
      <en>Throughout the French Presidency and since the Portuguese and Slovenian Presidencies, enormous progress has been made in yet another field in which national sovereignties wished to block any agreement or cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Tout au long de la Présidence française <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33169">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33172">depuis</DiscourseConnective> la Présidence portugaise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33204">et</DiscourseConnective> la Présidence slovène, on a fait d'énormes progrès dans un domaine où, là <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33281">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, les souverainetés nationales prétendaient empêcher tout accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33351">et</DiscourseConnective> toute coopération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29111" docOffset="196">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="33373" annotation_id="29111">
          <Alignment alignment="35467" annotation_id="29111">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29111" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, ladies and gentlemen, by adopting such a text, I believe we are helping to bring an end to the ideological debate on the nature and form of the European project.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4343" annotation_id="33373">
          <Alignment alignment="4109" annotation_id="33373">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33373" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, mes chers collègues, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33403">en</DiscourseConnective> adoptant un tel texte, je crois que nous sommes en train de contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33477">à</DiscourseConnective> épuiser le débat idéologique sur la nature <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33522">et</DiscourseConnective> la forme de la construction européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29282" docOffset="197">
      <en>It is an area and a power, <Alignment alignment="33620" annotation_id="29309">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29309" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it will be increasingly recognised in the fields of defence and foreign policy.</en>
      <fr>C'est un espace, c'est un pouvoir, c'est une puissance <Alignment alignment="41910" annotation_id="33620">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33620" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on le saura <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33635">de plus</DiscourseConnective> en plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33651">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33673">et</DiscourseConnective> de politique étrangère.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="29393" id="283" name="Geoffrey Van Orden">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="29393" docOffset="198">
      <en>Mr President, as British Conservatives, we are generally strong protagonists of open markets, <Alignment alignment="58485" annotation_id="29487">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29487" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="33849" annotation_id="29492">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29492" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a number of speakers have confirmed, the underlying thrust of this report is strengthening ESDP and EU integration rather than any real economic benefits.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33731">tant que</DiscourseConnective> conservateurs britanniques, nous sommes généralement de fervents partisans de l'ouverture des marchés, <Alignment alignment="29487" annotation_id="33843">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33843" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="24423" annotation_id="33849">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33849" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'ont confirmé plusieurs intervenants, l'idée sous-jacente de ce rapport consiste à renforcer la PESD <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33957">et</DiscourseConnective> l'intégration de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33982">plutôt qu'</DiscourseConnective>à tirer des bénéfices économiques réels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29650" docOffset="199">
      <en>It certainly has nothing to do with strengthening defence capabilities.</en>
      <fr>Le texte ne concerne certainement pas le renforcement des capacités en matière de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29722" docOffset="200">
      <en>I can see that there could be some marginal benefits in easier UK access to some other European countries' markets in defence-related procurement.</en>
      <fr>Je constate <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34136">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il pourrait y avoir certains bénéfices mineurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34186">à</DiscourseConnective> faciliter l'accès du Royaume-Uni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34221">à</DiscourseConnective> d'autres marchés de pays européens en matière de marchés publics de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29869" docOffset="201">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1054" annotation_id="29869">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29869" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is a far greater advantage for others to access the UK market, which has the largest defence spend - <Alignment alignment="68068" annotation_id="29980">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29980" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, by the way, the UK already has the most open defence procurement market in Europe.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13586" annotation_id="34303">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34303" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est beaucoup plus profitable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34340">pour</DiscourseConnective> d'autres pays d'accéder au marché britannique, qui consacre les dépenses les plus importantes à la défense - <Alignment alignment="15422" annotation_id="34454">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34454" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34457">par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>, le Royaume-Uni a toujours eu les marchés publics de défense les plus ouverts.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30068" docOffset="202">
      <en>Of particular concern is that, under the proposed rules, a government or firm that has made huge investment in some aspect of defence R&amp;D may no longer be in a position to recoup this investment in the development and production phase.</en>
      <fr>Un aspect particulièrement préoccupant est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34592">qu'</DiscourseConnective>au titre des règles proposées, un gouvernement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34642">ou</DiscourseConnective> une entreprise qui a considérablement investi dans certains aspects de la R&amp;D pour la défense ne pourrait plus être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34761">en</DiscourseConnective> mesure de recouvrer cet investissement durant la phase de développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34836">et</DiscourseConnective> de production.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30304" docOffset="203">
      <en>Development contracts are expected to be opened up to European competition, leaving a national government with no means of protecting intellectual property, jobs or export opportunities.</en>
      <fr>Les contrats de développement devraient être ouverts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34907">à</DiscourseConnective> la concurrence européenne, laissant un gouvernement national sans aucun moyen de protéger la propriété intellectuelle, les emplois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35040">ou</DiscourseConnective> les possibilités d'exportation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30491" docOffset="204">
      <en>It will be a brake on R&amp;D.</en>
      <fr>Une telle approche sera un frein <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35108">à</DiscourseConnective> la R&amp;D.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30518" docOffset="205">
      <en>There are other concerns as well, <Alignment alignment="27145" annotation_id="30552">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30552" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I have to say that this report is not really necessary from a defence, industrial or, indeed, economic point of view.</en>
      <fr>Il y a également d'autres inquiétudes, <Alignment alignment="11687" annotation_id="35157">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35157" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35171">à</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35173">dire que</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport n'est pas véritablement nécessaire du point de vue de la défense, de l'industrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35274">ou</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35278">effectivement</DiscourseConnective>, de l'économie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="30674" id="284" name="Ioan Mircea Paşcu">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="30674" docOffset="206">
      <en>Mr President, the directive on defence procurement is an important step towards both the EDEM and the ESDP.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, la directive relative à la passation de marchés publics dans le domaine de la défense est une étape importante vers le marché européen pour les équipements de la défense (EDEM) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35513">et</DiscourseConnective> la PESD.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30782" docOffset="207">
      <en>I recognise the difficulties of reconciling free market principles with inevitable discretion on defence deals, and common rules covering the award of public contracts with individual practices regarding defence contracts.</en>
      <fr>Je reconnais qu'il est difficile de réconcilier les principes du marché libre avec l'indispensable discrétion liée aux contrats dans le domaine de la défense, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35684">et</DiscourseConnective> des règles communes régissant l'attribution de marchés publics avec les pratiques particulières concernant les marchés publics de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31005" docOffset="208">
      <en>This very complex set of regulations has, of course, to pass the test of practice, <Alignment alignment="69196" annotation_id="31088">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31088" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> trying to fit in the same box adverse elements like transparency and secrecy, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31174" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> commonality and individuality, will require constant monitoring and the determination to penalise any individual attempt to favour one over the other in a continuous effort to keep a fine balance between all four.</en>
      <fr>Cet ensemble très complexe de règlements doit, bien entendu, être réaliste, <Alignment alignment="1615" annotation_id="35902">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35902" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>essayer de concilier des éléments contradictoires tels que la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35986">et</DiscourseConnective> le secret, l'intérêt commun <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36017">et</DiscourseConnective> particulier, exigera une surveillance permanente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36069">et</DiscourseConnective> il faudra décider de sanctionner toute tentative individuelle visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36141">à</DiscourseConnective> favoriser un aspect par rapport à l'autre dans un effort continu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36208">pour</DiscourseConnective> maintenir un bon équilibre entre les quatre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31392" docOffset="209">
      <en>Proper functioning will <Alignment alignment="42231" annotation_id="31416">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31416" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be both a function and a reflection of the determination of the EU bodies to referee this nascent European market, and of the true willingness of national defence champions and the Member States behind them to respect and play the game according to these new rules.</en>
      <fr>Le bon fonctionnement sera <Alignment alignment="9564" annotation_id="36285">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36285" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à la fois une fonction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36316">et</DiscourseConnective> une réflexion de la détermination des organes de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36373">à</DiscourseConnective> arbitrer ce marché européen émergent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36412">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la véritable volonté des champions de la défense nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36481">et</DiscourseConnective>, derrière eux, des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36517">à</DiscourseConnective> respecter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36529">et</DiscourseConnective> à jouer le jeu selon ces nouvelles règles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31687" docOffset="210">
      <en>One word on offsetting.</en>
      <fr>Un mot sur les compensations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="31711" docOffset="211">
      <en>For countries like mine, Romania, offset is, at least for the time being, an important mechanism to ensure the survival of our national industry.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36605">Pour</DiscourseConnective> des pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36619">comme</DiscourseConnective> le mien, la Roumanie, la compensation est, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36668">du moins</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36677">pour</DiscourseConnective> le moment, un mécanisme important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36716">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer la survie de notre industrie nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="31857" id="285" name="Marian-Jean Marinescu">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="31857" docOffset="212">
      <en>(RO) European unity and security have again been put in jeopardy at the moment by both the financial and economic crisis and the energy crisis.</en>
      <fr>(RO) L'unité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36782">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité européennes sont de nouveau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36825">en</DiscourseConnective> péril en raison de la crise économique et financière et de la crise énergétique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32001" docOffset="213">
      <en>This has shown once again that only unity and solidarity enable us to successfully tackle the major problems in the modern world.</en>
      <fr>Cela montre encore <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36928">une fois que</DiscourseConnective> seules l'unité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36956">et</DiscourseConnective> la solidarité permettent de s'attaquer efficacement aux grands problèmes du monde moderne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32131" docOffset="214">
      <en>The introduction of common, transparent rules governing procurement in the market for security and defence-related products is an important step in tightening European security policy.</en>
      <fr>L'introduction de règles communes transparentes pour la passation de marchés dans le domaine des produits liés à la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37174">et</DiscourseConnective> à la sécurité est un pas important vers la consolidation de la politique de sécurité européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32316" docOffset="215">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="37280" annotation_id="32322">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32322" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a mechanism specific to the market economy enabling European industry to compete successfully with major global players, especially in the United States.</en>
      <fr>C'est <Alignment alignment="8857" annotation_id="37280">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37280" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un mécanisme spécifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37314">à</DiscourseConnective> l'économie de marché qui permet à l'industrie européenne d'opposer une concurrence efficace aux principaux acteurs mondiaux, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37441">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> aux États-Unis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32481" docOffset="216">
      <en>A sound Community scheme needs to be set up as soon as possible for handling information security, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32580" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective> an adequate control system needs to be put in place for exports of security and defence-related products and equipment to third countries.</en>
      <fr>Il importe d'établir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37493">dès que</DiscourseConnective> possible un solide mécanisme communautaire garantissant la sécurité de l'information, ainsi qu'un système de contrôle adéquat des exportations de produits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37656">et</DiscourseConnective> d'équipements de défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37684">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité vers les pays tiers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="32725" docOffset="217">
      <en>The ratification and enforcement of the Lisbon Treaty will allow well-structured cooperation to be established on a permanent basis in the area of security policy, which is essential to the EU's future.</en>
      <fr>La ratification <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37736">et</DiscourseConnective> la mise en œuvre du traité de Lisbonne contribueront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37792">à</DiscourseConnective> l'instauration d'une coopération structurée permanente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37849">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de politique de sécurité, une coopération qui est essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37922">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="32928" id="286" name="Bogusław Rogalski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="32928" docOffset="218">
      <en>(PL) Since the 1990s it has been clear that the fragmentation of the European defence markets has had negative economic repercussions.</en>
      <fr>(PL) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37950">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> les années 1990, on sait avec certitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37997">que</DiscourseConnective> la fragmentation des marchés européens de la défense a des répercussions négatives sur l'économie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="33063" docOffset="219">
      <en>During the past 20 years, defence spending has been cut, leading to lower turnover and employment levels, as well as cuts in investment in the field of research and new military technologies.</en>
      <fr>Au cours de ces vingt dernières années, les dépenses ont été réduites dans ce secteur, entraînant une baisse du chiffre d'affaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38231">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'embauche. Les investissements dans le domaine de la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38301">et</DiscourseConnective> des nouvelles technologies militaires ont également été réduits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="33255" docOffset="220">
      <en>Today, even the large Member States have trouble funding new defence systems.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38382">même</DiscourseConnective> les grands États membres peinent à financer de nouveaux systèmes de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="33333" docOffset="221">
      <en>A European defence technological and industrial base should be created in order to develop the Member States' fundamental defence capabilities.</en>
      <fr>Une base industrielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38486">et</DiscourseConnective> technologique de défense européenne devrait être créée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38544">afin de</DiscourseConnective> développer les capacités de défense fondamentales des États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="33477" docOffset="222">
      <en>This step is vital, in order to meet global challenges in the field of defence.</en>
      <fr>Cette mesure est vitale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38646">si</DiscourseConnective> nous voulons relever les défis mondiaux dans ce secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="33557" docOffset="223">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="38718" annotation_id="33563">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33563" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> important to have a harmonised European legislative framework, which would allow the Member States to implement Community provisions without threatening their own defence interests.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="12662" annotation_id="38718">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38718" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> disposer d'un cadre législatif européen harmonisé permettant aux États membres d'appliquer les dispositions communautaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38851">sans</DiscourseConnective> mettre à mal leurs propres intérêts en matière de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="33750" docOffset="224">
      <en>We should not forget an important element, namely the introduction of a control procedure. It should aim to guarantee tenderers effective legal protection, foster transparency and prevent discrimination during the procurement process.</en>
      <fr>Il convient de ne pas oublier un élément important, à savoir l'introduction d'une procédure de contrôle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39020">afin de</DiscourseConnective> garantir aux soumissionnaires une protection juridique efficace, d'accroître la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39121">et</DiscourseConnective> de prévenir toute discrimination pendant la procédure de passation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="33985" id="287" name="Emmanouil Angelakas">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="33985" docOffset="225">
      <en>(EL) Mr President, I too should like to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Lambsdorff, and the shadow rapporteurs on the important work they have done.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais à mon tour féliciter le rapporteur, M. Lambsdorff, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39283">et</DiscourseConnective> les rapporteurs fictifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39310">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'important travail qu'ils ont accompli.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="34134" docOffset="226">
      <en>The main feature of the European market is the fragmentation that prevails at national level.</en>
      <fr>La principale particularité du marché européen tient à sa fragmentation au niveau national.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="34228" docOffset="227">
      <en>Exports of products relating to the defence and security sector in question are subject to national licensing systems which differ in terms of procedure, scope and deadlines.</en>
      <fr>Les exportations de produits liés au secteur de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39507">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39525">en</DiscourseConnective> question sont soumises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39551">à</DiscourseConnective> des systèmes d'autorisation nationaux, qui diffèrent entre eux au niveau de la procédure, du champ d'application <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39666">et</DiscourseConnective> des délais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="34403" docOffset="228">
      <en>This new legislation promotes transparency and lays the foundations for creating a single open European market in defence equipment, which is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34545" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> a basic factor in strengthening European security and defence policy.</en>
      <fr>Cette nouvelle législation favorise la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39733">et</DiscourseConnective> jette les bases d'un marché européen ouvert unique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39787">pour</DiscourseConnective> les équipements de défense - un facteur essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39842">pour</DiscourseConnective> le renforcement de la politique européenne de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39902">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="34620" docOffset="229">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="39928" annotation_id="34626">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34626" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> important that there are fundamental provisions governing the security of supply and information.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <Alignment alignment="672" annotation_id="39928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39928" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de veiller à ce qu'il existe des dispositions fondamentales garantissant la sécurité de l'approvisionnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40046">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'information.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="34729" docOffset="230">
      <en>The citation of Article 296 of the Treaty establishing the European Communities has <Alignment alignment="40148" annotation_id="34813">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34813" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> been clarified, but is now confined to actual derogations, <Alignment alignment="40228" annotation_id="34877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34877" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> provided for in the Treaty <Alignment alignment="40255" annotation_id="34907">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34907" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34911" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> requested by the European Court of Justice.</en>
      <fr>La citation de l'article 296 du traité établissant les Communautés européennes a <Alignment alignment="42779" annotation_id="40148">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40148" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> été clarifiée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40173">mais</DiscourseConnective> est à présent limitée aux dérogations en vigueur, <Alignment alignment="44802" annotation_id="40228">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40228" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> prévu dans le Traité <Alignment alignment="22172" annotation_id="40255">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40255" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demandé par la Cour de justice européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="34958" docOffset="231">
      <en>To close, I should like to point out that it is important that there are flexible arrangements which strengthen the role of small and medium-sized enterprises which, in some Member States, form a sector that employs thousands of workers.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40301">En</DiscourseConnective> conclusion, je rappellerai à quel point il est nécessaire de mettre en place des mécanismes flexibles qui renforcent le rôle des petites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40441">et</DiscourseConnective> moyennes entreprises, un secteur qui, dans certains États membres, emploie des milliers de travailleurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="35196" id="288" name="Nickolay Mladenov">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="35196" docOffset="232">
      <en>Mr President, I would <Alignment alignment="40586" annotation_id="35218">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35218" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to congratulate Mr Lambsdorff for the excellent work he has done and of course his shadows, particularly, Mrs Cederschiöld, but let me <Alignment alignment="31395" annotation_id="35363">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35363" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> underline something that Mr Toubon said: the fantastic work done by the French presidency in achieving agreement on this directive.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, je tiens <Alignment alignment="35218" annotation_id="40586">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40586" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40596">à</DiscourseConnective> féliciter M. Lambsdorff <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40622">pour</DiscourseConnective> son excellent travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40649">et</DiscourseConnective>, bien sûr, pour celui de ses rapporteurs fictifs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40702">notamment</DiscourseConnective> Mme Cederschiöld, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40730">mais</DiscourseConnective> permettez-moi <Alignment alignment="35363" annotation_id="40749">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40749" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de souligner un point soulevé par M. Toubon: le formidable travail réalisé par la présidence française qui est parvenue à un accord sur cette directive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="35500" docOffset="233">
      <en>I hope that <Alignment alignment="40922" annotation_id="35512">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35512" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we return to it in a few years' time we will realise that we should not have been afraid to talk about a European defence equipment market because of a common European market.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40917">que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="35512" annotation_id="40922">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40922" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous y reviendrons dans quelques années, nous comprendrons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40987">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne faut pas avoir peur de parler d'un marché européen des équipements de défense à cause d'un marché commun européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="35693" docOffset="234">
      <en>It is in the common defence interest of Europe <Alignment alignment="44417" annotation_id="35740">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35740" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is in the common interest of Europe to have more competition.</en>
      <fr>Il est dans l'intérêt commun de la défense européenne <Alignment alignment="20400" annotation_id="41165">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41165" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans l'intérêt commun de l'Europe de stimuler la concurrence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="35809" docOffset="235">
      <en>Let me highlight one part of this directive which is highly important for many Member States.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite mettre l'accent sur une partie de cette directive qui est d'une importance capitale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41326">pour</DiscourseConnective> de nombreux États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="35903" docOffset="236">
      <en>This is particularly the text concerning subcontracting.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41361">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit tout particulièrement du passage relatif à la sous-traitance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="35960" docOffset="237">
      <en>I am very happy that the agreements reached with the Council and the Commission on the text concerning subcontracting have reflected to a large extent what Parliament has been pushing for, namely that there is more transparency in terms of subcontracting; secondly, that there is no discrimination on a national basis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36278" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> subcontracts are being drafted <Alignment alignment="41802" annotation_id="36314">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36314" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> finally that national authorities have the ability to allow contractors to subcontract up to 30% of their contracts.</en>
      <fr>Je suis très satisfait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41453">que</DiscourseConnective> les accords conclus avec le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41493">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur le texte concernant la sous-traitance reflètent largement les aspects demandés par le Parlement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41611">notamment</DiscourseConnective> le fait d'encourager la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41658">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de sous-traitance, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41687">ensuite</DiscourseConnective> l'absence de discrimination fondée sur la nationalité lors de l'élaboration des contrats de sous-traitance <Alignment alignment="36314" annotation_id="41802">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41802" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41805">enfin</DiscourseConnective>, le fait d'accorder aux autorités nationales la capacité d'autoriser les contractants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41897">à</DiscourseConnective> sous-traiter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41912">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> 30 % de leurs contrats.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="36435" docOffset="238">
      <en>This is in the interests of bringing our industry together across Europe.</en>
      <fr>Ce texte contribuera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41965">à</DiscourseConnective> rassembler nos industries à travers l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="36509" id="289" name="Charlie McCreevy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="36509" docOffset="239">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, I would like to thank all the participants in the debate.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42077">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier tous ceux qui ont participé au débat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="36609" docOffset="240">
      <en>It is clear that the present text is a compromise and as such cannot take on board all the suggestions made with the attention of improving it.</en>
      <fr>Le présent texte représente clairement un compromis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42179">et</DiscourseConnective>, en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42186">tant que</DiscourseConnective> tel, il ne peut contenir toutes les suggestions faites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42250">dans l'intention de</DiscourseConnective> l'améliorer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="36753" docOffset="241">
      <en>At the same time, <Alignment alignment="42283" annotation_id="36771">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36771" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Parliament has many reasons to be satisfied.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="36771" annotation_id="42283">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42283" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42294">en</DiscourseConnective> parallèle, le Parlement a de nombreuses raisons d'être satisfait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="36825" docOffset="242">
      <en>Firstly, it was Parliament that asked the Commission in its resolution of 17 November 2005 in the Green Paper on defence procurement to prepare this directive.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42363">Tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective>, c'est le Parlement qui a demandé à la Commission, dans sa résolution du 17 novembre 2005 sur le livre vert relatif aux marchés publics de défense, d'élaborer cette directive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="36985" docOffset="243">
      <en>Hence, it is to a large extent Parliament's proposal.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42555">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42562">donc</DiscourseConnective>, dans une grande mesure, d'une proposition du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="37039" docOffset="244">
      <en>Secondly, and even more importantly, the current text has benefited enormously from your input during the process.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42624">Ensuite</DiscourseConnective>, un aspect <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42643">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus important, le texte actuel a considérablement bénéficié de votre contribution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="37154" docOffset="245">
      <en>A huge number of amendments from the Committee on Internal Market and Consumer Protection report have been integrated, in particular with regard to the scope, the provisions on remedies, and transparency.</en>
      <fr>Un très grand nombre d'amendements du rapport de la commission du marché intérieur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42817">et</DiscourseConnective> de la protection du consommateur ont été intégrés au texte, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42880">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42895">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne le champ d'application, les dispositions sur les recours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42971">et</DiscourseConnective> la transparence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="37359" docOffset="246">
      <en>The Commission can accept all these amendments and <Alignment alignment="43043" annotation_id="37410">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37410" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> supports the text.</en>
      <fr>La Commission peut accepter tous ces amendements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43040">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="6482" annotation_id="43043">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43043" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> soutenir le texte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="37439" docOffset="247">
      <en>We are convinced that this directive will make a difference and contribute to a real European defence market.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes convaincus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43091">que</DiscourseConnective> cette directive fera la différence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43130">et</DiscourseConnective> contribuera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43145">à</DiscourseConnective> l'établissement d'un marché européen de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="37549" docOffset="248">
      <en>Let us face it, only five years ago, the idea of building this market with Community instruments was pure science fiction to most people, <Alignment alignment="43378" annotation_id="37687">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="37687" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> today it is about to become a reality.</en>
      <fr>Regardons la situation en face, il y a à peine cinq ans, l'idée de créer ce marché avec des instruments communautaires était de la pure science fiction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43351">pour</DiscourseConnective> la majorité des gens, <Alignment alignment="23199" annotation_id="43378">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43378" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aujourd'hui, elle est sur le point de se concrétiser.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="37730" docOffset="249">
      <en>We should not miss this opportunity.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne devons pas laisser passer cette opportunité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="37767" id="291" language="DE" name="Alexander Graf Lambsdorff">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="37767" docOffset="250">
      <en>Madam President, I would urge my fellow Member Mr van Orden to consider the fact that the only person here who supports him is the German far-left extremist.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (DE) Madame la Présidente, j'invite instamment mon collège député M. van Orden <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43583">à</DiscourseConnective> considérer le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43604">que</DiscourseConnective> la seule personne qui le soutient est l'extrémiste de gauche allemand.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="37925" docOffset="251">
      <en>To Mr Pflüger from the left, I would say that a glance at the law will facilitate its understanding.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43679">À</DiscourseConnective> M. Pflüger, de la gauche, je dirais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43717">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43723">bref</DiscourseConnective> examen de la législation en question lui permettra de mieux saisir sa substance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38026" docOffset="252">
      <en>It is not about exports at all, it is about the European internal market.</en>
      <fr>Il n'est absolument pas question d'exportations, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43858">mais</DiscourseConnective> du marché intérieur européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38100" docOffset="253">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="95986" annotation_id="38100">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38100" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Otherwise</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, what Mrs Weiler said is correct.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="38100" annotation_id="43893">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43893" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ce qu'a dit Mme Weiler est juste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38144" docOffset="254">
      <en>She said that these products are expensive through lack of competition.</en>
      <fr>Elle a fait remarquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43963">que</DiscourseConnective> le coût élevé de ces produits était dû <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44006">à</DiscourseConnective> un manque de concurrence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38216" docOffset="255">
      <en>Yes, <Alignment alignment="44049" annotation_id="38221">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38221" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is no competition, they are expensive.</en>
      <fr>Et c'est vrai: <Alignment alignment="38221" annotation_id="44049">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44049" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'absence de concurrence, le prix de ces produits est élevé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38271" docOffset="256">
      <en>We will hopefully introduce more competition into the European internal market. This will certainly not make these products cheap, but perhaps more reasonably priced at least.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons renforcer la concurrence au sein du marché intérieur européen, pas au point de garantir des prix bas, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44229">mais</DiscourseConnective> peut-être au moins des prix raisonnables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38447" docOffset="257">
      <en>This is a big opportunity, an opportunity for the industry to open up new markets and an opportunity for medium-sized companies to penetrate these markets, too.</en>
      <fr>C'est une opportunité exceptionnelle, une possibilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44330">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie concernée d'ouvrir de nouveaux marchés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44386">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44389">pour</DiscourseConnective> les moyennes entreprises de pénétrer ces marchés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38608" docOffset="258">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="44444" annotation_id="38608">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38608" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - and this is quite important - it is <Alignment alignment="44490" annotation_id="38654">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38654" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an opportunity for transparency and thus for civil society, which will be able to keep a better eye on the way this market is structured and on what is happening, and for many non-governmental organisations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="759" annotation_id="44444">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44444" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44455">et</DiscourseConnective> c'est très important, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44483">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit <Alignment alignment="38654" annotation_id="44490">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44490" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'une occasion d'accroître la transparence, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44544">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44547">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective> d'une opportunité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44580">pour</DiscourseConnective> la société civile, qui pourra <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44615">mieux</DiscourseConnective> surveiller la structure de ce marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44658">et</DiscourseConnective> son évolution, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44676">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44686">pour</DiscourseConnective> les organisations non gouvernementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38867" docOffset="259">
      <en>I would like to expressly thank Mr Mladenov and Mr Toubon for their reference to the unusual work involved in this project.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais remercier expressément MM. Mladenov <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44779">et</DiscourseConnective> Toubon d'avoir mentionné la quantité de travail inhabituelle investie dans ce projet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="38991" docOffset="260">
      <en>In essence, it is a project under the second pillar, that is the strengthening of the European security and defence policy, using an instrument of the first pillar, namely an internal market directive.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agit par nature d'un projet du deuxième pilier, c'est-à-dire le renforcement de la politique européenne de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="44989">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense, qui utilise un instrument du premier pilier, à savoir une directive sur le marché intérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39193" docOffset="261">
      <en>Without the splendid work of the French Presidency mediating between the Member States - an extremely difficult task - it would never have succeeded.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45097">Sans</DiscourseConnective> l'excellent travail de la présidence française, qui a joué les médiateurs entre les différents États membres - une tâche extrêmement difficile -, il n'aurait jamais vu le jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39343" docOffset="262">
      <en>We must expand these opportunities.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons étendre le champ de ces possibilités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39379" docOffset="263">
      <en>It will be an opportunity for the political Europe. It will be an opportunity for the Common Foreign and Security Policy and an opportunity for the Europe of values and of peace.</en>
      <fr>Ce sera une opportunité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45353">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe politique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45378">pour</DiscourseConnective> la politique étrangère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45406">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité commune, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45430">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45440">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe des valeurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45466">et</DiscourseConnective> de la paix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39558" docOffset="264">
      <en>This is an opportunity that we must take advantage of.</en>
      <fr>C'est une opportunité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45503">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons saisir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="39613" id="292" name="Tobias Pflüger">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="39613" docOffset="265">
      <en>(DE) Madam President, I would like to make a request under Rule 145 of the Rules of Procedure.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Madame la Présidente, j'ai une requête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45571">à</DiscourseConnective> formuler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45582">en</DiscourseConnective> application de l'article 145 du règlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39708" docOffset="266">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="29849" annotation_id="39708">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39708" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you are addressed in person, you have the opportunity to respond briefly.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="34914" annotation_id="45628">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45628" sense="Contingency.Condition">Quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des propos nous sont personnellement destinés, nous avons la possibilité d'y réagir brièvement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39785" docOffset="267">
      <en>It will become clear relatively quickly who the extremists are here, <Alignment alignment="45795" annotation_id="39854">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="39854" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you take a look at what all this is about.</en>
      <fr>Les extrémistes présents ici seront assez rapidement identifiés, <Alignment alignment="39854" annotation_id="45795">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45795" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'on considère le fond du problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39900" docOffset="268">
      <en>It is about market extremism, which is evident in this area.</en>
      <fr>Nous parlons d'extrémisme de marché, qui apparaît clairement dans ce secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39961" docOffset="269">
      <en>I said that a more efficient defence industry within the European Union would naturally have an impact on arms exports.</en>
      <fr>J'ai dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="45921">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une industrie de la défense plus efficace au sein de l'Union européenne aurait forcément un impact sur les exportations d'armes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="40081" docOffset="270">
      <en>No one can deny that this is the case.</en>
      <fr>Nul ne peut contester ce fait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="40120" docOffset="271">
      <en>To suggest anything else would indicate a total fixation on the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Dire le contraire serait la preuve d'une fixation totale sur l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="40200" id="293" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="40200" docOffset="272">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="40222" docOffset="273">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="40257" docOffset="274">
      <en>Written statements (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclarations écrites (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="40287" id="294" language="PL" name="Bogdan Golik ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="40287" docOffset="275">
      <en>I would like to highlight the importance of the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on the coordination of procedures for the award of certain public works contracts, public supply contracts and public service contracts in the fields of defence and security, which I strongly support.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (PL) Je souhaiterais souligner l'importance de la proposition de directive du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="46355">et</DiscourseConnective> du Conseil relative à la coordination des procédures de passation de certains marchés publics de travaux, de fournitures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="46479">et</DiscourseConnective> de services dans les domaines de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="46526">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="46545">que</DiscourseConnective> je soutiens avec force.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="40607" docOffset="276">
      <en>The directive opens the way for basing public procurement in the field of security and defence on transparent criteria, without discriminating against tenderers from other EU Member States, whilst simultaneously guaranteeing the security of these countries.</en>
      <fr>Cette directive ouvre la voie à l'application de critères transparents dans les procédures de passation des marchés publics, interdisant tout traitement défavorable des soumissionnaires issus d'autres États membres de l'UE, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="46797">tout en</DiscourseConnective> garantissant la sécurité des pays adjudicateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="40865" docOffset="277">
      <en>That is why it is so important to be able to invoke the clause in the Treaty establishing the European Community which provides that its provisions may be disregarded <Alignment alignment="47058" annotation_id="41032">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41032" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that step is necessary to protect the essential interests of an EU Member State.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="46891">si</DiscourseConnective> important de pouvoir invoquer la clause qui, dans le traité établissant la Communauté européenne, prévoit la possibilité d'ignorer les dispositions de la directive <Alignment alignment="9257" annotation_id="47058">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47058" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela s'avère nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47085">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger les intérêts fondamentaux d'un État membre de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="41116" docOffset="278">
      <en>Joint production, joint purchasing, public procurement -especially in terms of the most technologically advanced, and therefore more expensive, equipment - will give the European Security and Defence Policy a better chance of success.</en>
      <fr>La production conjointe, l'achat conjoint, les marchés publics - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47216">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47231">en</DiscourseConnective> matière d'équipements de pointe, qui sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47276">aussi</DiscourseConnective> les plus coûteux - augmenteront les chances de succès de la politique européenne de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47375">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="41351" docOffset="279">
      <en>The proposal for a directive, which I support, is a positive step towards opening up the markets of the EU Member States and reducing rivalry in the sector between countries which could make use of shared and cost-effective solutions.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de directive, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47419">que</DiscourseConnective> je soutiens, est un pas positif vers l'ouverture des marchés des États membres de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47510">et</DiscourseConnective> l'atténuation des rivalités intrasectorielles entre des pays qui pourraient tirer profit de solutions communes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47624">et</DiscourseConnective> rentables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="41586" docOffset="280">
      <en>At the same time, I would like to express my reservations regarding the order of preference of standards examined during the process of drawing up technical specifications for the purchase of defence equipment.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47638">Parallèlement</DiscourseConnective>, je souhaiterais émettre des réserves quant à l'ordre de préférence des normes prises en considération lors de la rédaction des spécifications techniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47806">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'achat d'équipements de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="41797" docOffset="281">
      <en>Defence ministers should be responsible for establishing implementation priorities.</en>
      <fr>Les ministres de la défense devraient être chargés de la définition des priorités en matière de mise en œuvre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="41881" docOffset="282">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="47956" annotation_id="41881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41881" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="41893" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> noted the lack of any reference in this proposal to the Code of Best Practice in the Supply Chain of the European Defence Agency, which is implemented by suppliers.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="41881" annotation_id="47956">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47956" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, j'ai constaté l'absence de référence, dans cette proposition, au code de bonnes pratiques dans la chaîne d'approvisionnement adopté par l'Agence européenne de défense à l'intention des fournisseurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="42063" docOffset="283">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="48172" annotation_id="42069">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42069" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not clear whether this criterion should continue to be taken into account <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42153" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> selecting suppliers.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="11106" annotation_id="48172">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48172" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> impossible de savoir avec certitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48223">si</DiscourseConnective> ce critère continue de s'appliquer lors de la sélection de fournisseurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="42179" id="295" language="BG" name="Dushana Zdravkova ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="42179" docOffset="284">
      <en>It is my firm view that defence and security are of paramount importance to each Member State, <Alignment alignment="29869" annotation_id="42274">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42274" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are above all areas in the interest of every citizen in the European Union, as well as of the European defence industry.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (BG) Je suis persuadée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48335">que</DiscourseConnective> la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48350">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité sont des priorités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48384">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous les États membres, <Alignment alignment="2618" annotation_id="48413">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48413" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48426">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout des domaines d'intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48460">pour</DiscourseConnective> chaque citoyen de l'Union européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48503">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48513">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie européenne de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="42404" docOffset="285">
      <en>It goes without saying that the option of derogating from this directive will continue to apply.</en>
      <fr>Il va <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48562">sans</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48567">dire que</DiscourseConnective> la possibilité de déroger à cette directive continuera de s'appliquer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="42501" docOffset="286">
      <en>For this reason, it is vitally important that Member States are urged to improve their legislation governing public procurement in the area of national security.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48647">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> il est capital d'encourager les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48708">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer leur législation en matière de marchés publics dans le domaine de la sécurité nationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="42663" docOffset="287">
      <en>They should <Alignment alignment="48826" annotation_id="42675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="42675" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> use the opportunity provided by Article 296 of the Treaty establishing the European Community, solely on the condition that they have guaranteed a similar level of transparency, accountability, focus on results and efficiency, including an adequate mechanism for settling disputes which have arisen.</en>
      <fr>Ils ne devraient <Alignment alignment="42675" annotation_id="48826">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48826" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> faire usage de la possibilité prévue à l'article 296 du traité établissant la Communauté européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48939">que s'</DiscourseConnective>ils ont garanti un niveau similaire de transparence, de responsabilisation, d'orientation sur les résultats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49053">et</DiscourseConnective> d'efficacité, y compris un mécanisme adéquat de règlement des litiges.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="42980" docOffset="288">
      <en>I would like to state that a directive, no matter how comprehensive and specific it is, cannot replace the need for the EU's defence industry and, more generally, its security industry to have a clear vision.</en>
      <fr>J'ajouterai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49139">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une directive, aussi complète <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49172">et</DiscourseConnective> spécifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49186">soit</DiscourseConnective>-elle, ne peut remplacer le besoin d'une vision claire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49245">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie européenne de la défense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49287">et</DiscourseConnective>, plus généralement, pour celle de la sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="43189" docOffset="289">
      <en>The lack of any vision and strategy cannot be compensated for by rules and exceptions which will make countries 'cheat' to protect their private interests, wholesale or retail, according to the size of their defence industry.</en>
      <fr>L'absence de vision <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49357">ou</DiscourseConnective> de stratégie ne peut être compensé par des règles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49410">et</DiscourseConnective> des exceptions qui inciteront les pays à "tricher" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49464">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger leurs intérêts privés, que ce soit sur les marchés de gros <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49537">ou</DiscourseConnective> les marchés de détail, selon la taille de leur industrie de la défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="43415" docOffset="290">
      <en>For this reason, a strategy must be devised in this area, which will be in the interest of upholding European principles.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="49623">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective> d'élaborer une stratégie dans ce domaine, qui incitera au respect des principes européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
