<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>3. (</en>
    <fr>3. (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5" docOffset="1">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="24" id="066" name="Jan Andersson">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="24" docOffset="2">
      <en>rapporteur. - (SV) Thank you, Mr President.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (SV) Merci, Monsieur le Président.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="68" docOffset="3">
      <en>With reference to the letter which the European trade union organisation sent to all its members last week, I should like to say that I can understand the views of the trade union movement regarding the question whether any consultation took place between the social partners and the Commission.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="71">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la lettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="100">que</DiscourseConnective> la Confédération européenne des syndicats a envoyée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="156">à</DiscourseConnective> tous ses membres la semaine dernière, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="208">dire que</DiscourseConnective> je peux comprendre les points de vue du mouvement syndical <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="276">quant à</DiscourseConnective> la question de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="306">si</DiscourseConnective> une consultation a eu lieu entre les partenaires sociaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="366">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="364" docOffset="4">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="396" annotation_id="364">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="364" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is beyond our capabilities to do anything about that.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <Alignment alignment="364" annotation_id="396">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="396" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans l'incapacité d'agir sur cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="430" docOffset="5">
      <en>The content of this Directive will not change in any way.</en>
      <fr>Le contenu de cette directive ne changera aucunement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="488" docOffset="6">
      <en>What will happen is that its implementation will be postponed for four years.</en>
      <fr>Voilà ce qu'il va se passer: sa mise en œuvre sera reportée de quatre ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="566" docOffset="7">
      <en>The reason is that it may not be possible to use some incredibly important medical equipment <Alignment alignment="678" annotation_id="659">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="659" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> implementation takes place in April.</en>
      <fr>La raison est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="594">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne peut être possible d'utiliser du matériel médical incroyablement important <Alignment alignment="2327" annotation_id="678">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="678" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la mise en œuvre a lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="705">en</DiscourseConnective> avril.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="699" docOffset="8">
      <en>Studies are currently in progress to determine how this equipment can be made compatible with the Directive.</en>
      <fr>Des études sont actuellement menées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="751">pour</DiscourseConnective> déterminer la manière dont ce matériel peut être rendu compatible avec la directive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="808" docOffset="9">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="841" annotation_id="811">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="811" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> gave our backing to the postponement of the Directive with the full agreement of the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="82" annotation_id="841">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="841" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons soutenu le report de la directive avec l'accord sans réserve de la commission de l'emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="957">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires sociales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="950" id="067" name="Günter Verheugen">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="950" docOffset="10">
      <en>Vice-President of the Commission. - Mr President, on behalf of the Commission, I would like to give the following explanation.</en>
      <fr>Vice-président de la Commission. - Monsieur le Président, au nom de la Commission, je souhaiterais apporter l'explication suivante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1077" docOffset="11">
      <en>In proposing postponement of entry into force of this directive, the Commission was reacting responsibly to new scientific evidence - I repeat, new scientific evidence - namely a study commissioned by the Government of the United Kingdom and published in June 2007.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1115">En</DiscourseConnective> proposant de reporter l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1149">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur de cette directive, la Commission a réagi de manière responsable face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1230">à</DiscourseConnective> une nouvelle preuve scientifique - je répète, une nouvelle preuve scientifique -, à savoir une étude commandée par le gouvernement du Royaume-Uni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1378">et</DiscourseConnective> publiée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1389">en</DiscourseConnective> juin 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1343" docOffset="12">
      <en>This new scientific evidence showed that the potential entry into force of the directive in its present form in April 2008 would have a major unintended detrimental effect on the practice of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), the best performing and safest imaging technology in contemporary medicine.</en>
      <fr>Cette nouvelle preuve scientifique a montré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1447">que</DiscourseConnective> l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1460">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur éventuelle de la directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1498">en</DiscourseConnective> avril 2008 sous sa forme actuelle aurait un effet majeur et involontairement néfaste sur la pratique de l'imagerie par résonance magnétique (IRM), la technologie d'imagerie la plus performante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1694">et</DiscourseConnective> la plus sûre de la médecine contemporaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1644" docOffset="13">
      <en>I would like to add, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1665" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> I am responsible for that sector, that, without this technology, thousands of patients in the European Union would not get the best possible treatment.</en>
      <fr>Étant responsable de ce secteur, je souhaiterais ajouter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1797">que</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1801">sans</DiscourseConnective> cette technologie, des milliers de patients dans l'Union européenne n'auraient pas accès au meilleur traitement possible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1825" docOffset="14">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="1940" annotation_id="1833">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1833" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to add that our producers are world leaders in this sector.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="794" annotation_id="1940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1940" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ajouter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1958">que</DiscourseConnective> nos producteurs sont les leaders mondiaux dans ce secteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1903" docOffset="15">
      <en>Mr Andersson mentioned the question of consultation.</en>
      <fr>M. Andersson a soulevé la question de la consultation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1956" docOffset="16">
      <en>I would like to say that the workers' representatives have been fully informed and were involved in the discussions that took place with the social partners before the adoption of the Commission proposal.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2087">dire que</DiscourseConnective> les représentants des travailleurs ont été pleinement informés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2159">et</DiscourseConnective> ont été impliqués dans les discussions qui ont été menées avec les partenaires sociaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2249">avant</DiscourseConnective> l'adoption de la proposition de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2161" docOffset="17">
      <en>The difficulties which may arise from the implementation of the current directive and the future intentions of the Commission were highlighted and discussed at the level of the Advisory Committee on Safety and Health at Work created by the Council.</en>
      <fr>Les difficultés pouvant résulter de la mise en œuvre de l'actuelle directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2379">et</DiscourseConnective> les futures intentions de la Commission ont été soulignées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2441">et</DiscourseConnective> débattues au niveau du Comité consultatif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2486">pour</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2503">et</DiscourseConnective> la santé sur le lieu de travail, créé par le Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2410" docOffset="18">
      <en>This advisory committee includes three full members for each Member State, the national governments, trade unions and employers' organisations.</en>
      <fr>Ce comité consultatif est composé de trois membres titulaires par État membre: un représentant du gouvernement, un représentant syndical des travailleurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2714">et</DiscourseConnective> un représentant des employeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
