<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>3.</en>
    <fr>3.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Financing of the Special Court for Sierra Leone</en>
    <fr>Financement du tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="35">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="51" id="146" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="51" docOffset="2">
      <en>The next item is the debate on six motions for a resolution on the financing of the Special Court for Sierra Leone.</en>
      <fr>(FR) L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur six propositions de résolution concernant le financement du tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="175">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="167" docOffset="3">
      <en>I should point out that some of our colleagues are currently in Sierra Leone to monitor the elections there.</en>
      <fr>Je vous signale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="213">que</DiscourseConnective> certains de nos collègues sont actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="261">en</DiscourseConnective> Sierra Leone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="277">pour</DiscourseConnective> y suivre les élections.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="276" id="147" name="Józef Pinior ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="276" docOffset="4">
      <en>author. - (PL) Mr President, the development of international humanitarian law, together with the establishment of courts to try perpetrators of war crimes and crimes against humanity represented a mayor achievement by the international community after the Second World War.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, l'élaboration du droit humanitaire international, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="394">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la mise en place de tribunaux chargés de juger les responsables de crimes de guerre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="488">et</DiscourseConnective> de crimes contre l'humanité constituent une grande réussite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="551">pour</DiscourseConnective> la communauté internationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="585">depuis</DiscourseConnective> la Seconde Guerre mondiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="551" docOffset="5">
      <en>The role of the aforementioned institutions has developed further in the era of globalisation, especially in areas where national leaders are unable to establish a central authority around governments based on the rule of law and ensure the fundamental security of the inhabitants concerned.</en>
      <fr>Le rôle des institutions susmentionnées a évolué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="669">à</DiscourseConnective> l'époque de la mondialisation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="702">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans les régions dont les dirigeants nationaux sont incapables de mettre en place une autorité centrale autour des gouvernements basés sur l'État de droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="867">et</DiscourseConnective> d'assurer la sécurité fondamentale des habitants concernés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="843" docOffset="6">
      <en>The Special Court for Sierra Leone is making a significant contribution to the cause of peace and justice in the Mano River region of West Africa.</en>
      <fr>Le Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="950">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone contribue de manière significative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1006">à</DiscourseConnective> la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1016">et</DiscourseConnective> à la justice dans la région de la rivière Mano en Afrique occidentale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="990" docOffset="7">
      <en>I should like to highlight the programme undertaken by the Court involving the archiving and translation of documents relating to its work.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais également mettre en avant le programme entrepris par le tribunal et prévoyant l'archivage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1191">et</DiscourseConnective> la traduction de documents liés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1226">à</DiscourseConnective> ses travaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1130" docOffset="8">
      <en>I should <Alignment alignment="1252" annotation_id="1139">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1139" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to mention the victim protection programmes it has set up.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais <Alignment alignment="1139" annotation_id="1252">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1252" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mentionner les programmes de protection des victimes qu'il a mis en place.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1208" docOffset="9">
      <en>Activities of this nature are crucial to the establishment of governments based on the rule of law in West Africa in the longer term.</en>
      <fr>Les activités de cette nature sont indispensables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1387">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place de gouvernements reposant sur l'État de droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1452">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique occidentale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1475">à</DiscourseConnective> plus long terme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1342" docOffset="10">
      <en>In today's resolution on the financing of the Special Court for Sierra Leone the European Parliament is calling on the Commission and on all European and Member State institutions to guarantee the financial basis to enable the Court to complete its work in a measured and responsible manner.</en>
      <fr>Dans la résolution d'aujourd'hui sur le financement du Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1566">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone, le Parlement européen demande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1618">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1634">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1637">à</DiscourseConnective> toutes les institutions européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1675">et</DiscourseConnective> des États membres de garantir la base financière qui permette au tribunal d'achever ses travaux de manière mesurée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1793">et</DiscourseConnective> responsable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1634" id="148" name="Ryszard Czarnecki ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1634" docOffset="11">
      <en>author. - (PL) Mr President, it so happens that the next round of parliamentary elections is due to take place in Sierra Leone this coming weekend.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, il s'avère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1858">que</DiscourseConnective> le prochain tour des élections parlementaires aura lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1918">en</DiscourseConnective> Sierra Leone le week-end prochain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1782" docOffset="12">
      <en>I cannot but express my regret that the European Parliament delegation previously planned will not be present there.</en>
      <fr>Je ne peux m'empêcher de regretter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1991">que</DiscourseConnective> la délégation du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2031">auparavant</DiscourseConnective> prévue ne puisse y prendre part.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1899" docOffset="13">
      <en>We might well ask ourselves why the Special Court for Sierra Leone is so important.</en>
      <fr>Nous pouvons nous demander pourquoi le Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2131">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2156">si</DiscourseConnective> important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1983" docOffset="14">
      <en>This is not simply a case of one more of the many African countries with a history of rape and murder.</en>
      <fr>Il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2176">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2187">simplement</DiscourseConnective> d'un des nombreux pays africains dont l'histoire est marquée par le viol <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2271">et</DiscourseConnective> le meurtre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2086" docOffset="15">
      <en>It concerns the prestige and development of the international administration of justice in the area of criminal law.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agit du prestige <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2308">et</DiscourseConnective> du développement de l'administration internationale de la justice dans le domaine du droit pénal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2203" docOffset="16">
      <en>We have recently witnessed two spectacular failures of this very system, <Alignment alignment="22638" annotation_id="2276">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2276" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we should be honest with ourselves and recognise them as such.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons récemment été les témoins de deux spectaculaires échecs de ce système, <Alignment alignment="2276" annotation_id="2491">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2491" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devrions être honnêtes avec nous-mêmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2538">et</DiscourseConnective> admettre la réalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2343" docOffset="17">
      <en>I refer to the failed attempt to sentence Slobodan Milošević and the exceedingly controversial circumstances surrounding the death of Saddam Hussein.</en>
      <fr>Je fais ici référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2584">à</DiscourseConnective> la tentative vaine de condamner Slobodan Milošević <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2637">et</DiscourseConnective> les circonstances exagérément controversées entourant la mort de Saddam Hussein.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2493" docOffset="18">
      <en>Should a further fiasco now occur in the wake of these much-publicised events, that is to say, should the Court be obliged to cease operations due to a lack of financial resources, it would amount to the coup de grâce for international administration of justice in the area of criminal law.</en>
      <fr>Doit-on assister à un nouveau fiasco dans le sillage de ces événements hautement médiatisés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2814">en d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2834">si</DiscourseConnective> le tribunal était contraint de cesser ses activités en raison d'un manque de ressources financières, ce serait le coup de grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2965">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'administration internationale de la justice dans le domaine du droit pénal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2784" docOffset="19">
      <en>To go into detail, what is at stake is the allocation of less than USD 90 million over the next two and a quarter years, with more than a third of the total to be transferred this year.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3048">Pour</DiscourseConnective> aller plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3064">en</DiscourseConnective> détail, l'enjeu est l'allocation de moins de USD 90 millions au cours de deux années <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3152">et</DiscourseConnective> un trimestre, dont plus d'un tiers sera transféré cette année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2970" docOffset="20">
      <en>This is needed in order to ensure the continued operation of the Court.</en>
      <fr>Ce montant est indispensable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3247">à</DiscourseConnective> la poursuite des activités du tribunal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3042" docOffset="21">
      <en>The prestige of the administration of cross-border justice really does depend on the Special Court for Sierra Leone sentencing Charles Taylor, the former President of Liberia, and on it investigating 17 allegations of crimes against humanity and war crimes, including murders and sexual offences.</en>
      <fr>Le prestige de l'administration de la justice transfrontalière dépend réellement du Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3390">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone chargé de juger Charles Taylor, l'ancien président du Libéria, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3474">et</DiscourseConnective> d'enquêter sur 17 allégations de crimes contre l'humanité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3535">et</DiscourseConnective> de crimes de guerre, y compris des meurtres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3582">et</DiscourseConnective> des agressions sexuelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3339" docOffset="22">
      <en>I should like publicly to thank two countries from the floor of this House, namely the United Kingdom and the Netherlands, which have provided significant financial support for the Court's activities.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3620">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier publiquement deux pays de cette Assemblée, à savoir le Royaume-Uni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3699">et</DiscourseConnective> les Pays-Bas, qui ont apporté une large contribution financière aux activités du tribunal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3540" docOffset="23">
      <en>The United Nations <Alignment alignment="3815" annotation_id="3559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3559" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> has an important role to play.</en>
      <fr>Les Nations unies ont <Alignment alignment="3559" annotation_id="3815">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3815" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un rôle clé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3837">à</DiscourseConnective> jouer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3595" docOffset="24">
      <en>It cannot behave like Pontius Pilate and simply wash its hands of the matter.</en>
      <fr>Il ne peut, à l'instar de Ponce Pilate, tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3891">simplement</DiscourseConnective> se laver les mains de cette affaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3673" docOffset="25">
      <en>I am glad that the European Parliament will speak with one voice on this issue.</en>
      <fr>Je me réjouis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3953">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen parle d'une même voix sur cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3753" id="149" name="Marios Matsakis ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3753" docOffset="26">
      <en>author. - Mr President, those who strongly support the respect for human rights - Members of this House included - have fought hard to ensure that a Special Court for Sierra Leone was set up <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3944" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> notorious killers, like Charles Taylor and his criminal mob, faced trial and punishment.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, ceux qui soutiennent fermement le respect des droits de l'homme - y compris les membres de cette Assemblée - se sont vraiment battus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4192">pour</DiscourseConnective> s'assurer de la création d'un Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4244">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone qui aura à juger des criminels connus, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4304">comme</DiscourseConnective> Charles Taylor <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4325">et</DiscourseConnective> ses complices.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4037" docOffset="27">
      <en>Those same people now view with disbelief the grim prospect that the effort to bring Charles Taylor to book may end up becoming a farce <Alignment alignment="10249" annotation_id="4173">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4173" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Special Court in The Hague ran out of money half way through the trial.</en>
      <fr>Ces mêmes personnes sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4368">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> consternées de voir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4399">que</DiscourseConnective> les efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4415">pour</DiscourseConnective> amener Charles Taylor <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4442">à</DiscourseConnective> la barre pourraient être compromis <Alignment alignment="4173" annotation_id="4479">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4479" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4509">à</DiscourseConnective> La Haye a manqué de fonds à la moitié du procès.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4257" docOffset="28">
      <en>Such an eventuality will no doubt be a serious blow to international justice <Alignment alignment="4655" annotation_id="4334">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4334" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it will make our citizens lose all faith in the rule of law and order.</en>
      <fr>Une telle éventualité sera très certainement un sérieux coup porté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4627">à</DiscourseConnective> la justice internationale <Alignment alignment="4334" annotation_id="4655">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4655" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nos citoyens perdront toute confiance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4696">en</DiscourseConnective> la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4710">et</DiscourseConnective> au respect de l'ordre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4409" docOffset="29">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24006" annotation_id="4409">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4409" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it will send a very clear encouragement to criminals worldwide to pursue without fear their evil acts of committing genocides and other despicable atrocities against humanity.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4409" annotation_id="4736">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4736" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, les criminels à travers le monde en déduiront clairement qu'ils sont libres de poursuivre leurs actes malveillants en commettant des génocides <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4889">et</DiscourseConnective> autres atrocités contre l'humanité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4598" docOffset="30">
      <en>Irrespective of the outcome of the plea to somehow keep this Special Court on Sierra Leone alive and functioning, one cannot help but raise the following issues.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4928">Nonobstant</DiscourseConnective> le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4942">résultat</DiscourseConnective> du plaidoyer visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4971">à</DiscourseConnective> maintenir, d'une manière ou d'une autre, ce Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5034">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Léone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5055">et</DiscourseConnective> à le rendre opérationnel, on ne peut s'empêcher de soulever les points suivants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4760" docOffset="31">
      <en>Firstly, the USD 89 million requested by the court to conclude its operations is surely a vast amount of money.</en>
      <fr>En premier lieu, les 89 millions de dollars exigés par le tribunal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5206">pour</DiscourseConnective> finaliser ses opérations représentent très certainement une somme élevée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4872" docOffset="32">
      <en>How come it is so vast?</en>
      <fr>Comment se fait-il que ce montant soit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5324">si</DiscourseConnective> élevé?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4896" docOffset="33">
      <en>We all know that lawyers make a bomb, but not a nuclear bomb!</en>
      <fr>Nous savons tous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5351">que</DiscourseConnective> les avocats fabriquent des bombes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5389">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas des bombes nucléaires!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4958" docOffset="34">
      <en>Could not such a court operate on a more economically efficient budget?</en>
      <fr>Un tribunal de ce type ne pourrait-il pas fonctionner sur la base d'un budget plus restreint?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5030" docOffset="35">
      <en>Are there perhaps expensive extravagances and gross inefficiencies resulting in large amounts of financial waste?</en>
      <fr>Doit-on y voir peut-être des dépenses extravagantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5567">et</DiscourseConnective> une improductivité flagrante ayant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5605">pour</DiscourseConnective> conséquence des pertes financières faramineuses?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5144" docOffset="36">
      <en>Secondly, how much did it cost for a very similar court in The Hague to try, to the extent that it did, Slobodan Milošević?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5659">En second lieu</DiscourseConnective>, combien le procès de Slobodan Milošević à-t-il coûté au tribunal de La Haye <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5751">pour</DiscourseConnective> la partie lui incombant?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5268" docOffset="37">
      <en>Was the budget <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5283" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> not subject to limitations <Alignment alignment="5813" annotation_id="5315">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5315" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> why was that so?</en>
      <fr>Le budget n'était-il pas limité <Alignment alignment="8231" annotation_id="5813">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5813" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pourquoi?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5336" docOffset="38">
      <en>Is it perhaps different to commit a crime against humanity in Europe than in Africa?</en>
      <fr>Commettre un crime contre l'humanité est peut-être différent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5887">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5900">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5421" docOffset="39">
      <en>These questions need answers, which, from my experience in this House, I know I am not going to get, <Alignment alignment="25597" annotation_id="5522">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5522" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our citizens may have to resign themselves to believing not that the rule of law holds true <Alignment alignment="27001" annotation_id="5618">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5618" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that money rules the law.</en>
      <fr>Ces questions méritent réponses. Et de par mon expérience au sein de cette Assemblée, je sais que je n'obtiendrai aucune réponse <Alignment alignment="5522" annotation_id="6041">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6041" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nos citoyens devront probablement se résigner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6090">à</DiscourseConnective> croire que ce n'est pas la règle de droit qui prévaut <Alignment alignment="5618" annotation_id="6146">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6146" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'argent en ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6166">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il règle le droit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5648" id="150" name="Bernd Posselt ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5648" docOffset="40">
      <en>author. - (DE) Mr President, West Africa was once known as a region where there was a great deal of positive development.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, l'Afrique occidentale était jadis connue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6267">comme</DiscourseConnective> une région marquée par un grand changement positif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5770" docOffset="41">
      <en>Today Sierra Leone has become a synonym for the particular horrors which we have witnessed across Africa over these past few years.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, la Sierra Leone est devenue synonyme des horreurs dont nous avons été témoins dans toute l'Afrique ces dernières années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5902" docOffset="42">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="6470" annotation_id="5905">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5905" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have a responsibility to ensure that the forthcoming elections not only help to restore democracy but also, and far more importantly, restore justice and the rule of law.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="5905" annotation_id="6470">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6470" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pour responsabilité de veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6511">que</DiscourseConnective> les prochaines élections aident <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6547">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6561">à</DiscourseConnective> restaurer la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6587">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6592">également</DiscourseConnective>, point bien plus important, à restaurer la justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6653">et</DiscourseConnective> l'État de droit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6086" docOffset="43">
      <en>This must include the prosecution of the massive crimes that have taken place in this country.</en>
      <fr>Ceci doit englober le jugement des crimes à grande échelle commis dans ce pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6181" docOffset="44">
      <en>After all, Europeans were among those who used Mr Taylor as a means by which to enrich themselves from, and in, Sierra Leone.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6753">Après tout</DiscourseConnective>, les Européens ont eux aussi utilisé M. Taylor pour s'enrichir grâce à la Sierra Leone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6851">et</DiscourseConnective> au sein <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6862">même</DiscourseConnective> de ce pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6307" docOffset="45">
      <en>That is why I believe that the process of dealing with these crimes cannot be allowed to fail due to a lack of funds.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6879">Aussi</DiscourseConnective> j'estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6894">que</DiscourseConnective> le processus de jugement de ces crimes ne peut échouer en raison d'un manque de fonds.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6425" docOffset="46">
      <en>We Europeans have a responsibility in that regard, <Alignment alignment="7040" annotation_id="6476">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6476" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I <Alignment alignment="7054" annotation_id="6482">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6482" sense="Comparison.Concession">nonetheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> believe that the questions that have been raised here are justified.</en>
      <fr>Nous, Européens, avons une responsabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7027">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="6476" annotation_id="7040">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7040" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'estime <Alignment alignment="6482" annotation_id="7054">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7054" sense="Comparison.Concession">néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7064">que</DiscourseConnective> les questions soulevées ici sont justifiées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6563" docOffset="47">
      <en>It is apparent that we will not make progress in the long term with ad hoc tribunals.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne progresserons manifestement pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7153">à</DiscourseConnective> long terme au moyen de tribunaux ad hoc.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6649" docOffset="48">
      <en>It is apparent that what we need in the long term is a single universal jurisdiction to deal with these criminal dictators.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons manifestement besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7228">à</DiscourseConnective> long terme d'une juridiction universelle unique chargée de ces dictateurs criminels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6773" docOffset="49">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7315" annotation_id="6773">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6773" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, that does not help us at the moment.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6773" annotation_id="7315">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7315" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela ne nous aide cependant pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7352">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'instant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6819" docOffset="50">
      <en>The first task now is to press ahead with the trials that have already begun and, in particular, to press ahead with securing the conviction of Mr Taylor, for that will send out a warning signal to criminals who are committing crimes against humanity today <Alignment alignment="26515" annotation_id="7076">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7076" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> who may do so in future: I would mention Zimbabwe's dictator, Mr Mugabe, in this context.</en>
      <fr>La première tâche consiste à présent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7405">à</DiscourseConnective> poursuivre de toute urgence les procès en cours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7455">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7459">notamment</DiscourseConnective> de veiller de toute urgence à la condamnation de M. Taylor, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7529">car</DiscourseConnective> cela enverra un avertissement aux responsables de crimes contre l'humanité d'aujourd'hui <Alignment alignment="7076" annotation_id="7622">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7622" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ceux qui pourraient s'y adonner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7657">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir: je citerais ici le dictateur du Zimbabwe, M. Mugabe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7169" docOffset="51">
      <en>Mr Mugabe must be shown what could happen to him <Alignment alignment="7766" annotation_id="7218">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7218" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he continues with his horrendous crimes.</en>
      <fr>M. Mugabe doit voir ce qui pourrait arriver <Alignment alignment="7218" annotation_id="7766">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7766" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il persiste à commettre ses abominables crimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7262" docOffset="52">
      <en>That is why we need uniform criteria and stable institutions to deal with these massive crimes.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle nous avons besoin de critères uniformes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7886">et</DiscourseConnective> d'institutions stables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7912">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire face à ces crimes à grande échelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7358" id="151" name="Mikel Irujo Amezaga ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7358" docOffset="53">
      <en>author. - (ES) Mr President, I was lucky enough to be part of the Election Observation Mission that participated in the elections held in August in Sierra Leone <Alignment alignment="5722" annotation_id="7519">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7519" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I must say first and foremost that we were all extremely impressed with how professionally the mission, led by my Group colleague, Mrs Isler Béguin, was run and is still being run.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (ES) Monsieur le Président, j'ai eu la chance de prendre part <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8031">à</DiscourseConnective> la mission d'observation des élections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8072">en</DiscourseConnective> Sierra Leone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8088">en</DiscourseConnective> août <Alignment alignment="7519" annotation_id="8096">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8096" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je dois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8107">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8118">dire que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons tous été extrêmement impressionnés par le professionnalisme avec lequel la mission, dirigée par ma collègue au sein du groupe, Mme Isler Béguin, a été menée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8295">et</DiscourseConnective> l'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8304">encore</DiscourseConnective> actuellement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7704" docOffset="54">
      <en>As such, I had the opportunity to be able to visit the Special Court in situ and hear directly from Mrs Mansaray, head of the Registry, about the work the Court is doing.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8328">tant que</DiscourseConnective> tel, j'ai eu l'occasion de me rendre au Tribunal spécial sur place <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8404">et</DiscourseConnective> Mme Mansaray, chef du greffe, a pu m'expliquer le travail du tribunal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7875" docOffset="55">
      <en>During the visit we were constantly told that <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7921" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> there were no justice there would be no peace.</en>
      <fr>Au cours de cette visite, nous avons constamment pu nous entendre dire que sans justice, il n'y aurait pas de paix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7971" docOffset="56">
      <en>That is precisely why this Court is so important.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8600">précisément</DiscourseConnective> pour cette raison que le tribunal est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8650">si</DiscourseConnective> important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8021" docOffset="57">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8664" annotation_id="8021">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8021" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> stated many times in this resolution, it is crucial for the continued consolidation of the peace process in Sierra Leone to ensure that the crimes do not go unpunished</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8021" annotation_id="8664">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8664" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le stipule souvent cette résolution, il est crucial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8722">pour</DiscourseConnective> la consolidation continue du processus de paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8774">en</DiscourseConnective> Sierra Leone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8790">que</DiscourseConnective> les crimes ne restent pas impunis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8192" docOffset="58">
      <en>It was very expensive <Alignment alignment="8852" annotation_id="8214">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8214" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it costs a lot of money <Alignment alignment="8884" annotation_id="8242">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8242" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Court's work has been of epic proportions; ensuring complete respect for the rule of law in a country that has been devastated by a civil war is very difficult.</en>
      <fr>Cela a coûté très cher <Alignment alignment="8214" annotation_id="8852">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8852" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela coûte encore énormément <Alignment alignment="8242" annotation_id="8884">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8884" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le travail du tribunal a pris des proportions épiques; veiller au plein respect de l'État de droit dans un pays dévasté par une guerre civile est très compliqué.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8415" docOffset="59">
      <en>The first task was to gather all the testimonies <Alignment alignment="8325" annotation_id="8464">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8464" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that was no mean feat: the population had to be convinced that there would be no reprisals <Alignment alignment="9217" annotation_id="8559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8559" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that they would not be subjected to any more humiliation.</en>
      <fr>La première mission consistait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9081">à</DiscourseConnective> recueillir des témoignages <Alignment alignment="8464" annotation_id="9110">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9110" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce ne fut pas un mince exploit: il a fallu convaincre la population qu'il n'y aurait aucune représaille <Alignment alignment="8559" annotation_id="9217">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9217" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9220">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils ne seraient plus soumis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9251">à</DiscourseConnective> des humiliations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8621" docOffset="60">
      <en>The second task was to convince the people that all those involved in human rights violations could be tried, not just the guerrilla leaders.</en>
      <fr>La deuxième mission consistait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9302">à</DiscourseConnective> convaincre les gens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9324">que</DiscourseConnective> toutes les personnes responsables de violations des droits de l'homme seraient jugées, et pas uniquement les chefs de la guérilla.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8763" docOffset="61">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9459" annotation_id="8763">
          <Alignment alignment="9459" annotation_id="8763">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8763" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, I must point out that the defence of the accused has been scrupulously respected.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8763" annotation_id="9459">
          <Alignment alignment="8763" annotation_id="9459">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9459" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, je dois ajouter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9484">que</DiscourseConnective> la défense des accusés a été scrupuleusement respectée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8858" docOffset="62">
      <en>The Court <Alignment alignment="34379" annotation_id="8868">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8868" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> took a historic decision in 2004 to refuse to recognise the applicability of a national amnesty for the perpetrators of war crimes and crimes against humanity.</en>
      <fr>Le tribunal a <Alignment alignment="8868" annotation_id="9558">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9558" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pris une décision historique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9597">en</DiscourseConnective> 2004 et refusé de reconnaître l'applicabilité d'une amnistie nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9671">pour</DiscourseConnective> les responsables de crimes de guerre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9713">et</DiscourseConnective> de crimes contre l'humanité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9033" docOffset="63">
      <en>Without justice then, there is no peace.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9745">Sans</DiscourseConnective> justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9758">donc</DiscourseConnective>, il ne peut y avoir de paix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9074" docOffset="64">
      <en>It is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9080" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> important to contribute to the funding of this Court.</en>
      <fr>Aussi est-il important de contribuer au financement de ce tribunal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9139" docOffset="65">
      <en>We are obliged to contribute towards peace and stability in the Mano River region.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes obligés de contribuer à la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9904">et</DiscourseConnective> à la stabilité dans la région de la rivière Mano.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9222" docOffset="66">
      <en>The Special Court is itself an example for the reform of Sierra Leone's judicial system <Alignment alignment="10056" annotation_id="9310">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9310" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would call on the Commission here to look into the possibility of providing financial support for the projects carried out by the United Nations with a view to reforming the country's judicial system.</en>
      <fr>Le Tribunal spécial est lui-même un exemple de la réforme du système judiciaire de la Sierra Leone <Alignment alignment="9310" annotation_id="10056">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10056" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je demanderais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10074">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission ici présente d'envisager la possibilité d'une aide financière aux projets menés par les Nations unies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10192">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> réformer le système judiciaire du pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9517" id="152" name="Tadeusz Zwiefka">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9517" docOffset="67">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (PL) Mr President, the Special Court for Sierra Leone is entitled to count on our particular attention, <Alignment alignment="10371" annotation_id="9654">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9654" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is rightly presented as a new and almost perfect model for the pursuit of justice.</en>
      <fr>au nom du PPE-DE. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, le Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10310">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone peut compter sur toute notre attention, <Alignment alignment="9654" annotation_id="10371">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10371" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il est à juste titre présenté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10408">comme</DiscourseConnective> un modèle nouveau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10432">et</DiscourseConnective> presque parfait de quête de justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9743" docOffset="68">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="31707" annotation_id="9743">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9743" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it has proved that an international court dealing with war crimes may be located in the country where those crimes were committed, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9887" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> allowing local people to have direct access to justice.</en>
      <fr>Il a <Alignment alignment="9743" annotation_id="10477">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10477" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> prouvé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10497">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un tribunal international traitant de crimes de guerre pouvait se situer dans un pays où ces crimes ont été commis, permettant ainsi à la population locale d'accéder directement à la justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9948" docOffset="69">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10692" annotation_id="9948">
          <Alignment alignment="10692" annotation_id="9948">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9948" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="22254" annotation_id="9961">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9961" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Special Court for Sierra Leone is compared with similar bodies in other parts of the world, it can be seen that this arrangement has allowed the Court to be fully effective whilst incurring significantly lower costs.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9948" annotation_id="10692">
          <Alignment alignment="9948" annotation_id="10692">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10692" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="9961" annotation_id="10701">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10701" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'on compare le Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10737">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10758">à</DiscourseConnective> des organes similaires dans d'autres coins de la planète, on constate <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10830">que</DiscourseConnective> cette situation a permis au tribunal d'être pleinement efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10898">tout en</DiscourseConnective> réduisant significativement les coûts.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10185" docOffset="70">
      <en>For the first time in history an incumbent head of state of an African country, Charles Taylor, has been successfully convicted of crimes against humanity.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10945">Pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois, un chef d'État d'un pays africain, Charles Taylor, a été jugé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11030">pour</DiscourseConnective> crimes contre l'humanité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10341" docOffset="71">
      <en>It has <Alignment alignment="14713" annotation_id="10348">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10348" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> proved possible to establish a legal definition of the notion of child soldiers and forced marriages, <Alignment alignment="11182" annotation_id="10455">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10455" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10458" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> to enable those guilty of such crimes to be convicted.</en>
      <fr>Il a <Alignment alignment="10812" annotation_id="11066">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11066" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> été possible de procéder à une définition juridique de la notion d'enfants-soldats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11159">et</DiscourseConnective> de mariages forcés, <Alignment alignment="10455" annotation_id="11182">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11182" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> permettre la condamnation des responsables de ces crimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10516" docOffset="72">
      <en>The Special Court for Sierra Leone may unfortunately have to cease its operations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10598" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> it is running out of funds.</en>
      <fr>Le Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11268">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone pourrait hélas être contraint de cesser ses activités étant donné le manque de fonds.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10629" docOffset="73">
      <en>The sum required to allow proceedings against the most notorious criminals to continue is less than USD 90 million.</en>
      <fr>Le montant nécessaire à la poursuite des criminels les plus notoires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11444">s'</DiscourseConnective>élève <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11452">à moins de</DiscourseConnective> USD 90 millions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10745" docOffset="74">
      <en>I hereby call on all the Member States and on the Commission to provide funds to support the Special Court for Sierra Leone as soon as possible.</en>
      <fr>J'invite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11489">dès lors</DiscourseConnective> tous les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11521">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11538">à</DiscourseConnective> allouer des fonds <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11558">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> soutenir le Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11597">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone dans les plus brefs délais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10890" docOffset="75">
      <en>Continuation of the peace process and reconciliation in Sierra Leone and the whole of West Africa will be seriously threatened <Alignment alignment="11784" annotation_id="11017">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11017" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> funding for the Court does not become available.</en>
      <fr>La poursuite du processus de paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11680">et</DiscourseConnective> de réconciliation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11701">en</DiscourseConnective> Sierra Leone <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11717">et</DiscourseConnective> dans l'ensemble de l'Afrique occidentale sera gravement menacée <Alignment alignment="11017" annotation_id="11784">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11784" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le tribunal ne dispose pas du financement nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11069" id="153" name="Genowefa Grabowska">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11069" docOffset="76">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (PL) Mr President, Commissioner, I fully support all those who have appealed for this job to be seen through to the end and for justice to de dispensed in Sierra Leone.</en>
      <fr>au nom du PSE. - (PL) Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, je soutiens pleinement tous ceux qui ont demandé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11958">que</DiscourseConnective> cette tâche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11974">soit</DiscourseConnective> menée à bien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11992">et</DiscourseConnective> en ont appelé à l'application de la justice en Sierra Leone.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11268" docOffset="77">
      <en>This simply must happen.</en>
      <fr>Cela doit tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12071">simplement</DiscourseConnective> devenir une réalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11293" docOffset="78">
      <en>The perpetrators of crimes cannot be allowed to believe that they will enjoy impunity, regardless of where they may reside, be it in Europe, in Africa or in any other part of the world.</en>
      <fr>On ne peut laisser croire aux responsables de crimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12156">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils jouiront de l'impunité, où qu'ils vivent, que ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12212">soit</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12217">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12228">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12239">ou</DiscourseConnective> ailleurs dans le monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11479" docOffset="79">
      <en>I should, <Alignment alignment="12277" annotation_id="11489">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11489" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, like to take this opportunity to highlight a particular problem, which I believe to be very significant.</en>
      <fr>J'aimerais <Alignment alignment="11489" annotation_id="12277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12277" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> profiter de cette opportunité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12317">pour</DiscourseConnective> mettre en avant un problème particulier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12363">que</DiscourseConnective> j'estime très significatif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11603" docOffset="80">
      <en>We are witnessing a proliferation of courts established by the United Nations, a kind of mushrooming of criminal courts.</en>
      <fr>Nous assistons à la prolifération des tribunaux mis en place par les Nations unies, une sorte d'éclosion de tribunaux pénaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11724" docOffset="81">
      <en>An International Criminal Court was set up in Rome.</en>
      <fr>Un tribunal pénal international a été mis en place <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12572">à</DiscourseConnective> Rome.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11776" docOffset="82">
      <en>An International Criminal Tribunal to deal with the crimes that took place in the former Yugoslavia was <Alignment alignment="12657" annotation_id="11880">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11880" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> set up, <Alignment alignment="12685" annotation_id="11893">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11893" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> another to deal with the crimes committed in Rwanda.</en>
      <fr>Un tribunal pénal international chargé des crimes commis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12637">en</DiscourseConnective> ex-Yougoslavie a <Alignment alignment="11880" annotation_id="12657">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12657" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> été mis en place, <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="12685">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12685" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un autre est chargé des crimes commis au Rwanda.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11950" docOffset="83">
      <en>Now we have the Special Court for Sierra Leone.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons à présent le Tribunal spécial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12778">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Sierra Leone.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11998" docOffset="84">
      <en>I appreciate that all these courts are necessary, <Alignment alignment="12844" annotation_id="12048">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12048" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="12849" annotation_id="12052">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12052" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are to be established their funding must be guaranteed from the outset.</en>
      <fr>Je reconnais la nécessité de ces tribunaux, <Alignment alignment="12048" annotation_id="12844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12844" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="13045" annotation_id="12849">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12849" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils sont mis en place, il faut en assurer le financement dès le départ.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12132" docOffset="85">
      <en>That is a sine qua non.</en>
      <fr>C'est là une condition sine qua non.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12156" docOffset="86">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="12969" annotation_id="12158">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12158" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> call on the Commissioner to raise the matter of financing such institutions at the forthcoming EU-Africa summit, due to take place before the end of this year.</en>
      <fr>J'invite <Alignment alignment="9392" annotation_id="12969">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12969" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la commissaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12999">à</DiscourseConnective> soulever la question du financement de ces institutions lors du prochain sommet UE-Afrique, prévu à la fin de cette année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12328" docOffset="87">
      <en>These institutions are necessary and must be properly funded.</en>
      <fr>Ces institutions sont indispensables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13161">et</DiscourseConnective> doivent être correctement financées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12390" docOffset="88">
      <en>It is embarrassing to have to discuss sums of this nature.</en>
      <fr>Il est embarrassant de débattre de telles sommes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12449" id="154" name="Viviane Reding">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12449" docOffset="89">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the European Commission is strongly committed to assisting in the transition of Sierra Leone from a situation of post-conflict to one of development and to support its efforts in sustaining peace, stability and democracy.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, la Commission européenne est fermement engagée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13353">à</DiscourseConnective> apporter son soutien à la Sierra Léone afin qu'elle effectue la transition lui permettant de passer d'un contexte post-conflictuel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13486">à</DiscourseConnective> un contexte visant à réaliser le développement. Elle consolide par ailleurs le maintien de la paix, de la stabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13604">et</DiscourseConnective> de la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12713" docOffset="90">
      <en>We have fully supported past, current and future actions of the Court in bringing perpetrators of war crimes to justice, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12834" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> recognising the suffering of the Sierra Leoneans during the civil war.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons réellement apporté notre aide au Tribunal afin qu'il puisse traduire en justice les criminels de guerre, que ce soit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13753">pour</DiscourseConnective> des affaires passées, présentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13790">et</DiscourseConnective> à venir. Ces actions permettent d'admettre la souffrance des Sierra léonais durant la guerre civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12910" docOffset="91">
      <en>The work of the Special Court sends an important signal to everyone that serious crimes against humanity, genocide and war crimes will no longer remain unpunished, no matter where they have taken place.</en>
      <fr>Le travail du Tribunal spécial est un avertissement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13946">pour</DiscourseConnective> chacun: les crimes graves contre l'humanité, les génocides <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14010">et</DiscourseConnective> les crimes de guerre ne resteront désormais pas impunis, quel que soit l'endroit où ils sont perpétrés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13113" docOffset="92">
      <en>The Commission has been providing financial assistance to the court since 2002.</en>
      <fr>La Commission apporte son soutien financier au Tribunal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14173">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 2002.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13193" docOffset="93">
      <en>This assistance was granted indirectly in 2002, by supporting the project worth almost EUR 685 000 through a coalition of NGOs led by No Peace Without Justice to identify human rights violations, to raise awareness among the legal profession and to provide legal assistance to the Government of Sierra Leone.</en>
      <fr>Ces fonds ont été attribués de manière indirecte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14235">en</DiscourseConnective> 2002, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14244">en</DiscourseConnective> appui au projet évalué à environ 685 000 euros par le biais d'un consortium d'ONG sous la tutelle de l'organisation No Peace Without Justice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14388">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>identifier les abus infligés aux droits de l'homme, de susciter la prise de conscience au sein de la profession juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14517">et</DiscourseConnective> d'apporter une aide juridique au gouvernement de la Sierra Léone.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13502" docOffset="94">
      <en>Since 2003, the Commission has provided the funds to the Special Court directly, through the European Initiative for Democracy and Human Rights <Alignment alignment="14741" annotation_id="13646">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13646" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> already mentioned.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14586">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> 2003, la Commission a financé directement le Tribunal spécial, par le biais de l'Initiative européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14696">pour</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14715">et</DiscourseConnective> les droits de l'homme, <Alignment alignment="13646" annotation_id="14741">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14741" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> précédemment indiqué.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13668" docOffset="95">
      <en>An overall budget of about EUR 2.1 million has been allocated to the Court by means of three Victims' Justice and Legacy projects.</en>
      <fr>Un budget <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14779">total</DiscourseConnective> d'environ 2,1 millions d'euros a été alloué au Tribunal par le biais de trois projets visant à rendre justice aux victimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14908">et</DiscourseConnective> à leurs mémoires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13799" docOffset="96">
      <en>The overall objective of these projects was inter alia to ensure that the Special Court contributes to a broader understanding of justice for victims of the conflict.</en>
      <fr>L'objectif global des ces projets était, entre autres, de s'assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14997">que</DiscourseConnective> le Tribunal spécial contribue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15031">à</DiscourseConnective> une prise de conscience accrue de ce qu'est la justice aux victimes du conflit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13966" docOffset="97">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="15996" annotation_id="13966">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13966" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in 2006, the emphasis was given to the coverage and proximity of Charles Taylor's trial <Alignment alignment="15221" annotation_id="14064">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14064" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it targeted civil society groups as well as the people of Liberia and the subregion.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13966" annotation_id="15113">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15113" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15123">en</DiscourseConnective> 2006, la couverture médiatique du procès de Charles Taylor <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15185">et</DiscourseConnective> de son entourage était amplifiée <Alignment alignment="14064" annotation_id="15221">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15221" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle s'attachait par ailleurs à prendre en considération les groupes de civils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15303">autant</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15310">que</DiscourseConnective> les habitants du Libéria <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15339">et</DiscourseConnective> des sous-régions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14153" docOffset="98">
      <en>The Special Court will be supported in 2008 by the new European Instrument for Democracy and Human Rights, which was adopted in the context of the new Financial Framework 2007-2013.</en>
      <fr>Le Tribunal spécial recevra le soutien, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15400">en</DiscourseConnective> 2008, du nouvel Instrument européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15439">pour</DiscourseConnective> la promotion de la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15474">et</DiscourseConnective> des droits de l'homme, qui a été adopté dans le cadre de la nouvelle perspective financière 2007-2013.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14335" docOffset="99">
      <en>The amount of EUR 600 000 has been reserved in the annual action plan from the 2007 budget.</en>
      <fr>Un montant de 600 000 euros a été attribué dans le plan d'action annuel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15652">pour</DiscourseConnective> le budget 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14427" docOffset="100">
      <en>The Commission is holding the talks with the Court to identify the project proposal for the 2007 funding.</en>
      <fr>La Commission poursuit le dialogue avec le Tribunal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15725">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>identifier le projet de financement pour 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14533" docOffset="101">
      <en>It has been said several times by different Members that there are difficulties to find sufficient means for financing the Special Court.</en>
      <fr>Un certain nombre de membres ont indiqué à plusieurs reprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15841">que</DiscourseConnective> des difficultés subsistent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15872">quant à</DiscourseConnective> l'obtention de fonds suffisants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15912">pour</DiscourseConnective> financer le Tribunal spécial.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14671" docOffset="102">
      <en>That is why the Commission is considering raising this matter with the Member States <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14756" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it is <Alignment alignment="16066" annotation_id="14766">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14766" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> exploring the possibility of financing the Court and its outreach activities through other financial instruments.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle la Commission envisage de soulever cette question auprès des États membres; elle examine <Alignment alignment="14766" annotation_id="16066">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16066" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la possibilité de financer le Tribunal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16118">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que ses activités de proximité par le biais d'instruments financiers autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14885" id="155" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14885" docOffset="103">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14907" docOffset="104">
      <en>The vote is due to take place at the end of the debates, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14964" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective> in just a moment.</en>
      <fr>Le vote est prévu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16238">à</DiscourseConnective> l'issue des débats, c'est-à-dire dans un instant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
