<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Conservation of fisheries resources through technical measures (debate)</en>
    <fr>Conservation des ressources halieutiques par des mesures techniques (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="72" id="212" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="72" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Mr Visser, on behalf of the Committee on Fisheries, on the proposal for a Council regulation concerning the conservation of fisheries resources through technical measures - C6-0282/2008 -.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de Cornelis Visser, au nom de la commission de la pêche, sur la proposition de règlement du Conseil relatif à la conservation des ressources halieutiques par des mesures techniques - C6-0282/2008 -.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="292" id="213" language="ES" name="Carmen Fraga Estévez">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="292" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, I wish to thank the rapporteur for highlighting some of the main concerns raised by the Commission's proposal.</en>
      <fr>rapporteure suppléante. - (ES) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais remercier le rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="400">pour</DiscourseConnective> avoir pointé du doigt certaines des principales inquiétudes soulevées par la proposition de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="417" docOffset="3">
      <en>One is the new tendency to regulate individual areas of issues that are pillars of the common policy.</en>
      <fr>La première source d'inquiétude est cette nouvelle tendance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="572">à</DiscourseConnective> vouloir réglementer individuellement certains domaines qui sont des piliers de la politique commune.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="519" docOffset="4">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12659" annotation_id="519">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="519" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this approach may, in theory, be understandable in the case of technical measures, we must be very careful to make sure that subsequent regional regulations are limited to aspects relating solely to the application and regulation of technical details.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="519" annotation_id="675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="675" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="684">en</DiscourseConnective> théorie, on peut considérer qu'une telle approche est justifiable dans le cas des mesures techniques, nous devons être très prudents et veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="836">que</DiscourseConnective> les règlementations nationales qui s'ensuivront se limiteront strictement aux aspects d'application <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="940">et</DiscourseConnective> de réglementation de détails techniques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="777" docOffset="5">
      <en>I mention this <Alignment alignment="996" annotation_id="792">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="792" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> drawing up framework regulations containing minimum measures which are <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="871" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> followed by different laws for individual areas is, together with an increasing tendency to turn to comitology, one of the options the Commission is prepared to take <Alignment alignment="2078" annotation_id="1042">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1042" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> faced with the prospect of a codecision procedure on fisheries, as the Directorate-General for Maritime Affairs and Fisheries itself freely admits in the Green Paper on the reform of the Common Fisheries Policy.</en>
      <fr>Je dis cela <Alignment alignment="792" annotation_id="996">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="996" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'élaboration de règlements cadres prévoyant des mesures minimales devant être complétées par différentes réglementations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1128">en</DiscourseConnective> fonction des domaines, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1154">au même titre que</DiscourseConnective> la tendance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1184">à</DiscourseConnective> recourir de plus en plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1211">à</DiscourseConnective> la comitologie, fait partie des options envisagées par la Commission <Alignment alignment="1042" annotation_id="1282">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1282" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la pêche venait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1301">à</DiscourseConnective> être soumise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1316">à</DiscourseConnective> la procédure de codécision. Cela, la direction générale des affaires maritimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1397">et</DiscourseConnective> de la pêche l'admet ouvertement dans son Livre vert sur la réforme de la politique commune de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1257" docOffset="6">
      <en>We should <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1267" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> bear in mind that it is not an ordinary policy we are talking about here, but a common policy, which requires total clarity as regards what may be involved in a more or less covert handing-over of control to Member States <Alignment alignment="1751" annotation_id="1494">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1494" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an excessive territorialisation of what should be common rules intended not to disrupt competition and to avoid discrimination among fleets.</en>
      <fr>N'oublions pas non plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1528">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ne s'agit pas ici d'une politique ordinaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1579">mais</DiscourseConnective> bien d'une politique commune. Il faut donc lever toute ambiguïté concernant les implications de tout transfert, plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1701">ou</DiscourseConnective> moins dissimulé, du contrôle aux États membres <Alignment alignment="1494" annotation_id="1751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1751" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de toute territorialisation excessive de ce qui devrait être des règles communes visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1842">à</DiscourseConnective> garantir la concurrence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1868">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1871">à</DiscourseConnective> éviter toute discrimination entre les flottes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1638" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1920" annotation_id="1638">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1638" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="11020" annotation_id="1649">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1649" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it may be reasonable for very local species to have their minimum size regulated by regional regulations, those cases should make up the lowest number; minimum sizes in general, like measurements of nets or criteria according to which catches can be unloaded and sold, should be universal and adopted by the Council and Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1638" annotation_id="1920">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1920" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="1649" annotation_id="1927">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1927" sense="Comparison.Contrast">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il peut être censé de réglementer au niveau régional la taille minimale de certaines espèces très locales, cela doit néanmoins rester l'exception. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2076">En</DiscourseConnective> règle générale, les tailles minimales, s'agissant par exemple des filets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2152">ou</DiscourseConnective> des critères concernant les prises pouvant être débarquées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2214">et</DiscourseConnective> vendues, doivent être universelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2252">et</DiscourseConnective> adoptées par le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2279">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1987" docOffset="8">
      <en>Some of the main changes introduced by the Committee on Fisheries <Alignment alignment="15744" annotation_id="2053">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2053" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> move in that direction, trying to limit any application of the comitology procedure to details alone and insisting that the Council should have rules at its disposal in order to establish seasonal closures, net dimensions and measures to eliminate or reduce discards, for we understand that all Community fisheries have to be bound by certain rules that are the same for everyone.</en>
      <fr>Certains des principaux changements proposés par la commission de la pêche vont <Alignment alignment="2053" annotation_id="2376">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2376" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans ce sens et tentent de limiter l'application de la procédure de comitologie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2466">à</DiscourseConnective> de seuls points de détail, tout en insistant sur la nécessité pour le Conseil de disposer d'instruments réglementaires lui permettant de fixer des périodes de fermeture saisonnières, la taille des filets, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2673">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que des mesures permettant d'éliminer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2717">ou</DiscourseConnective> de réduire les rejets. En effet, selon nous, toutes les pêcheries de la Communauté doivent être tenues de respecter certaines règles communes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2439" docOffset="9">
      <en>It should be remembered that the only truly communitised aspect of this policy that we call 'common' is access to markets, <Alignment alignment="9080" annotation_id="2562">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2562" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the conservation and management policy - let us stop calling it a control policy - leaves certain room for manoeuvre that Member States generally have no qualms in using to the benefit of their fleets and to the detriment of those of others.</en>
      <fr>N'oublions pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2878">que</DiscourseConnective> la seule dimension véritablement communautarisée de cette politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2950">que</DiscourseConnective> nous appelons "commune" est l'accès aux marchés, <Alignment alignment="983" annotation_id="3003">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3003" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la politique de conservation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3043">et</DiscourseConnective> de gestion - cessons de l'appeler politique de contrôle - laisse, elle, certaines marges de manœuvre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3148">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres n'hésitent généralement pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3198">à</DiscourseConnective> utiliser au bénéfice de leurs flottes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3238">et</DiscourseConnective> au détriment de celles des autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2810" docOffset="10">
      <en>We have just witnessed the Commission's strong commitment to communitising and standardising control, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2912" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> it would prove difficult to understand the way in which the remaining measures serve, <Alignment alignment="3467" annotation_id="3002">
          <Alignment alignment="3467" annotation_id="3002">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3002" sense="Comparison.Contrast">on the contrary</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, to break up and fragment that control, or the fact that different rules are created for the same activity, depending on where it is carried out.</en>
      <fr>La Commission, comme nous venons de l'entendre, dit être toute acquise à la communautarisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3371">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'harmonisation du contrôle. Comment dès lors expliquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3432">que</DiscourseConnective> les mesures restantes servent, <Alignment alignment="3303" annotation_id="3467">
          <Alignment alignment="3002" annotation_id="3467">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3467" sense="Comparison.Contrast">au contraire</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3481">à</DiscourseConnective> démanteler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3494">et</DiscourseConnective> à fragmenter ce contrôle?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>

<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3165" docOffset="12">
      <en>This jeopardises the entire credibility of the Common Fisheries Policy and its own future as such, something that should not be assumed before the 2012 reform.</en>
      <fr>Ceci menace la crédibilité globale de la politique commune de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3723">et</DiscourseConnective> son avenir sous cette forme, dont on ne peut préjuger <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3780">tant que</DiscourseConnective> ne sera pas adoptée la réforme de 2012.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3325" docOffset="13">
      <en>Finally, with regard to the controversial 'one net' rule, I believe that Parliament has offered the Commission a good alternative approach, indicating in which cases this may be unviable; it should, <Alignment alignment="9821" annotation_id="3524">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3524" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, be acceptable to take more than one fishing net on board.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3829">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3836">s'</DiscourseConnective>agissant de la controversée règle du "filet unique", je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3900">que</DiscourseConnective> l'approche proposée par le Parlement à la Commission constitue une bonne solution de remplacement. Cette approche consiste à énumérer les cas dans lesquels il ne serait pas viable d'appliquer une telle règle et où l'on pourrait <Alignment alignment="3524" annotation_id="4132">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4132" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> admettre le transport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4159">de plus</DiscourseConnective> d'un filet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4178">à</DiscourseConnective> bord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3593" docOffset="14">
      <en>Hence, I hope the Commission can show sensitivity to what are clearly major concerns for the fishing industry and our own Committee on Fisheries.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4195">donc</DiscourseConnective> que la Commission se montrera sensible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4239">à</DiscourseConnective> ce qui sont clairement des préoccupations majeures du secteur de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4315">et</DiscourseConnective> de notre propre commission de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3739" id="214" name="Joe Borg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3739" docOffset="15">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, let me express my thanks to the rapporteur, Mr Visser, Ms Fraga and the Fisheries Committee for the draft report on the Commission's proposal for technical measures for the Atlantic and the North Sea.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, permettez-moi d'adresser mes remerciements au rapporteur, M. Visser, à Mme Fraga <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4494">et</DiscourseConnective> à la commission de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4525">pour</DiscourseConnective> le projet de rapport sur la proposition de la Commission d'instaurer des mesures techniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4622">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Atlantique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4640">et</DiscourseConnective> la mer du Nord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3982" docOffset="16">
      <en>This is a very technical file and, <Alignment alignment="4701" annotation_id="4017">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4017" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you are aware, technical conservation measures in the Atlantic <Alignment alignment="4779" annotation_id="4083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4083" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the North Sea originate to a large extent from existing rules.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4662">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un dossier très technique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4697">et</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="1660" annotation_id="4701">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4701" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez, les mesures techniques de conservation dans l'Atlantique <Alignment alignment="4083" annotation_id="4779">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4779" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la mer du Nord trouvent largement leur origine dans la réglementation déjà existante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4150" docOffset="17">
      <en>In Community legislation the measures are spread out in different regulations: the 1998 general technical measures regulation for the Atlantic and the North Sea; the additional technical measures regulation for the recovery of cod and hake; and the annual TAC and quota regulation, which <Alignment alignment="30968" annotation_id="4438">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4438" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> contains a number of technical conservation measures.</en>
      <fr>Dans la législation communautaire, ces mesures sont réparties entre plusieurs règlements: le règlement de 1998 sur les mesures techniques générales destinées à l'Atlantique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5041">et</DiscourseConnective> à la mer du Nord; le règlement supplémentaire prévoyant des mesures techniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5123">pour</DiscourseConnective> la reconstitution du stock de cabillaud <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5168">et</DiscourseConnective> de merluche; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5184">enfin</DiscourseConnective>, le TAC annuel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5205">et</DiscourseConnective> la réglementation en matière de quotas, qui contient <Alignment alignment="4438" annotation_id="5261">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5261" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un certain nombre de mesures techniques de conservation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4497" docOffset="18">
      <en>Apart from this legal complexity, the present rules are in some cases very complicated and difficult to implement and control.</en>
      <fr>Outre cette complexité juridique, les règles actuelles sont parfois très compliquées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5413">et</DiscourseConnective> difficiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5427">à</DiscourseConnective> mettre en œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5445">et</DiscourseConnective> à contrôler.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4624" docOffset="19">
      <en>The Commission adopted the proposal for a new Regulation on technical conservation measures for the Atlantic on 4 June of last year.</en>
      <fr>La Commission a adopté le 4 juin de l'année dernière la proposition de nouveau règlement relatif aux mesures techniques de conservation des ressources <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5612">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Atlantique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4757" docOffset="20">
      <en>The proposal was drafted after extensive consultation of stakeholders and Member States during 2006 and 2007.</en>
      <fr>Cette proposition avait été élaborée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5668">après</DiscourseConnective> consultation étendue des différents acteurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5718">et</DiscourseConnective> des États membres au cours de 2006 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5756">et</DiscourseConnective> 2007.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4867" docOffset="21">
      <en>It groups together all the relevant rules into one single legislative act, which will <Alignment alignment="17788" annotation_id="4953">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4953" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> improve legal consistency.</en>
      <fr>Elle regroupe toutes les règles pertinentes au sein d'un seul acte législatif, qui améliorera <Alignment alignment="4953" annotation_id="5859">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5859" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la cohérence juridique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4990" docOffset="22">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3308" annotation_id="4990">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4990" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the proposal seeks to simplify, clarify and streamline the various rules.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4990" annotation_id="5898">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5898" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la proposition cherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5935">à</DiscourseConnective> simplifier, à clarifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5961">et</DiscourseConnective> à rationaliser les différentes réglementations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5077" docOffset="23">
      <en>Special attention has been paid to simplifying onboard inspections and reducing the costs for fishermen.</en>
      <fr>Une attention toute particulière a été accordée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6060">à</DiscourseConnective> la simplification des inspections à bord des navires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6115">et</DiscourseConnective> à la réduction des coûts supportés par les pêcheurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5182" docOffset="24">
      <en>There are <Alignment alignment="16575" annotation_id="5192">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5192" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> some additional rules to reduce discards, such as the establishment of a legal framework for real-time closures, already applied in the North Sea.</en>
      <fr>Il y a <Alignment alignment="4968" annotation_id="6178">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6178" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> quelques règles supplémentaires visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6223">à</DiscourseConnective> réduire les rejets, telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6252">que</DiscourseConnective> la création d'un cadre juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6289">pour</DiscourseConnective> les fermetures avec effet immédiat, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6330">déjà</DiscourseConnective> appliqué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6344">en</DiscourseConnective> mer du Nord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5344" docOffset="25">
      <en>A new decision-making structure is being proposed, using a Council-level decision for the general and essential provisions and comitology for the more detailed and technical region-specific provisions, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5546" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective> avoiding micro-management at a political level.</en>
      <fr>Une nouvelle structure décisionnelle est proposée, et celle-ci utilise une décision prise au niveau du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6471">pour</DiscourseConnective> les dispositions générales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6503">et</DiscourseConnective> essentielles, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6520">et</DiscourseConnective> la comitologie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6538">pour</DiscourseConnective> les dispositions plus détaillées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6576">et</DiscourseConnective> techniques spécifiques aux régions, évitant ainsi la micro-gestion au niveau politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5602" docOffset="26">
      <en>This new approach is not supported in your report, where Amendments 1, 6, 7, 25 and 26 call for Council regulations both for general and for detailed technical rules.</en>
      <fr>Cette nouvelle approche n'est pas soutenue dans votre rapport, où les amendements 1, 6, 7, 25 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6761">et</DiscourseConnective> 26 appellent à l'adoption de règlements du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6815">pour</DiscourseConnective> les règles générales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6841">comme pour</DiscourseConnective> les règles techniques détaillées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5769" docOffset="27">
      <en>The Commission, particularly in the framework of the CFP reform, does not want to continue with micro-management measures at a political level.</en>
      <fr>La Commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6901">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans le cadre de la réforme de la PCP, ne souhaite pas conserver les mesures de micro-gestion au niveau politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5913" docOffset="28">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12244" annotation_id="5913">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5913" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, taking into account the point made in the report regarding comitology, the Commission is ready to study any procedure which, <Alignment alignment="14503" annotation_id="6047">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6047" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> maintaining comitology for regional technical rules, will enable the raising at Council level of any matter which appears to be essential or political.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5913" annotation_id="7026">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7026" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, en tenant compte de l'observation formulée dans le rapport concernant la comitologie, la Commission est prête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7147">à</DiscourseConnective> étudier toute procédure qui, <Alignment alignment="7876" annotation_id="7178">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7178" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7186">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> la comitologie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7212">pour</DiscourseConnective> les règles techniques à usage régional, permettra d'évoquer au niveau du Conseil tout thème qui paraîtrait fondamental <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7336">ou</DiscourseConnective> de nature politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6205" docOffset="29">
      <en>The Commission can partially accept Amendments 2 and 3, relating to additional illustrations of fishing gears, <Alignment alignment="4315" annotation_id="6316">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6316" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> needed, and to certain specific market provisions, particularly on the minimum size of species, with the aim of harmonising measures.</en>
      <fr>La Commission peut accepter partiellement les amendements 2 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7420">et</DiscourseConnective> 3 relatifs aux illustrations supplémentaires des engins de pêche, <Alignment alignment="6316" annotation_id="7489">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7489" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7503">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7506">à</DiscourseConnective> certaines conditions spécifiques en termes de marché, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7562">notamment en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la taille minimale des espèces, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7623">dans le but d'</DiscourseConnective>harmoniser les mesures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6453" docOffset="30">
      <en>In line with discard policy, the Commission is proposing new rules about real-time closures and moving-on provisions for specific fisheries in order to reduce discarding practices.</en>
      <fr>Conformément à sa politique en matière de rejets, la Commission propose de nouvelles règles relatives aux fermetures avec effet immédiat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7798">et</DiscourseConnective> aux dispositions en matière de poursuite des activités concernant certaines formes de pêche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7894">afin de</DiscourseConnective> réduire l'importance des pratiques de rejet en mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6634" docOffset="31">
      <en>Both measures are considered to be efficient tools and, in order to reduce discards, are important in order to allow for a switch from rules dealing with landings to provisions on real catches.</en>
      <fr>Ces deux mesures sont considérées comme des outils efficaces <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8015">et</DiscourseConnective>, dans la perspective d'une réduction du volume des rejets, elles sont importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8100">en vue d'</DiscourseConnective>abandonner les règles traitant les débarquements de prises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8168">pour</DiscourseConnective> passer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8180">à</DiscourseConnective> des dispositions portant sur les captures réelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6828" docOffset="32">
      <en>For that reason, the Commission cannot accept Amendments 4, 5, 21, 23 and 24.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8233">Pour</DiscourseConnective> cette raison, la Commission ne peut pas accepter les amendements 4, 5, 21, 23 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8316">et</DiscourseConnective> 24.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6906" docOffset="33">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8323" annotation_id="6906">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6906" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Amendment 20, only in so far <Alignment alignment="5415" annotation_id="6944">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6944" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it calls for 'quantity' to be replaced by 'weight' to define the level of by-catch, is acceptable.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6906" annotation_id="8323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8323" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'amendement 20, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8351">pour</DiscourseConnective> la seule raison <Alignment alignment="6944" annotation_id="8372">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8372" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il appelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8386">à</DiscourseConnective> remplacer la "quantité" par le "poids" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8427">pour</DiscourseConnective> définir le volume des prises accessoires, est acceptable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7046" docOffset="34">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8490" annotation_id="7046">
          <Alignment alignment="35713" annotation_id="7046">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7046" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> we can positively consider the second part of the amendment regarding the derogations on distance.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7046" annotation_id="8490">
          <Alignment alignment="7046" annotation_id="8490">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8490" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, nous pouvons envisager positivement la deuxième partie de l'amendement concernant les dérogations en matière de distance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7157" docOffset="35">
      <en>The parameters of such a derogation, <Alignment alignment="35331" annotation_id="7194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7194" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, would have to be studied in some detail and will be laid out in the implementing regulation.</en>
      <fr>Les paramètres d'une telle dérogation mériteraient <Alignment alignment="7194" annotation_id="8677">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8677" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'être étudiés de manière plus détaillée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8729">et</DiscourseConnective> seront exposés dans le règlement d'exécution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7296" docOffset="36">
      <en>The Commission, mainly for inspection purposes, intends to implement the one-net-rule provision, which should be applicable to most European fisheries.</en>
      <fr>La Commission entend, principalement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8815">à</DiscourseConnective> des fins d'inspection, appliquer la règle du filet unique, qui devrait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8888">s'</DiscourseConnective>appliquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8900">à</DiscourseConnective> la plupart des pêcheries européennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7448" docOffset="37">
      <en>The Commission is ready to examine possible derogations for specific fisheries, where these are justified and well argued, <Alignment alignment="21057" annotation_id="7571">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7571" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> where they take into account the criteria set out in Amendment 11.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est prête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8964">à</DiscourseConnective> examiner les possibles dérogations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9001">pour</DiscourseConnective> des formes spécifiques de pêche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9039">lorsque</DiscourseConnective> celles-ci sont justifiées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9073">et</DiscourseConnective> bien argumentées, <Alignment alignment="7571" annotation_id="9094">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9094" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9097">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>elles prennent en considération les critères exposés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9157">à</DiscourseConnective> l'amendement 11.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7642" docOffset="38">
      <en>Such derogations should be part of the regional regulations.</en>
      <fr>Ces dérogations devraient faire partie des réglementations régionales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7703" docOffset="39">
      <en>The other aspects of the Commission's proposal are very technical, with many details related to the construction and use of fishing gears in the Atlantic.</en>
      <fr>Les autres aspects de la proposition de la Commission sont de nature très technique, et contiennent de nombreux détails relatifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9376">à</DiscourseConnective> la construction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9394">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'utilisation d'engins de pêche dans l'océan Atlantique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7858" docOffset="40">
      <en>I note that the rapporteur and the Fisheries Committee <Alignment alignment="5641" annotation_id="7913">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7913" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> addressed the very technical elements of the proposal and suggested a number of amendments, with the intention of improving the proposal.</en>
      <fr>J'observe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9466">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9484">et</DiscourseConnective> la commission de la pêche ont <Alignment alignment="7913" annotation_id="9517">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9517" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> abordé les éléments très techniques de la proposition, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9582">et</DiscourseConnective> ont suggéré une série d'amendements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9621">dans l'intention d'</DiscourseConnective>améliorer la proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8056" docOffset="41">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10785" annotation_id="8056">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8056" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I must express my reservations regarding Amendments 8, 9, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16 and 22.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8056" annotation_id="9666">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9666" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je me vois contraint d'exprimer des réserves en ce qui concerne les amendements 8, 9, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9779">et</DiscourseConnective> 22.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8154" docOffset="42">
      <en>The technical rules proposed on the basis of scientific advice have been simplified in comparison with current legislation, and will facilitate inspection on board and reduce costs for fishermen.</en>
      <fr>Les règles techniques proposées sur la base de conseils scientifiques ont été simplifiées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9876">par comparaison</DiscourseConnective> avec la législation actuelle; elles faciliteront l'inspection <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9954">à</DiscourseConnective> bord des navires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9973">et</DiscourseConnective> réduiront les coûts supportés par les pêcheurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8350" docOffset="43">
      <en>The Commission cannot accept Amendments 18 and 19, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8401" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective> the provisions proposed are already in force, subsequent to a political agreement in Council on a proposal from the Commission based on scientific advice, <Alignment alignment="23410" annotation_id="8562">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8562" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> no new information is available to justify any modification.</en>
      <fr>La Commission ne peut pas accepter les amendements 18 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10078">et</DiscourseConnective> 19, les dispositions qu'ils proposent se trouvant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10131">déjà</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10136">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur à la suite d'un accord politique obtenu au Conseil sur une proposition émanant de la Commission et basée sur des conseils scientifiques, <Alignment alignment="4712" annotation_id="10284">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10284" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aucune nouvelle information de nature <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10325">à</DiscourseConnective> justifier une quelconque modification n'étant disponible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8627" docOffset="44">
      <en>I can support the idea set out in Amendment 27, <Alignment alignment="6275" annotation_id="8675">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8675" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="27685" annotation_id="8679">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8679" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="14819" annotation_id="8690">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8690" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> introducing new technical measures, the Commission agrees to delay their entry into force so as to allow fishermen enough time to make the necessary adaptations.</en>
      <fr>Je peux appuyer l'idée exposée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10416">à</DiscourseConnective> l'amendement 27, <Alignment alignment="1777" annotation_id="10435">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10435" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="8679" annotation_id="10438">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10438" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="15566" annotation_id="10454">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10454" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">au moment de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mettre en place de nouvelles mesures techniques, la Commission accepte de retarder leur entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10562">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10573">de manière à</DiscourseConnective> laisser aux pêcheurs suffisamment de temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10629">pour</DiscourseConnective> procéder aux adaptations nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8857" docOffset="45">
      <en>Let me again express my gratitude to the rapporteur and the Committee for their work on this proposal.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi d'exprimer une nouvelle fois ma gratitude envers le rapporteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10749">et</DiscourseConnective> la commission parlementaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10780">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail qu'ils ont accompli au sujet de cette proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8960" id="215" language="PT" name="Paulo Casaca">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8960" docOffset="46">
      <en>Mr President, I too should like to congratulate the Commission on its legislative initiative, and also our rapporteur who is represented here today by our fellow Member, Mrs Fraga.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PSE. - (PT) Monsieur le Président, je souhaiterais, moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10920">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, féliciter la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10951">pour</DiscourseConnective> son initiative législative, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10984">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que notre rapporteur, représenté ici aujourd'hui par notre collègue, Mme Fraga.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9141" docOffset="47">
      <en>I believe that it was indeed vitally urgent to simplify the legislative framework in this respect.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11079">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11091">en effet</DiscourseConnective> plus qu'urgent de simplifier le cadre législatif dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9240" docOffset="48">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11166" annotation_id="9240">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9240" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I <Alignment alignment="11185" annotation_id="9251">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9251" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> believe that we must go much further, particularly in two fundamental areas, the first of which is discards.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7941" annotation_id="11166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11166" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je suis <Alignment alignment="14430" annotation_id="11185">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11185" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11198">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons aller bien plus loin, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11236">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> dans deux domaines fondamentaux, avec en premier lieu les rejets.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9365" docOffset="49">
      <en>I believe that the planned reform must, in principle, purely and simply prohibit any discards.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11326">que</DiscourseConnective> la réforme prévue doit, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11354">en</DiscourseConnective> principe, mener à une interdiction pure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11397">et</DiscourseConnective> simple de tous les rejets.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9460" docOffset="50">
      <en>Discards must be absolutely prohibited.</en>
      <fr>Les rejets doivent être absolument interdits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9500" docOffset="51">
      <en>Secondly, I believe that we must establish the principle of respect for stricter rules than the European ones by all vessels in regions in which the regional or national authorities understand it as such.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11473">En second lieu</DiscourseConnective>, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11498">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons établir le principe du respect par toutes les embarcations des normes plus strictes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11598">que</DiscourseConnective> les normes européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11625">que</DiscourseConnective> les autorités régionales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11654">ou</DiscourseConnective> nationales auront jugé utile d'adopter dans certaines régions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9705" docOffset="52">
      <en>These are two fundamental principles that are absent here, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9764" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I hope that these will be taken into account in the reform of the common fisheries policy.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont deux principes fondamentaux qui sont absents ici et dont j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11794">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il sera tenu compte dans le cadre de la réforme de la politique commune de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9859" id="216" name="Avril Doyle">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9859" docOffset="53">
      <en>Mr President, I welcome these measures to encourage selective fishing practices, which minimise harm to the complex ecosystem in which the resources are found, <Alignment alignment="20696" annotation_id="10019">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10019" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> enabling responsible fishing to continue, and to maximise returns <Alignment alignment="12189" annotation_id="10091">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10091" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> minimising by-catches and subsequent discards.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, je me félicite de ces mesures visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11947">à</DiscourseConnective> encourager les pratiques de pêche sélective, qui réduisent au maximum les dommages portés au complexe écosystème dans lequel se trouvent les ressources, <Alignment alignment="5121" annotation_id="12102">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12102" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> autorisant la poursuite d'une pêche responsable, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12159">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12162">à</DiscourseConnective> maximiser la rentabilité <Alignment alignment="10091" annotation_id="12189">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12189" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> réduisant le volume des prises accessoires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12240">et</DiscourseConnective> des rejets qui en découlent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10144" docOffset="54">
      <en>We must get to the point of banning discards as soon as possible, Commissioner.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons aborder le plus rapidement possible, Monsieur le Commissaire, la question de l'interdiction des rejets en mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10224" docOffset="55">
      <en>The variety of the fishing grounds found in the EU is part of our strength, but consequently an additional complication <Alignment alignment="1850" annotation_id="10344">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10344" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> producing legislation that is adequate, responsive and coherent.</en>
      <fr>La variété des zones de pêche que l'on trouve au sein de l'Union européenne compte parmi nos points forts, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12502">mais</DiscourseConnective> constitue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12517">aussi</DiscourseConnective> une complication supplémentaire <Alignment alignment="10344" annotation_id="12555">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12555" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il s'agit d'établir une législation à la fois adéquate, réactive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12627">et</DiscourseConnective> cohérente.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10414" docOffset="56">
      <en>Each of the seas in Europe has its own specificity, <Alignment alignment="14870" annotation_id="10466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10466" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is important to recognise the level of knowledge and expertise that can be provided by the stakeholders on the ground and to resist the temptation to micro-manage on an EU level.</en>
      <fr>Chacune des mers européennes possède sa spécificité propre, <Alignment alignment="11420" annotation_id="12701">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12701" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est important de reconnaître l'ampleur des connaissances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12764">et</DiscourseConnective> des compétences qui peuvent être fournies par les acteurs de terrain, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12837">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que de résister à la tentation de procéder <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12886">à</DiscourseConnective> une micro-gestion au niveau de la Communauté européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10652" docOffset="57">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12945" annotation_id="10652">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10652" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is our last debate on fisheries in this political mandate, I would like to thank you, Commissioner, and all your staff for your huge commitment and thorough knowledge of your brief and for the time and attention you always gave to the PECH Committee.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="10652" annotation_id="12945">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12945" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12954">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de notre dernier débat sur la pêche au cours de cette législature, je voudrais vous remercier, Monsieur le Commissaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13081">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que toute votre équipe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13111">pour</DiscourseConnective> votre engagement considérable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13146">et</DiscourseConnective> votre parfaite connaissance du dossier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13189">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13200">pour</DiscourseConnective> le temps <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13214">et</DiscourseConnective> l'attention que vous avez toujours consacrés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13262">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10911" docOffset="58">
      <en>You were always available for us.</en>
      <fr>Vous vous êtes toujours montré disponible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10945" docOffset="59">
      <en>It has been much appreciated and noted <Alignment alignment="13372" annotation_id="10984">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10984" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the comparison made with other Commissioners' availability.</en>
      <fr>Cela a été très apprécié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13359">et</DiscourseConnective> remarqué, <Alignment alignment="10984" annotation_id="13372">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13372" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'on a pu faire la comparaison avec la disponibilité d'autres commissaires européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11048" id="217" name="Joe Borg">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11048" docOffset="60">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, first of all I would like to thank Mrs Davis for her kind words just expressed.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13525">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13536">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier Mme Davis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13558">pour</DiscourseConnective> les paroles aimables qu'elle vient de prononcer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11170" docOffset="61">
      <en>I would like to say that with regard to this regulation, <Alignment alignment="13668" annotation_id="11227">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11227" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I said in my opening statement, the issue of comitology is aimed at simplifying the currently over-complex system of decision-making on very technical issues.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13624">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>en ce qui concerne ce règlement, et <Alignment alignment="11227" annotation_id="13668">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13668" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai exprimé dans ma déclaration introductive, le dispositif de la comitologie est destiné <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13768">à</DiscourseConnective> simplifier le système aujourd'hui trop complexe de la prise de décisions sur des questions très techniques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11389" docOffset="62">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2716" annotation_id="11389">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11389" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I agree that we have to have a procedure in place that will <Alignment alignment="24945" annotation_id="11458">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11458" sense="Comparison.Contrast">nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> allow an issue to be raised at Council level should any matter appear to be of a significant or political nature.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11389" annotation_id="13878">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13878" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je suis d'accord pour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13911">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est nécessaire de mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13947">en</DiscourseConnective> place une procédure permettant <Alignment alignment="1139" annotation_id="13981">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13981" sense="Comparison.Contrast">néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'évoquer un sujet au niveau du Conseil, s'il s'avère que celui-ci revêt une grande importance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14086">ou</DiscourseConnective> possède un caractère politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11585" docOffset="63">
      <en>On the question of discards, we have already started to take measures to reduce discards, in particular within the parameters of the North Sea and of the cod recovery plan.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14121">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la question des rejets, nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14175">déjà</DiscourseConnective> commencé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14189">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre des mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14211">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> les réduire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14234">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans le cadre des paramètres spécifiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14285">à</DiscourseConnective> la mer du Nord, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14303">et</DiscourseConnective> du plan de reconstitution pour le cabillaud.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11758" docOffset="64">
      <en>We will continue <Alignment alignment="31723" annotation_id="11775">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11775" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will be coming up with further proposals, <Alignment alignment="1776" annotation_id="11824">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11824" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on the banning of high grading, in a general manner which we will be proposing for 2010, <Alignment alignment="14556" annotation_id="11925">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11925" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we hope that we will be dealing with this issue holistically in the discussions on the reform of the common fisheries policy with a view, I hope, to the final result being the total elimination of discards.</en>
      <fr>Nous continuerons, <Alignment alignment="11780" annotation_id="14370">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14370" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous allons présenter d'autres propositions, <Alignment alignment="11824" annotation_id="14418">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14418" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> au sujet de l'interdiction de l'accroissement du volume des prises, que nous allons, de manière générale, proposer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14545">pour</DiscourseConnective> 2010, <Alignment alignment="11925" annotation_id="14556">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14556" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous espérons traiter cette question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14596">globalement</DiscourseConnective> dans le cadre des discussions sur la réforme de la politique commune de la pêche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14690">en</DiscourseConnective> vue, je l'espère, d'aboutir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14721">finalement</DiscourseConnective> à l'élimination totale des rejets.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12136" docOffset="65">
      <en>I would like myself to thank the Members of Parliament, in particular the members of the Fisheries Committee, for the constant support they have given the Commission in dealing with the sometimes intricate and politically sensitive issue of fisheries.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14780">quant à</DiscourseConnective> moi, remercier les membres du Parlement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14829">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> les membres de la commission de la pêche, du soutien constant qu'ils ont apporté à la Commission dans le traitement de la question parfois complexe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14993">et</DiscourseConnective> politiquement sensible, de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12388" id="218" language="ES" name="Carmen Fraga Estévez">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12388" docOffset="66">
      <en>Mr President, I am grateful to the commissioner for one comment he made <Alignment alignment="18742" annotation_id="12460">
          <Alignment alignment="15104" annotation_id="12460">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12460" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, which is that he is prepared to reconsider the Commission's position on the issue of comitology.</en>
      <fr>rapporteure suppléante. - (ES) Monsieur le Président, il y a une chose <Alignment alignment="12460" annotation_id="15104">
          <Alignment alignment="7616" annotation_id="15104">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15104" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> que j'ai été ravie d'entendre de la bouche du commissaire, à savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15187">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il était prêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15204">à</DiscourseConnective> reconsidérer la position de la Commission sur la question de la comitologie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12572" docOffset="67">
      <en>I welcome the news <Alignment alignment="11685" annotation_id="12591">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12591" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Parliament has clearly shown that, throughout this debate in the Committee on Fisheries, it does not agree with the Commission's keenness - also apparent in the draft Green Paper on the reform of the Common Fisheries Policy - to turn to the subject of comitology excessively and with particular interest.</en>
      <fr>Je m'en félicite, <Alignment alignment="12591" annotation_id="15301">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15301" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement a clairement montré, tout au long du débat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15361">en</DiscourseConnective> commission de la pêche, son désaccord avec la propension de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15438">à</DiscourseConnective> privilégier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15452">à</DiscourseConnective> l'excès la procédure de comitologie, ce qui transparaît, entre autres, dans le projet de livre vert sur la réforme de la politique commune de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12904" docOffset="68">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="26442" annotation_id="12904">
          <Alignment alignment="10216" annotation_id="12904">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12904" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the Commission justifies this in the Green Paper, alleging that proceedings may now be delayed, given the codecision procedure that Parliament is going to apply to the area of fisheries for the first time, <Alignment alignment="15840" annotation_id="13123">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13123" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">once</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Treaty of Lisbon comes into effect.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12904" annotation_id="15606">
          <Alignment alignment="12904" annotation_id="15606">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15606" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, pour justifier cette proposition, la Commission évoque, dans son livre vert, l'allongement des procédures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15722">que</DiscourseConnective> pourrait engendrer le passage à la codécision avec le Parlement dans le domaine de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15818">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois <Alignment alignment="6400" annotation_id="15840">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15840" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15855">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur du traité de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13168" docOffset="69">
      <en>I do not believe this to be true; I feel that legislative procedures are often delayed not <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13259" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> of Parliament or the codecision procedure <Alignment alignment="31383" annotation_id="13309">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13309" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="14961" annotation_id="13314">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13314" sense="Expansion.Restatement">rather</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="16075" annotation_id="13322">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13322" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sometimes the Commission is also late in presenting its proposals.</en>
      <fr>Je ne pense pas que ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15912">soit</DiscourseConnective> vrai. Selon moi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15934">si</DiscourseConnective> les procédures législatives prennent parfois du temps, c'est souvent dû non pas au Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16030">et</DiscourseConnective> à la procédure de codécision, <Alignment alignment="1211" annotation_id="16063">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16063" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="13314" annotation_id="16068">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16068" sense="Expansion.Restatement">plutôt</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="13322" annotation_id="16075">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16075" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">au fait</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, parfois, la Commission accuse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16118">aussi</DiscourseConnective> un retard dans le dépôt de ses propositions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13397" docOffset="70">
      <en>In my view, this is a matter of interest and one that should be debated.</en>
      <fr>Je pense que c'est une question digne d'intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16217">et</DiscourseConnective> dont il faudrait débattre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13470" docOffset="71">
      <en>I understand the commissioner's point <Alignment alignment="16292" annotation_id="13508">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13508" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he says that with a regulation as technical as this one, some aspects have to be decided by comitology and cannot all be dealt with by the Council.</en>
      <fr>Je comprends ce que veut dire le commissaire <Alignment alignment="13508" annotation_id="16292">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16292" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il évoque le côté particulièrement technique du règlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16357">pour</DiscourseConnective> justifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16372">que</DiscourseConnective> certains aspects soient décidés par la procédure de comitologie plutôt que par le Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13661" docOffset="72">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="16467" annotation_id="13661">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13661" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I think, Commissioner, that there is a certain difference between what you consider to be 'technical' <Alignment alignment="34698" annotation_id="13772">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13772" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> what we in Parliament consider to be 'technical'.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13661" annotation_id="16467">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16467" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Monsieur le Commissaire, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16512">que</DiscourseConnective> l'interprétation de la notion de "technique" diffère quelque peu entre le Parlement <Alignment alignment="13772" annotation_id="16600">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16600" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13826" docOffset="73">
      <en>We are more restrictive than you tend to be.</en>
      <fr>Nous l'interprétons de manière plus restrictive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16666">que</DiscourseConnective> vous n'avez tendance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16691">à</DiscourseConnective> le faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13871" docOffset="74">
      <en>As a final point - I do not wish to spend too long on a matter for which I am not the rapporteur - I wish to mention the one net rule.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16703">Pour conclure</DiscourseConnective>, parce que je ne veux pas m'étendre à l'excès sur un sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16776">pour</DiscourseConnective> lequel je ne suis pas rapporteure, je souhaiterais revenir sur la règle du filet unique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14006" docOffset="75">
      <en>Commissioner, during the debates we had in the Committee on Fisheries, it became apparent that the Commission defends this principle chiefly for reasons of control.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, durant nos débats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16913">en</DiscourseConnective> commission de la pêche, il nous est apparu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16959">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission défendait ce principe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16999">surtout</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17007">pour</DiscourseConnective> des raisons de contrôle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14171" docOffset="76">
      <en>We all understand that the issue of control is a great deal simpler with the single net rule, <Alignment alignment="17134" annotation_id="14265">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14265" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this matter <Alignment alignment="13233" annotation_id="14281">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14281" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> poses serious problems for certain fisheries, <Alignment alignment="33418" annotation_id="14332">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14332" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you are indeed aware.</en>
      <fr>Nous comprenons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17053">que</DiscourseConnective> la règle du filet unique simplifie considérablement la question du contrôle, <Alignment alignment="14265" annotation_id="17134">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17134" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="14332" annotation_id="17140">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17140" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez, elle pose <Alignment alignment="14281" annotation_id="17171">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17171" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de sérieux problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17202">à</DiscourseConnective> certains opérateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14357" docOffset="77">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17225" annotation_id="14357">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14357" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, let us not always use the issue of control in order to be highly restrictive at times, for some decisions do not always need to be made.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4892" annotation_id="17225">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17225" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ne nous abritons pas toujours derrière la question du contrôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17294">pour</DiscourseConnective> justifier des mesures parfois extrêmement restrictives. Certaines décisions ne sont pas toujours nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14505" id="219" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14505" docOffset="78">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14527" docOffset="79">
      <en>The vote will take place on Wednesday 22 April 2009.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu mercredi 22 avril 2009.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
