<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>2006 Annual report on the CFSP - Annual report on the implementation of the European Security Strategy and ESDP (continuation of debate)</en>
    <fr>Rapport annuel 2006 sur la PESC - Stratégie européenne de sécurité, PESD (suite du débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="137" id="049" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="137" docOffset="1">
      <en>We will continue with the joint debate on the report by Jacek Saryusz-Wolski, on the 2006 annual report on the CFSP, and the report by Helmut Kuhne, on the implementation of the European Security Strategy and ESDP.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Nous allons poursuivre ce débat commun sur le rapport de Jacek Saryusz-Wolski, sur le rapport annuel 2006 sur la PESC <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="213">et</DiscourseConnective> sur le rapport d'Helmut Kuhne, relatif à la mise en œuvre de la stratégie européenne de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="313">et</DiscourseConnective> de la PESD.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="352" id="050" name="Marie Anne Isler Béguin">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="352" docOffset="2">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, it is a pleasure for me to speak before these delegations <Alignment alignment="432" annotation_id="429">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="429" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have such close ties with them.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, c'est également un plaisir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="378">pour</DiscourseConnective> moi que de parler en présence de ces délégations <Alignment alignment="429" annotation_id="432">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="432" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous entretenons des relations très étroites avec elles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="470" docOffset="3">
      <en>It is precisely on the South Caucasus, would you believe, High Commissioner, that I would like to focus my intervention.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="499">précisément</DiscourseConnective> sur le Caucase du Sud, vous vous en doutez Monsieur le Haut Commissaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="584">que</DiscourseConnective> je voudrais focaliser mon intervention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="591" docOffset="4">
      <en>We heard the good news that you will be going to Georgia for a couple of days tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>En effet, nous avons appris une bonne nouvelle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="676">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="685">que</DiscourseConnective> demain et après-demain, vous vous rendez en Géorgie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="679" docOffset="5">
      <en>It was high time that this happened <Alignment alignment="4751" annotation_id="715">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="715" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I thank you for that.</en>
      <fr>Il était grand temps de le faire <Alignment alignment="715" annotation_id="775">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="775" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je souhaiterais vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="799">en</DiscourseConnective> remercier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="741" docOffset="6">
      <en>You will <Alignment alignment="824" annotation_id="750">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="750" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be going to Abkhazia <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="776" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> on that point, you explained that the weekend might not be enough time to resolve the issue.</en>
      <fr>Vous allez <Alignment alignment="750" annotation_id="824">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="824" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous rendre en Abkhazie et vous précisez, sur ce point, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="886">que</DiscourseConnective> le week-end ne suffira peut-être pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="927">pour</DiscourseConnective> régler le problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="873" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="952" annotation_id="873">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="873" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you manage to do it in a weekend, I will be the first to congratulate you.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="873" annotation_id="952">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="952" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous y parvenez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="971">en</DiscourseConnective> un week-end, je vous en félicite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="951" docOffset="8">
      <en>This is a hard task, we know, <Alignment alignment="8366" annotation_id="981">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="981" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the most important thing is that the European Union is engaging in it.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1008">En effet</DiscourseConnective>, la tâche est dure, et nous le savons, <Alignment alignment="981" annotation_id="1056">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1056" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le plus important est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1083">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1106">s'</DiscourseConnective>investisse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1056" docOffset="9">
      <en>In my opinion, this is almost a test of the maturity of EU foreign policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1120">À</DiscourseConnective> mon avis, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1135">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit là d'une sorte de test de la maturité de notre politique étrangère.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1131" docOffset="10">
      <en>We know that Russia, which is one of our partners, is now involved in the conflict.</en>
      <fr>En effet, la Russie, qui est un partenaire, est aujourd'hui impliquée dans le conflit, nous le savons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1215" docOffset="11">
      <en>According to the UN report, Georgia has agreed to suspend UAV flights over Abkhazia.</en>
      <fr>Selon le rapport de l'ONU, la Géorgie a accepté de suspendre les vols de drones au-dessus de l'Abkhazie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1300" docOffset="12">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1332" annotation_id="1300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1300" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, yesterday we learnt that Russia has deployed its military forces to supposedly build railways.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1300" annotation_id="1418">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1418" sense="Comparison.Contrast">En revanche</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous avons appris hier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1454">que</DiscourseConnective> la Russie a renvoyé des forces de la défense russe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1509">pour</DiscourseConnective> soi-disant construire des chemins de fer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1404" docOffset="13">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1556" annotation_id="1404">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1404" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is the case, I think it is too early to talk about peacekeeping forces.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1404" annotation_id="1556">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1556" sense="Contingency.Condition">Dans ce cas</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je ne pense pas qu'il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1591">soit</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1596">encore</DiscourseConnective> possible de parler de forces de maintien de la paix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1484" docOffset="14">
      <en>This is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1492" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective> a difficult task.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1656">Ainsi</DiscourseConnective>, la tâche s'annonce lourde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1520" docOffset="15">
      <en>You said that you were going to support Georgia's peace plan, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1582" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective> my question to you, High Commissioner, is this: are you <Alignment alignment="1861" annotation_id="1641">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1641" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> going to support, as part of this peace plan, the introduction of an Abkhaz-Georgian civil police force supervised by the EU or the OSCE?</en>
      <fr>Vous avez dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1704">que</DiscourseConnective> vous alliez vous engager aux côtés de la Géorgie pour soutenir le plan de paix et la question, Monsieur le Haut Commissaire, est la suivante: allez-vous <Alignment alignment="1641" annotation_id="1861">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1861" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> soutenir, dans le cadre de ce plan de paix, la mise en place d'une police civile abkhazo-géorgienne supervisée par l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2005">ou</DiscourseConnective> l'OSCE?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1784" docOffset="16">
      <en>This would be a real step forward, and one that we have been waiting for from the EU for a long time in this conflict, <Alignment alignment="20373" annotation_id="1903">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1903" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is a neighbouring country.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agirait d'un véritable pas en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2051">avant que</DiscourseConnective> nous attendons depuis longtemps de la part de l'Union européenne dans ce conflit, <Alignment alignment="550" annotation_id="2143">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2143" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous sommes en présence de pays du voisinage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1941" docOffset="17">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="857" annotation_id="1941">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1941" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the question that arises today, and which our fellow Members have just asked, is this: are we going to develop the Neighbourhood Policy as part of our foreign policy?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1941" annotation_id="2193">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2193" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la question qui se pose aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2239">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2242">que</DiscourseConnective> nos amis viennent nous poser est la suivante: allons-nous développer la politique de voisinage dans le cadre de notre politique étrangère?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2119" id="051" name="Hanna Foltyn-Kubicka">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2119" docOffset="18">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, may I remind you that in last year's report from the Council on the main aspects and basic choices of Common Foreign and Security Policy, Parliament expressed deep disquiet at the announcement by the then Russian President, Vladimir Putin, that Russia was withdrawing from further participation in the Treaty on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2413">puis</DiscourseConnective>-je vous rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2435">que</DiscourseConnective> dans le rapport de l'année dernière du Conseil sur les principaux aspects <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2513">et</DiscourseConnective> choix fondamentaux de la politique étrangère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2561">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité commune, le Parlement a exprimé sa profonde inquiétude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2631">à</DiscourseConnective> l'annonce par le président russe de l'époque, Vladimir Poutine, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2697">que</DiscourseConnective> la Russie se retirait du traité sur les forces armées conventionnelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2772">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe ?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2487" docOffset="19">
      <en>Despite the express declaration by the European Parliament, the EU authorities took no serious action on this.</en>
      <fr>Malgré la déclaration expresse du Parlement européen, les autorités de l'Union n'ont pas entrepris d'action sérieuse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2901">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2598" docOffset="20">
      <en>In July 2007, <Alignment alignment="2931" annotation_id="2612">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2612" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Russian State Duma unanimously passed an act suspending Russia's participation in this Treaty.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2914">En</DiscourseConnective> juillet 2007, <Alignment alignment="2612" annotation_id="2931">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2931" sense="Comparison.Contrast">toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la Douma russe a adopté unanimement une loi suspendant la participation de la Russie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3027">à</DiscourseConnective> ce traité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2720" docOffset="21">
      <en>There is no doubt that this fact is of fundamental importance for security in Europe, <Alignment alignment="2885" annotation_id="2806">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2806" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Russia possesses the greatest conventional armed forces potential on our continent.</en>
      <fr>Il ne fait aucun doute <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3063">que</DiscourseConnective> ce fait est d'une importance fondamentale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3109">pour</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3126">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe, <Alignment alignment="2806" annotation_id="3137">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3137" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est la Russie qui possède le plus grand potentiel en matière de forces armées conventionnelles sur notre continent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2893" docOffset="22">
      <en>This is why I believe that the matter of getting the Russian Federation to re-accede to this international agreement is an important priority.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3263">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3287">que</DiscourseConnective> faire réadhérer la Fédération de Russie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3331">à</DiscourseConnective> cet accord international est une priorité importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3036" docOffset="23">
      <en>The authorities of the EU and its Member States should use all means available to them to bring this about, not least <Alignment alignment="11937" annotation_id="3154">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3154" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in recent times Russian expenditure on arms has risen by 700%.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3409">et</DiscourseConnective> de ses États membres devraient mettre en œuvre tous les moyens dont elles disposent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3496">pour</DiscourseConnective> y parvenir, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3513">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="3154" annotation_id="3528">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3528" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'on prend en considération le fait que les dépenses russes en armement ont récemment progressé de 700 %.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3225" id="052" name="Willy Meyer Pleite">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3225" docOffset="24">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, Mr El Baradei, who is not someone who can be accused of being radical, said at the last Munich Conference on Security Policy that a 1% reduction in arms expenditure could solve the hunger problems in the world.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, M. El Baradei, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3685">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on ne peut accuser d'être une personne radicale, a dit lors de la dernière conférence de Munich sur la politique de sécurité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3817">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une réduction de 1 % des dépenses en armement pourrait résoudre les problèmes de faim dans le monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3455" docOffset="25">
      <en>The contribution that the European Union is making to achieving this goal is to ask the Member States for military expenditure to be increased, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3599" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> as a result this civilisation has reached the immoral situation of having the highest arms expenditure in the world in 2006, more than in the Cold War: 17 times more than we spend on international cooperation.</en>
      <fr>La contribution de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3959">pour</DiscourseConnective> atteindre cet objectif consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3996">à</DiscourseConnective> demander aux États membres d'accroître leurs dépenses militaires, ce qui donne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4077">comme</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4083">résultat</DiscourseConnective> que cette civilisation en est arrivée à la situation immorale d'être la région du monde où les dépenses en armement ont été les plus élevées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4233">en</DiscourseConnective> 2006, plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4247">que</DiscourseConnective> lors de la guerre froide: 17 fois plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4290">que</DiscourseConnective> ce que nous dépensons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4316">pour</DiscourseConnective> la coopération internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3813" docOffset="26">
      <en>I think that we are going along the wrong path.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4361">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons emprunté la mauvaise voie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3861" docOffset="27">
      <en>The militarisation of security has created a more unjust, more violent world.</en>
      <fr>La militarisation de la sécurité a créé un monde plus injuste, plus violent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3939" docOffset="28">
      <en>You might remember that we were told that the immorality of the invasion of Iraq was going to resolve the problem of the Middle East and reduce the price of oil.</en>
      <fr>Vous vous souvenez peut-être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4509">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on nous a dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4529">que</DiscourseConnective> l'immoralité de l'invasion de l'Iraq allait résoudre le problème du Moyen-Orient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4614">et</DiscourseConnective> réduire le prix du pétrole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4101" docOffset="29">
      <en>The evidence is conclusive.</en>
      <fr>Nous voyons ce qu'il en est.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4129" docOffset="30">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I think that we are on the wrong track.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4683">et</DiscourseConnective> messieurs, je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4706">que</DiscourseConnective> nous sommes sur la mauvaise voie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4191" docOffset="31">
      <en>We need to demilitarise security and go back to the old values of a Europe in which, in the midst of the Cold War, on foreign policy people like Willy Brandt and Olaf Palme were proposing the zero armament objective.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons besoin de démilitariser la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4791">et</DiscourseConnective> de retourner aux anciennes valeurs d'une Europe dans laquelle, au beau milieu de la guerre froide, des personnes telles que Willy Brandt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4931">et</DiscourseConnective> Olaf Palme proposaient en termes de politique étrangère l'objectif de l'armement zéro.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4408" docOffset="32">
      <en>With regard to our link to North American security, it depends which administration we are talking about.</en>
      <fr>Concernant notre lien avec la sécurité nord-américaine, tout dépend de quelle administration nous parlons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4514" docOffset="33">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3897" annotation_id="4514">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4514" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have our principles and values been the same as those of the Bush administration?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4514" annotation_id="5128">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5128" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nos principes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5145">et</DiscourseConnective> valeurs ont-ils été les mêmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5178">que</DiscourseConnective> ceux de l'administration Bush?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4599" docOffset="34">
      <en>Do you recall the CIA flights, the torture in Guantanamo, the death penalty, and the systematic violation of human rights throughout the world?</en>
      <fr>Vous souvenez-vous des vols de la CIA, des tortures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5265">à</DiscourseConnective> Guantanamo, de la peine de mort, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5300">et</DiscourseConnective> de la violation systématique des droits de l'homme à travers le monde?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4743" docOffset="35">
      <en>No, ladies and gentlemen, I think that we need to move towards autonomous, denuclearised security, and a system that generates sufficient security to resolve the fundamental problems which, in addition to terrorism, are hunger, poverty and discrimination.</en>
      <fr>Non, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5388">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5411">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons besoin de nous orienter vers une sécurité autonome, dénucléarisée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5493">et</DiscourseConnective> vers un système générant suffisamment de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5546">pour</DiscourseConnective> résoudre les problèmes fondamentaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5587">que</DiscourseConnective> sont, outre le terrorisme, la faim, la pauvreté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5639">et</DiscourseConnective> la discrimination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4999" id="053" name="Hélène Goudin">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4999" docOffset="36">
      <en>(SV) Mr President, today's debate was a foretaste of what is to come <Alignment alignment="5754" annotation_id="5068">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5068" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Treaty of Lisbon is adopted.</en>
      <fr>(SV) Monsieur le Président, le débat d'aujourd'hui était un avant-goût de ce qui nous attend <Alignment alignment="4548" annotation_id="5754">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5754" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le traité de Lisbonne est adopté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5104" docOffset="37">
      <en>Increased militarisation, increased supranationality and increased costs for the EU at the expense of Member States' independence.</en>
      <fr>Accroissement de la militarisation, accroissement de la supranationalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5864">et</DiscourseConnective> accroissement des coûts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5891">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'UE aux dépens de l'indépendance des États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5235" docOffset="38">
      <en>The EU is now to represent us all.</en>
      <fr>L'objet de l'UE est de nous représenter tous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5270" docOffset="39">
      <en>The wishes of 27 states will become as of one.</en>
      <fr>Les souhaits de 27 États vont devenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6033">comme</DiscourseConnective> ceux d'un seul.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5317" docOffset="40">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="9730" annotation_id="5319">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5319" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> look on in amazement <Alignment alignment="6091" annotation_id="5350">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5350" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Parliament - which claims to be the champion of democracy - chooses a federalist course without respecting either Ireland's referendum or intergovernmental cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Je suis <Alignment alignment="1226" annotation_id="6063">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6063" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> stupéfaite de voir <Alignment alignment="5350" annotation_id="6091">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6091" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement européen - qui se veut le champion de la démocratie - choisit une voie fédéraliste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6191">sans</DiscourseConnective> respecter le référendum irlandais ni la coopération intergouvernementale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5535" docOffset="41">
      <en>The Treaty of Lisbon means a further step towards a common foreign minister, common military forces and a common intelligence service, <Alignment alignment="6442" annotation_id="5670">
          <Alignment alignment="6442" annotation_id="5670">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5670" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in short</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, a common defence and foreign policy.</en>
      <fr>Le traité de Lisbonne signifie un pas supplémentaire vers un ministre des affaires étrangères commun, des forces armées communes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6399">et</DiscourseConnective> des services de renseignements communs, <Alignment alignment="3044" annotation_id="6442">
          <Alignment alignment="5670" annotation_id="6442">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6442" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en bref</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, une politique étrangère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6475">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense commune.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5717" docOffset="42">
      <en>Citizens of Ireland, you are the only ones who have been given the opportunity to halt this dangerous development.</en>
      <fr>Citoyens irlandais, vous êtes les seuls à qui l'opportunité d'arrêter cette évolution dangereuse a été donnée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5832" docOffset="43">
      <en>I urge to you to vote 'no' on 12 June, just <Alignment alignment="6671" annotation_id="5876">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5876" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we should do in Parliament tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Je vous prie instamment de voter "non" le 12 juin, exactement <Alignment alignment="5876" annotation_id="6671">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6671" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devrions le faire demain au Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5916" id="054" name="Roger Helmer">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5916" docOffset="44">
      <en>Mr President, I have a question for you.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, j'ai une question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6767">pour</DiscourseConnective> vous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5957" docOffset="45">
      <en>How is it that the High Representative, Mr Solana, can come to this House and tell us a direct untruth?</en>
      <fr>Comment se fait-il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6797">que</DiscourseConnective> le haut représentant, M. Solana, puisse venir dans l'enceinte du Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6876">et</DiscourseConnective> prononcer un mensonge absolu?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6061" docOffset="46">
      <en>I sat here and heard him say that everyone wants a stronger European Union and a stronger CFSP.</en>
      <fr>J'étais assis ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6927">et</DiscourseConnective> je l'ai entendu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6946">dire que</DiscourseConnective> tout le monde souhaite une Union européenne plus forte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7010">et</DiscourseConnective> une PESC plus forte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6157" docOffset="47">
      <en>I represent 4.2 million people in the East Midlands of the United Kingdom.</en>
      <fr>Je représente 4,2 millions de personnes dans les East Midlands du Royaume-Uni.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6232" docOffset="48">
      <en>Not one of them has ever said that they want a stronger European Union or a stronger CFSP, <Alignment alignment="635" annotation_id="6323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6323" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> many have said to me they would like to see our country out of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Aucune d'entre elles n'a jamais dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7149">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles voulaient une Union européenne plus forte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7200">ou</DiscourseConnective> une PESC plus forte, <Alignment alignment="6323" annotation_id="7224">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7224" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> beaucoup m'ont dit qu'elles aimeraient voir notre pays sortir de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6413" docOffset="49">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7319" annotation_id="6413">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6413" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you believe this is what the European people want, why will you not let them vote on the European Constitution and the Lisbon Treaty which are designed to deliver it?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6413" annotation_id="7319">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7319" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous croyez que c'est ce que veut le peuple européen, pourquoi ne pas le laisser voter sur la constitution européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7440">et</DiscourseConnective> le traité de Lisbonne dont le but est de donner forme à cette évolution?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6583" docOffset="50">
      <en>Have you forgotten that the French voted against it <Alignment alignment="6475" annotation_id="6635">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6635" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Dutch voted against it?</en>
      <fr>Avez-vous oublié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7533">que</DiscourseConnective> les Français <Alignment alignment="6635" annotation_id="7550">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7550" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les Néerlandais ont voté contre ce projet?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6667" docOffset="51">
      <en>Do you not know that 80% of my constituents want a referendum <Alignment alignment="7676" annotation_id="6729">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6729" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="6910" annotation_id="6734">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6734" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they were given it, at least 80% of them would vote 'no'?</en>
      <fr>Ignorez-vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7609">que</DiscourseConnective> 80 % des électeurs de ma circonscription veulent un référendum <Alignment alignment="6729" annotation_id="7676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7676" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, <Alignment alignment="6734" annotation_id="7684">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7684" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils l'obtenaient, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7704">au moins</DiscourseConnective> 80 % d'entre eux voteraient "non"?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6795" docOffset="52">
      <en>The British people that I represent want trade and cooperation in Europe, <Alignment alignment="15936" annotation_id="6869">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6869" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they are absolutely opposed to political union and a European army.</en>
      <fr>Les Britanniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7765">que</DiscourseConnective> je représente veulent une Europe de commerce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7814">et</DiscourseConnective> de coopération, <Alignment alignment="6869" annotation_id="7833">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7833" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils sont absolument opposés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7866">à</DiscourseConnective> une union politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7888">et</DiscourseConnective> à une armée européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6941" id="055" name="José Ignacio Salafranca Sánchez-Neyra">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6941" docOffset="53">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, cooperation between Parliament <Alignment alignment="7977" annotation_id="6991">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6991" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Council has significantly improved in recent years, <Alignment alignment="22520" annotation_id="7051">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7051" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> recognised in Mr Saryusz-Wolski's report, <Alignment alignment="22791" annotation_id="7096">
          <Alignment alignment="12032" annotation_id="7096">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7096" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> thanks to the establishment of flexible mechanisms and the appearances by the President-in-Office of the Council, the High Representative and the Special Representatives.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, la coopération entre le Parlement <Alignment alignment="6991" annotation_id="7977">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7977" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Conseil s'est significativement améliorée ces dernières années, <Alignment alignment="7051" annotation_id="8047">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8047" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le reconnaît le rapport de M. Saryusz-Wolski, <Alignment alignment="7096" annotation_id="8099">
          <Alignment alignment="7096" annotation_id="8099">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8099" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> grâce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8120">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place de mécanismes flexibles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8163">et</DiscourseConnective> aux apparitions du président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8195">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil, du haut représentant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8240">et</DiscourseConnective> des représentants spéciaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7281" docOffset="54">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8271" annotation_id="7281">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7281" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the report <Alignment alignment="16764" annotation_id="7301">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7301" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> says, as the Chairman of my group, that this cooperation between Parliament and the Council could be improved, especially in terms of timing.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7281" annotation_id="8271">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8271" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le rapport dit <Alignment alignment="7301" annotation_id="8297">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8297" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8308">comme</DiscourseConnective> le président de mon groupe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8342">que</DiscourseConnective> cette coopération entre le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8383">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil pourrait encore être améliorée, particulièrement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8446">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de timing.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7448" docOffset="55">
      <en>The report by Mr Saryusz-Wolski, whom I would like to congratulate on his work, includes a specific initiative: establishing an interinstitutional agreement from the beginning of next year, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7638" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>, on the basis of the guidelines of the new Treaty, stable and dynamic criteria for cooperation can be established.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport de M. Saryusz-Wolski, dont je voudrais féliciter le travail, comprend une initiative spécifique: l'adoption d'un accord interinstitutionnel à partir du début de l'année prochaine, qui nous permettrait, sur la base des directives du nouveau traité, d'établir des critères stables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8757">et</DiscourseConnective> dynamiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8771">pour</DiscourseConnective> la coopération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7761" docOffset="56">
      <en>High Representative, I would like to get an idea of your assessment of this proposal in the report.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Haut Représentant, j'aimerais connaître votre opinion sur cette proposition formulée dans le rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7861" docOffset="57">
      <en>Secondly, I would <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7879" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> like to thank the other rapporteur, Mr Kuhne, for his report on the European Security Strategy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8906">Deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, j'aimerais remercier l'autre rapporteur, M. Kuhne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8971">pour</DiscourseConnective> son rapport sur la stratégie européenne de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7980" docOffset="58">
      <en>I think that what we need here is a long-term strategy that will enable us to deal with the new shape of the threats that we face, which can be revised <Alignment alignment="9218" annotation_id="8132">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8132" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> circumstances change, and in any case every five years, coinciding with Parliament's legislative periods.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9038">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons besoin à ce niveau d'une stratégie à long terme qui nous permettra de gérer les nouvelles formes de menaces auxquelles nous devons faire face, qui pourra être revue <Alignment alignment="8132" annotation_id="9218">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9218" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> fonction des changements de circonstances, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9264">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9267">en tout cas</DiscourseConnective> tous les cinq ans, soit la durée des législatures du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8243" docOffset="59">
      <en>There have been some very remarkable speeches.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons entendu plusieurs discours vraiment remarquables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8290" docOffset="60">
      <en>I do not think that it is a question of spending more, <Alignment alignment="9463" annotation_id="8345">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8345" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="9468" annotation_id="8349">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8349" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have 3 parallel satellite systems - Mr von Wogau already referred to this today - 5 telecommunications systems, 23 armoured vehicle systems and 87 different arms programmes, we will not be able to continue to make progress along the line that we want to follow.</en>
      <fr>Je ne crois pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9420">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9426">soit</DiscourseConnective> question de dépenser davantage, <Alignment alignment="8345" annotation_id="9463">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9463" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="8349" annotation_id="9468">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9468" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous aurons 3 systèmes satellitaires parallèles - M. von Wogau a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9542">déjà</DiscourseConnective> évoqué ce point aujourd'hui - 5 systèmes de télécommunications, 23 systèmes de véhicules blindés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9644">et</DiscourseConnective> 87 programmes d'armement différents, nous ne serons pas en mesure de continuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9726">à</DiscourseConnective> progresser sur la voie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9751">que</DiscourseConnective> nous voulons suivre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8620" docOffset="61">
      <en>With the 27 Member States, the European Union has approximately 2 million soldiers, 10 000 tanks and 3 000 fighter planes.</en>
      <fr>Avec ses 27 États membres, l'Union européenne compte environ 2 millions de soldats, 10 000 chars <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9873">et</DiscourseConnective> 3 000 avions de combat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8743" docOffset="62">
      <en>I think that this is a sufficiently large force for us to be able to take serious action.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9909">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9915">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'une force suffisamment importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9958">pour</DiscourseConnective> nous permettre d'entreprendre une action sérieuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8833" docOffset="63">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7070" annotation_id="8833">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8833" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we have additional problems with sending a battalion to conflicts such as in Chad, where the aim is not to wage war but to provide protection in crisis situations and mediate in conflict situations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8833" annotation_id="10014">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10014" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous avons d'autres problèmes lorsqu'il est question d'envoyer un bataillon sur des conflits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10118">comme</DiscourseConnective> celui du Tchad, où l'objectif n'est pas de faire la guerre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10183">mais</DiscourseConnective> d'apporter une protection dans des situations de crise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10243">et</DiscourseConnective> de jouer un rôle de médiateur dans des situations conflictuelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9041" docOffset="64">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="20203" annotation_id="9041">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9041" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Mr President, I think that we need to contribute and mobilise all of our resources <Alignment alignment="19298" annotation_id="9135">
          <Alignment alignment="19298" annotation_id="9135">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9135" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the European Union, with all of the capacity that it has, does not continue to be utterly irrelevant on the international stage.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9041" annotation_id="10312">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10312" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Monsieur le Président, j'estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10354">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10381">et</DiscourseConnective> mobiliser toutes nos ressources <Alignment alignment="9135" annotation_id="10416">
          <Alignment alignment="9135" annotation_id="10416">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10416" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de sorte que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne, avec toute sa capacité, cesse d'être un acteur totalement insignifiant sur la scène internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
