<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>European satellite navigation programmes (EGNOS and Galileo) (signature)</en>
    <fr>Programmes européens de radionavigation par satellite (EGNOS <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="61">et</DiscourseConnective> Galileo) (signature de l'acte)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="73" id="253" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="73" docOffset="1">
      <en>Mr President-in-Office, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, through this public signing of the legal instrument on the Galileo programme we are emphasising the importance we attach to the European satellite navigation programmes EGNOS and Galileo.</en>
      <fr>(DE) M. le Président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="116">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice, Madame la commissaire, mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="161">et</DiscourseConnective> messieurs, par cette signature officielle de l'instrument juridique du programme Galileo, nous soulignons l'importance que nous attachons aux programmes européens de navigation par satellite, EGNOS <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="362">et</DiscourseConnective> Galileo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="321" docOffset="2">
      <en>The regulation being signed today is a signal reminder that many aims can only be achieved in the framework of the European Union and not by individual Member States acting alone.</en>
      <fr>La réglementation qui nous occupe aujourd'hui est un signal qui nous rappelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="452">que</DiscourseConnective> de nombreux objectifs ne peuvent être réalisés que dans le cadre de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="543">et</DiscourseConnective> non par les seuls États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="501" docOffset="3">
      <en>EGNOS and Galileo can and will give the European Union the means to establish a European alternative and complement to other systems.</en>
      <fr>EGNOS <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="585">et</DiscourseConnective> Galileo donneront à l'Union européenne les moyens d'apporter une alternative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="665">et</DiscourseConnective> un complément aux systèmes existants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="635" docOffset="4">
      <en>At the same time, they will enable us to enhance the competitiveness of our industry in major strategic technological fields.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="706">En outre</DiscourseConnective>, ils nous permettront de consolider la compétitivité de notre industrie dans d'importants domaines technologiques stratégiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="761" docOffset="5">
      <en>Galileo is to comprise a network of 30 satellites and a ground-control infrastructure.</en>
      <fr>Galileo se composera d'un réseau de trente satellites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="897">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une infrastructure de contrôle au sol.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="848" docOffset="6">
      <en>The text of the regulation we shall be signing today is the result of negotiations between the European institutions which were brought to a successful conclusion at first reading.</en>
      <fr>Le texte que nous nous apprêtons à signer est le fruit de négociations entre les institutions européennes conclues avec succès dès le stade de la première lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1029" docOffset="7">
      <en>The institutions found solutions that made it possible to establish such a highly complex technical system, particularly by agreeing on Community funding of EUR 3.4 billion.</en>
      <fr>Les institutions ont su dégager des solutions qui permettent le déploiement d'un système <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1194">aussi</DiscourseConnective> complexe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1210">notamment en</DiscourseConnective> s'accordant sur un financement communautaire à hauteur de 3,4 milliards d'euros.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1203" docOffset="8">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1304" annotation_id="1203">
          <Alignment alignment="1304" annotation_id="1203">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1203" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">As a result</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, Galileo can become operational from 2013 at the latest.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3950" annotation_id="1304">
          <Alignment alignment="1203" annotation_id="1304">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1304" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">En conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, Galileo devrait être opérationnel d'ici 2013 au <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1368">plus tard</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1272" docOffset="9">
      <en>As President of the European Parliament I would like to express my very special thanks to the chairman of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy, Angelika Niebler, and the rapporteur of the European Parliament, Etelka Barsi-Pataky, for their successful efforts, as well as to the Slovenian Presidency for its significant commitment to this very important strategic dossier.</en>
      <fr>En ma qualité de Président du Parlement européen, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1438">à</DiscourseConnective> exprimer ma gratitude envers la présidente de la commission de l'industrie, de la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1532">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'énergie, Mme Angelika Niebler, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1571">et</DiscourseConnective> le rapporteur du Parlement européen, Mme Etelka Barsi-Pataky, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1636">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail accompli, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1662">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'envers la Présidence slovène <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1700">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'engagement dont elle a fait preuve dans cet important dossier stratégique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1654" docOffset="10">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1665" docOffset="11">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="1810" annotation_id="1667">
          <Alignment alignment="1813" annotation_id="1667">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1667" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> hope that this public signing will underline that we intend to go on working with vigour and dedication to achieve tangible progress for our citizens.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <Alignment alignment="1667" annotation_id="1810">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1810" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que cette signature publique démontrera notre volonté de poursuivre avec ténacité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1901">et</DiscourseConnective> dévouement nos activités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1929">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>obtenir des avancées concrètes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1967">pour</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1823" docOffset="12">
      <en>Thank you for being here today, and thank you for your attention.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie pour votre présence aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2045">et</DiscourseConnective> pour l'attention que vous m'avez accordée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1889" docOffset="13">
      <en>I now invite the representative of the Council, Jean-Pierre Jouyet, to address us.</en>
      <fr>J'invite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2100">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> le représentant du Conseil, M. Jean-Pierre Jouyet, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2162">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre la parole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1972" docOffset="14">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1983" id="254" name="Jean-Pierre Jouyet">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1983" docOffset="15">
      <en>President-in-Office. - (FR) Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, it will now be possible to ascertain precise positioning and timing information with the satellite radio navigation system launched by the European Union and the European Space Agency.</en>
      <fr>Président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2212">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil. - Monsieur le Président, cher Hans-Gert Pöttering, Madame la Commissaire, chère Benita, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2333">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs les députés, connaître sa position dans l'espace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2395">et</DiscourseConnective> dans le temps sera désormais possible avec le système de radionavigation par satellite lancé par l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2514">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Agence spatiale européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2246" docOffset="16">
      <en>I should like to join you, Mr President, in paying tribute to the Slovenian Presidency, which has brought this difficult agreement to a successful conclusion.</en>
      <fr>Et je tiens, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2560">comme</DiscourseConnective> vous l'avez fait, Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2607">à</DiscourseConnective> rendre hommage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2624">à</DiscourseConnective> la Présidence slovène, qui a brillamment conclu cet accord difficile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2405" docOffset="17">
      <en>I should <Alignment alignment="2705" annotation_id="2414">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2414" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to pay tribute to Mrs Niebler, Chairman of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy, your rapporteur and those leading Members of the European Parliament who have made the adoption of this Regulation possible.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <Alignment alignment="2414" annotation_id="2705">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2705" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2715">à</DiscourseConnective> rendre hommage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2732">à</DiscourseConnective> Mme Niebler, la présidente de la commission, à votre rapporteur, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2799">et</DiscourseConnective> aux responsables du Parlement européen qui ont permis l'adoption de ce règlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2640" docOffset="18">
      <en>This is a major step forward that we are taking today by adopting this Regulation on Galileo.</en>
      <fr>C'est en effet une étape très importante qui est franchie aujourd'hui avec l'adoption de ce règlement Galileo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2734" docOffset="19">
      <en>It will enable the deployment of the publicly funded global satellite positioning system.</en>
      <fr>Il va permettre le déploiement, sur fonds publics, du système de positionnement global par satellite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2824" docOffset="20">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3097" annotation_id="2824">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2824" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Mr Pöttering has said, this system is based on a constellation of 30 satellites and ground stations and will provide users in many sectors with information on their location.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2824" annotation_id="3097">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3097" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'a indiqué le Président Pöttering, ce système repose sur une constellation de trente satellites <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3200">et</DiscourseConnective> de stations terrestres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3227">et</DiscourseConnective> il permettra de fournir des informations concernant leur positionnement à des usagers dans de nombreux secteurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3002" docOffset="21">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3349" annotation_id="3002">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3002" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, for many of our citizens, this is an indication of real progress being made by Europe.</en>
      <fr>C'est <Alignment alignment="3002" annotation_id="3349">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3349" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'illustration de l'Europe au concret <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3392">pour</DiscourseConnective> nombre de nos concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3100" docOffset="22">
      <en>It will not only ensure our independence by providing a signal that could replace the American GPS signal, <Alignment alignment="3552" annotation_id="3207">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3207" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3219" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> that service is down, <Alignment alignment="3585" annotation_id="3246">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3246" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it <Alignment alignment="3596" annotation_id="3253">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3253" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> goes much further, <Alignment alignment="3618" annotation_id="3277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3277" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it will provide services that are not currently available through GPS: the tracking of people in distress, which is <Alignment alignment="3745" annotation_id="3401">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3401" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> essential to the role that Europe must play in relation to its citizens, or the establishment of a safety of life service that is particularly suited to air traffic management.</en>
      <fr>Il permet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3434">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> d'assurer notre indépendance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3477">en</DiscourseConnective> fournissant un signal qui pourra se substituer au signal GPS américain, <Alignment alignment="3207" annotation_id="3552">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3552" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">notamment en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cas d'interruption, <Alignment alignment="3246" annotation_id="3585">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3585" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il va <Alignment alignment="1298" annotation_id="3596">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3596" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> bien plus loin, <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="3618">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3618" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il permettra de disposer de services <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3659">que</DiscourseConnective> le GPS ne peut offrir aujourd'hui: la localisation de personnes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3727">en</DiscourseConnective> détresse; cela <Alignment alignment="1191" annotation_id="3745">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3745" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> est très important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3770">pour</DiscourseConnective> le rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3783">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe doit jouer auprès de nos concitoyens, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3834">ou</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place d'un système de sauvegarde de la vie, particulièrement adapté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3916">à</DiscourseConnective> la navigation aérienne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3583" docOffset="23">
      <en>Galileo will <Alignment alignment="3960" annotation_id="3596">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3596" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> bring tangible results to the daily lives of our citizens.</en>
      <fr>Galileo apportera <Alignment alignment="3596" annotation_id="3960">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3960" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des résultats très concrets dans la vie quotidienne de nos concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3665" docOffset="24">
      <en>The European Commission, Commissioner, and the European Space Agency have launched the selection process for companies that will be involved in the deployment of the various lots awarded to implement this system; the establishment of Galileo is obviously <Alignment alignment="4342" annotation_id="3920">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3920" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> of major importance for the competitiveness of European industry.</en>
      <fr>La Commission européenne, Madame la Commissaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4086">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Agence spatiale européenne ont lancé le processus de sélection des entreprises qui participeront au déploiement des différents lots attribués <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4233">pour</DiscourseConnective> mettre en œuvre ce système, et la mise en place de Galileo est bien évidemment d'une importance majeure <Alignment alignment="3920" annotation_id="4342">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4342" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4352">pour</DiscourseConnective> la compétitivité de l'industrie européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3991" docOffset="25">
      <en>Overall, the management of the Galileo programme will be placed under the political control of Parliament and the Council.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4401">Au total</DiscourseConnective>, la gestion de ce programme Galileo sera placée sous le contrôle politique de votre Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4504">et</DiscourseConnective> du Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4114" docOffset="26">
      <en>You may rest assured that the French Presidency is determined to work very closely with the European Parliament; it proposes that the Galileo Interinstitutional Panel, the GIP, which involves the three EU institutions - the Commission, Parliament and the Council - meet as soon as possible in order to discuss the conditions necessary for the successful implementation of this programme, which is very important for the European Union as a whole.</en>
      <fr>La Présidence française, soyez-en persuadés, est déterminée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4579">à</DiscourseConnective> travailler très étroitement avec le Parlement européen et propose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4647">que</DiscourseConnective> le groupe interinstitutionnel "Galileo", le GIP, qui associe les trois institutions européennes - la Commission, le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4777">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil - se réunisse au plus vite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4818">afin de</DiscourseConnective> se pencher sur les conditions de réalisation de ce programme très important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4902">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4561" id="255" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4561" docOffset="27">
      <en>Thank you very much, Minister.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Merci Monsieur le ministre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4592" docOffset="28">
      <en>Mr Jouyet and I shall now sign the Galileo Regulation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4647" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I would like to ask Commissioner Ferrero-Waldner, Angelika Niebler, chairman of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy, and Etelka Barsi-Pataky, the rapporteur, to step forward and join us.</en>
      <fr>M. Jouyet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4984">et</DiscourseConnective> moi-même allons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5003">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> procéder à la signature du règlement. J'invite la commissaire, Mme Ferrero-Waldner, la présidente de la commission de l'industrie, de la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5161">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'énergie, Mme Angelika Niebler, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5200">et</DiscourseConnective> la rapporteure du Parlement européen, Mme Etelka Barsi-Pataky, à nous rejoindre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4849" docOffset="29">
      <en>(Signing of the Galileo Regulation)</en>
      <fr>(Signature du règlement Galileo)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4885" docOffset="30">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
