<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Directives concerning the protection of health and safety of workers: simplifying and rationalising practical implementation reports (debate)</en>
    <fr>Simplification <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15">et</DiscourseConnective> rationalisation des rapports relatifs à la mise en œuvre pratique des directives concernant la protection de la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="136">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité au travail (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="142" id="457" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="142" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Mrs Figueiredo, on behalf of the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs, on the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Council Directive 89/391/EEC, its individual Directives and Council Directives 83/477/EEC, 91/383/EEC, 92/29/EEC and 94/33/EC with a view to simplifying and rationalising the reports on practical implementation - C6-0242/2006 -.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de Ilda Figueiredo, au nom de la commission de l'emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="264">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires sociales, sur la proposition de directive du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="344">et</DiscourseConnective> du Conseil modifiant la directive 89/391/CEE du Conseil, ses directives particulières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="433">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les directives du Conseil 83/477/CEE, 91/383/CEE, 92/29/CEE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="503">et</DiscourseConnective> 94/33/CE, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="516">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> la simplification <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="544">et</DiscourseConnective> de la rationalisation des rapports relatifs à la mise en œuvre pratique - C6-0242/2006 -.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="566" id="458" name="Vladimír Špidla">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="566" docOffset="2">
      <en>Member of the Commission. (CS) Madam President, Mrs Figueiredo, honourable Members, I should first like to thank Parliament and the Council for their efforts in reaching agreement so quickly on this proposal.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, Mme Figueiredo, Mesdames et Messieurs, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="710">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> remercier le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="746">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="760">pour</DiscourseConnective> leurs efforts, qui ont permis de trouver un accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="816">si</DiscourseConnective> rapidement sur cette proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="775" docOffset="3">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="862" annotation_id="777">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="777" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcome the Figueiredo report, which kick-started the constructive dialogue chaired by the Council, where the foundations were laid for the adoption of the proposed directive at first reading.</en>
      <fr>Je salue <Alignment alignment="777" annotation_id="862">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="862" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le rapport Figueiredo, qui a donné un coup de fouet au dialogue constructif présidé par le Conseil, qui jette les fondations de l'adoption de la proposition de directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1038">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="975" docOffset="4">
      <en>The Commission's proposed directive forms part of the process of simplifying the legal environment.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de directive de la Commission fait partie du processus de simplification de l'environnement juridique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1075" docOffset="5">
      <en>The purpose of this proposal is to simplify and rationalise the responsibilities of the Member States and the Commission as regards reports on the implementation of directives relating to worker health and safety, without backsliding on the principle of protection.</en>
      <fr>Cette proposition vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1200">à</DiscourseConnective> simplifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1213">et</DiscourseConnective> à rationaliser les responsabilités des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1269">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1289">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les rapports sur la mise en œuvre des directives relatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1367">à</DiscourseConnective> la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1378">et</DiscourseConnective> à la sécurité des travailleurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1413">sans</DiscourseConnective> retomber dans l'erreur sur le principe de la protection.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1341" docOffset="6">
      <en>This is a fundamental condition.</en>
      <fr>C'est là une condition fondamentale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1374" docOffset="7">
      <en>The new text harmonises the timeframes for delivering national reports that will be published once every five years, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1491" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this obligation is extended to all existing directives.</en>
      <fr>Le nouveau texte harmonise les délais de soumission des rapports nationaux qui seront publiés une fois tous les cinq ans. Cette obligation est étendue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1663">à</DiscourseConnective> toutes les directives existantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1551" docOffset="8">
      <en>The plan is for only one report, including a general section dealing with the general principles of the framework directive, supplemented by special chapters on aspects relating to the individual directives.</en>
      <fr>Le plan ne concerne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1719">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un rapport comprenant une section générale traitant des principes généraux de la directive-cadre, complétée par des chapitres spéciaux concernant les aspects se rapportant aux directives individuelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1759" docOffset="9">
      <en>This will allow for a general overview of practical implementation.</en>
      <fr>Cela permettra une vue d'ensemble générale sur l'application pratique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1827" docOffset="10">
      <en>The simplification will apply to the national bodies, which will draw up only one report every five years, the Commission, which will draw up only one national report per Member State instead of the current 500 reports, and the social partners, which will <Alignment alignment="2260" annotation_id="2083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2083" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> contribute one report every five years.</en>
      <fr>La simplification s'appliquera aux organismes nationaux, qui ne rédigeront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2070">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un rapport tous les cinq ans, à la Commission, qui ne rédigera qu'un seul rapport national par État membre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2180">au lieu</DiscourseConnective> des 500 rapports actuels; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2214">et</DiscourseConnective> aux partenaires sociaux, qui contribueront <Alignment alignment="2083" annotation_id="2260">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2260" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à un rapport tous les cinq ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2128" docOffset="11">
      <en>The Commission, in close cooperation with the consultative committee on health and safety at work, will set up a body charged with helping the Member States to draw up coherent reports.</en>
      <fr>La Commission, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2313">en</DiscourseConnective> étroite collaboration avec le comité consultatif sur la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2378">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité au travail, mettra sur pied un organisme chargé d'aider les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2467">à</DiscourseConnective> rédiger des rapports cohérents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2314" docOffset="12">
      <en>The Commission is ready to adopt the amendments for which you voted.</en>
      <fr>La Commission est prête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2525">à</DiscourseConnective> adopter les amendements en faveur desquels vous avez voté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2383" docOffset="13">
      <en>I will strengthen the role of the tripartite advisory committee on health and safety at work in defining the structure of the reports, in clearly establishing the content of the reports and in setting deadlines for the Member States and the Commission to draw up the reports.</en>
      <fr>Je renforcerai le rôle du comité consultatif tripartite sur la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2655">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité au travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2681">en</DiscourseConnective> définissant la structure des rapports, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2723">en</DiscourseConnective> établissant clairement le contenu des rapports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2773">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2776">en</DiscourseConnective> fixant des échéances aux États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2818">et</DiscourseConnective> à la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2837">pour</DiscourseConnective> la rédaction des rapports.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2659" docOffset="14">
      <en>Thank you.</en>
      <fr>Merci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2670" id="459" name="Ilda Figueiredo ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2670" docOffset="15">
      <en>rapporteur. (PT) Issues of workers' health and working conditions, the organisation of health, hygiene and safety services in the workplace and the list of occupational diseases were first debated in Community circles in 1989 with the publication of Framework Directive 89/391.</en>
      <fr>Les questions de la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2902">et</DiscourseConnective> des conditions de travail des travailleurs, de l'organisation des services de santé, d'hygiène <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3000">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité sur le lieu du travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3038">et</DiscourseConnective> de la liste des maladies professionnelles ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3087">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> été débattues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3114">en</DiscourseConnective> 1989 dans les cercles communautaires, avec la publication de la directive-cadre 89/391.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2948" docOffset="16">
      <en>Since then, other directives have been adopted covering workers' health, the organisation of occupational health services, working conditions, young workers, temporary workers, and those manning ships, <Alignment alignment="951" annotation_id="3150">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3150" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> fulfilling the International Labour Organisation Conventions.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3205">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> lors, d'autres directives ont été adoptées qui couvrent la santé des travailleurs, l'organisation des services de santé au travail, les conditions de travail, les jeunes travailleurs, les travailleurs temporaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3425">et</DiscourseConnective> les équipages des navires, complétant <Alignment alignment="3150" annotation_id="3466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3466" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les conventions de l'Organisation internationale du travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3220" docOffset="17">
      <en>Almost all of these and other directives stipulate that the Member States should submit a report to the Commission on their practical implementation and the points of view of the social partners.</en>
      <fr>Presque toutes ces directives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3563">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres directives précisent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3596">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres doivent soumettre un rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3647">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur leur mise en œuvre pratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3695">et</DiscourseConnective> les points de vue des partenaires sociaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3416" docOffset="18">
      <en>The truth is that some Member States have not done so.</en>
      <fr>La vérité est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3755">que</DiscourseConnective> certains États membres ne l'ont pas fait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3471" docOffset="19">
      <en>With the proposal before us, it is hoped that greater attention will be paid to the effective implementation of the directives concerned and to working conditions.</en>
      <fr>Avec la proposition à l'examen, nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3847">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une plus grande attention sera consacrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3891">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en œuvre effective des directives concernées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3946">et</DiscourseConnective> aux conditions de travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3635" docOffset="20">
      <en>It is an attempt to reduce the millions of accidents at work per year and thousands of deaths and injuries leading to permanent incapacity across the EU.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3979">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'une tentative de réduire les millions d'accidents qui surviennent chaque année sur les lieux de travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4092">et</DiscourseConnective> les milliers de décès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4117">et</DiscourseConnective> d'accidents qui mènent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4143">à</DiscourseConnective> une incapacité permanente dans l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3789" docOffset="21">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4196" annotation_id="3789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3789" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I have said, the drafting of practical implementation reports by the Member States, is laid down in several different directives, but required at different intervals, some every four years, some every five, and others without any specific timeframe.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3789" annotation_id="4196">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4196" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai dit, la rédaction de rapports de mise en œuvre pratique par les États membres figure dans plusieurs directives, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4322">mais</DiscourseConnective> ces rapports sont requis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4352">à</DiscourseConnective> intervalles différents, certains tous les quatre ans, d'autres tous les cinq ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4435">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres encore <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4454">sans</DiscourseConnective> aucun délai spécifique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4042" docOffset="22">
      <en>Now, <Alignment alignment="4494" annotation_id="4047">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4047" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commissioner has just told us, the Commission is proposing that one single report be drawn up every five years.</en>
      <fr>À présent, <Alignment alignment="4047" annotation_id="4494">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4494" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le commissaire vient de nous le dire, la Commission propose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4560">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un seul rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4579">soit</DiscourseConnective> rédigé tous les cinq ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4166" docOffset="23">
      <en>In order that the proposal for one report every five years meets the needs of safeguarding health and safety at work, the specific aspects of each directive must not in any way be watered down or underplayed, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4375" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this is something that this report seeks to address.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4610">Pour que</DiscourseConnective> la proposition d'un rapport tous les cinq ans réponde aux besoins de protection de la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4711">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité au travail, les aspects spécifiques de chaque directive ne doivent nullement être atténués <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4820">ou</DiscourseConnective> minimisés, c'est un aspect auquel ce rapport tente de répondre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4432" docOffset="24">
      <en>We have <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4440" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">accordingly</DiscourseConnective> tabled a number of proposals, of which I should like to highlight those that refer to the structure of the report itself, which should include a specific questionnaire.</en>
      <fr>C'est pour cela que nous avons déposé plusieurs propositions. Je voudrais souligner les propositions qui se réfèrent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5004">à</DiscourseConnective> la structure du rapport lui-même, qui devrait inclure un questionnaire spécifique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4621" docOffset="25">
      <en>The report should <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4639" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">accordingly</DiscourseConnective> include a general section dealing with the common principles and aspects applicable to all the directives and other specific chapters regarding the implementation of each of the particular characteristics of each directive, with the inclusion of specific indicators, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4918" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> available.</en>
      <fr>Ainsi, ce rapport devrait inclure une section générale traitant des principes communs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5175">et</DiscourseConnective> des aspects applicables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5202">à</DiscourseConnective> toutes les directives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5226">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres chapitres spécifiques qui concernent la mise en œuvre de chacune des caractéristiques particulières de chaque directive, avec l'inclusion des indicateurs spécifiques, le cas échéant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4934" docOffset="26">
      <en>The five-yearly report will provide a practical assessment of the various directives and, where appropriate and available, separate data by gender on equality between men and women.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport quinquennal fournira une évaluation pratique des différentes directives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5504">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5508">lorsque</DiscourseConnective> cela s'avèrera approprié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5541">et</DiscourseConnective> disponible, des données séparées concernant l'égalité entre les hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5615">et</DiscourseConnective> les femmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5116" docOffset="27">
      <en>It will <Alignment alignment="5649" annotation_id="5124">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5124" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> include relevant information on the prevention measures taken by the Member States in order to make a suitable assessment of how the legislation is working in practice.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport inclura <Alignment alignment="5124" annotation_id="5649">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5649" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des informations pertinentes sur les mesures de prévention prises par les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5743">afin de</DiscourseConnective> se livrer à une évaluation appropriée du fonctionnement de la législation dans la pratique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5298" docOffset="28">
      <en>We strongly believe that there needs to be a policy of genuinely improving the practices of the various Member States.</en>
      <fr>Nous pensons fermement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5866">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il doit y avoir une véritable politique d'amélioration des pratiques des différents États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5417" docOffset="29">
      <en>The Commission must <Alignment alignment="23163" annotation_id="5437">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5437" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, as a matter of urgency, submit a more thorough report on the current situation in the Member States in the various areas of workers' safety and health in the workplace.</en>
      <fr>La Commission doit <Alignment alignment="5437" annotation_id="5987">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5987" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> soumettre d'urgence un rapport plus approfondi concernant la situation actuelle des États membres dans les différents domaines de la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6136">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité sur les lieux du travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5612" docOffset="30">
      <en>Lastly, I should like to highlight the close cooperation that was possible with the MEPs from the different political groups in the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs, with the Executive Committee and with the Council.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6180">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais souligner l'étroite coopération qui a été possible avec les eurodéputés des différents groupes politiques de la commission de l'emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6334">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires sociales, avec le comité exécutif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6384">et</DiscourseConnective> avec le Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5839" docOffset="31">
      <en>This cooperation will certainly enable us to obtain agreement at first reading.</en>
      <fr>Cette coopération nous permettra certainement d'obtenir l'accord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6469">en</DiscourseConnective> première lecture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5919" docOffset="32">
      <en>I thank you all for the work that has been done.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie tous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6512">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail accompli.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5968" id="460" name="Mihael Brejc">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5968" docOffset="33">
      <en>on behalf of the PPE-DE Group. - (SL) First of all, I would like to express satisfaction with this report on behalf of the Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats, <Alignment alignment="13335" annotation_id="6174">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6174" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it constitutes one of the first steps towards a significant relaxation of the burden imposed on Member States with regard to various administrative tasks.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6538">Tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais dire ma satisfaction concernant ce rapport, au nom du groupe du parti populaire européen (démocrates-chrétiens) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6676">et</DiscourseConnective> des démocrates européens, <Alignment alignment="6174" annotation_id="6705">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6705" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il constitue un des premiers pas vers un allégement significatif du fardeau imposé aux États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6815">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de tâches administratives.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6337" docOffset="34">
      <en>At the same time, this directive will contribute to the simplification and clarification of the work of the Commission.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6853">En même temps</DiscourseConnective>, cette directive contribuera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6896">à</DiscourseConnective> simplifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6909">et</DiscourseConnective> clarifier le travail de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6457" docOffset="35">
      <en>In the PPE-DE Group we are very pleased to note that the agreement with the rapporteur has worked <Alignment alignment="20680" annotation_id="6555">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6555" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that we have been able to secure such a broad consensus within our committee.</en>
      <fr>Dans le groupe PPE-DE, nous sommes très heureux de constater <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7012">que</DiscourseConnective> l'accord avec le rapporteur a fonctionné <Alignment alignment="6555" annotation_id="7057">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7057" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7060">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons pu garantir un consensus large au sein de notre commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6637" docOffset="36">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7135" annotation_id="6637">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6637" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I remember rightly, we adopted this report with only one vote against.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6637" annotation_id="7135">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7135" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mes souvenirs sont bons, nous avons adopté ce rapport par une seule voix contre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6711" docOffset="37">
      <en>In terms of its contents, the report sends yet another clear message to the European public that the Commission, the Council and Parliament are taking decisions to rationalise procedures and to improve communication between the Member States and EU institutions <Alignment alignment="30924" annotation_id="6973">
          <Alignment alignment="7508" annotation_id="6973">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6973" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> everyone can reap the benefits of such action.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7219">Pour</DiscourseConnective> ce qui est de son contenu, ce rapport adresse un autre message clair au public européen: la Commission, le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7339">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement prennent des décisions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7378">pour</DiscourseConnective> rationaliser les procédures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7411">et</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la communication entre les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7465">et</DiscourseConnective> les institutions de l'Union européenne, <Alignment alignment="6973" annotation_id="7508">
          <Alignment alignment="6973" annotation_id="7508">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7508" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">pour que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> chacun puisse profiter de cette action.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7028" docOffset="38">
      <en>This directive and the single report will in no respect lead to any watering down of standards relating to health and safety at work.</en>
      <fr>Cette directive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7573">et</DiscourseConnective> le rapport unique ne conduiront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7608">en</DiscourseConnective> aucun cas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7621">à</DiscourseConnective> l'affaiblissement des normes en matière de santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7672">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité au travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7162" docOffset="39">
      <en>My political group considers this report in its entirety, that is the directive, as an important step forward, <Alignment alignment="7819" annotation_id="7273">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7273" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, of course, we would like to see similar initiatives being taken in other fields and by other commissioners.</en>
      <fr>Mon groupe politique considère ce rapport dans sa totalité, c'est-à-dire la directive, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7786">comme</DiscourseConnective> un pas important en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7812">avant</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="7273" annotation_id="7819">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7819" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> bien sûr nous voudrions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7848">que</DiscourseConnective> des initiatives similaires soient prises dans d'autres domaines par d'autres commissaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7386" docOffset="40">
      <en>Let me mention just one example: in the field of terrorism, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7446" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for instance</DiscourseConnective>, the European Parliament has adopted around 60 different documents, directives, regulations etc.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi de ne donner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7970">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un seul exemple: dans le domaine du terrorisme, le Parlement européen a adopté environ 60 documents, directives, règlements, etc. différents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7556" docOffset="41">
      <en>Things are quite hard to fathom out, <Alignment alignment="8162" annotation_id="7593">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7593" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for instance</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Schengen Treaty, the single market and a host of other examples.</en>
      <fr>Il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8122">plutôt</DiscourseConnective> difficile de démêler l'écheveau, <Alignment alignment="7593" annotation_id="8162">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8162" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le traité de Schengen, le marché unique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8208">et</DiscourseConnective> tout un tas d'autres exemples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7675" docOffset="42">
      <en>In a nutshell, this report is a fine example of how we can secure broad consensus within political groups about regulating our common concerns in the future.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8242">En résumé</DiscourseConnective>, ce rapport est un excellent exemple de la manière dont nous pouvons garantir un consensus large au sein des groupes politiques concernant la manière de réguler nos préoccupations communes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8441">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7833" docOffset="43">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="8465" annotation_id="7841">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7841" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to thank Commissioner Špidla for his participation.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="7841" annotation_id="8465">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8465" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remercier le commissaire Špidla <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8507">pour</DiscourseConnective> sa participation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7903" id="461" name="Harald Ettl">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7903" docOffset="44">
      <en>on behalf of the PSE Group. - (DE) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to thank Mrs Figueiredo for her work.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8562">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais remercier Mme Figueiredo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8613">pour</DiscourseConnective> son travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8025" docOffset="45">
      <en>She worked closely with the shadow rapporteur and produced a sound draft report for the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs.</en>
      <fr>Elle a travaillé étroitement avec le rapporteur fictif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8686">et</DiscourseConnective> elle a produit un projet de rapport équilibré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8735">pour</DiscourseConnective> la commission de l'emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8766">et</DiscourseConnective> des affaires sociales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8157" docOffset="46">
      <en>The Commission proposal aims towards systematisation and a uniform model for the directives on worker protection.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de la Commission vise une systématisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8849">et</DiscourseConnective> un modèle uniforme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8871">pour</DiscourseConnective> les directives sur la protection des travailleurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8271" docOffset="47">
      <en>In a single implementation report to be submitted every five years and for which we have been waiting quite a long time already, the Member States are to report to the Commission on the practical application of the directives in question.</en>
      <fr>Dans un rapport unique de mise en œuvre, qui sera soumis tous les cinq ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9002">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9005">que</DiscourseConnective> nous attendons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9024">déjà</DiscourseConnective> depuis longtemps, les États membres devront faire rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9087">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission de l'application pratique des directives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9144">en</DiscourseConnective> question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8510" docOffset="48">
      <en>This plan will certainly provide the single-state authorities - which is the truth of the matter - with a better overview.</en>
      <fr>Ce plan fournira certainement un meilleur aperçu aux autorités de chaque État, ce qui est le cœur de la question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8633" docOffset="49">
      <en>Comprehensive and effective worker protection is a basic prerequisite for ensuring and maintaining the health of workers.</en>
      <fr>La protection générale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9294">et</DiscourseConnective> effective des travailleurs est une condition préalable essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9364">pour</DiscourseConnective> garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9378">et</DiscourseConnective> maintenir la santé des travailleurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8755" docOffset="50">
      <en>4 500 employees die in the EU every year as a result of accidents in the workplace, <Alignment alignment="9517" annotation_id="8839">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8839" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> over 4 million people are affected by accidents at work each year.</en>
      <fr>4 500 salariés meurent chaque année dans les accidents qui se produisent sur les lieux du travail, <Alignment alignment="8839" annotation_id="9517">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9517" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> plus de 4 millions de personnes sont concernées par des accidents sur les lieux du travail chaque année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8912" docOffset="51">
      <en>A summary report of this nature can provide us with important information with regard to what preventive measures we need to implement and make a contribution to improving the quality of worker protection in the EU.</en>
      <fr>Un rapport succinct de cette nature peut nous fournir des informations importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9715">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les mesures préventives que nous devons mettre en œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9790">et</DiscourseConnective> apporter une contribution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9819">à</DiscourseConnective> l'amélioration de la qualité de la protection des travailleurs dans l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9128" id="462" name="Leopold Józef Rutowicz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9128" docOffset="52">
      <en>on behalf of the UEN Group. - (PL) Mr President, the report on simplifying and rationalising reports and the practical implementation of directives is extremely important for employment policy.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, le rapport concernant les rapports de simplification <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9985">et</DiscourseConnective> de rationalisation, ainsi que la mise en œuvre pratique des directives est extrêmement important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10085">pour</DiscourseConnective> la politique de l'emploi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9322" docOffset="53">
      <en>The emerging common jobs market requires constant health and safety monitoring for our citizens in EU countries.</en>
      <fr>Le marché émergent des emplois communs nécessite un suivi constant de la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10195">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité de nos concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9435" docOffset="54">
      <en>Different conditions in individual countries require constant monitoring to ensure that the directives are adhered to, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9554" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> five-yearly analyses of their suitability, effectiveness, transparency, costs and effects are needed.</en>
      <fr>Les différentes conditions dans chaque pays nécessitent un suivi constant afin de veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10328">que</DiscourseConnective> les directives soient respectées. Des analyses quinquennales de leur durabilité, efficacité, transparence, coûts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10445">et</DiscourseConnective> effets sont nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9660" docOffset="55">
      <en>These analyses, based on clear and transparent guidelines, should help to improve the legal situation and common policy as regards health and safety.</en>
      <fr>Ces analyses basées sur des orientations claires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10522">et</DiscourseConnective> transparentes devraient contribuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10560">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la situation juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10595">et</DiscourseConnective> la politique commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10619">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10639">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9810" docOffset="56">
      <en>There is <Alignment alignment="10662" annotation_id="9819">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9819" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a need to continuously monitor health and safety directives, and the effect of these directives on the health and safety strategy within the Member States.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="9771" annotation_id="10662">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10662" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nécessaire de suivre continuellement les directives en matière de santé et de sécurité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10760">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que l'effet de ces directives sur la stratégie en matière de santé et de sécurité dans les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9980" docOffset="57">
      <en>In this regard, the European Agency for Health and Safety at Work and the European Foundation for the Improvement of Living and Working Conditions have an important role to play.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10872">À cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, l'agence européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10905">pour</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10922">et</DiscourseConnective> la santé au travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10945">et</DiscourseConnective> la fondation européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10972">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'amélioration des conditions de vie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11014">et</DiscourseConnective> de travail ont un rôle important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11050">à</DiscourseConnective> jouer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10159" docOffset="58">
      <en>I thank Mrs Ilda Figueiredo for her report.</en>
      <fr>Je remercie Mme Ilda Figueiredo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11091">pour</DiscourseConnective> son rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10203" id="463" name="Andreas Mölzer">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10203" docOffset="59">
      <en>on behalf of the ITS Group. - (DE) Mr President, the modern working world has brought with it new phenomena, ranging from the growth of psychiatric problems, via the taking of more and more sick leave and increasing burn-out to new forms of aggression such as workplace bullying.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, le monde moderne du travail a entraîné avec lui de nouveaux phénomènes, qui vont de la progression des problèmes psychiatriques, en passant par les congés de maladie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11298">de plus</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11306">en plus</DiscourseConnective> nombreux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11323">et</DiscourseConnective> le burn out, à de nouvelles formes d'agression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11373">comme</DiscourseConnective> le harcèlement moral sur le lieu de travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10483" docOffset="60">
      <en>It almost seems to be good form in the working environment to put workers under permanent time pressure and to impose on them unplanned extra burdens and tight deadlines.</en>
      <fr>Il semble de bon ton dans l'environnement du travail de soumettre les travailleurs à une pression permanente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11533">et</DiscourseConnective> de leur imposer des délais serrés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11570">et</DiscourseConnective> des charges de travail supplémentaires imprévues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10654" docOffset="61">
      <en>Anyone who succumbs to the long-term negative impact of this on their health has to explain themselves in interviews <Alignment alignment="11751" annotation_id="10771">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10771" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they return to work after a period of sick leave, the idea being that illness is a result of personal misconduct.</en>
      <fr>Tous ceux qui succombent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11648">à</DiscourseConnective> l'impact négatif à long terme de cette situation sur leur santé doivent s'expliquer lors d'entrevues <Alignment alignment="10771" annotation_id="11751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11751" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">à</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leur retour au travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11776">après</DiscourseConnective> une période de congé de maladie, l'idée étant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11828">que</DiscourseConnective> la maladie est le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11850">résultat</DiscourseConnective> d'une faute personnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10890" docOffset="62">
      <en>Older workers are being pushed off into early retirement en masse, and younger ones labelled as unproductive.</en>
      <fr>Les travailleurs les plus âgés sont incités à prendre leur retraite anticipée en masse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11971">et</DiscourseConnective> les plus jeunes sont étiquetés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12005">comme</DiscourseConnective> étant improductifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11000" docOffset="63">
      <en>Initiatives such as Move Europe which relate to workplace health management are, of course, to be welcomed.</en>
      <fr>Des initiatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12047">comme</DiscourseConnective> Move Europe qui se rapportent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12083">à</DiscourseConnective> la gestion de la santé sur le lieu de travail méritent bien sûr d'être saluées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11108" docOffset="64">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12165" annotation_id="11108">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11108" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, such health promotion programmes are often run in companies that are organised in such a way that illness is simply not permitted.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11108" annotation_id="12165">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12165" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ces programmes de promotion de la santé sont souvent promus au sein de sociétés organisées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12267">de manière à</DiscourseConnective> ne pas permettre la maladie tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12313">simplement</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11248" docOffset="65">
      <en>It is pressure within companies, in combination with the fear of losing their jobs, that ensures that employees struggle into work against the advice of their doctors.</en>
      <fr>C'est la pression au sein de l'entreprise, combinée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12377">à</DiscourseConnective> la crainte de perdre son emploi, qui pousse les salariés à retourner au travail contre l'avis de leurs médecins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11416" docOffset="66">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12492" annotation_id="11416">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11416" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, short-term contracted activities and part-time work bring with them the constant fear of not having a job and financial worries which are <Alignment alignment="11313" annotation_id="11564">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11564" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> reflected in psychological problems.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4704" annotation_id="12492">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12492" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, les activités à court terme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12529">et</DiscourseConnective> le travail à temps partiel entraînent dans leur sillage la crainte constante de ne pas avoir d'emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12634">et</DiscourseConnective> les soucis financiers se traduisent <Alignment alignment="9855" annotation_id="12673">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12673" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12681">en</DiscourseConnective> problèmes psychologiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11606" docOffset="67">
      <en>Absenteeism and unfitness for work, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11642" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>, not only generate high costs within the companies concerned, but also burden public health budgets.</en>
      <fr>L'absentéisme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12724">et</DiscourseConnective> l'inaptitude au travail génèrent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12760">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> des coûts élevés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12791">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'entreprise concernée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12820">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> un fardeau pour les budgets de la santé publique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11751" docOffset="68">
      <en>Against this backdrop we should not be surprised about the rising numbers of those suffering from eating disorders, obesity and mental illness, nor about falling birth rates.</en>
      <fr>Dans ces circonstances, il ne faut pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12920">s'</DiscourseConnective>étonner du nombre croissant de personnes souffrant de troubles de l'alimentation, d'obésité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13014">et</DiscourseConnective> de maladie mentale, ni de la chute du taux des naissances.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11926" docOffset="69">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13076" annotation_id="11926">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11926" sense="Contingency.Condition">As long as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> work means permanent stress and children represent a poverty trap, the demographic change that is resulting in a lack of children and an overaging of the population will continue.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11926" annotation_id="13076">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13076" sense="Contingency.Condition">Tant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le travail représentera un stress permanent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13129">et</DiscourseConnective> que les enfants représenteront un piège susceptible de faire sombrer dans la pauvreté, le changement démographique qui conduit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13259">à</DiscourseConnective> une pénurie d'enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13283">et</DiscourseConnective> à un vieillissement de la population se poursuivra.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12117" docOffset="70">
      <en>With this in mind, we must ensure more job security.</en>
      <fr>Gardant cela <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13351">à</DiscourseConnective> l'esprit, nous devons garantir une plus grande sécurité de l'emploi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12170" docOffset="71">
      <en>It must be possible for a sole breadwinner to feed a family <Alignment alignment="13495" annotation_id="12230">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12230" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it must be possible for a woman to decide to have children without that meaning impoverishment.</en>
      <fr>Il doit être possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13444">à</DiscourseConnective> un seul soutien de famille de nourrir sa famille <Alignment alignment="12230" annotation_id="13495">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13495" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il doit être possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13520">à</DiscourseConnective> une femme de décider d'avoir des enfants, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13564">sans que</DiscourseConnective> cela ne signifie un appauvrissement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12330" docOffset="72">
      <en>Those who are sick must be allowed to get better.</en>
      <fr>Les personnes malades doivent pouvoir aller <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13654">mieux</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12380" docOffset="73">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13661" annotation_id="12380">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12380" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we could achieve that <Alignment alignment="13694" annotation_id="12405">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12405" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we would surely have taken a big step forwards on the road to meeting the Lisbon objectives.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12380" annotation_id="13661">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13661" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous pouvons parvenir à cela, <Alignment alignment="12405" annotation_id="13694">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13694" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous aurons certainement accompli un grand pas en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13750">avant</DiscourseConnective> vers les objectifs de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12503" id="464" name="Marie Panayotopoulos-Cassiotou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12503" docOffset="74">
      <en>(EL) Mr President, with regard to all the previous directives we are given the impression that we exerted insufficient control, which did not help with their comprehensive implementation.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13816">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne toutes les directives précédentes, nous avons l'impression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13894">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons exercé un contrôle insuffisant, qui n'a pas contribué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13963">à</DiscourseConnective> leur mise en œuvre générale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12691" docOffset="75">
      <en>Even the directive's explicit provision regarding the submission of reports by Member States on their state legislative provisions, which includes opinions of social partners, has not helped solve the problem, to date.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13994">Même</DiscourseConnective> la disposition explicite de la directive qui prévoit la soumission de rapports des États membres concernant leurs dispositions législatives, qui reprend les avis des partenaires sociaux, n'a pas contribué à résoudre le problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14227">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> présent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12910" docOffset="76">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="22860" annotation_id="12910">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12910" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I too applaud your proposal Commissioner, considering that it complies with the goals of other European Union policies, especially with regard to the improvement of the regulatory framework on increasing corporate competitiveness.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12910" annotation_id="14244">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14244" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, j'applaudis moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14270">aussi</DiscourseConnective> à votre proposition, Monsieur le commissaire, compte tenu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14334">du fait qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle est conforme aux objectifs d'autres politiques de l'Union européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14420">surtout</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14428">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne l'amélioration du cadre réglementaire sur l'augmentation de la compétitivité des entreprises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13152" docOffset="77">
      <en>The present proposal has added value, considering that it allows - through a single report every five years - for a better evaluation of the consequences and community provisions in the fields of health and safety at work as well as hygiene services; the need for a reduction in accidents at work is urgent <Alignment alignment="14877" annotation_id="13459">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13459" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> work-related diseases must be combated in order for workers, corporations and society in general, to benefit.</en>
      <fr>La présente proposition apporte une valeur ajoutée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14592">car</DiscourseConnective> elle permet - à travers un seul rapport tous les cinq ans - une meilleure évaluation des conséquences des dispositions communautaires dans les domaines de la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14760">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité au travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14789">et</DiscourseConnective> les services d'hygiène; la nécessité de réduire les accidents au travail est urgente <Alignment alignment="13459" annotation_id="14877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14877" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les maladies liées au travail doivent être combattues au bénéfice des travailleurs, des entreprises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14980">et</DiscourseConnective> de la société <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14997">en</DiscourseConnective> général.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13573" docOffset="78">
      <en>I congratulate the rapporteur <Alignment alignment="15036" annotation_id="13603">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13603" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> she cooperated with the political groups, reached a consensus within the Council and managed to include in the recitals one of my amendments referring to the utilisation of the work of both the European Agency for Safety and Health at Work (Bilbao) and the European Foundation for the Improvement of Living and Working Conditions (Dublin), in the context of the results from the evaluation of national policies on health and safety at work.</en>
      <fr>Je félicite le rapporteur, <Alignment alignment="13603" annotation_id="15036">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15036" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elle a coopéré avec les groupes politiques, qu'elle a obtenu un consensus au sein du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15138">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'elle est parvenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15162">à</DiscourseConnective> inclure dans les considérants un de mes amendements faisant référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15234">à</DiscourseConnective> l'utilisation du travail de l'agence européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15284">pour</DiscourseConnective> la santé et la sécurité au travail (Bilbao) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15333">et</DiscourseConnective> de la fondation européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15363">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'amélioration des conditions de vie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15405">et</DiscourseConnective> de travail (Dublin), dans le contexte des résultats de l'évaluation des politiques nationales sur la santé et la sécurité au travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14052" docOffset="79">
      <en>It is important that the European Commission takes into consideration the findings of the two aforementioned institutions, in order to draft the basic questionnaire for the Member States, which will substitute the multiple reports.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15553">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne prenne en considération les conclusions des deux institutions susmentionnées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15659">afin de</DiscourseConnective> rédiger le questionnaire de base <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15700">pour</DiscourseConnective> les États membres, qui remplacera les rapports multiples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14284" docOffset="80">
      <en>The question is whether a reduction in quantity can bring about an improvement in quality.</en>
      <fr>La question est de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15789">si</DiscourseConnective> une réduction quantitative peut entraîner une amélioration qualitative.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14375" docOffset="81">
      <en>We certainly hope so.</en>
      <fr>Nous l'espérons vraiment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14397" id="465" language="CS" name="Vladimír Špidla">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14397" docOffset="82">
      <en>Honourable Members, I should like, once again, to thank you for the work you have done on this proposal.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames et Messieurs, une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15922">encore</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais vous remercier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15957">pour</DiscourseConnective> votre travail sur cette proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14502" docOffset="83">
      <en>I am sure that the vote will pave the way for us to agree on the proposal, which will lead to a substantial simplification of the administrative process, a reduction in unnecessary, bureaucratic obstacles and most importantly to a more effective implementation of the directive on health and safety at work.</en>
      <fr>Je suis sûr <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16011">que</DiscourseConnective> le vote nous permettra de trouver un accord sur la proposition, qui conduira <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16092">à</DiscourseConnective> une simplification considérable de la procédure administrative, à une réduction des obstacles bureaucratiques inutiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16213">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16216">surtout</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16224">à</DiscourseConnective> une mise en œuvre plus efficace de la directive sur la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16287">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité au travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14810" docOffset="84">
      <en>I should like, <Alignment alignment="18760" annotation_id="14825">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14825" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I may, to make one further remark, <Alignment alignment="16383" annotation_id="14863">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14863" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> some speeches did not directly relate solely to the subject of this directive, but to health and safety at work in general.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14825" annotation_id="16314">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16314" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le permettez, je voudrais faire une <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16358">remarque</DiscourseConnective> supplémentaire, <Alignment alignment="14863" annotation_id="16383">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16383" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">dans la mesure où</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> certaines interventions ne se rapportaient pas directement au sujet de cette directive, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16489">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16494">à</DiscourseConnective> la santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16505">et</DiscourseConnective> à la sécurité au travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16533">en</DiscourseConnective> général.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14995" docOffset="85">
      <en>Obviously, the figure of 4 500 fatal accidents per year seems relatively low in comparison to the 250 million workers, <Alignment alignment="16678" annotation_id="15114">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15114" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are talking about 4 500 human lives.</en>
      <fr>Évidemment, le chiffre de 4 500 accidents mortels par an semble relativement peu élevé par rapport aux 250 millions de travailleurs, <Alignment alignment="15114" annotation_id="16678">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16678" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous parlons de 4 500 vies humaines.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15158" docOffset="86">
      <en>From this perspective, the figure is excessively high <Alignment alignment="16775" annotation_id="15212">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15212" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is up to us to do all we can to bring that figure down.</en>
      <fr>De ce point de vue, le chiffre est excessivement élevé <Alignment alignment="15212" annotation_id="16775">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16775" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16784">à</DiscourseConnective> nous qu'il revient de faire tout ce qui est en notre pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16847">pour</DiscourseConnective> le réduire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15275" docOffset="87">
      <en>Thank you.</en>
      <fr>Merci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15286" id="466" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15286" docOffset="88">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15308" docOffset="89">
      <en>The vote will take place tomorrow at 12 noon.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu demain, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16916">à</DiscourseConnective> midi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
