<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statement by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclaration de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="27" id="305" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, I would like first of all to ask for your understanding and to apologise for the fact that the session is starting so late, <Alignment alignment="178" annotation_id="173">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="173" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I was only told two minutes ago that I will be asked to make a statement on a very sad event.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="38">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="64">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> faire appel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="89">à</DiscourseConnective> votre compréhension <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="111">et</DiscourseConnective> vous prier de m'excuser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="138">du fait que</DiscourseConnective> la séance commence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="169">si</DiscourseConnective> tard, <Alignment alignment="519" annotation_id="178">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="178" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on vient de me demander il y a quelques instants de faire une déclaration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="257">à propos</DiscourseConnective> d'un tragique événement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="271" docOffset="2">
      <en>I would like to make this statement now with your consent.</en>
      <fr>Avec votre permission, je voudrais faire cette déclaration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="350">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="330" docOffset="3">
      <en>It is with great sadness and outrage that we have heard today about events in the town of Winnenden in Baden-Württemberg in Germany, where fifteen people were tragically killed at the Albertville secondary school.</en>
      <fr>C'est avec une profonde stupeur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="394">et</DiscourseConnective> une immense tristesse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="419">que</DiscourseConnective> nous apprenons aujourd'hui les événements survenus dans la ville de Winnenden, dans le Bade-Wurtemberg <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="526">en</DiscourseConnective> Allemagne, où quinze personnes ont été tuées au lycée Albertville.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="544" docOffset="4">
      <en>The perpetrator, a seventeen-year-old former student at the school, later committed suicide.</en>
      <fr>L'agresseur, un ancien élève du lycée âgé de 17 ans, a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="651">ensuite</DiscourseConnective> mis fin à ses jours.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="637" docOffset="5">
      <en>During a shootout at a supermarket in the town, two policemen who were in pursuit of the perpetrator were injured.</en>
      <fr>Au cours d'un échange de coups de feu devant un supermarché de la ville, deux policiers qui poursuivaient l'assassin ont été blessés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="752" docOffset="6">
      <en>On behalf of the European Parliament I would like to express my deepest condolences and my solidarity with the families and all the relatives of the victims, who are innocent young students and three teachers from the school.</en>
      <fr>Au nom du Parlement européen, je voudrais exprimer mes plus sincères condoléances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="896">et</DiscourseConnective> ma solidarité avec les familles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="931">et</DiscourseConnective> tous les proches des victimes, de jeunes élèves innocents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="992">et</DiscourseConnective> trois enseignants du lycée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="978" docOffset="7">
      <en>This tragedy takes place only six months after a similar terrible gun rampage at a school in Kauhajoki in Finland.</en>
      <fr>Cette tragédie survient six mois seulement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1066">après</DiscourseConnective> une affreuse tuerie du même type dans une école de Kauhajoki <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1133">en</DiscourseConnective> Finlande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1093" docOffset="8">
      <en>As responsible politicians in the European Union and in all the Member States, it is our task to do everything we possibly can to ensure that acts like this are anticipated at an early stage and prevented from occurring, <Alignment alignment="553839" annotation_id="1314">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1314" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is something that we can influence.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1149">tant que</DiscourseConnective> responsables politiques de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1204">et</DiscourseConnective> de tous les États membres, il nous incombe de faire tout notre possible en matière de prévention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1304">pour que</DiscourseConnective> de tels actes soient anticipés au plus tôt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1356">et</DiscourseConnective> empêcher qu'ils ne se produisent, <Alignment alignment="1314" annotation_id="1393">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1393" sense="Contingency.Condition">pour autant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous puissions réellement y faire quelque chose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1358" docOffset="9">
      <en>We are <Alignment alignment="555774" annotation_id="1365">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1365" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> shocked by another tragic event in the state of Alabama in the United States, where a gunman on the rampage shot at least ten people <Alignment alignment="559583" annotation_id="1503">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1503" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> turning his gun on himself.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes <Alignment alignment="1365" annotation_id="1470">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1470" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sous le choc de l'annonce d'un tragique événement similaire survenu dans l'État d'Alabama aux États-Unis, où un homme armé a tué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1609">au moins</DiscourseConnective> dix personnes <Alignment alignment="1503" annotation_id="1632">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1632" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> retourner l'arme contre lui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1538" docOffset="10">
      <en>I would like once again to express on behalf of everyone here our deepest sympathy and our solidarity with the victims and their families.</en>
      <fr>Au nom de l'ensemble de notre Parlement, je voudrais manifester une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1743">encore</DiscourseConnective> notre très profonde sympathie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1780">et</DiscourseConnective> notre totale solidarité avec les victimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1825">et</DiscourseConnective> leurs familles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1677" docOffset="11">
      <en>I would be grateful <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1697" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> you would take time to remember those who have been killed.</en>
      <fr>Je vous serais reconnaissant de bien vouloir prendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1897">le temps d'</DiscourseConnective>honorer la mémoire des victimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1760" docOffset="12">
      <en>(The House rose and observed a minute's silence)</en>
      <fr>(L'Assemblée, debout, observe une minute de silence)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
