<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>8.</en>
    <fr>8.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Statute of the European Ombudsman (</en>
    <fr>Statut du Médiateur européen (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="39" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Before the vote on Amendment 8:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="36">avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote sur l'amendement 8:</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="73" id="135" name="Janez Lenarčič">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="73" docOffset="3">
      <en>President-in-Office of the Council. - (SL) The Presidency wishes on behalf of the Council to confirm its approval of the amendment of the Statute for the European Ombudsman, which has been the subject of voting in this esteemed assembly.</en>
      <fr>président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="80">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil. - (SL) La présidence souhaite, au nom du Conseil, confirmer son adoption de la modification du statut du Médiateur européen, qui a fait l'objet d'un vote au sein de cette honorable Assemblée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="311" docOffset="4">
      <en>I would like to take this opportunity to thank the European Parliament and the European Commission for their creative cooperation. On the basis of this creative cooperation, we reached agreement on the modification of the Statute in a relatively short time.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais profiter de cette opportunité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="338">pour</DiscourseConnective> remercier le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="375">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="403">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur coopération créative, sur la base de laquelle nous avons conclu un accord sur la modification du statut dans un laps de temps assez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="545">bref</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="569" docOffset="5">
      <en>Special thanks on behalf of the Council are owed to the rapporteur Mrs Jäätteenmäki, the chairman of the AFCO committee Mr Leinen, and Mr Méndez de Vigo MEP.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil remercie particulièrement le rapporteur, Mme Jäätteenmäki, le président de la commission AFCO, M. Leinen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="668">et</DiscourseConnective> le député M. Méndez de Vigo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="727" docOffset="6">
      <en>The Council welcomes this important achievement.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil salue ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="720">résultat</DiscourseConnective> important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="776" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="656" annotation_id="776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="776" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Indeed</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we believe that the amendment of the Statute will increase the confidence of citizens in the proper functioning of European institutions and the European Union as a whole.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="776" annotation_id="740">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="740" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous croyons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="763">que</DiscourseConnective> la modification du statut augmentera la confiance des citoyens dans le bon fonctionnement des institutions européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="886">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'ensemble de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
