<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>CFP and the ecosystem approach to fisheries management (short presentation)</en>
    <fr>La PCP <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7">et</DiscourseConnective> l'approche écosystémique de la gestion de la pêche (brève présentation)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="76" id="206" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="76" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Mr Guerreiro, on behalf of the Committee on Fisheries, on the CFP and the ecosystem approach to fisheries management.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de M. Guerreiro, au nom de la commission de la pêche, sur le rapport sur la PCP <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="197">et</DiscourseConnective> l'approche écosystémique de la gestion des pêches .</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="225" id="207" language="PT" name="Pedro Guerreiro">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="225" docOffset="2">
      <en>This Commission communication raises a diverse range of questions as part of the debate on a possible reform of the common fisheries policy by 2012.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (PT) Cette communication de la Commission soulève nombre de questions indissociables du débat sur une réforme éventuelle de la politique commune de la pêche à l'horizon 2012.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="374" docOffset="3">
      <en>My report, which has been adopted by Parliament's Committee on Fisheries, puts forward a number of factors that we consider important in the context of this debate.</en>
      <fr>Mon rapport, tel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="458">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il a été adopté par la commission de la pêche du Parlement, met en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="528">avant</DiscourseConnective> un certain nombre de facteurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="564">que</DiscourseConnective> nous considérons importants dans le contexte du présent débat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="539" docOffset="4">
      <en>Fishing is a fundamental activity for guaranteeing human beings' food and survival, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="623" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this is the primordial objective of any fisheries policy.</en>
      <fr>La pêche est une activité cruciale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="666">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer l'alimentation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="694">et</DiscourseConnective> la survie des êtres humains, qui est l'objectif primordial de toute politique de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="685" docOffset="5">
      <en>In this context, it is worth underlining the importance of fishing in the waters of each Member State's EEZ for its sovereignty and independence, particularly in terms of food.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce sens, il convient de souligner l'importance de la pêche dans les eaux de la ZEE de chaque État membre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="899">pour</DiscourseConnective> sa souveraineté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="920">et</DiscourseConnective> son indépendance, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="941">notamment</DiscourseConnective> au niveau alimentaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="862" docOffset="6">
      <en>The common fisheries policy (CFP) should promote the modernisation and sustainable development of the fishing industry, safeguarding its socio-economic viability and the sustainability of fish stocks and guaranteeing the supply of fish to the public as well as food sovereignty and security, the preservation of jobs and improved living conditions for fishermen.</en>
      <fr>La politique commune de la pêche (PCP) devra promouvoir la modernisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1047">et</DiscourseConnective> le développement durable du secteur de la pêche en assurant sa viabilité socioéconomique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1139">et</DiscourseConnective> la durabilité des ressources, ainsi qu'en garantissant l'approvisionnement public en poisson et la souveraineté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1254">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité alimentaires, le maintien de l'emploi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1307">et</DiscourseConnective> l'amélioration des conditions de vie des pêcheurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1225" docOffset="7">
      <en>Taking account of its own objectives, a CFP must <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1274" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective> not be subordinate to other Community policies that have since been defined.</en>
      <fr>Compte tenu de ses propres objectifs, une PCP ne doit pas être subordonnée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1436">à</DiscourseConnective> d'autres politiques communautaires définies entre-temps.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1361" docOffset="8">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1495" annotation_id="1361">
          <Alignment alignment="6319" annotation_id="1361">
            <Alignment alignment="1495" annotation_id="1361">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1361" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, a fisheries policy is not and cannot be a policy for the oceans or for the marine environment.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1361" annotation_id="1495">
          <Alignment alignment="3370" annotation_id="1495">
            <Alignment alignment="1361" annotation_id="1495">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1495" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, une politique de la pêche n'est pas, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1552">et</DiscourseConnective> ne peut pas être, une politique des océans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1598">ou</DiscourseConnective> du milieu marin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1472" docOffset="9">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1472" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Since</DiscourseConnective> fishing is an activity that exploits a self-renewable resource, the first and principal task of fisheries management is to control total fishing effort in such a way <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1644" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> to guarantee the maximum sustainable catch.</en>
      <fr>La première <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1630">et</DiscourseConnective> principale tâche de gestion de la pêche, en tant qu'activité qui exploite une ressource auto-renouvelable, consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1749">à</DiscourseConnective> contrôler l'effort <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1770">total</DiscourseConnective> de pêche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1786">de manière à</DiscourseConnective> garantir une capture maximale durable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1691" docOffset="10">
      <en>A policy for fisheries must start from the assumption of an interdependence between the welfare of fishing communities and the sustainability of ecosystems, of which they are an integral part, <Alignment alignment="16252" annotation_id="1884">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1884" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> by recognising the specific features and importance of small-scale inshore fishing and artisanal fishing.</en>
      <fr>Une politique de la pêche doit partir de l'hypothèse de l'interdépendance entre le bien-être des communautés de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1956">et</DiscourseConnective> la durabilité des écosystèmes, dont ils font partie intégrante, <Alignment alignment="3763" annotation_id="2023">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2023" sense="Expansion.Restatement">notamment en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> reconnaissant la spécificité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2065">et</DiscourseConnective> l'importance de la petite pêche côtière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2108">et</DiscourseConnective> de la pêche artisanale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2004" docOffset="11">
      <en>The application of an ecosystem approach to marine management necessarily requires multidisciplinary and intersectoral action between the various measures that have an impact on marine ecosystems, going far beyond and upstream of those adopted in the area of fisheries.</en>
      <fr>L'application d'une approche écosystémique de la gestion du milieu marin requiert nécessairement une action multidisciplinaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2262">et</DiscourseConnective> intersectorielle entre les différentes mesures qui ont un impact sur les écosystèmes marins, en allant bien au-delà <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2381">et</DiscourseConnective> en amont de celles qui sont adoptées dans le domaine de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2274" docOffset="12">
      <en>The proposal for an ecosystem-based analysis of the assessment of fishery resources must be based on validated scientific data, rather than on hunches based on preconceived ideas.</en>
      <fr>La proposition d'analyse écosystémique de l'évaluation des ressources halieutiques ne peut reposer que sur des données scientifiques validées, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2593">plutôt que</DiscourseConnective> sur des intuitions fondées sur des idées préconçues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2454" docOffset="13">
      <en>It must <Alignment alignment="2669" annotation_id="2462">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2462" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be recognised that there are significant differences between the various marine areas and the resources that occur in each of them, between the various fleets and gear used and between their respective impacts on ecosystems, which requires fisheries management measures that are diversified, specific and adapted to each case, with fishermen being compensated for their socio-economic consequences where necessary.</en>
      <fr>Il convient <Alignment alignment="2462" annotation_id="2669">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2669" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de reconnaître <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2694">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il existe des différences importantes entre les différentes zones marines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2771">et</DiscourseConnective> les ressources qui se développent dans chacune d'entre elles, les différents flottes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2859">et</DiscourseConnective> les engins utilisés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2882">et</DiscourseConnective> les influences respectives sur les écosystèmes, ce qui nécessite des mesures de gestion de la pêche diversifiées, spécifiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3011">et</DiscourseConnective> adaptées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3023">à</DiscourseConnective> chaque cas, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3037">en</DiscourseConnective> indemnisant, le cas échéant, les pêcheurs de leurs conséquences socio-économiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2882" docOffset="14">
      <en>In order to guarantee the sustainability of resources, fishing activity and the respective local communities, we believe it is vital that the Member States should exercise their sovereignty over their 12 miles of territorial waters and for the area corresponding to the EEZs of the outermost regions to be considered an exclusive access zone.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3123">Si</DiscourseConnective> l'on entend assurer la durabilité des ressources, de l'activité de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3199">et</DiscourseConnective> des communautés de pêche locales, nous estimons essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3260">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres exercent leur souveraineté sur les 12 milles de mer territoriale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3347">et</DiscourseConnective> sur la zone correspondant aux ZEE des régions ultrapériphériques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3415">à</DiscourseConnective> considérer comme zone d'accès exclusive.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3225" docOffset="15">
      <en>In this context, there is some concern at proposals regarding access to resources that aim to promote a system of transferable individual quotas, which would have consequences in terms of the concentration of fishing activity and the individual appropriation of fishing rights.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce sens, les propositions relatives à l'accès aux ressources qui visent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3535">à</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir un système de quotas individuels transférables, non dénué de conséquences sur la concentration de l'activité de pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3666">et</DiscourseConnective> sur l'appropriation individuelle des droits de pêche, sont préoccupantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3503" docOffset="16">
      <en>It should <Alignment alignment="3754" annotation_id="3513">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3513" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be pointed out that a policy that encourages the indiscriminate scrapping of vessels, that takes no account of the specific features of fleets, resources, needs as regards consumption in each Member State and the socio-economic impact, is inappropriate and unjustified.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <Alignment alignment="3513" annotation_id="3754">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3754" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">encore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3773">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il serait inapproprié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3798">et</DiscourseConnective> injustifié d'adopter une politique qui encouragerait la démolition aveugle de navires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3888">sans</DiscourseConnective> tenir compte des spécificités des flottes, des ressources, des besoins de consommation de chaque État membre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4002">ou</DiscourseConnective> de leurs répercussions socio-économiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3788" docOffset="17">
      <en>Lastly, I should like to emphasise that the sharp decline in income in the industry stems not only from restrictions on fishing activity, but <Alignment alignment="4216" annotation_id="3930">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3930" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> from the stagnation/fall in first-sale prices, accompanied by the increase in production costs (diesel and petrol).</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4047">Pour terminer</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais souligner le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4092">que</DiscourseConnective> la forte baisse des revenus dans le secteur est due <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4148">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> aux restrictions imposées à l'activité de pêche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4211">mais</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="846" annotation_id="4216">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4216" sense="Expansion.Restatement">surtout</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4224">à</DiscourseConnective> la stagnation /baisse des prix à la première vente, sans négliger le facteur d'augmentation des coûts de production (gasoil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4350">et</DiscourseConnective> essence).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4060" id="208" name="Androulla Vassiliou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4060" docOffset="18">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, the Commission welcomes the report presented and the support given to our perspectives regarding the ecosystem approach.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - (EN) Monsieur le président, la Commission salue le rapport présenté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4458">et</DiscourseConnective> le soutien apporté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4480">à</DiscourseConnective> nos perspectives concernant l'approche de l'écosystème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4223" docOffset="19">
      <en>One of the main messages the Commission gives in its communication is that, <Alignment alignment="5969" annotation_id="4299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4299" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> fisheries depend on healthy marine ecosystems, fisheries management cannot take on the role of overall ocean management on its own.</en>
      <fr>Dans sa communication, l'un des principaux messages de la Commission consiste à dire que <Alignment alignment="4664" annotation_id="4627">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4627" sense="Comparison.Contrast">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la pêche dépend d'écosystèmes marins en bonne santé, la gestion de la pêche ne peut assumer seule une fonction de gestion globale des océans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4437" docOffset="20">
      <en>Healthy marine ecosystems can only be safeguarded through a policy which involves all sectors which impact on these ecosystems.</en>
      <fr>La santé des écosystèmes marins ne peut être préservée qu'au moyen d'une politique impliquant tous les secteurs qui ont un impact sur ces écosystèmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4565" docOffset="21">
      <en>This is why the Commission sees the maritime policy, and especially its environmental pillar, the Marine Strategy Directive, as key to the implementation of an ecosystem approach.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4923">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> la Commission considère la politique maritime, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4985">et</DiscourseConnective> particulièrement son pilier environnemental, la directive "stratégie pour le milieu marin", <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5080">comme</DiscourseConnective> essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5098">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place d'une approche d'écosystème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4745" docOffset="22">
      <en>This approach will give assurances to the fishing industry that all human impacts on marine ecosystems, not only fisheries, are addressed in a proportionate and coherent way.</en>
      <fr>Cette approche garantira <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5171">à</DiscourseConnective> l'industrie halieutique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5197">que</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble des impacts humains sur les écosystèmes marins, pas uniquement la pêche, seront traités de manière proportionnée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5325">et</DiscourseConnective> cohérente.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4920" docOffset="23">
      <en>This is <Alignment alignment="4291" annotation_id="4928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4928" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the overall thrust of the report <Alignment alignment="14533" annotation_id="4966">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4966" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we appreciate the agreement on this point.</en>
      <fr>C'est <Alignment alignment="4928" annotation_id="5345">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5345" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'orientation globale du rapport <Alignment alignment="4966" annotation_id="5388">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5388" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous apprécions l'accord sur ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5013" docOffset="24">
      <en>I will emphasise that this does not mean that one policy is subordinate to another - that we, by taking this approach are establishing a hierarchy between, <Alignment alignment="5593" annotation_id="5169">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5169" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for instance</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Marine Strategy Directive and the common fisheries policy.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens à souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5451">que</DiscourseConnective> cela ne signifie pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5476">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une politique est subordonnée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5509">à</DiscourseConnective> l'autre - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5521">que</DiscourseConnective> nous établissons, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5543">en</DiscourseConnective> adoptant cette approche, une hiérarchie entre, <Alignment alignment="2894" annotation_id="5593">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5593" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la directive "stratégie pour le milieu marin" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5652">et</DiscourseConnective> la politique commune de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5246" docOffset="25">
      <en>The Marine Strategy Directive serves the common fisheries policy by being the necessary integrative instrument to safeguard the resource base for fisheries in the future, <Alignment alignment="5896" annotation_id="5417">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5417" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the common fisheries policy will contribute to the Marine Strategy Directive by putting in place management measures necessary to support the objectives for healthy marine ecosystems.</en>
      <fr>La directive "stratégie pour le milieu marin" sert la politique commune de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5773">en</DiscourseConnective> jouant le rôle d'instrument intégrateur nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5827">afin de</DiscourseConnective> sauvegarder la base des ressources <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5870">pour</DiscourseConnective> la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5884">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir, <Alignment alignment="5417" annotation_id="5896">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5896" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la politique commune de la pêche contribuera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5944">à</DiscourseConnective> la directive "stratégie pour le milieu marin" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5992">en</DiscourseConnective> mettant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6003">en</DiscourseConnective> place les mesures de gestion nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6047">pour</DiscourseConnective> soutenir les objectifs relatifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6084">à</DiscourseConnective> la santé des écosystèmes marins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5605" docOffset="26">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6119" annotation_id="5605">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5605" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> stated in the report, meeting food needs, safeguarding fishing industries and fishing communities, and preserving the sustainability of marine ecosystems are not irreconcilable.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5605" annotation_id="6119">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6119" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> indiqué dans le rapport, la réalisation de la satisfaction des besoins alimentaires, la sauvegarde de la viabilité du secteur stratégique de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6275">et</DiscourseConnective> des communautés vivant de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6313">et</DiscourseConnective> le maintien de la durabilité des écosystèmes marins ne sont pas des objectifs inconciliables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5786" docOffset="27">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7450" annotation_id="5786">
          <Alignment alignment="6410" annotation_id="5786">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5786" sense="Comparison.Contrast">On the contrary</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, in the long term there is a synergy between these objectives.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5786" annotation_id="6410">
          <Alignment alignment="5786" annotation_id="6410">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6410" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Au contraire</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, sur le long terme, il existe une synergie entre ces objectifs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5865" docOffset="28">
      <en>The report touches on many questions regarding the specific instruments to be utilised in the future.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport aborde de nombreuses questions concernant les instruments spécifiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6568">à</DiscourseConnective> utiliser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6579">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5967" docOffset="29">
      <en>These are important and pertinent questions which we will address in the debate regarding the reform of the common fisheries policy.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont des questions importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6625">et</DiscourseConnective> pertinentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6640">que</DiscourseConnective> nous aborderons au cours du débat sur la réforme de la politique commune de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6100" docOffset="30">
      <en>I will <Alignment alignment="13793" annotation_id="6107">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6107" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not comment specifically on these questions here.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1266" annotation_id="6730">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6730" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je ne présenterai pas d'observations spécifiques sur ces questions aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6167" docOffset="31">
      <en>I will, <Alignment alignment="6835" annotation_id="6175">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6175" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, point out that there are a couple of points where we may be in disagreement.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <Alignment alignment="6175" annotation_id="6835">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6835" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à préciser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6856">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pouvons être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6878">en</DiscourseConnective> désaccord sur certains points.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6261" docOffset="32">
      <en>It is indicated that fishermen affected by management plans and measures to protect ecosystems should be subsidised or compensated.</en>
      <fr>Il est indiqué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6927">que</DiscourseConnective> les pêcheurs affectés par les plans de reconstitution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6985">et</DiscourseConnective> les mesures de protection des écosystèmes doivent bénéficier de mécanismes de subvention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7077">ou</DiscourseConnective> de compensation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6393" docOffset="33">
      <en>We do not think that direct subsidies is a way forward, <Alignment alignment="7164" annotation_id="6449">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6449" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the solution is to help the industry to be more economically resilient and to help coastal communities diversify into other economic activities.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pensons pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7117">que</DiscourseConnective> des subventions directes soient indiquées, <Alignment alignment="6449" annotation_id="7164">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7164" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7169">que</DiscourseConnective> la solution consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7194">à</DiscourseConnective> aider le secteur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7213">à</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7215">mieux</DiscourseConnective> résister sur le plan économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7253">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7256">à</DiscourseConnective> aider les communautés côtières à se diversifier dans d'autres activités économiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6603" docOffset="34">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="7350" annotation_id="6609">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6609" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> indicated that restocking from aquaculture may be an instrument to replenish wild fish stocks.</en>
      <fr>Il est <Alignment alignment="6609" annotation_id="7350">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7350" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> indiqué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7368">que</DiscourseConnective> la reconstitution des stocks au moyen de l'aquaculture peut aider à remettre à niveau les stocks de poissons sauvages.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6709" docOffset="35">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="15409" annotation_id="6709">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6709" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this may be an option in a few very specific cases, we do not think that this is the way forward in general.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6709" annotation_id="7491">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7491" sense="Comparison.Concession">S'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il peut s'agir d'une option dans certains cas très spécifiques, nous ne pensons pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7577">que</DiscourseConnective> cela <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7586">soit</DiscourseConnective> la solution d'une manière générale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6827" docOffset="36">
      <en>Fish stocks should be rebuilt by proper management of the human impacts on the marine ecosystems, including the impacts of both fisheries and other sectors.</en>
      <fr>Les stocks de poissons doivent être reconstitués grâce à une gestion appropriée des impacts humains sur les écosystèmes marins, en ce compris les impacts de la pêche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7793">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres secteurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6984" docOffset="37">
      <en>We will return to a more detailed debate on the instruments for fisheries management in the context of the debate and development of the common fisheries policy reform, starting with our publication of a green paper in April.</en>
      <fr>Nous mènerons un débat plus approfondi sur les instruments de gestion de la pêche dans le cadre de l'examen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7923">et</DiscourseConnective> du développement de la réforme de la politique commune de la pêche, et nous commencerons par publier un livre vert <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8041">en</DiscourseConnective> avril.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7210" docOffset="38">
      <en>In the mean time, I thank Parliament for its support for our approach <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7280" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> expressed through this report.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8051">En attendant</DiscourseConnective>, je remercie le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8090">pour</DiscourseConnective> son soutien en faveur de notre approche, exprimé dans ce rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7314" id="209" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7314" docOffset="39">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7336" docOffset="40">
      <en>The vote will take place on Tuesday at 12 noon.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu mardi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8204">à</DiscourseConnective> 12 heures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7384" docOffset="41">
      <en>Written Statement (Rule 142)</en>
      <fr>Déclarations écrites (article 142)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7413" id="993" language="RO" name="Daciana Octavia Sârbu ">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7413" docOffset="42">
      <en>Current fish stocks in European Union waters are continuing to dwindle, both due to excessive fishing and the use of unsuitable equipment and to the impact which other sectors, in particular tourism, are having on marine biology life.</en>
      <fr>par écrit. - (RO) Les stocks de poissons continuent de diminuer dans les eaux de l'Union européenne en raison de la pêche excessive, de l'utilisation d'équipements inappropriés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8429">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'impact d'autres secteurs - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8464">notamment</DiscourseConnective> le tourisme - sur les ressources biologiques marines.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7648" docOffset="43">
      <en>Scientific research into identifying the factors that influence marine ecosystems, including the impact of climate change, will provide the opportunity to determine the development of fishery resources and ensure that precautionary measures are taken to prevent the rapid, continuous depletion of fish stocks.</en>
      <fr>La recherche scientifique sur l'identification des facteurs qui influencent les écosystèmes marins - y compris le changement climatique - va permettre de préciser l'évolution des ressources halieutiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8731">et</DiscourseConnective> de garantir l'adoption de mesures préventives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8780">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>empêcher l'épuisement rapide et continu des stocks de poissons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7958" docOffset="44">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7958" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> fishing is an essential activity for guaranteeing food and man's survival, managing the fishery resources' sustainability becomes vitally important at a time <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8119" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> marine biodiversity is deteriorating.</en>
      <fr>La pêche étant une activité fondamentale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8892">pour</DiscourseConnective> garantir l'alimentation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8921">et</DiscourseConnective> la survie des êtres humains, gérer la durabilité des ressources halieutiques devient vital compte tenu de la détérioration de la biodiversité marine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8162" docOffset="45">
      <en>For this reason, social, economic and environmental aspects need to be taken into account in all the initiatives promoting the sustainable development of the European Union's coastal areas.</en>
      <fr>Il est donc primordial d'intégrer les aspects sociaux, économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9141">et</DiscourseConnective> environnementaux dans toutes les initiatives visant à promouvoir le développement durable des régions côtières de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
