<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>7.</en>
    <fr>7.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Cooperation in vocational education and training to support the Europe 2020 strategy (</en>
    <fr>Coopération européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26">en</DiscourseConnective> matière d'enseignement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="52">et</DiscourseConnective> de formation professionnels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="83">pour</DiscourseConnective> appuyer la stratégie Europe 2020 (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="90" id="137" name="Emilie Turunen">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="90" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, yes, it is a very simple oral amendment replacing the word 'harmonisation' with 'cooperation' since this is more appropriate and more precise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="246" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> we are talking about vocational training.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, oui, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="159">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un amendement oral très simple remplaçant le terme "harmonisation" par le terme "coopération", <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="263">car</DiscourseConnective> il est plus approprié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="289">et</DiscourseConnective> plus précis, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="305">s'</DiscourseConnective>agissant de formation professionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="291" docOffset="3">
      <en>(The President asked the speaker to read out the whole text of the amendment)</en>
      <fr>(Le Président demande à l'oratrice de lire à voix haute le texte intégral de l'amendement oral)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="369" docOffset="4">
      <en>So it will read: 'Takes the view that better cooperation among Member States' different education systems - bridging those differences and ensuring mutual recognition of certificates and diplomas among the Member States - should be emphasised in order to heighten cross-border collaboration and aid mobility'.</en>
      <fr>Il faudra lire: "considère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="469">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il conviendrait d'harmoniser davantage les différents systèmes éducatifs des États membres - de neutraliser leurs différences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="598">et</DiscourseConnective> de reconnaître les certificats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="632">et</DiscourseConnective> les diplômes entre États membres - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="670">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la collaboration transfrontalière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="724">et</DiscourseConnective> d'encourager la mobilité".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
