<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>6.</en>
    <fr>6.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>EU relations with the Gulf Cooperation Council (</en>
    <fr>Relations de l'Union européenne avec le Conseil de coopération du Golfe (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="52" id="085" language="FR" name="Dominique Baudis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="52" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, I would like to thank the shadow rapporteurs, <Alignment alignment="161" annotation_id="112">
          <Alignment alignment="161" annotation_id="112">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="112" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> Mr Howitt, Mrs Brepoels, Mrs Brantner and Mrs Jäätteenmäki, with whom we prepared these amendments. Thanks to the amendments, we have a report that fully accounts for the events taking place in the Gulf, <Alignment alignment="386" annotation_id="330">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="330" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which states very clearly Parliament's position on the repression afflicting that region.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - Monsieur le Président, je voudrais remercier les rapporteurs fictifs, <Alignment alignment="1051" annotation_id="161">
          <Alignment alignment="1971" annotation_id="161">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="161" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> M. Howitt, Mme Brepoels, Mme Brantner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="214">et</DiscourseConnective> Mme Jäätteenmäki, avec qui nous avons préparé ces amendements, qui permettent d'avoir un rapport qui rend pleinement compte des événements dont le Golfe est le théâtre, <Alignment alignment="2532" annotation_id="386">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="386" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui expriment très clairement une position de notre Parlement face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="456">à</DiscourseConnective> la répression qui sévit dans cette région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="424" docOffset="3">
      <en>The first amendment, 16th new citation, is as follows:</en>
      <fr>Le premier amendement, 16e visa nouveau, est le suivant:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="479" docOffset="4">
      <en>'- having regard to the declarations by the High Representative of 10, 15 and 17 March, and the Council conclusions of 21 March on Bahrain and underlining in this context its full support for the freedom of expression and the right of citizens to peacefully demonstrate,'</en>
      <fr>" vu les déclarations de la haute représentante des 10, 15 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="617">et</DiscourseConnective> 17 mars, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="629">et</DiscourseConnective> les conclusions du Conseil du 21 mars sur Bahreïn, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="683">et</DiscourseConnective> soulignant dans ce contexte son plein soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="732">pour</DiscourseConnective> la liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="761">et</DiscourseConnective> le droit des citoyens de manifester pacifiquement,"</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="751" docOffset="5">
      <en>This is the first amendment, <Alignment alignment="844" annotation_id="780">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="780" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is of course the English-language version, which has been distributed, that is deemed authentic.</en>
      <fr>C'est le premier amendement <Alignment alignment="780" annotation_id="844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="844" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est, évidemment, la version en anglais, qui a été distribuée, qui fait foi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="884" id="087" name="Dominique Baudis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="884" docOffset="6">
      <en>(FR) The second amendment, recital A, is as follows:</en>
      <fr>Le deuxième amendement, considérant A, est le suivant:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="937" docOffset="7">
      <en>'Whereas current EU-GCC relations require constant reviewing and updating in view of recent important and rapidly unfolding developments on the ground, which are evolving rapidly, at the heart of which needs to be the pursuit of human rights and democracy.'</en>
      <fr>"Que les relations Union européenne-CCG actuelles requièrent des adaptations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1057">et</DiscourseConnective> des mises à jour constantes compte tenu des développements récents importants, qui évoluent rapidement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1164">et</DiscourseConnective> que la poursuite des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1206">et</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie doivent être au cœur de ces adaptations."</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1195" id="089" name="Dominique Baudis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1195" docOffset="8">
      <en>(FR) A new recital A bis:</en>
      <fr>Un nouveau considérant A bis:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1221" docOffset="9">
      <en>'A bis. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1229" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Whereas</DiscourseConnective> demonstrators have expressed legitimate democratic aspirations in several GCC States; <Alignment alignment="1415" annotation_id="1323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1323" sense="Comparison.Contrast">whereas</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the violent reaction of the authorities to the protests in Bahrain resulted in deaths, injuries and imprisonments; <Alignment alignment="1558" annotation_id="1446">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1446" sense="Comparison.Contrast">whereas</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Saudi, UAE and Kuwaiti troops have arrived in the country under the banner of the GCC to participate in the repression of demonstrators,'</en>
      <fr>"A bis. considérant les aspirations démocratiques légitimes exprimées par les manifestants dans plusieurs États du CCG; <Alignment alignment="407" annotation_id="1415">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1415" sense="Comparison.Contrast">considérant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la réaction violente des autorités face aux protestations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1489">à</DiscourseConnective> Bahreïn a conduit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1509">à</DiscourseConnective> de nombreux morts, blessés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1538">et</DiscourseConnective> emprisonnements, <Alignment alignment="1276" annotation_id="1558">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1558" sense="Comparison.Contrast">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que des soldats de l'Arabie saoudite, des Émirats arabes unis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1623">et</DiscourseConnective> du Koweït sont arrivés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1649">à</DiscourseConnective> Bahreïn sous la bannière du CCG <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1683">pour</DiscourseConnective> participer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1699">à</DiscourseConnective> la répression des manifestants,"</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1592" id="091" name="Dominique Baudis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1592" docOffset="10">
      <en>(FR) In paragraph 7, after the first paragraph, the first indent should now read:</en>
      <fr>Au paragraphe numéro 7, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1758">après</DiscourseConnective> le premier alinéa, un premier tiret:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1674" docOffset="11">
      <en>'- ensure respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms, with special regard to the freedom of speech and of assembly and the right to demonstrate peacefully, and to listen to and take into account the legitimate demands of protesters as well as to ensure their security;'</en>
      <fr>" garantir le respect des droits de l'homme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1845">et</DiscourseConnective> des libertés fondamentales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1876">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> la liberté de parole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1912">et</DiscourseConnective> d'assemblée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1928">et</DiscourseConnective> le droit de manifester pacifiquement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1968">et</DiscourseConnective> d'écouter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1981">et</DiscourseConnective> prendre en compte les demandes légitimes des manifestants et assurer leur sécurité,"</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1951" id="093" name="Dominique Baudis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1951" docOffset="12">
      <en>(FR) A new paragraph 7a:</en>
      <fr>Un nouveau paragraphe 7 bis:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1976" docOffset="13">
      <en>'7a. Calls on all Member States in the Gulf Cooperation Council to recognise a continuing popular movement for democratic reform within the wider region, and calls for the full engagement with emerging civil society groups to promote a process of genuine peaceful democratic transition, within their own countries, with partners in the region and with the full support of the European Union;'</en>
      <fr>"7 bis. appelle tous les États membres du CCG <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2144">à</DiscourseConnective> reconnaître un mouvement populaire permanent pour des réformes politiques dans l'ensemble de la région, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2250">et</DiscourseConnective> appelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2261">à</DiscourseConnective> un plein engagement, avec les groupes de la société civile émergents, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2333">pour</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir un processus de transition démocratique pacifique au sein de leurs propres pays, avec les partenaires de la région, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2465">et</DiscourseConnective> le soutien entier de l'Union européenne;"</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2369" id="095" name="Dominique Baudis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2369" docOffset="14">
      <en>(FR) A new paragraph 7b:</en>
      <fr>Un nouveau paragraphe 7 ter:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2394" docOffset="15">
      <en>ʻ7b. Expresses its deep concern at the violent response of and the use of force against protesters by Bahraini authorities and at the participation of foreign troops under the GCC banner in the repression of demonstrators; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2617" sense="Comparison.Contrast">whereas</DiscourseConnective> this stands in stark contrast to the GCC's support for the protection of the citizens demanding freedom and democracy in Libya; calls for an immediate end to violence against peaceful protesters and for a political dialogue that can lead to further necessary political reforms in the country;'</en>
      <fr>"7 ter. exprime sa profonde préoccupation face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2586">à</DiscourseConnective> la violente réponse des autorités bahreïnies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2633">et</DiscourseConnective> l'usage de la force contre les manifestants, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2681">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la participation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2708">à</DiscourseConnective> la répression des manifestants de troupes étrangères, sous la bannière du CCG; considère que cela est tout à fait en contradiction avec le soutien du CCG <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2864">pour</DiscourseConnective> la protection des citoyens qui demandent la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2918">et</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2935">en</DiscourseConnective> Libye; appelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2953">à</DiscourseConnective> un arrêt immédiat des violences contre les manifestants pacifiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3022">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3025">à</DiscourseConnective> un dialogue politique qui peut conduire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3067">à</DiscourseConnective> de profondes réformes politiques nécessaires dans le pays;"</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2919" id="097" name="Dominique Baudis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2919" docOffset="16">
      <en>(FR) A new paragraph 18a:</en>
      <fr>Un nouveau paragraphe 18 bis:</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2945" docOffset="17">
      <en>'18a. Takes note of the declaration by the GCC of 7 March 2011 in Abu Dhabi, which states that "the Ministerial council demands that the Security Council takes the steps necessary to protect civilians, including a no-fly zone in Libya”, which declaration has contributed to the decision of the Arab League and <Alignment alignment="3489" annotation_id="3255">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3255" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the United Nations Security Council to pronounce themselves in favour of such a zone;'</en>
      <fr>"18 bis. prend acte de la déclaration du CCG du 7 mars dernier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3222">à</DiscourseConnective> Abou Dhabi, par laquelle il demande au Conseil de sécurité des Nations unies de prendre les mesures nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3336">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger les civils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3361">en</DiscourseConnective> Libye, dont l'imposition d'une zone d'exclusion aérienne, cette déclaration ayant contribué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3456">à</DiscourseConnective> la décision de la Ligue arabe, <Alignment alignment="3255" annotation_id="3489">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3489" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">puis</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> du Conseil de sécurité de l'ONU <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3526">à</DiscourseConnective> se prononcer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3541">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur d'une telle zone;"</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
