<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statement by the President of the European Parliament's delegation to the Conciliation Committee - Novel foods (debate)</en>
    <fr>Déclaration du président de la délégation du Parlement européen auprès du comité de conciliation - nouveaux aliments (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="120" id="480" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="120" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the debate on the statement by the President of the European Parliament's delegation to the Conciliation Committee - novel foods.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur la déclaration du président de la délégation du Parlement européen auprès du comité de conciliation - nouveaux aliments</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="267" docOffset="2">
      <en>Conciliation procedure regarding the amendment of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 and the repeal of Regulation (EC) No 258/97 and Commission Regulation (EC) No 1852/2001 on novel foods.</en>
      <fr>Procédure de conciliation concernant la modification du règlement (CE) n° 1331/2008 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="366">et</DiscourseConnective> l'abrogation du règlement (CE) n° 258/97 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="410">et</DiscourseConnective> du règlement de la Commission (CE) n° 1852/2001 concernant les nouveaux aliments.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="450" id="481" language="IT" name="Gianni Pittella">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="450" docOffset="3">
      <en>Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, we are disappointed that it has not been possible to reach agreement on the Novel Foods Regulation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="602" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that <Alignment alignment="8370" annotation_id="611">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="611" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is not possible to guarantee adequate information for consumers on the foods that we eat or to ensure that Europe has clear, strict rules on foods from cloned animals.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="551">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, nous sommes déçus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="583">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un accord sur le règlement concernant les nouveaux aliments n'ait pu être trouvé. <Alignment alignment="611" annotation_id="668">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="668" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous ne pouvons ni garantir que les consommateurs sont correctement informés de ce qu'ils mangent, ni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="780">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe dispose de règles claires et strictes concernant les aliments provenant d'animaux clonés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="793" docOffset="4">
      <en>What I have said is not meant to be controversial: it is not Parliament's fault.</en>
      <fr>Loin de moi l'idée de susciter la controverse; le Parlement n'est pas responsable de la situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="874" docOffset="5">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="874" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective> we have been unable to regulate cloning - one of the main sticking points in these negotiations - it is <Alignment alignment="1093" annotation_id="981">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="981" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the governments have not shown enough willingness.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'avons pas pu réglementer le clonage - l'une des principales pierres d'achoppement de ces négociations - <Alignment alignment="1120" annotation_id="1093">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1093" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les gouvernements n'étaient pas disposés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1144">à</DiscourseConnective> le faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1040" docOffset="6">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1156" annotation_id="1040">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1040" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - and I address this point to the governments and the Commission - food safety and information on the products that reach our tables are basic principles of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1550" annotation_id="1156">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1156" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1168">et</DiscourseConnective> je m'adresse aux gouvernements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1202">et</DiscourseConnective> à la Commission - la sécurité alimentaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1247">et</DiscourseConnective> l'information relative aux produits qui aboutissent dans nos assiettes figurent parmi les principes fondamentaux de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1225" docOffset="7">
      <en>Everybody says so, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1244" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1248" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> we have to act <Alignment alignment="1423" annotation_id="1268">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1268" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">accordingly</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1281" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective> else it becomes a slogan that consumers do not believe.</en>
      <fr>Tout le monde le clame, reste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1416">à</DiscourseConnective> agir <Alignment alignment="1268" annotation_id="1423">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1423" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">en conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, pour éviter que ces principes se transforment en un slogan auquel les consommateurs ne croient plus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1340" docOffset="8">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1340" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective> these issues are being discussed, Parliament is not prepared to look the other way and content itself with the kind of general reassurances that the Council provided during the negotiations.</en>
      <fr>Face à de tels sujets, le Parlement refuse de se voiler la face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1604">ou</DiscourseConnective> de se satisfaire du réconfort général offert par le Conseil lors des pourparlers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1536" docOffset="9">
      <en>On such a sensitive and serious food safety issue, it is not acceptable just to dab on a touch of face powder to look good to the consumers.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1689">En</DiscourseConnective> présence de thèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1711">aussi</DiscourseConnective> délicats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1726">et</DiscourseConnective> graves que la sécurité alimentaire, nous ne pouvons nous contenter de nous repoudrer le nez, pour que les consommateurs nous voient sous notre meilleur jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1677" docOffset="10">
      <en>Parliament was calling for a credible solution: the labelling of all foodstuffs derived from cloned animals and their offspring.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement demandait une solution crédible: l'étiquetage de tous les produits alimentaires provenant d'animaux clonés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2007">et</DiscourseConnective> de leurs descendants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1806" docOffset="11">
      <en>That really would have been a step in the right direction.</en>
      <fr>Nous aurions alors vraiment fait un pas dans la bonne direction.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1865" docOffset="12">
      <en>I would like to make another remark on a more general level: the governments continue to think that it is their prerogative to make all decisions.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi aussi de faire une <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2130">remarque</DiscourseConnective> plus générale: les gouvernements continuent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2183">à</DiscourseConnective> penser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2192">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils ont le pouvoir de tout régenter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2012" docOffset="13">
      <en>It is still not clear to them that there is an institution - the European Parliament - which codecides.</en>
      <fr>Ils n'ont toujours pas compris <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2263">que</DiscourseConnective> l'institution qu'est le Parlement européen prend part aux décisions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2116" docOffset="14">
      <en>We are directly elected by the citizens <Alignment alignment="2382" annotation_id="2156">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2156" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are determined to enforce our rights.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes élus directement par les citoyens <Alignment alignment="1444" annotation_id="2382">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2382" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sommes bien décidés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2405">à</DiscourseConnective> faire valoir nos droits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2201" docOffset="15">
      <en>I invite the governments to read the Treaty of Lisbon carefully, <Alignment alignment="3120" annotation_id="2266">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2266" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am sure they have not paid attention to all parts of it.</en>
      <fr>J'exhorte les gouvernements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2460">à</DiscourseConnective> lire attentivement le traité de Lisbonne, <Alignment alignment="2266" annotation_id="2504">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2504" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis sûr qu'ils en ont négligé certains chapitres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2333" docOffset="16">
      <en>I would like now to appeal to the Commission and to Commissioner Dalli, whose conduct during the negotiations was admirable, <Alignment alignment="12542" annotation_id="2458">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2458" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> perhaps the Commission did not explain his role in conciliating the positions.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2576">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> de m'adresser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2601">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2617">et</DiscourseConnective> au commissaire Dalli, qui a mené les négociations de main de maître, <Alignment alignment="1635" annotation_id="2689">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2689" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Commission n'ait peut-être pas expliqué le rôle de conciliation qui lui incombait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2546" docOffset="17">
      <en>Commissioner, I invite you to table a proposal on cloning as soon as possible in order to regulate the sector effectively once and for all.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Commissaire, je vous invite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2824">à</DiscourseConnective> présenter au plus vite une proposition sur le clonage, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2881">afin de</DiscourseConnective> réglementer ce secteur avec efficacité, une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2938">pour</DiscourseConnective> toutes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2686" docOffset="18">
      <en>That is what the people of Europe are calling for <Alignment alignment="3002" annotation_id="2736">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2736" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> what Parliament is calling for as well.</en>
      <fr>C'est ce que demandent et la population européenne <Alignment alignment="2736" annotation_id="3002">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3002" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2780" docOffset="19">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="6700" annotation_id="2788">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2788" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to acknowledge the Hungarian Presidency - which inherited this thorny problem only in the final stage of the procedure - for having made every possible effort to make up for lost time.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <Alignment alignment="557" annotation_id="3028">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3028" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3034">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier la Présidence hongroise, qui a hérité de cet épineux problème, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3109">en</DiscourseConnective> fin de procédure. Elle a fait tout ce qu'elle pouvait pour rattraper le temps perdu et j'en remercie tous les représentants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2983" docOffset="20">
      <en>I thank all the Hungarian Presidency representatives for that.</en>
      <fr>Je sais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3245">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils n'ont absolument rien à se reprocher.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3046" docOffset="21">
      <en>I know they do not deserve any blame at all, which is due <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3104" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">instead</DiscourseConnective> to the stalemate that occurred within the Council between the different national government positions.</en>
      <fr>Ce sont les divergences entre gouvernements nationaux qui ont poussé le Conseil dans l'impasse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3215" docOffset="22">
      <en>Lastly, I would like to thank the rapporteur, who was magnificent: highly passionate, enthusiastic and competent.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3386">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, je voudrais remercier la rapporteure, qui a été formidable et qui s'est montrée extrêmement passionnée, enthousiaste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3510">et</DiscourseConnective> compétente.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3329" docOffset="23">
      <en>She has followed this dossier with a love that really does credit to her, <Alignment alignment="10169" annotation_id="3403">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3403" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I believe all of us owe her a huge vote of thanks, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3458" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> we <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3464" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> do to the whole delegation from Parliament, all our fellow Members, the chair of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, and everyone else.</en>
      <fr>Elle a suivi le dossier avec un dévouement qui l'honore <Alignment alignment="3403" annotation_id="3581">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3581" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense que, par notre vote, nous devrions tous la remercier et remercier les membres de la délégation parlementaire, nos collègues, le président de la commission de l'environnement, de la santé publique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3789">et</DiscourseConnective> de la sécurité alimentaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3819">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que tous les autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3634" docOffset="24">
      <en>We all worked together day and night to achieve a goal.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons œuvré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3863">sans</DiscourseConnective> relâche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3876">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>atteindre notre objectif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3690" docOffset="25">
      <en>We were not successful, <Alignment alignment="10294" annotation_id="3714">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3714" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the questions have been raised <Alignment alignment="3984" annotation_id="3749">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3749" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am sure that, <Alignment alignment="3999" annotation_id="3769">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3769" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Commissioner Dalli is true to his word, we will be able to find a way again to provide ourselves with good regulations on cloning and novel foods.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'y sommes pas arrivés, <Alignment alignment="1358" annotation_id="3938">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3938" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les questions ont été mises sur le tapis <Alignment alignment="3749" annotation_id="3984">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3984" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis sûr <Alignment alignment="2515" annotation_id="3999">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3999" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le commissaire Dalli tient ses promesses, nous pourrons, par d'autres voies, nous doter de solides outils législatifs sur le clonage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4139">et</DiscourseConnective> les nouveaux aliments.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3919" id="482" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3919" docOffset="26">
      <en>Thank you, Mr Pittella, not least for the enthusiasm with which you made your statement.</en>
      <fr>Merci, Monsieur Pittella, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4191">aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4197">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'enthousiasme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4217">que</DiscourseConnective> vous avez mis dans votre déclaration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4008" docOffset="27">
      <en>I will now give the floor to Mrs Győri to respond on behalf of the Council, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4084" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective> I understand that you have lost your voice, <Alignment alignment="4400" annotation_id="4137">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4137" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a representative will be speaking on your behalf.</en>
      <fr>Je donne la parole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4278">à</DiscourseConnective> Mme Győri, au nom du Conseil, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4310">pour</DiscourseConnective> répondre. J'ai cru comprendre, toutefois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4357">que</DiscourseConnective> vous aviez un problème de voix et que, <Alignment alignment="4137" annotation_id="4400">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4400" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de ce fait</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, votre représentant parlerait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4441">en</DiscourseConnective> votre nom.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4190" docOffset="28">
      <en>I invite you to take the floor on behalf of the Council.</en>
      <fr>Je vous donne la parole au nom du Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4247" id="483" language="HU" name="Enikő Győri">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4247" docOffset="29">
      <en>Madam President, Commissioner, honourable Members, today's debate is a good occasion for me to present the Presidency's observations on the recently held conciliation on the proposal for a regulation on novel foods.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers députés, le débat d'aujourd'hui me donne l'occasion de vous exposer les remarques de la Présidence à propos de la récente procédure de conciliation relative à la proposition de règlement sur les nouveaux aliments.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4463" docOffset="30">
      <en>It is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4469" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> an excellent opportunity for the Presidency to learn Parliament's opinion on this important issue.</en>
      <fr>De son côté, la Présidence a l'occasion de prendre connaissance de l'opinion du Parlement sur cette question importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4573" docOffset="31">
      <en>Our European institutions have suffered a major collective failure.</en>
      <fr>Nos institutions européennes ont essuyé un sérieux revers collectif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4641" docOffset="32">
      <en>There is no other course <Alignment alignment="4971" annotation_id="4666">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4666" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> to learn from this experience in a constructive manner based on professional criteria.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pouvons <Alignment alignment="4666" annotation_id="4971">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4971" sense="Comparison.Contrast">qu'en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tirer des enseignements constructifs, selon des critères professionnels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4757" docOffset="33">
      <en>It is in this spirit that I turn to you today.</en>
      <fr>C'est dans cet esprit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5072">que</DiscourseConnective> je m'adresse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5089">à</DiscourseConnective> vous aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4804" docOffset="34">
      <en>I have come not only to speak but also to listen to you.</en>
      <fr>Je suis ici <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5121">pour</DiscourseConnective> vous parler, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5139">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> pour vous écouter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4861" docOffset="35">
      <en>I would like to begin by emphasising that the Presidency genuinely regrets that your institution and ours, the Council, were unable to reach agreement. This is all the more true <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5039" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> both the Presidency and the Council attributed great importance to this proposal.</en>
      <fr>J'insisterai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5182">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5207">que</DiscourseConnective> la Présidence regrette sincèrement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5246">que</DiscourseConnective> votre institution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5268">et</DiscourseConnective> la nôtre, le Conseil, n'aient pu arriver <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5312">à</DiscourseConnective> un accord, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5325">d'autant plus que</DiscourseConnective> la proposition revêtait une importance considérable aux yeux de la Présidence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5421">et</DiscourseConnective> du Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5129" docOffset="36">
      <en>This was an unrivalled opportunity for us to update the European Union regulation in an area which directly affects us all: food.</en>
      <fr>C'était une occasion unique d'actualiser la réglementation européenne, dans un domaine qui nous concerne tous directement: l'alimentation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5259" docOffset="37">
      <en>There was a real chance for the European Union to show how it contributes in a tangible manner to making the lives of European citizens better.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne tenait là l'occasion de prouver <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5626">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle contribue activement à l'amélioration des conditions de vie de ses citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5403" docOffset="38">
      <en>The proposed regulation would have been a particularly good means of answering disputed questions on food from cloned animals by tightening the provisions of the 1997 regulation.</en>
      <fr>La proposition de règlement nous aurait permis de répondre à des controverses suscitées par les aliments dérivés d'animaux clonés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5842">en</DiscourseConnective> renforçant les dispositions du règlement de 1997.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5582" docOffset="39">
      <en>The 1997 regulation provides that such food products can only be marketed after an authorisation procedure.</en>
      <fr>Celui-ci prévoit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5912">que</DiscourseConnective> ces produits ne peuvent être commercialisés qu'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5963">après</DiscourseConnective> une procédure d'autorisation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5690" docOffset="40">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5999" annotation_id="5690">
          <Alignment alignment="5999" annotation_id="5690">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5690" sense="Comparison.Contrast">In contrast</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, as a result of the recent conciliation procedure, a clear, albeit temporary, agreement was reached. All parties agreed that the marketing of food from cloned animals must be completely prohibited.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5690" annotation_id="5999">
          <Alignment alignment="2736" annotation_id="5999">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5999" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Par contre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6011">à</DiscourseConnective> l'issue de la procédure de conciliation, un accord clair, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6071">quoique</DiscourseConnective> temporaire, a été conclu, dans lequel toutes les parties reconnaissent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6150">que</DiscourseConnective> la commercialisation de denrées alimentaires provenant d'animaux clonés doit être totalement interdite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5900" docOffset="41">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5900" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>, this ban would have come into effect immediately after the regulation entered into force.</en>
      <fr>Cette interdiction serait devenue effective dès l'entrée en vigueur du règlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6003" docOffset="42">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6961" annotation_id="6003">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6003" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the conciliation had been successful, we could now be jointly welcoming an imminent ban on the marketing of food from cloned animals.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6003" annotation_id="6340">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6340" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la conciliation avait porté ses fruits, nous pourrions aujourd'hui nous réjouir de l'interdiction imminente de la commercialisation d'aliments dérivés d'animaux clonés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6140" docOffset="43">
      <en>This prohibition could have entered into force as early as the end of this month.</en>
      <fr>Cette interdiction aurait pu entrer en vigueur dès la fin du mois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6222" docOffset="44">
      <en>Unfortunately, this was not to be.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6579">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, il n'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6601">en</DiscourseConnective> fut pas ainsi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6257" docOffset="45">
      <en>In the light of the failed negotiations, we may be apt to blame each other. At the same time, it is our common interest and duty not to give in to this inclination but to seek a solution together.</en>
      <fr>Nous pourrions nous rejeter la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6650">faute de</DiscourseConnective> l'échec des négociations, mais il est de notre intérêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6714">et</DiscourseConnective> de notre devoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6733">à</DiscourseConnective> tous de l'éviter et de chercher plutôt une solution tous ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6454" docOffset="46">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6454" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective> the conciliation procedure has come to an end, the needs and expectations of European consumers have not altered at all, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6584" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="5473" annotation_id="6588">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6588" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am pleased to note that we have another chance to make progress.</en>
      <fr>La procédure de conciliation est terminée, mais les besoins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6862">et</DiscourseConnective> les attentes des consommateurs européens n'ont pas changé. <Alignment alignment="3334" annotation_id="6924">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6924" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je suis heureuse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6957">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une nouvelle occasion de progresser nous soit donnée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6665" docOffset="47">
      <en>It is up to us to restart this process as soon and as effectively as possible.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7014">À</DiscourseConnective> nous de relancer le processus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7046">aussi</DiscourseConnective> rapidement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7063">et</DiscourseConnective> efficacement que possible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6744" docOffset="48">
      <en>We must do our utmost especially to ensure that what we have agreed in the negotiations to date is not lost.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons faire de notre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7120">mieux</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7126">pour</DiscourseConnective> ne pas perdre ce sur quoi nous avons pu nous mettre d'accord lors des négociations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6853" docOffset="49">
      <en>At third reading, we have reached the point where, in principle, we have agreed on an immediate ban on food from cloned animals.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7215">En</DiscourseConnective> troisième lecture, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7237">en</DiscourseConnective> principe, nous nous sommes accordés sur l'interdiction immédiate des aliments produits à partir d'animaux clonés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6982" docOffset="50">
      <en>We must not allow this agreement in principle to be lost.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pouvons nous permettre de gâcher cet accord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7040" docOffset="51">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7407" annotation_id="7040">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7040" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Likewise</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we must protect the major advance made in relation to engineered nanomaterials and traditional food from third countries as well as similar, important issues.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7040" annotation_id="7407">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7407" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De même</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous devons protéger les progrès majeurs réalisés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7466">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de nanomatériaux manufacturés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7507">et</DiscourseConnective> d'aliments traditionnels de pays tiers ou d'autres sujets tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7573">aussi</DiscourseConnective> importants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7209" docOffset="52">
      <en>I believe that what we eat is important to all of us, <Alignment alignment="1010" annotation_id="7263">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7263" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the kind of nourishment our children and grandchildren grow up on is even more important.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7600">que</DiscourseConnective> nous accordons tous de l'importance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7640">à</DiscourseConnective> ce que nous mangeons <Alignment alignment="7263" annotation_id="7663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7663" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que l'alimentation de nos enfants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7700">et</DiscourseConnective> de nos petits-enfants nous tient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7736">encore</DiscourseConnective> bien plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7753">à</DiscourseConnective> cœur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7357" docOffset="53">
      <en>I would like to take this opportunity of thanking the Commissioner and his organisational units for the hard work they have done over the last few months.</en>
      <fr>J'en profite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7774">pour</DiscourseConnective> remercier le commissaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7804">et</DiscourseConnective> ses unités opérationnelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7834">pour</DiscourseConnective> le travail acharné de ces derniers mois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7512" docOffset="54">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="7894" annotation_id="7514">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7514" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcome the fact that the Commission - <Alignment alignment="11894" annotation_id="7558">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7558" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it has unofficially informed us - is working on drafting a new proposal at an accelerated pace, striving to preserve as many elements of the provisional agreement reached during the recent negotiations as possible in the new legislative proposal.</en>
      <fr>Je me réjouis <Alignment alignment="2160" annotation_id="7894">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7894" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7900">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission - <Alignment alignment="7558" annotation_id="7920">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7920" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle nous en a informés par voie informelle - travaille sur une proposition, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8003">à</DiscourseConnective> un rythme accéléré, en s'efforçant de préserver, dans la nouvelle proposition législative, autant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8103">que</DiscourseConnective> faire se peut les éléments de l'accord provisoire conclu lors des récentes négociations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7808" docOffset="55">
      <en>The Presidency guarantees its support to both the Commission and Parliament, and hopes that an opportunity to adopt this new proposal will arise as soon as possible.</en>
      <fr>La Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8210">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement peuvent compter sur le soutien de la Présidence, qui espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8286">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pourrons, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8305">dès que</DiscourseConnective> possible, adopter la nouvelle proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7974" docOffset="56">
      <en>Madam President, honourable Members, we are aware that the Commission has little room for manoeuvre.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, chers députés, nous savons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8405">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission dispose d'une marge de manœuvre très réduite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8075" docOffset="57">
      <en>After all, it is the task of the Council and Parliament as the two colegislators to find a solution which satisfies the needs and expectations of European citizens through joint efforts.</en>
      <fr>Tout bien réfléchi, c'est aux colégistateurs, le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8526">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement, qu'il incombe de trouver une solution qui satisfait les besoins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8607">et</DiscourseConnective> les attentes des citoyens européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8262" docOffset="58">
      <en>In the light of all this, I look forward to your views with truly great interest.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8647">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>, c'est avec grand intérêt que j'attends vos observations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
