<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Composition of committees and delegations : see Minutes</en>
    <fr>Composition des commissions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28">et</DiscourseConnective> des délégations: voir procès-verbal</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="56" id="018" name="Nirj Deva">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="56" docOffset="1">
      <en>Mr President, given that the Japanese earthquake and the suffering in Japan have taken second place recently, would it not be appropriate for this Parliament to mark them and to join with the people of Japan, and their democracy, expressing our condolences by observing a minute's silence?</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, le tremblement de terre survenu au Japon <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="136">et</DiscourseConnective> les souffrances de la population japonaise étant passés au second plan récemment, ne serait-il pas opportun <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="247">que</DiscourseConnective> notre Parlement témoigne de sa sympathie pour le peuple japonais et sa démocratie, et que nous leur exprimions nos condoléances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="379">en</DiscourseConnective> observant une minute de silence?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="346" id="019" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="346" docOffset="2">
      <en>Last week we held a meeting of all Members of the European Parliament with the President of the European Commission and the President of the Council of the European Union, Mr Van Rompuy.</en>
      <fr>La semaine dernière, une réunion a rassemblé tous les députés du Parlement européen, le président de la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="541">et</DiscourseConnective> le président du Conseil de l'Union européenne, M. Van Rompuy.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="533" docOffset="3">
      <en>At the beginning of that meeting I sent expressions of sympathy to the entire Japanese nation.</en>
      <fr>Au début de cette réunion j'ai transmis l'expression de notre sympathie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="678">à</DiscourseConnective> toute la nation japonaise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="628" docOffset="4">
      <en>I spoke, too, of the terrible suffering.</en>
      <fr>J'ai parlé, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="719">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, des terribles souffrances qu'elle endure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="669" docOffset="5">
      <en>We feel deeply for the Japanese people.</en>
      <fr>Nous ressentons une profonde sympathie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="807">pour</DiscourseConnective> le peuple japonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="709" docOffset="6">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="886" annotation_id="712">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="712" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> stood to observe a minute's silence in the Chamber to honour the memory of those who died in this catastrophe.</en>
      <fr>L'Assemblée a <Alignment alignment="584" annotation_id="846">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="846" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> observé une minute de silence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="886">pour</DiscourseConnective> honorer la mémoire de ceux qui ont trouvé la mort dans cette catastrophe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="828" docOffset="7">
      <en>There was <Alignment alignment="351439" annotation_id="838">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="838" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a brief discussion on the subject.</en>
      <fr>Il y a eu <Alignment alignment="333" annotation_id="975">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="975" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une brève discussion sur le sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="878" docOffset="8">
      <en>I think the House has done everything necessary to express our solidarity with the Japanese people.</en>
      <fr>Je pense que l'Assemblée a fait tout le nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1067">pour</DiscourseConnective> exprimer notre solidarité avec le peuple japonais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="978" docOffset="9">
      <en>Thank you very much.</en>
      <fr>Merci beaucoup.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="999" docOffset="10">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
