<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>15.</en>
    <fr>15.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Strengthening Chemical, Biological, Radiological and Nuclear Security in the European Union - an EU CBRN Action Plan (</en>
    <fr>Le renforcement de la sécurité chimique, biologique, radiologique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="70">et</DiscourseConnective> nucléaire dans l'Union européenne - un plan d'action de l'UE dans le domaine CBRN (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="123" id="137" language="PT" name="Ana Gomes">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="123" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear (CBRN) risks are inherent to possible terrorist attacks, industrial accidents or natural disasters.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, les risques chimiques, biologiques, radiologiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="230">et</DiscourseConnective> nucléaires (CBRN) sont inhérents aux attentats terroristes, aux accidents industriels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="319">ou</DiscourseConnective> aux catastrophes naturelles éventuels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="284" docOffset="3">
      <en>Incidents of this kind, whether accidental or criminal in origin, know no borders and are potentially devastating for human lives, infrastructure, the environment and public health.</en>
      <fr>Les incidents de ce genre, qu'ils soient d'origine naturelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="422">ou</DiscourseConnective> criminelle, ne connaissent pas de frontière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="469">et</DiscourseConnective> ont des effets potentiellement dévastateurs sur les vies humaines, les infrastructures, l'environnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="576">et</DiscourseConnective> la santé publique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="466" docOffset="4">
      <en>They do not occur just in remote areas: we need only recall the recent disaster caused by the leak of toxic sludge from a factory in Hungary and the series of letter-bombs posted from Yemen to various addresses in the United States and Europe.</en>
      <fr>Ils ne se produisent pas uniquement dans les régions éloignées: rappelons-nous la récente catastrophe provoquée par la fuite de boues toxiques d'une usine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="753">en</DiscourseConnective> Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="764">et</DiscourseConnective> la série de lettres piégées envoyées du Yémen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="813">à</DiscourseConnective> différentes adresses aux États-Unis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="851">et</DiscourseConnective> en Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="710" docOffset="5">
      <en>It is crucial for the European Union to make every effort to develop the necessary cooperation between the Member States' civilian and military capabilities and resources in order to prevent, detect and respond effectively to CBRN attacks or disasters.</en>
      <fr>Il est crucial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="880">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="903">s'</DiscourseConnective>efforce de développer la coopération nécessaire entre les capacités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="973">et</DiscourseConnective> les ressources civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="999">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1031">afin de</DiscourseConnective> prévenir, de détecter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1061">et</DiscourseConnective> de répondre efficacement aux attaques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1102">ou</DiscourseConnective> aux catastrophes CBRN.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="963" docOffset="6">
      <en>Such cooperation requires a special European crisis-response mechanism, working in collaboration with a European civil protection force. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1100" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>, this House has long been calling for such a force to be established.</en>
      <fr>Une telle coopération implique un mécanisme européen spécifique de réponse aux crises allié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1220">à</DiscourseConnective> une force de protection civile européenne dont ce Parlement réclame la mise en place depuis longtemps.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1178" docOffset="7">
      <en>The EU Action Plan <Alignment alignment="1355" annotation_id="1197">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1197" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> needs strengthening.</en>
      <fr>Le plan d'action de l'UE doit <Alignment alignment="671" annotation_id="1355">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1355" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être renforcé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1228" docOffset="8">
      <en>The existing plan, which the Council approved in 2009, is weak <Alignment alignment="812" annotation_id="1291">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1291" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in practice, is not being implemented by all Member States.</en>
      <fr>Le plan existant, approuvé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1412">en</DiscourseConnective> 2009 par le Conseil, est insuffisant <Alignment alignment="1291" annotation_id="1452">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1452" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans la pratique, il n'est pas mis en œuvre par tous les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1356" docOffset="9">
      <en>It just needs one link to crack for the whole chain of intervention to fail.</en>
      <fr>Il suffit qu'un maillon casse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1558">pour que</DiscourseConnective> toute la chaîne de l'intervention échoue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1433" docOffset="10">
      <en>It is vital to give the Commission a stronger monitoring, guiding and coordinating role, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1522" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> the plan urgently needs to be implemented in all Member States.</en>
      <fr>Il est essentiel de renforcer le rôle de suivi, d'orientation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1671">et</DiscourseConnective> de coordination de la Commission et il est urgent que le plan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1736">soit</DiscourseConnective> appliqué par tous les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1590" docOffset="11">
      <en>This report proposes greater civilian-military cooperation in terms of pooling efforts for CBRN disaster prevention, detection, preparation and response.</en>
      <fr>Ce rapport propose d'intensifier la coopération civile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1833">et</DiscourseConnective> militaire dans les efforts concertés de prévention, de détection, de préparation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1917">et</DiscourseConnective> de réponse aux catastrophes CBRN.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1744" docOffset="12">
      <en>The EU has to bring all the Member States together to put in place integrated national systems for implementing the plan.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne doit réunir tous les États membres afin qu'ils mettent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2028">en</DiscourseConnective> place des systèmes nationaux intégrés d'application du plan.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1866" docOffset="13">
      <en>In this respect, the CBRN Action Plan is an opportunity to put the Treaty of Lisbon solidarity clause into practice.</en>
      <fr>Le plan d'action dans le domaine CBRN est, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2135">en ce sens</DiscourseConnective>, l'occasion de mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2168">en</DiscourseConnective> pratique la clause de solidarité du traité de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
