<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statements by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclarations de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="28" id="006" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="28" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ten days ago in Moscow, more people died at the hands of terrorists.</en>
      <fr>Il y a dix jours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="47">à</DiscourseConnective> Moscou, des terroristes ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="77">à</DiscourseConnective> nouveau semé la mort.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="97" docOffset="2">
      <en>We share the pain of the victims' families, and hope that those responsible for these attacks will be found quickly and tried.</en>
      <fr>Nous partageons la peine des familles des victimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="152">et</DiscourseConnective> nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="169">que</DiscourseConnective> les responsables de ces attaques seront rapidement trouvés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="232">et</DiscourseConnective> jugés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="224" docOffset="3">
      <en>The European Parliament condemns and has always condemned acts of violence of this sort.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen condamne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="273">et</DiscourseConnective> a toujours condamné les actes de violence de cette nature.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="313" docOffset="4">
      <en>Today marks the 70th anniversary of the issue of the order by Stalin to shoot over 20 000 Polish Army officers.</en>
      <fr>Nous célébrons aujourd'hui le 70e anniversaire de la publication par Staline de l'ordre d'exécuter plus de 20 000 officiers de l'armée polonaise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="425" docOffset="5">
      <en>They were prisoners of war, and were being held captive following the aggression of the USSR against Poland in September 1939.</en>
      <fr>Ces militaires étaient des prisonniers de guerre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="530">et</DiscourseConnective> ils étaient maintenus en captivité à la suite de l'agression de la Pologne par l'URSS <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="619">en</DiscourseConnective> septembre 1939.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="552" docOffset="6">
      <en>During the last parliamentary term, Members had the opportunity to watch the film 'Katyń', which tells the story of these events.</en>
      <fr>Au cours de la dernière législature, des députés ont eu l'occasion de visionner le film "Katyń", qui relate l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="748">histoire de</DiscourseConnective> ces événements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="682" docOffset="7">
      <en>Last Friday, it was broadcast for the first time on Russian public television.</en>
      <fr>Ce film a été diffusé vendredi dernier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="815">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois sur la chaîne de télévision publique russe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="761" docOffset="8">
      <en>For the first time, the Prime Ministers of Poland and the Russian Federation are paying tribute to the victims of the crime in Katyń together, today, 7 April.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="881">Pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois aujourd'hui, le 7 avril, les premiers ministres de Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="962">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Fédération de Russie rendent conjointement hommage aux victimes de ce crime commis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1054">à</DiscourseConnective> Katyń.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="920" docOffset="9">
      <en>This important step on the road to Polish-Russian reconciliation, and also on the road to reconciliation in the East, is <Alignment alignment="1211" annotation_id="1041">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1041" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a signal to the whole of Europe and is the next stage of the reconciliation of the Eastern and Western parts of our continent, which we all want.</en>
      <fr>Cette étape importante sur la voie de la réconciliation russo-polonaise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1136">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que sur la voie de la réconciliation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1179">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe orientale, représente <Alignment alignment="378" annotation_id="1211">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1211" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un signal lancé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1233">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ensemble de l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1258">et</DiscourseConnective> constitue la prochaine étape de la réconciliation entre les parties orientale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1339">et</DiscourseConnective> occidentale de notre continent - une réconciliation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1394">que</DiscourseConnective> nous souhaitons tous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1192" docOffset="10">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1203" docOffset="11">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="1115" annotation_id="1211">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1211" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to inform you that the European Commission will be represented by Mr Šefčovič at today's plenary sitting. Mr Barroso is unable to attend, today, for important family reasons.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <Alignment alignment="720" annotation_id="1448">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1448" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1458">à</DiscourseConnective> vous signaler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1474">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne sera représentée par M. Šefčovič <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1536">à</DiscourseConnective> l'occasion de la séance plénière d'aujourd'hui, M. Barroso étant dans l'impossibilité d'être présent aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1651">pour</DiscourseConnective> d'importantes raisons familiales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
