<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Interinstitutional Agreement on the Transparency Register (signing)</en>
    <fr>Accord interinstitutionnel du registre de transparence (signature)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="68" id="125" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="68" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ladies and Gentlemen, dear colleagues, let us take our seats for the official signing of a very important agreement between the European Parliament and the European Commission: the 'lobbyists register'.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="76">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, chers collègues, asseyons-nous pour assister à la signature officielle d'un accord très important entre le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="216">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission: l'accord interinstitutionnel du registre de transparence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="271" docOffset="2">
      <en>We voted on the Casini report at the last plenary session in Strasbourg <Alignment alignment="381" annotation_id="343">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="343" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> now we will have the official signing.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons voté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="308">pour</DiscourseConnective> le rapport Casini lors de la dernière session plénière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="368">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg <Alignment alignment="1659" annotation_id="381">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="381" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aujourd'hui nous assistons à la signature officielle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="386" docOffset="3">
      <en>We voted on 11 May 2011.</en>
      <fr>Le vote a eu lieu le 11 mai 2011.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="411" docOffset="4">
      <en>For the official signing, I should like to welcome Minister Győri and Maroš Šefčovič, Vice-President of the European Commission, and our colleagues Diana Wallis, Vice-President of the European Parliament, who was in the negotiator's team, Vice-President Isabelle Durant, Vice-President Rainer Wieland and Carlo Casini, Chair of the Committee on Constitutional Affairs and also the rapporteur.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="472">Pour</DiscourseConnective> la signature officielle, permettez-moi d'accueillir la ministre Győri <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="547">et</DiscourseConnective> Maroš Šefčovič, vice-président de la Commission européenne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="610">et</DiscourseConnective> nos collègues Diana Wallis, vice-présidente du Parlement européen qui faisait partie de l'équipe de négociation, la vice-présidente Isabelle Durant, et le vice-président Rainer Wieland <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="798">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que Carlo Casini, président de la commission des affaires constitutionnelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="881">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="884">également</DiscourseConnective> rapporteur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="804" id="126" name="Enikő Győri">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="804" docOffset="5">
      <en>President-in-Office of the Council. - Mr President, honourable Members, I would like to read out the Council's political statement on the transparency register.</en>
      <fr>présidente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="917">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, honorables parlementaires, permettez-moi de lire la déclaration politique du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1056">à propos</DiscourseConnective> du registre de transparence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="965" docOffset="6">
      <en>'The Council considers transparency as a principle of paramount importance for the European Union.</en>
      <fr>"Le Conseil estime que la transparence est un principe primordial <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1160">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1064" docOffset="7">
      <en>The treaties provide that, in order to promote good governance and ensure the participation of civil society, the Union's institutions, bodies, offices and agencies shall conduct their work as openly as possible <Alignment alignment="1425" annotation_id="1276">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1276" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that decisions shall be taken as openly and as closely as possible to the citizens.</en>
      <fr>Les traités disposent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1207">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1212">afin de</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir une bonne gouvernance, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1254">et</DiscourseConnective> d'assurer la participation de la société civile, les institutions, organes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1332">et</DiscourseConnective> organismes de l'Union œuvrent dans le plus grand respect possible du principe d'ouverture <Alignment alignment="871" annotation_id="1425">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1425" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1428">que</DiscourseConnective> les décisions sont prises dans le plus grand respect possible du principe d'ouverture <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1518">et</DiscourseConnective> le plus près possible des citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1364" docOffset="8">
      <en>'In line with these provisions, the Council remains committed to giving the fullest possible effect to the principle of transparency.</en>
      <fr>Conformément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1570">à</DiscourseConnective> ces dispositions, le Conseil reste déterminé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1617">à</DiscourseConnective> conférer le plus large effet possible au principe de transparence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1498" docOffset="9">
      <en>It <Alignment alignment="1698" annotation_id="1501">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1501" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> recognises that citizens expect that those who act on their behalf at the EU level respect the highest possible standards.</en>
      <fr>Il constate <Alignment alignment="1127" annotation_id="1698">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1698" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1711">que</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens attendent des personnes qui agissent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1765">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur compte au niveau de l'UE qu'elles respectent les normes les plus élevées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1629" docOffset="10">
      <en>'The Council <Alignment alignment="1849" annotation_id="1642">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1642" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> welcomes and supports the initiative undertaken by the European Parliament and the Commission to establish a joint "Transparency Register”.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1642" annotation_id="1849">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1849" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">En conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le Conseil salue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1882">et</DiscourseConnective> soutient l'initiative lancée par le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1940">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1964">à</DiscourseConnective> mettre en place un "registre de transparence" commun.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1792" docOffset="11">
      <en>'The Council considers that transparency should guide relations with interest representatives <Alignment alignment="2136" annotation_id="1886">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1886" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the Register provides a useful basis on which to build and interact with them in an open, inclusive and consistent fashion.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil est d'avis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2042">que</DiscourseConnective> la transparence devrait guider les relations avec les représentants des groupes d'intérêt <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="2136">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2136" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2139">que</DiscourseConnective> le registre de transparence fournirait une base utile sur laquelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2210">s'</DiscourseConnective>appuyer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2220">pour</DiscourseConnective> interagir avec eux dans un esprit d'ouverture, sans exclusive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2287">et</DiscourseConnective> de manière cohérente.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2019" docOffset="12">
      <en>'The Council has received the invitation of the European Parliament and the Commission to join the Register.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil a été invité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2336">à</DiscourseConnective> participer au registre de transparence par le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2403">et</DiscourseConnective> la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2128" docOffset="13">
      <en>The Council is ready to consider having a role in the Register and looks forward to discuss the possible modalities with the two other institutions.'</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil est prêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2441">à</DiscourseConnective> envisager de jouer un rôle dans le cadre de ce registre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2499">et</DiscourseConnective> attend avec intérêt d'examiner les éventuelles modalités de sa participation avec les deux autres institutions."</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2278" id="127" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2278" docOffset="14">
      <en>It would be the best solution <Alignment alignment="2644" annotation_id="2308">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2308" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> all the European institutions were to have the same register for outside interests.</en>
      <fr>La meilleure solution serait <Alignment alignment="2308" annotation_id="2644">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2644" sense="Contingency.Condition">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> toutes les institutions européennes possèdent le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2697">même</DiscourseConnective> registre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2711">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne les intérêts extérieurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2395" docOffset="15">
      <en>Now I would like to invite my colleagues and the Vice-President of the Commission to join me in front of the podium for the signing of the document.</en>
      <fr>J'invite à présent mes collègues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2790">et</DiscourseConnective> les vice-présidents de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2830">à</DiscourseConnective> me rejoindre sur le podium <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2859">pour</DiscourseConnective> la signature du document.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
