<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Statement by the President</en>
    <fr>Déclaration de la Présidence</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="27" id="007" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27" docOffset="1">
      <en>I have several things to say <Alignment alignment="62" annotation_id="56">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="56" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we begin.</en>
      <fr>J'ai plusieurs choses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="51">à</DiscourseConnective> déclarer <Alignment alignment="879" annotation_id="62">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="62" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">pour commencer</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="69" docOffset="2">
      <en>There are five brief points.</en>
      <fr>Il y a cinq points que je voudrais brièvement aborder.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="98" docOffset="3">
      <en>Thursday, 27 January, will mark the 66th anniversary of the liberation of the Auschwitz-Birkenau German Nazi concentration and extermination camp.</en>
      <fr>Le jeudi 27 janvier marquera le soixante-sixième anniversaire de la libération du camp de concentration <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="237">et</DiscourseConnective> d'extermination nazi allemand d'Auschwitz-Birkenau.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="245" docOffset="4">
      <en>Every year on this day, we honour the memory of the more than 1 million people who were murdered there.</en>
      <fr>Chaque année, ce jour-là, nous honorons la mémoire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="343">de plus</DiscourseConnective> d'un million de personnes qui y ont été tuées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="349" docOffset="5">
      <en>This gives us the strength to work together to build a peaceful future for a united Europe, a Europe which will not experience such nightmares again.</en>
      <fr>Cela nous donne la force de travailler ensemble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="446">à</DiscourseConnective> la construction d'un avenir pacifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="486">pour</DiscourseConnective> une Europe unie, une Europe qui ne revivra plus de tels cauchemars.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="499" docOffset="6">
      <en>Secondly, on 13 January, the people of Lithuania celebrated the 20th anniversary of 'Bloody Sunday', <Alignment alignment="676" annotation_id="600">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="600" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Soviet army tried to overthrow the democratically elected government of the independent Lithuania.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="559">Deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, le 13 janvier, la population lituanienne a commémoré le vingtième anniversaire du "dimanche sanglant", <Alignment alignment="139" annotation_id="676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="676" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'armée soviétique avait essayé de renverser le gouvernement élu démocratiquement de la Lituanie indépendante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="708" docOffset="7">
      <en>Lithuanians defended their liberty, <Alignment alignment="835" annotation_id="744">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="744" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> today enjoy equal rights as members of the Euro-Atlantic community.</en>
      <fr>Les Lituaniens ont défendu leur liberté <Alignment alignment="744" annotation_id="835">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="835" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> jouissent aujourd'hui de droits égaux en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="879">tant que</DiscourseConnective> membres de la communauté euro-atlantique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="816" docOffset="8">
      <en>In remembering this anniversary, an anniversary which is important for Europe, we express solidarity, today, with the people of Belarus, who are <Alignment alignment="1093" annotation_id="961">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="961" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> our neighbours, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="982" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> who are still waiting for freedom and democracy to come to their country.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="930">En</DiscourseConnective> souvenir de cet anniversaire, un anniversaire important <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="989">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe, nous manifestons aujourd'hui notre solidarité avec le peuple de Biélorussie, nos voisins <Alignment alignment="984" annotation_id="1093">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1093" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, qui attend toujours de voir triompher la liberté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1153">et</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie dans son pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1060" docOffset="9">
      <en>Thirdly, on 23 December 2010, the European Union ratified the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1185">Troisièmement</DiscourseConnective>, le 23 décembre 2010, l'Union européenne a ratifié la convention des Nations unies relative aux droits des personnes handicapées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1192" docOffset="10">
      <en>The Convention, together with the European Commission's disability strategy, will enable equal civil, political and economic rights to be guaranteed by 2020 to the nearly 80 million citizens of the Union who are affected by some kind of disability.</en>
      <fr>La convention, conjointement avec la stratégie de la Commission européenne en matière de handicap, permettra de garantir, d'ici 2020, des droits civils, politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1493">et</DiscourseConnective> économiques égaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1514">à</DiscourseConnective> près de 80 millions de citoyens européens touchés par un handicap.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1441" docOffset="11">
      <en>Fourthly, I would <Alignment alignment="1614" annotation_id="1459">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1459" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to reiterate that we are seriously concerned by the disappearance of the Chinese lawyer, Gao Zhisheng.</en>
      <fr>Quatrièmement, je souhaiterais <Alignment alignment="1178" annotation_id="1614">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1614" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> rappeler notre sérieuse préoccupation concernant la disparition de l'avocat chinois Gao Zhisheng.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1572" docOffset="12">
      <en>According to the latest reports, he is being mistreated and subjected to torture.</en>
      <fr>Les derniers rapports indiquent qu'il serait maltraité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1777">et</DiscourseConnective> torturé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1654" docOffset="13">
      <en>The European Parliament has already taken up Mr Zhisheng's case several times.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1813">déjà</DiscourseConnective> abordé le cas de M. Zhisheng à plusieurs occasions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1733" docOffset="14">
      <en>Today, I would like to call upon the Chinese authorities to reveal the place where he is being detained and give details of his state of health.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, je voudrais lancer un appel aux autorités chinoises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1935">afin que</DiscourseConnective> son lieu de détention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1966">et</DiscourseConnective> son état de santé soient communiqués.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1878" docOffset="15">
      <en>Finally, since our last meeting before Christmas, the Belgian Presidency has ended, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1962" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> the leadership of the European Union Council has been assumed by Hungary.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2007">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2014">depuis</DiscourseConnective> notre dernière session <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2044">avant</DiscourseConnective> Noël, la Belgique a passé le témoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2086">à</DiscourseConnective> la Hongrie à la présidence du Conseil de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2040" docOffset="16">
      <en>We are going to talk about both presidencies during this part-session of Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Nous évoquerons ces deux Présidences pendant la présente période de session du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2125" docOffset="17">
      <en>Since our last meeting, important political events have <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2181" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> taken place.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2239">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> notre dernière session, des événements politiques importants se sont produits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2199" docOffset="18">
      <en>I am thinking of the election in Belarus and the recent clashes in Tunisia.</en>
      <fr>Je pense aux élections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2348">en</DiscourseConnective> Biélorussie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2363">et</DiscourseConnective> aux récents affrontements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2392">en</DiscourseConnective> Tunisie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2275" docOffset="19">
      <en>Both of these are on the order of business of our plenary part-session.</en>
      <fr>Ces deux sujets sont inscrits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2434">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre des travaux de notre période de session plénière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2347" docOffset="20">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="2506" annotation_id="2355">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2355" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to remind everyone that several serious natural disasters struck in the last weeks of the Christmas period.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="990" annotation_id="2506">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2506" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> rappeler à chacun <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2534">que</DiscourseConnective> plusieurs catastrophes naturelles graves ont marqué les dernières semaines de la période de Noël.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2473" docOffset="21">
      <en>We sympathise with the victims' families, <Alignment alignment="2686" annotation_id="2515">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2515" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we would like to express our condolences to them and to the governments of the countries affected.</en>
      <fr>Nous compatissons avec les familles des victimes, <Alignment alignment="2515" annotation_id="2686">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2686" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous tenons à leur présenter nos condoléances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2735">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'aux gouvernements des pays touchés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
