<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>8.</en>
    <fr>8.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Commission White Paper: "Adapting to climate change: Towards a European framework for action" (</en>
    <fr>Livre blanc de la Commission: «Adaptation au changement climatique: vers un cadre d'action européen» (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="99" id="093" language="IT" name="Vittorio Prodi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="99" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, climate change is a real threat that we must be ready to face despite the varying impact it will have on our countries.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="138">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, les changements climatiques constituent une réelle menace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="210">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons être prêts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="237">à</DiscourseConnective> affronter, en dépit de l'impact variable qu'ils auront sur nos pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="255" docOffset="3">
      <en>The degradation of ecosystems will cause a severe blow to the health of our economies and of European citizens.</en>
      <fr>La dégradation des écosystèmes sera un coup terrible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="361">pour</DiscourseConnective> la santé de nos économies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="392">et</DiscourseConnective> des citoyens européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="367" docOffset="4">
      <en>We have already in the past called for climate diplomacy and justice: now we have to build it, speaking with a single voice.</en>
      <fr>Par le passé, nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="444">déjà</DiscourseConnective> réclamé une diplomatie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="472">et</DiscourseConnective> une justice relatives au climat: <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="508">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> nous devons les élaborer, en parlant d'une seule voix.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="492" docOffset="5">
      <en>I am convinced that the European Union must maintain the lead in the battle against climate change <Alignment alignment="2257" annotation_id="591">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="591" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that any delay in implementing that action will increase environmental, social and economic costs out of all proportion.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="592">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne doit conserver son rôle de chef de file dans la bataille contre les changements climatiques, <Alignment alignment="1201" annotation_id="708">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="708" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="711">que</DiscourseConnective> tout retard dans la mise en œuvre de cette mesure augmentera les coûts environnementaux, sociaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="812">et</DiscourseConnective> économiques de manière démesurée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="716" docOffset="6">
      <en>We must first of all recognise the central role of local and regional authorities and the need to work with them to coordinate environmental and economic innovation facilitated by technological progress.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="861">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout reconnaître le rôle central des autorités locales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="922">et</DiscourseConnective> régionales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="937">et</DiscourseConnective> la nécessité de travailler avec elles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="978">pour</DiscourseConnective> coordonner l'innovation environnementale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1024">et</DiscourseConnective> économique facilitée par les progrès technologiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="920" docOffset="7">
      <en>By adopting the White Paper, we call on the Commission and Member States to promote public-private partnerships to help finance all of the initiatives tied to the adaptation policies.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1080">En</DiscourseConnective> adoptant le Livre blanc, nous encourageons la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1140">et</DiscourseConnective> les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1161">à</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir les partenariats public-privé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1204">pour</DiscourseConnective> aider à financer toutes les initiatives liées aux politiques d'adaptation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1104" docOffset="8">
      <en>Each square metre of our territory has to be cared for to preserve the soil and retain water <Alignment alignment="1385" annotation_id="1197">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1197" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1200" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> to prevent erosion and to supply the aquifers, including through direct reinjection of surface waters.</en>
      <fr>Chaque mètre carré de notre territoire doit être protégé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1341">pour</DiscourseConnective> préserver les sols <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1365">et</DiscourseConnective> conserver l'eau, <Alignment alignment="344" annotation_id="1385">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1385" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de manière à</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> empêcher l'érosion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1417">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1420">à</DiscourseConnective> approvisionner les nappes aquifères, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1459">notamment</DiscourseConnective> par réinjection directe d'eaux de surface.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1306" docOffset="9">
      <en>In order for adaptation to be possible, a systemic approach which includes renewable energies will be necessary.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1512">Afin de</DiscourseConnective> rendre possible une telle adaptation, une approche systémique comprenant des énergies renouvelables sera nécessaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1419" docOffset="10">
      <en>I would like to warmly thank all of my colleagues who contributed to the success of this report.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais remercier vivement tous mes collègues qui ont contribué au succès de ce rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1516" docOffset="11">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
