<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Cooperating with developing countries on promoting good governance in tax matters (short presentation)</en>
    <fr>Coopérer avec les pays en développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="40">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>encourager la bonne gouvernance dans le domaine fiscal (brève présentation)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="103" id="223" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="103" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Mrs Joly, on behalf of the Committee on Development, on Tax and development - Cooperating with developing countries on promoting good governance in tax matters.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de Eva Joly, au nom de la commission du développement, sur la fiscalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="230">et</DiscourseConnective> le développement - coopérer avec les pays en développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="292">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>encourager la bonne gouvernance dans le domaine fiscal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="295" id="224" language="FR" name="Eva Joly">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="295" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, it is with some satisfaction that I present this report on tax and development to you tonight.</en>
      <fr>rapporteure. - Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, c'est avec une certaine satisfaction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="472">que</DiscourseConnective> je vous présente ce soir ce rapport sur la fiscalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="529">et</DiscourseConnective> le développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="440" docOffset="3">
      <en>It represents an important stage in a battle that began a long time ago, which I am now pursuing in the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>C'est en effet une étape importante d'un combat débuté il y a longtemps et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="625">que</DiscourseConnective> je poursuis aujourd'hui au sein du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="565" docOffset="4">
      <en>I would like to thank my colleagues in the Committee on Development, with whom the work has been extremely productive.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="693">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier mes collègues de la commission du développement, avec qui la collaboration a été particulièrement fructueuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="684" docOffset="5">
      <en>I hope that it will find confirmation during tomorrow's votes.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="824">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle se confirmera au cours des votes de demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="747" docOffset="6">
      <en>Developing countries have been very badly hit by the financial and economic crisis and the rising prices of agricultural materials and now need substantial new sources of funding more than ever.</en>
      <fr>Sévèrement frappés par la crise financière <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="919">et</DiscourseConnective> économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="933">et</DiscourseConnective> par la hausse des prix des matières agricoles, les pays en développement ont plus que jamais besoin de nouvelles et substantielles sources de financement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="942" docOffset="7">
      <en>Amid this context of global crisis, tax revenue, which is the oldest source of development funding, is a major issue and a genuine challenge.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte de crise globale, mobiliser les recettes fiscales, source la plus ancienne de financement du développement, constitue un enjeu de taille tout autant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1257">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un véritable défi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1084" docOffset="8">
      <en>Effective taxation systems not only provide funding for vital public services.</en>
      <fr>Des systèmes fiscaux efficaces ne permettent pas seulement de financer les services publics indispensables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1163" docOffset="9">
      <en>By promoting the transparent, responsible use of government revenue, they are <Alignment alignment="13683" annotation_id="1241">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1241" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> one of the foundations of a responsible democracy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1387">En</DiscourseConnective> promouvant l'utilisation transparente et responsable des recettes publiques, ils sont <Alignment alignment="4589" annotation_id="1476">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1476" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la base d'un système démocratique responsable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1297" docOffset="10">
      <en>Contributing towards raising equitable, progressive and transparent taxes should in no way lead to removing or reducing official development assistance (ODA).</en>
      <fr>Permettre la levée d'un impôt équitable, progressif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1581">et</DiscourseConnective> transparent ne doit aucunement mener <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1621">à</DiscourseConnective> la suppression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1638">ou</DiscourseConnective> à la baisse de l'aide publique au développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1456" docOffset="11">
      <en>It should not provide a further excuse for Member States that are increasingly inclined to reduce their share of GDP which is devoted to ODA.</en>
      <fr>Cela ne doit pas être l'excuse supplémentaire d'États membres toujours plus enclins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1774">à</DiscourseConnective> diminuer la part de leur PIB dédiée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1812">à</DiscourseConnective> l'APD.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1598" docOffset="12">
      <en>Whilst ODA may be imperfect and have much room for improvement, it is no less vital for countries that have been severely affected by both economic and climate-related crises.</en>
      <fr>L'aide publique au développement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1855">certes</DiscourseConnective> imparfaite, certes largement perfectible, n'en reste pas moins indispensable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1939">à</DiscourseConnective> des pays durement frappés par des crises économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1994">et</DiscourseConnective> climatiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1774" docOffset="13">
      <en>It is not a question of replacing aid, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1813" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>, but of redirecting it towards developing effective taxation systems, to which the multinationals must contribute on the basis of their actual profits. In this way, poor countries will be able to take ownership of their development once again, reduce poverty and compensate for the loss of customs revenue caused by the liberalisation of the markets, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2174" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective> in the long term, they will be able to manage without foreign aid.</en>
      <fr>Il ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2016">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit donc pas de remplacer l'aide, il s'agit de la réorienter vers l'élaboration de systèmes fiscaux efficaces auxquels les multinationales contribuent à hauteur de leurs bénéfices réels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2205">pour</DiscourseConnective> permettre aux pays pauvres de se réapproprier leur développement, de réduire la pauvreté, de compenser les pertes des ressources douanières dues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2355">à</DiscourseConnective> la libéralisation des marchés et de s'affranchir à long terme de l'aide étrangère.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2249" docOffset="14">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21877" annotation_id="2249">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2249" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the countries of the South are not only victims of their own ineffective taxation systems.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2249" annotation_id="2440">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2440" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les pays du Sud ne sont pas seulement victimes de l'inefficacité de leurs systèmes fiscaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2349" docOffset="15">
      <en>They are <Alignment alignment="2549" annotation_id="2358">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2358" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> victims of the tax dumping imposed by the Bretton Woods bodies, of the cost of illicit capital flight, <Alignment alignment="5658" annotation_id="2466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2466" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> of tax havens.</en>
      <fr>Ils le sont <Alignment alignment="154" annotation_id="2549">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2549" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> du dumping fiscal imposé par les instances de Bretton Woods, des prix des transferts illicites <Alignment alignment="2466" annotation_id="2654">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2654" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de l'existence des paradis fiscaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2485" docOffset="16">
      <en>Every year, they sustain colossal losses of tax revenue estimated at over ten times the amount of aid they receive from rich countries.</en>
      <fr>Ils subissent, chaque année, de colossales pertes de recettes fiscales estimées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2773">à</DiscourseConnective> plus de dix fois le montant des aides allouées par les pays riches.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2621" docOffset="17">
      <en>This report emphasises this fact.</en>
      <fr>Ce rapport le rappelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2655" docOffset="18">
      <en>As for the OECD guidelines, far from being adequate, they actually pose a threat.</en>
      <fr>Les lignes directrices de l'OCDE, loin d'être suffisantes, sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2931">même</DiscourseConnective> dangereuses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2737" docOffset="19">
      <en>By allowing non-cooperative jurisdictions to be taken off the grey lists simply by signing cooperation agreements without imposing any automatic exchange of information, they are creating the illusion that tax havens are legitimate and conferring credibility on a system that is harmful to public finances in North and South alike.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2949">En</DiscourseConnective> permettant à des juridictions non coopératives de sortir des listes grises par la simple signature d'accords de coopération n'imposant pas l'échange automatique d'information, elles donnent l'illusion de la légalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3168">à</DiscourseConnective> des paradis fiscaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3190">et</DiscourseConnective> légitiment un système dommageable aux finances publiques du Sud <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3257">comme</DiscourseConnective> du Nord.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3069" docOffset="20">
      <en>Putting an end to tax havens is a vital step towards these countries' development, <Alignment alignment="3363" annotation_id="3152">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3152" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Union must make it an absolute priority.</en>
      <fr>Mettre un terme aux paradis fiscaux est une étape essentielle du développement de ces pays <Alignment alignment="4181" annotation_id="3363">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3363" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> doit être la priorité absolue de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3210" docOffset="21">
      <en>The EU must shoulder its responsibilities <Alignment alignment="3472" annotation_id="3252">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3252" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the United States has done and produce clear, binding legislation coupled with genuine sanction mechanisms in order to put an end to tax havens, which are like weapons of mass destruction for the development of poor countries.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne doit prendre ses responsabilités; <Alignment alignment="3568" annotation_id="3472">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3472" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">à</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'image des États-Unis, elle doit établir une législation claire et contraignante, assortie de réels mécanismes de sanctions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3599">pour</DiscourseConnective> stopper les paradis fiscaux, véritables armes de destruction massive <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3673">pour</DiscourseConnective> le développement des pays pauvres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3482" docOffset="22">
      <en>The EU must prevent profit and transfer price manipulation by companies, especially European companies, which both benefit from and abuse detrimental taxation systems.</en>
      <fr>Elle doit empêcher les manipulations des bénéfices <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3764">et</DiscourseConnective> les prix des transferts opérés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3798">notamment</DiscourseConnective> par les entreprises européennes qui usent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3850">et</DiscourseConnective> abusent de systèmes fiscaux néfastes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3650" docOffset="23">
      <en>It must impose the introduction of a transparent, binding international mechanism that will place a duty on all multinational companies, especially those in the extractive industries, to automatically declare the profits they make and the taxes they pay in each of the countries in which they operate.</en>
      <fr>Elle doit imposer la mise en place d'un mécanisme international transparent et contraignant, obligeant toutes les sociétés multinationales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4031">notamment</DiscourseConnective> extractives, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4054">à</DiscourseConnective> déclarer automatiquement les profits qu'elles réalisent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4112">et</DiscourseConnective> les impôts qu'elles acquittent dans chacun des pays où elles opèrent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3952" docOffset="24">
      <en>This is a vital first step towards stopping those who are getting rich on the back of the Southern countries' misery.</en>
      <fr>C'est un premier pas indispensable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4220">pour</DiscourseConnective> stopper ceux qui s'enrichissent sur la misère des populations du Sud.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4070" docOffset="25">
      <en>It is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4076" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> a vital step towards restoring the European Union's credibility.</en>
      <fr>C'est un pas indispensable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4322">pour</DiscourseConnective> rendre à l'Union européenne sa crédibilité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4146" id="225" name="Elena Băsescu">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4146" docOffset="26">
      <en>(RO) Mr President, against the background of the current economic crisis, promoting good governance on tax matters is a necessity at both EU level and outside it.</en>
      <fr>(RO) Monsieur le Président, au vu de la crise économique actuelle, il est nécessaire de promouvoir une bonne gouvernance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4492">en</DiscourseConnective> matière fiscale, que ce soit au sein de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4540">ou</DiscourseConnective> hors de ses frontières.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4309" docOffset="27">
      <en>I should point out that every state is responsible for deciding its own fiscal policy.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens à rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4587">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il appartient à chaque État de choisir sa propre politique fiscal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4396" docOffset="28">
      <en>In this context, the practice of putting up obstacles must be avoided and cooperation between countries encouraged.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte, il faut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4683">donc</DiscourseConnective> éviter de lever des obstacles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4718">et</DiscourseConnective> encourager la coopération entre les pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4512" docOffset="29">
      <en>Combating tax havens is a key priority. They help detract from the quality of the political system in developing countries.</en>
      <fr>Lutter contre les paradis fiscaux constitue une priorité majeure car ils favorisent la dégradation des systèmes politiques des pays en développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4636" docOffset="30">
      <en>They <Alignment alignment="4929" annotation_id="4641">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4641" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> encourage economic crime, making it more profitable. This <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4704" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">in turn</DiscourseConnective> helps increase the inequitable distribution of tax revenues.</en>
      <fr>Ils encouragent <Alignment alignment="4641" annotation_id="4929">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4929" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la criminalité économique en la rendant plus rentable, ce qui entraîne une répartition inéquitable des recettes fiscales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4773" docOffset="31">
      <en>Another measure involves increasing the exchange of information between all Member States.</en>
      <fr>Il serait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5071">également</DiscourseConnective> utile de développer l'échange d'informations entre les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4864" docOffset="32">
      <en>At the same time, there needs to be a greater level of participation from developing countries in the relevant international forums.</en>
      <fr>Mais il faut que, dans le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5177">même</DiscourseConnective> temps, les pays en développement participent davantage aux instances internationales compétentes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4997" id="226" name="Franziska Keller">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4997" docOffset="33">
      <en>Mr President, tax and taxing is an extremely important topic <Alignment alignment="1963" annotation_id="5058">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5058" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we talk about development policies.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, la fiscalité est une question extrêmement importante <Alignment alignment="5058" annotation_id="5361">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5361" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les politiques de développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5099" docOffset="34">
      <en>It is a crucial topic for policy coherence for development <Alignment alignment="5490" annotation_id="5158">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5158" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, without a proper tax system, without proper policies on tax havens, we will never be coherent in our development policies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5289" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>, at the moment, we are not.</en>
      <fr>Elle est également primordiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5430">pour</DiscourseConnective> la cohérence des politiques en faveur du développement <Alignment alignment="5158" annotation_id="5490">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5490" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5495">sans</DiscourseConnective> un système fiscal approprié ou <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5531">sans</DiscourseConnective> politiques adéquates sur les paradis fiscaux, nous ne serons jamais cohérents dans nos politiques de développement, comme c'est le cas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5671">pour</DiscourseConnective> le moment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5321" docOffset="35">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19693" annotation_id="5321">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5321" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I very much welcome this report <Alignment alignment="5742" annotation_id="5364">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5364" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I hope that tomorrow, you, the Members of this House, will not water it down.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5321" annotation_id="5687">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5687" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je me félicite grandement de ce rapport <Alignment alignment="5364" annotation_id="5742">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5742" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5752">que</DiscourseConnective> vous, députés de ce Parlement, ne l'étoufferez pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5446" docOffset="36">
      <en>We need to complement the Commission communication, which has serious shortcomings, <Alignment alignment="23578" annotation_id="5530">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5530" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, by not addressing problems within the OECD and by not addressing the impact of tax competition on tax revenues.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions compléter la communication de la Commission, qui contient de sérieuses lacunes, <Alignment alignment="5530" annotation_id="5902">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5902" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">notamment en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> n'abordant pas les problèmes au sein de l'OCDE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5962">ou</DiscourseConnective> l'impact de la concurrence en matière d'impôts sur les recettes fiscales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5655" docOffset="37">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6039" annotation_id="5655">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5655" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want to comply with the Lisbon Treaty, <Alignment alignment="6098" annotation_id="5700">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5700" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want our development policies to be coherent, we need to take action now <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5779" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I ask you to support this report in full.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5655" annotation_id="6039">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6039" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous souhaitons nous conformer au traité de Lisbonne et <Alignment alignment="5700" annotation_id="6098">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6098" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons que nos politiques soient cohérentes, nous devons agir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6169">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, c'est pourquoi je vous demande de soutenir ce rapport dans son ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5825" id="227" name="João Ferreira">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5825" docOffset="38">
      <en>(PT) Mr President, <Alignment alignment="6282" annotation_id="5844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5844" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cooperation in the field of tax is important and necessary, we should not ignore the fact that tax policy is a crucial instrument of economic and social policy, on whose definition obvious political criteria and evaluations have an impact.</en>
      <fr>(PT) Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="1270" annotation_id="6282">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6282" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la coopération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6305">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de fiscalité est importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6344">et</DiscourseConnective> nécessaire, il ne faut pas oublier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6382">que</DiscourseConnective> la politique fiscale constitue un instrument fondamental de la politique économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6470">et</DiscourseConnective> sociale qui peut être influencé par la définition de critères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6535">et</DiscourseConnective> d'évaluations politiques clairs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6090" docOffset="39">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="337" annotation_id="6090">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6090" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it does not fall to the European Union to export so-called 'good governance in tax matters', <Alignment alignment="1988" annotation_id="6194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6194" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the rapporteur quite rightly mentions.</en>
      <fr>Il n'appartient <Alignment alignment="6090" annotation_id="6587">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6587" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6596">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne de promouvoir cette "bonne gouvernance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6656">en</DiscourseConnective> matière fiscale", <Alignment alignment="6552" annotation_id="6677">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6677" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'a très bien rappelé la rapporteure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6236" docOffset="40">
      <en>Developing countries' sovereignty, choices and options must be entirely respected, whilst paying attention to their specific situation and conditions.</en>
      <fr>Il faut pleinement respecter la souveraineté, les décisions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6781">et</DiscourseConnective> les options des pays en développement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6823">tout en</DiscourseConnective> tenant compte des spécificités de leur situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6880">et</DiscourseConnective> de leurs conditions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6387" docOffset="41">
      <en>I have two observations about two hot topics.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens à formuler deux remarques au sujet de deux questions brûlantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6433" docOffset="42">
      <en>Firstly, the so-called Economic Partnership Agreements, which we have been imposing on developing countries despite their resistance, and which severely constrain these countries' tax systems, along with causing other severe damage.</en>
      <fr>Je commencerai par ce qu'on appelle les "accords de partenariat économique" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7053">que</DiscourseConnective> nous imposons aux pays en développement contre leur gré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7113">et</DiscourseConnective> limitent considérablement les régimes fiscaux de ces États, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7176">tout en</DiscourseConnective> leur causant d'autres dommages conséquents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6666" docOffset="43">
      <en>Secondly, tax havens, which continue to exist and lead to losses of revenue equivalent to USD 800 billion every year according to the report.</en>
      <fr>Je parlerai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7240">ensuite</DiscourseConnective> des paradis fiscaux qui existent toujours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7290">et</DiscourseConnective> entraînent, selon le rapport, des pertes de recettes de 800 milliards de dollars par an.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6808" docOffset="44">
      <en>These two examples are paradigms of the inconsistency of the European Union's policies regarding its stated development cooperation objectives.</en>
      <fr>Ces deux exemples démontrent l'incohérence des politiques de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7462">quant à</DiscourseConnective> ses objectifs affichés en matière de coopération au développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6952" id="228" name="Maria Damanaki">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6952" docOffset="45">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Mr President, on behalf of the Commission, I would like to thank the European Parliament, and especially the Committee on Development, for this report.</en>
      <fr>membre de la Commission. - Monsieur le Président, au nom de la Commission, je voudrais remercier le Parlement européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7657">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7660">plus particulièrement</DiscourseConnective> la commission du développement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7714">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7132" docOffset="46">
      <en>I am pleased to see that Mrs Eva Joly's report highlights, and gives added strength to, the message of the Commission's communication on tax and development.</en>
      <fr>Je me réjouis de voir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7753">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapport d'Eva Joly souligne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7788">et</DiscourseConnective> renforce le message de la communication de la Commission sur la fiscalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7865">et</DiscourseConnective> le développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7290" docOffset="47">
      <en>It <Alignment alignment="4186" annotation_id="7293">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7293" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sets very ambitious targets and provides powerful guidance for the European Union to strengthen revenue mobilisation in developing countries.</en>
      <fr>Il définit <Alignment alignment="3848" annotation_id="7897">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7897" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des objectifs très ambitieux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7936">et</DiscourseConnective> propose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7947">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne des directives majeures visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7999">à</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la mobilisation des recettes dans les pays en développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7440" docOffset="48">
      <en>Domestic resource mobilisation is central for sustainable growth, poverty reduction, good governance and the provision of public goods needed to achieve the Millennium Development Goals.</en>
      <fr>La mobilisation des ressources intérieures est primordiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8131">pour</DiscourseConnective> une croissance durable, une réduction de la pauvreté, une bonne gouvernance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8212">et</DiscourseConnective> la fourniture de biens publics nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8258">pour</DiscourseConnective> réaliser les objectifs du Millénaire pour le développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7627" docOffset="49">
      <en>We need to improve synergies between tax and development policies and assist developing countries in building better tax systems and administrations.</en>
      <fr>Il faut améliorer les effets des synergies entre la politique fiscale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8393">et</DiscourseConnective> celle du développement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8420">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> aider les pays en développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8463">à</DiscourseConnective> créer des systèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8484">et</DiscourseConnective> administrations fiscaux plus efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7777" docOffset="50">
      <en>We face a serious problem.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes confrontés à un sérieux problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7804" docOffset="51">
      <en>I was personally impressed by your figures stating that the amount of illicit outflows is about ten times the amount of aid money going into developing countries.</en>
      <fr>J'ai été personnellement choquée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8606">en</DiscourseConnective> entendant les chiffres relatifs aux flux illicites sortants, qui sont environ dix fois supérieurs aux aides financières dont bénéficient les pays en développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7967" docOffset="52">
      <en>This is really striking.</en>
      <fr>C'est tout à fait terrifiant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7992" docOffset="53">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9580" annotation_id="7992">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7992" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must work simultaneously at two complementary levels.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="7992" annotation_id="8815">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8815" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> agir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8825">simultanément</DiscourseConnective> sur deux terrains complémentaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8052" docOffset="54">
      <en>First, we need to support effective domestic tax systems <Alignment alignment="8950" annotation_id="8109">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8109" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, secondly, we need to work towards a transparent, cooperative and fair international tax environment to help developing countries fight against tax evasion and harmful tax competition.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8886">premièrement</DiscourseConnective> soutenir des systèmes fiscaux nationaux efficaces, <Alignment alignment="8109" annotation_id="8950">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8950" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8953">deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective> axer nos efforts sur un environnement fiscal international transparent, coopératif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9049">et</DiscourseConnective> équitable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9062">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>aider les pays en développement à lutter contre l'évasion fiscale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9135">et</DiscourseConnective> la concurrence fiscale dommageable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8298" docOffset="55">
      <en>Your report calls on the Commission firstly to take better account of the impact of trade liberalisation and, secondly, not to be limited to the OECD principles in the fight against tax evasion and harmful tax competition.</en>
      <fr>Votre rapport invite la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9209">à</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9212">premièrement</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9226">mieux</DiscourseConnective> prendre en considération l'impact de la libéralisation des échanges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9300">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9304">deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, ne pas se limiter aux principes établis par l'OCDE en matière de lutte contre l'évasion fiscal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9413">et</DiscourseConnective> de concurrence fiscale dommageable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8521" docOffset="56">
      <en>I would like to refer to these challenges.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaiterais évoquer ces deux défis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8564" docOffset="57">
      <en>Concerning the first matter, I can assure you that we are fully committed to supporting successful fiscal transition through increased support for capacity building, demand-driven regional and international capacity development initiatives, and better donor coordination at EU and international levels.</en>
      <fr>En ce qui concerne le premier, je peux vous assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9544">que</DiscourseConnective> nous nous engageons pleinement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9579">à</DiscourseConnective> soutenir une transition fiscale réussie en consolidant l'appui au renforcement des capacités, en encourageant des initiatives de développement régional <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9733">et</DiscourseConnective> international axé sur la demande, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9770">et</DiscourseConnective> en assurant une meilleure coordination entre les donateurs aux niveaux européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9853">et</DiscourseConnective> international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8867" docOffset="58">
      <en>Concerning the second matter, the Commission considers tax evasion and harmful tax competition as major obstacles to domestic resource mobilisation.</en>
      <fr>Quant au second défi, la Commission considère que l'évasion fiscale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9939">et</DiscourseConnective> la concurrence fiscale dommageable constituent des obstacles majeurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10011">pour</DiscourseConnective> la mobilisation des ressources intérieures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9016" docOffset="59">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13314" annotation_id="9016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9016" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we are helping developing countries to develop capacities to address these challenges and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9117" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> promoting better international cooperation in tax matters.</en>
      <fr>Nous aidons <Alignment alignment="4558" annotation_id="10072">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10072" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les pays en développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10103">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer leurs capacités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10131">afin de</DiscourseConnective> faire face à ces défis, tout en encourageant une meilleure coopération internationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10225">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de fiscalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9181" docOffset="60">
      <en>A lot of work has already been undertaken since the adoption of our Communication.</en>
      <fr>De nombreux efforts ont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10274">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été consentis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10293">depuis</DiscourseConnective> l'adoption de notre communication.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9264" docOffset="61">
      <en>Concrete action has been made possible by the Parliament's financial support.</en>
      <fr>Des mesures concrètes ont été rendues possibles grâce au soutien financier du Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9342" docOffset="62">
      <en>Your 2010 allocation of EUR 708 000 has allowed us to fund a series of important activities in order to promote tax governance.</en>
      <fr>Le crédit de 708 000 euros accordé par le Parlement nous a permis de financer une série d'activités capitales visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10541">à</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir une bonne gouvernance fiscale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9470" docOffset="63">
      <en>These activities include technical seminars of the African Tax Administration Forum, support to the extractive industries, transparency initiatives and the financing of a side event at the United Nations on domestic resource mobilisation.</en>
      <fr>Ces activités comprennent des séminaires techniques du Forum africain d'administration fiscale, l'aide aux industries extractives, les initiatives de transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10748">et</DiscourseConnective> le financement de conférences parallèles sur la mobilisation des ressources intérieures aux Nations unies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9709" docOffset="64">
      <en>We will <Alignment alignment="10875" annotation_id="9717">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9717" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> provide technical assistance to implement tax information exchange agreements.</en>
      <fr>Nous fournissons <Alignment alignment="9717" annotation_id="10875">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10875" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une assistance technique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10910">afin de</DiscourseConnective> mettre en œuvre des accords d'échange de renseignements fiscaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9801" docOffset="65">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4454" annotation_id="9801">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9801" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Commission is preparing a Communication to assess the feasibility of introducing a country-by-country reporting requirement into EU legislation.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9801" annotation_id="10983">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10983" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la Commission prépare une communication visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11039">à</DiscourseConnective> évaluer la faisabilité de l'introduction dans la législation de l'UE d'exigences en matière de rapports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11145">pour</DiscourseConnective> chaque pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9960" docOffset="66">
      <en>We had a public consultation, which ended last January, <Alignment alignment="7784" annotation_id="10016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10016" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> now we will continue with an impact assessment on this important issue.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons lancé une consultation publique, qui a pris fin en janvier dernier, <Alignment alignment="10016" annotation_id="11242">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11242" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous poursuivrons avec une évaluation d'impact sur cette question fondamentale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10092" docOffset="67">
      <en>This could help developing countries to combat tax evasion more effectively.</en>
      <fr>Ces mesures pourraient aider les pays en développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11380">à</DiscourseConnective> lutter plus efficacement contre l'évasion fiscale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10169" docOffset="68">
      <en>I sincerely want to thank Parliament for your support and your commitment on these issues.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11442">à</DiscourseConnective> remercier chaleureusement le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11483">pour</DiscourseConnective> son soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11500">et</DiscourseConnective> son engagement sur ces questions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10260" docOffset="69">
      <en>I am convinced that much progress can be made to strengthen tax governance <Alignment alignment="11641" annotation_id="10335">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10335" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am glad to see that these topics have <Alignment alignment="11685" annotation_id="10379">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10379" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> been included in the agendas of the G20 and the G8.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11556">que</DiscourseConnective> davantage de progrès peuvent être réalisés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11603">pour</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la gouvernance fiscale <Alignment alignment="974" annotation_id="11641">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11641" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je me réjouis de voir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11666">que</DiscourseConnective> ces sujets ont <Alignment alignment="10379" annotation_id="11685">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11685" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> été inscrits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11708">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre du jour du G20 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11733">et</DiscourseConnective> du G8.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10436" id="229" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10436" docOffset="70">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10458" docOffset="71">
      <en>The vote will take place at midday on Tuesday, 8 March.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu mardi 8 mars <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11793">à</DiscourseConnective> 12 heures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
