<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>2.</en>
    <fr>2.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Madagascar</en>
    <fr>Madagascar</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="14" id="215" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14" docOffset="2">
      <en>The next item is the debate on six motions for resolutions on Madagascar.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur six propositions de résolution concernant Madagascar.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="88" id="216" name="Raül Romeva i Rueda">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="88" docOffset="3">
      <en>author. - Mr President, this is <Alignment alignment="20534" annotation_id="120">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="120" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">indeed</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a topic for decision.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (ES) Monsieur le Président, nous devons <Alignment alignment="120" annotation_id="155">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="155" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">en effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> prendre des décisions à ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="149" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is a topic we have to discuss.</en>
      <fr>Cette question doit faire l'objet d'un débat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="183" docOffset="5">
      <en>There is a political crisis in Madagascar <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="225" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> this brings us to the necessity of responding <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="275" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">accordingly</DiscourseConnective> to the necessities <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="306" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> of the country.</en>
      <fr>Madagascar est en proie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="268">à</DiscourseConnective> la crise politique, d'où la nécessité d'apporter une réponse appropriée aux besoins de ce pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="327" docOffset="6">
      <en>The power-sharing deal has been negotiated under the auspices of the African Union between the current President Rajoelina and the former President Ravalomanana.</en>
      <fr>L'accord sur la répartition des pouvoirs a été négocié sous les auspices de l'Union africaine entre l'actuel président Rajoelina <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="495">et</DiscourseConnective> l'ancien président Ravalomanana.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="489" docOffset="7">
      <en>There is the Maputo Agreement and Addis Ababa Additional Act, which remain the only political and democratic solution to the current crisis.</en>
      <fr>L'accord de Maputo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="550">et</DiscourseConnective> l'acte additionnel d'Addis-Abeba demeurent la seule solution politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="624">et</DiscourseConnective> démocratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="640">à</DiscourseConnective> la crise actuelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="630" docOffset="8">
      <en>We must not forget this.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne devons pas l'oublier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="655" docOffset="9">
      <en>The Maputo Agreement foresees the establishment of a national unity government with a transition period of 15 months.</en>
      <fr>L'accord de Maputo prévoit l'établissement d'un gouvernement d'unité nationale avec une période de transition de 15 mois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="773" docOffset="10">
      <en>Let me signal as well that, after this fact, there are some specific and local situations that are worrying in terms of the government issuing a decree legalising the export of unprocessed and endangered wood threatening the biodiversity of the country.</en>
      <fr>Permettez-moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="827">également</DiscourseConnective> de souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="850">que</DiscourseConnective>, au-delà de ces éléments, il existe certaines situations spécifiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="923">et</DiscourseConnective> locales qui sont préoccupantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="957">en ce sens</DiscourseConnective> où le gouvernement adopte un décret légalisant l'exportation de bois non traité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1048">et</DiscourseConnective> menacé de disparition, ce qui met en péril la biodiversité du pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1027" docOffset="11">
      <en>This might cause a lot of problems in the future <Alignment alignment="1178" annotation_id="1076">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1076" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they can be lost forever.</en>
      <fr>Cela pourrait entraîner une foule de problèmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1166">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir, <Alignment alignment="2253" annotation_id="1178">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1178" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces essences pourraient disparaître à jamais.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1110" docOffset="12">
      <en>In this context, we have to remind the Commission and the Member States that to send an election observation operation to Madagascar could be a mistake.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce contexte, nous devons rappeler à la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1283">et</DiscourseConnective> aux États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1304">que</DiscourseConnective> l'envoi d'une mission d'observation des élections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1358">à</DiscourseConnective> Madagascar pourrait constituer une erreur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1263" docOffset="13">
      <en>We ask not to send a delegation to this country under the current circumstances, to the elections the current government is organising in March, <Alignment alignment="7525" annotation_id="1408">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1408" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these elections circumvent the Maputo Agreement.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons de ne pas envoyer de délégation dans ce pays, dans les circonstances actuelles, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1498">pour</DiscourseConnective> observer les élections que le gouvernement actuel organise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1562">en</DiscourseConnective> mars, <Alignment alignment="15439" annotation_id="1571">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1571" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">étant donné que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> lesdites élections sabotent l'accord de Maputo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1460" docOffset="14">
      <en>I insist: in this framework, under this consensus <Alignment alignment="11767" annotation_id="1510">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1510" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on the basis of the agreement in Maputo, we should not follow this observation election mission.</en>
      <fr>J'insiste, dans ce contexte, sur la nécessité d'établir un consensus <Alignment alignment="11838" annotation_id="1704">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1704" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'annuler, sur la base de l'accord de Maputo, cette mission d'observation des élections.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1611" docOffset="15">
      <en>This has to be accompanied as well by full respect of human rights in the country and full respect of democratic principles and the rule of law.</en>
      <fr>Cela doit s'accompagner du <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1823">total</DiscourseConnective> respect des droits de l'homme, dans ce pays, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1874">et</DiscourseConnective> du <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1880">total</DiscourseConnective> respect des principes démocratiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1922">et</DiscourseConnective> de la prééminence du droit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1756" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1953" annotation_id="1756">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1756" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these conditions are fulfilled <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1790" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> we can talk about this, but in the current situation, in the current context, I think it would be a mistake.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6417" annotation_id="1953">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1953" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces conditions sont remplies, nous pourrons en débattre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2013">mais</DiscourseConnective> dans la situation actuelle, dans le contexte actuel, je pense que ce serait une erreur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1904" id="217" language="FR" name="Renate Weber">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1904" docOffset="17">
      <en>Mr President, problems of instability persist in Madagascar despite the initiatives of the African Union and the UN.</en>
      <fr>auteure. - Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2140">à</DiscourseConnective> Madagascar, les problèmes d'instabilité persistent malgré les initiatives de l'Union africaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2237">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'ONU.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2021" docOffset="18">
      <en>Mr Rajoelina refuses to share power and is removing everyone who opposes him.</en>
      <fr>M. Rajoelina refuse de partager le pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2293">et</DiscourseConnective> éloigne tous ceux qui s'opposent à lui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2099" docOffset="19">
      <en>He recently affirmed his intention to organise general elections without taking account of the timetable provided for in the Maputo and Addis Ababa agreements.</en>
      <fr>Récemment, il a affirmé son intention d'organiser des élections générales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2410">sans</DiscourseConnective> tenir compte du calendrier prévu par les accords de Maputo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2474">et</DiscourseConnective> d'Addis-Abeba.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2259" docOffset="20">
      <en>It is no exaggeration to say that the anti-constitutional regime of Andry Rajeolina has taken over the three estates and is doing its best to take over the media as well.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est pas une exagération d'affirmer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2532">que</DiscourseConnective> le régime anticonstitutionnel d'Andry Rajeolina s'est approprié les trois pouvoirs de l'État, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2630">et</DiscourseConnective> il fait de son <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2648">mieux</DiscourseConnective> sur les médias <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2669">aussi</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2430" docOffset="21">
      <en>Unfortunately for Madagascar, the human rights violations by the previous president's regime have continued <Alignment alignment="16402" annotation_id="2538">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2538" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Andry Rajeolina declared himself president of the High Transitional Authority.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2676">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2693">pour</DiscourseConnective> Madagascar, les violations des droits de l'homme du régime de l'ancien président ont continué <Alignment alignment="2538" annotation_id="2792">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2792" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>Andry Rajeolina s'est autoproclamé président de la haute autorité de transition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2623" docOffset="22">
      <en>The security forces which he directs have frequently intervened in a violent manner to disperse opposition demonstrations <Alignment alignment="3021" annotation_id="2745">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2745" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there have been deaths and injuries.</en>
      <fr>Les forces de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2905">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il dirige sont fréquemment intervenues d'une manière violente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2970">pour</DiscourseConnective> disperser des manifestations de l'opposition, <Alignment alignment="2745" annotation_id="3021">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3021" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il y a eu des morts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3044">et</DiscourseConnective> des blessés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2786" docOffset="23">
      <en>In its report dated 4 February 2010, Amnesty International shows that parliamentarians, senators, lawyers, leaders of the opposition and journalists have been subject to arrest and arbitrary and illegal detention <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2999" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that some were mistreated during their arrest, <Alignment alignment="12461" annotation_id="3050">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3050" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the authorities have not conducted any enquiries.</en>
      <fr>Dans son rapport du 4 février 2010, Amnesty International montre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3125">que</DiscourseConnective> des parlementaires, des sénateurs, des avocats, des dirigeants de l'opposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3208">et</DiscourseConnective> des journalistes ont fait l'objet d'arrestations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3260">et</DiscourseConnective> de détentions arbitraires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3289">et</DiscourseConnective> illégales, certains étant maltraités lors de leur arrestation, <Alignment alignment="3050" annotation_id="3355">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3355" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les autorités n'ont mené aucune enquête.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3106" docOffset="24">
      <en>Unfortunately, once again, the facts prove that those who take power by force reign with force.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3406">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, une fois de plus, la réalité nous montre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3464">que</DiscourseConnective> ceux qui arrivent au pouvoir par la violence règnent avec violence.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3202" id="218" language="FR" name="Véronique De Keyser">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3202" docOffset="25">
      <en>Mr President, there is consensus on this motion for a resolution.</en>
      <fr>auteure. - Monsieur le Président, sur cette résolution-ci, il y a un consensus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3268" docOffset="26">
      <en>The illegal transitional regime headed by Andry Rajoelina is in the process of plunging Madagascar into chaos.</en>
      <fr>À Madagascar, un régime de transition illégal conduit par Andry Rajoelina est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3694">en</DiscourseConnective> train de plonger le pays dans le chaos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3379" docOffset="27">
      <en>It is preparing to make free and easy with the forthcoming elections, which he has announced for March 2010, at the end of a process which has nothing democratic about it <Alignment alignment="3882" annotation_id="3550">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3550" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which is taking place outside the Maputo and Addis Ababa agreements.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3740">s'</DiscourseConnective>apprête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3750">à</DiscourseConnective> faire main basse sur les prochaines élections, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3799">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il annonce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3813">pour</DiscourseConnective> mars 2010, au terme d'un processus qui n'a rien de démocratique <Alignment alignment="3550" annotation_id="3882">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3882" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui passe outre aux accords de Maputo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3923">et</DiscourseConnective> d'Addis-Abeba.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3623" docOffset="28">
      <en>The illegal nominations of questionable political personalities, the widespread human rights violations and the harassment and arbitrary arrest of parliamentarians, religious leaders and civilians have upset the international community and led it to impose sanctions.</en>
      <fr>Les nominations illégales de personnalités politiques contestées, les violations généralisées des droits de l'homme, le harcèlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4073">et</DiscourseConnective> l'arrestation arbitraire de parlementaires, de religieux, de civils ont ému la communauté internationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4181">et</DiscourseConnective> l'ont amenée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4197">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre des sanctions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3891" docOffset="29">
      <en>Madagascar's membership of the Southern Africa Development Community and the African Union has been frozen.</en>
      <fr>L'appartenance de Madagascar à la Communauté de développement de l'Afrique australe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4306">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'Union africaine est gelée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3999" docOffset="30">
      <en>The United States are refusing it the advantages of the African Growth and Opportunity Act.</en>
      <fr>Les États-Unis lui refusent les avantages de l'Africain Growth and Opportunity Act.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4091" docOffset="31">
      <en>The donors of the International Monetary Fund have reduced their budget by 50%, the UN will examine the situation of this country on 15 February <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4236" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> the European Union has, I believe, suspended its development aid, <Alignment alignment="4236" annotation_id="4306">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4306" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> maintaining its humanitarian aid.</en>
      <fr>Les donneurs du Fonds monétaire international ont réduit de 50 % leur budget et l'ONU examinera la situation du pays ce 15 février, tandis que l'Union européenne a, je crois, suspendu son aide au développement <Alignment alignment="4306" annotation_id="4634">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4634" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4642">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> son aide humanitaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4346" docOffset="32">
      <en>The situation is <Alignment alignment="4692" annotation_id="4363">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4363" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tragic, catastrophic, for a population living on less than a dollar a day.</en>
      <fr>La situation est <Alignment alignment="3526" annotation_id="4692">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4692" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tragique, catastrophique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4723">pour</DiscourseConnective> une population qui vit avec moins d'un dollar par jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4448" docOffset="33">
      <en>We are terribly concerned about this situation <Alignment alignment="11908" annotation_id="4495">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4495" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this joint emergency motion for a resolution is proof of our concern.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes terriblement inquiets de cette situation, <Alignment alignment="4495" annotation_id="4838">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4838" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette résolution d'urgence, qui est consensuelle, en témoigne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4569" docOffset="34">
      <en>We support the mediation efforts being made by Joaquim Chissano, the former president of the Republic of Mozambique, and urge the four political groups to return to the negotiating table.</en>
      <fr>Nous y soutenons les efforts de médiation de Joaquim Chissano, ex-président de la République du Mozambique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5012">et</DiscourseConnective> demandons instamment aux quatre groupes politiques de retourner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5079">à</DiscourseConnective> la table des négociations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4757" docOffset="35">
      <en>There can be no other solution.</en>
      <fr>Il n'y aura pas d'autre solution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4789" docOffset="36">
      <en>We are <Alignment alignment="13920" annotation_id="4796">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4796" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> calling on the African Union and the Southern African Development Community to resume contact in order to bring the transitional process to a proper conclusion <Alignment alignment="18762" annotation_id="4961">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4961" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we call on the Commission to report to us on the consultation process under way with Madagascar under Article 96 of the Cotonou Agreement.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons <Alignment alignment="5736" annotation_id="5157">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5157" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5163">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union africaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5183">et</DiscourseConnective> à la Communauté de développement de l'Afrique australe de reprendre contact <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5262">pour</DiscourseConnective> mener <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5273">à</DiscourseConnective> bonne fin le processus de transition, <Alignment alignment="6829" annotation_id="5313">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5313" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous prions la Commission de nous rendre compte du processus de consultation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5393">en</DiscourseConnective> cours avec Madagascar, suite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5425">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 96 de l'accord de Cotonou.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5104" id="219" name="Bernd Posselt">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5104" docOffset="37">
      <en>author. - (DE) Mr President, there is concern in some of the world's capital cities that our motion for a resolution could lead to an escalation in the situation in Madagascar.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, certaines capitales du monde craignent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5541">que</DiscourseConnective> notre proposition de résolution puisse entraîner une escalade de la situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5623">à</DiscourseConnective> Madagascar.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5281" docOffset="38">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="32517" annotation_id="5281">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5281" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, our aim is to bring peace to the region.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5021" annotation_id="5637">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5637" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, notre but est d'amener la paix dans la région.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5331" docOffset="39">
      <en>I refer, in particular, to Article 14 and 15, which are quite clearly focused on dialogue.</en>
      <fr>Je fais référence, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5714">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>, aux articles 14 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5746">et</DiscourseConnective> 15, qui sont clairement centrés sur le dialogue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5422" docOffset="40">
      <en>The African Union, the European Union, the UN, neighbouring countries, the Contact Group and, last but not least, France, have all been called upon to play their part in ensuring that the four (at a minimum) different political movements that there are in Madagascar can find common ground, that Madagascar does not become a failing state, that it does not drift further towards catastrophe <Alignment alignment="10041" annotation_id="5813">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5813" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that, <Alignment alignment="6200" annotation_id="5823">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5823" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">instead</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it finds a peaceful and negotiated solution.</en>
      <fr>L'Union africaine, l'Union européenne, les Nations unies, les pays limitrophes, le Groupe de contact, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5900">sans</DiscourseConnective> oublier la France, ont tous été appelés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5945">à</DiscourseConnective> jouer leur rôle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5963">en</DiscourseConnective> garantissant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5979">que</DiscourseConnective> les quatre différents mouvements politiques (au minimum) qui existent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6053">à</DiscourseConnective> Madagascar puissent trouver un terrain d'entente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6105">que</DiscourseConnective> Madagascar ne devienne pas un pays en faillite, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6157">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il n'aille pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6175">à</DiscourseConnective> la catastrophe <Alignment alignment="5813" annotation_id="6192">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6192" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6195">que</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="5823" annotation_id="6200">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6200" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">au lieu de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela, le pays trouve une solution issue de négociations pacifiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5877" docOffset="41">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10912" annotation_id="5877">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5877" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this will only be possible <Alignment alignment="6320" annotation_id="5913">
          <Alignment alignment="6320" annotation_id="5913">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5913" sense="Contingency.Condition">as long as</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> nobody tries to establish a dictatorship there, nobody withdraws from the peace process and all the parties return to the negotiating table, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6065" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6068" sense="Expansion.Alternative">otherwise</DiscourseConnective> this wonderful, but ravaged, country will have no future.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5877" annotation_id="6279">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6279" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, cela sera uniquement possible <Alignment alignment="5913" annotation_id="6320">
          <Alignment alignment="580" annotation_id="6320">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6320" sense="Contingency.Condition">tant que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> personne n'essaiera d'y établir une dictature, que personne ne se retirera du processus de paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6425">et</DiscourseConnective> que toutes les parties retourneront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6464">à</DiscourseConnective> la table des négociations, sans quoi ce pays magnifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6522">mais</DiscourseConnective> dévasté n'aura aucun avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6136" id="220" language="FR" name="Marie-Christine Vergiat">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6136" docOffset="42">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the same is happening in Madagascar as in numerous other countries around the world, towards which the European Union has demonstrated a lack of political power.</en>
      <fr>auteure. - Monsieur le Président, mes chers collègues, il en est de Madagascar <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6635">comme</DiscourseConnective> de beaucoup d'autres pays à travers le monde, vis-à-vis desquels l'Union européenne témoigne de son impuissance politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6334" docOffset="43">
      <en>This is particularly true in Africa.</en>
      <fr>Ceci est particulièrement vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6795">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6371" docOffset="44">
      <en>One year <Alignment alignment="6813" annotation_id="6380">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6380" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Andry Rajoelina illegally seized power, the large island of Madagascar seems to be slipping deeper and deeper into a social, economic and financial crisis which its people did not need.</en>
      <fr>Un an <Alignment alignment="6380" annotation_id="6813">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6813" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">après</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la prise de pouvoir illégale d'Andry Rajoelina, la grande île de Madagascar semble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6902">s'</DiscourseConnective>enfoncer de plus en plus dans une crise sociale, économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6964">et</DiscourseConnective> financière, et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6982">pourtant</DiscourseConnective> sa population n'avait pas besoin de cela.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6572" docOffset="45">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19920" annotation_id="6572">
          <Alignment alignment="17223" annotation_id="6572">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6572" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, this country has become one of the poorest countries in the world, with the large majority of the population there living on less than a dollar a day.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9387" annotation_id="7033">
          <Alignment alignment="10157" annotation_id="7033">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7033" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En effet</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, ce pays est devenu l'un des plus pauvres du monde, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7094">et</DiscourseConnective> la grande majorité de la population y vit désormais avec moins d'un dollar par jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6732" docOffset="46">
      <en>Human rights violations are increasing.</en>
      <fr>Les atteintes aux droits de l'homme s'y multiplient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6772" docOffset="47">
      <en>Religious leaders, parliamentarians, journalists and leaders of civil society are subject to intimidation and harassment and are being arrested and thrown into prison.</en>
      <fr>Religieux, parlementaires, journalistes, responsables de la société civile font l'objet de manœuvres d'intimidation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7351">et</DiscourseConnective> de harcèlement, ils sont arrêtés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7387">et</DiscourseConnective> jetés en prison.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6940" docOffset="48">
      <en>The international community, <Alignment alignment="7440" annotation_id="6969">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6969" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, has been sparing in its efforts, refusing to recognise that this is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7046" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">in fact</DiscourseConnective> a coup d'état <Alignment alignment="25722" annotation_id="7068">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7068" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the government put in place by Andry Rajoelina in Madagascar is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7141" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">in fact</DiscourseConnective> a military government.</en>
      <fr>La communauté internationale n'a <Alignment alignment="75" annotation_id="7440">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7440" sense="Comparison.Contrast">pourtant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pas ménagé ses efforts, refusant de reconnaître <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7497">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7503">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit bien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7515">d'un coup</DiscourseConnective> d'État <Alignment alignment="2023" annotation_id="7532">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7532" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7535">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est bien un gouvernement militaire qui a été mis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7590">en</DiscourseConnective> place par Andry Rajoelina <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7619">à</DiscourseConnective> Madagascar.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7172" docOffset="49">
      <en>Madagascar has been suspended from the African Union and the Southern Africa Development Community.</en>
      <fr>Madagascar a été suspendue de l'Union africaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7681">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Communauté de développement d'Afrique australe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7272" docOffset="50">
      <en>Since 2 February 2009, numerous attempts have been made, including by the UN and the EU, resulting in the Maputo and Addis Ababa agreements.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7738">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> le 2 février 2009, de nombreuses tentatives ont été faites, y compris par l'ONU <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7825">et même</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne, et c'est ce qui a donné lieu aux accords de Maputo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7904">et</DiscourseConnective> d'Addis-Abeba.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7413" docOffset="51">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="31052" annotation_id="7413">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7413" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, since November 2009, these agreements seem to have become mired down as a result of the divisions between the various protagonists and the refusal by some of them to participate in the implementation of these agreements.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1922" annotation_id="7922">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7922" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7928">depuis</DiscourseConnective> novembre 2009, ces accords semblent s'enliser du fait des divisions entre les différents protagonistes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8038">et</DiscourseConnective> du refus de certains d'entre eux de participer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8088">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en œuvre de ces accords.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7643" docOffset="52">
      <en>We in the Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left consider that it is time to let the Malagasy people speak <Alignment alignment="12801" annotation_id="7776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7776" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that it is high time that democratic rules were respected.</en>
      <fr>Au groupe GUE/NGL, nous considérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8159">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est temps de redonner la parole aux Malgaches <Alignment alignment="7776" annotation_id="8211">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8211" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8214">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il est grand temps de respecter les règles démocratiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7839" docOffset="53">
      <en>Andry Rajoelina, the strongman of the regime, prefers to organise his elections unilaterally, without consulting the Malagasy people, in defiance of the aforementioned agreements.</en>
      <fr>M. Andry Rajoelina, l'homme fort du régime, préfère organiser des élections de façon unilatérale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8372">sans</DiscourseConnective> consultation du peuple malgache, au mépris des accords précédemment cités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8019" docOffset="54">
      <en>He unilaterally set an initial date for so-called democratic elections in March 2010, but now appears to be talking about a date somewhere between the end of March and the end of 2010.</en>
      <fr>Il a fixé unilatéralement une date <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8487">pour</DiscourseConnective> de soi-disant élections démocratiques, tout d'abord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8544">en</DiscourseConnective> mars 2010, et il semble aujourd'hui qu'il parle d'une date non déterminée entre la fin mars <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8639">et</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'année 2010.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8204" docOffset="55">
      <en>That is why we want humanitarian aid to be strengthened, for judicial proceedings to be instituted <Alignment alignment="24701" annotation_id="8303">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8303" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> for the European Union to throw all its weight behind ensuring that civil society is involved in the steps taken.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8666">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous souhaitons que l'aide humanitaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8720">soit</DiscourseConnective> renforcée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8736">que</DiscourseConnective> des poursuites judiciaires soient engagées <Alignment alignment="8303" annotation_id="8783">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8783" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8786">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne pèse de tout son poids <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8832">pour que</DiscourseConnective> la société civile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8859">soit</DiscourseConnective> associée aux démarches entreprises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8421" id="221" name="Charles Tannock">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8421" docOffset="56">
      <en>author. - Mr President, <Alignment alignment="32499" annotation_id="8445">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8445" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the African Union aspires to have anything like the authority and respect accorded to the EU in international affairs, then Madagascar is surely a case in which the AU should act decisively.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="8445" annotation_id="8938">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8938" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union africaine attend de l'Union européenne qu'elle lui confère respect <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9016">et</DiscourseConnective> autorité dans les affaires internationales, elle se doit impérativement d'agir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9098">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne Madagascar.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8639" docOffset="57">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2486" annotation_id="8639">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8639" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">Instead</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have seen the usual vacillation and tepid diplomacy following the fall of President Marc Ravalomanana, which is sadly reminiscent of the situation in Zimbabwe.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2402" annotation_id="9129">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9129" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">Au lieu de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela, la chute du président Marc Ravalomanana a été suivie d'un sentiment de déjà vu: une approche hésitante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9249">et</DiscourseConnective> une diplomatie timide qui évoquent tristement la situation du Zimbabwe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8810" docOffset="58">
      <en>It is time for the African Union to accept its responsibilities with regard to Madagascar, where political tension and chaos have been endemic for some time.</en>
      <fr>L'Union africaine doit désormais assumer ses responsabilités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9385">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard de Madagascar, en proie aux tensions politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9443">et</DiscourseConnective> au chaos <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9455">depuis</DiscourseConnective> quelques temps.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8968" docOffset="59">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="33477" annotation_id="8968">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8968" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the AU cannot bring itself to sort out this mess, then it is reasonably fair to ask why the EU should do so.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3895" annotation_id="9478">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9478" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union africaine ne peut s'extirper elle-même de cette situation inextricable, on est en droit de se demander pourquoi l'Union européenne devrait agir de la sorte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9080" docOffset="60">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9646" annotation_id="9080">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9080" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we should continue to remain engaged with Madagascar in order to facilitate a smooth return to democratic government and to promote reconciliation.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9080" annotation_id="9646">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9646" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous devons poursuivre notre engagement auprès de Madagascar <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9718">afin de</DiscourseConnective> faciliter le retour en douceur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9757">à</DiscourseConnective> un gouvernement démocratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9788">et</DiscourseConnective> de promouvoir la réconciliation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9237" docOffset="61">
      <en>It is vital that those politicians and military officers who have been cited and carried out human rights abuses should be brought to justice.</en>
      <fr>Il est impératif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9841">que</DiscourseConnective> les responsables politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9873">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires précités, coupables de violations des droits de l'homme, soient traduits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9960">en</DiscourseConnective> justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9380" docOffset="62">
      <en>Targeted sanctions against the illegitimate regime of Andry Rajoelina <Alignment alignment="10061" annotation_id="9450">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9450" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> offer an effective way to punish those who perpetrate the ongoing instability without harming the overwhelming majority of the Malagasy people, who must be heartedly sick of the tensions and sporadic violence in their beautiful country.</en>
      <fr>L'adoption de sanctions ciblées contre le régime illégitime d'Andry Rajoelina représente <Alignment alignment="2822" annotation_id="10061">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10061" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une solution efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10093">pour</DiscourseConnective> punir ceux qui entretiennent l'instabilité actuelle, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10151">sans</DiscourseConnective> porter préjudice à grande majorité de la population locale, laquelle doit être fortement touchée par les tensions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10270">et</DiscourseConnective> les violences sporadiques qui frappent son beau pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9692" id="222" language="RO" name="Cristian Dan Preda">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9692" docOffset="63">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6908" annotation_id="9692">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9692" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> has already been emphasised, the state of uncertainty and political instability reigning in Madagascar has been going on for well over a year.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8561" annotation_id="10327">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10327" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10340">déjà</DiscourseConnective> été souligné, Madagascar vit dans un climat d'incertitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10403">et</DiscourseConnective> d'instabilité politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10430">depuis</DiscourseConnective> bien plus d'un an.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9838" docOffset="64">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="10839" annotation_id="9838">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9838" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there have been some glimmers of hope at times during the negotiation process, the actions being taken by Andry Rajoelina only serve to hamper the process, complicating the restoration of constitutional order.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11529" annotation_id="10456">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10456" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le processus de négociation a fait naître quelques lueurs d'espoir ponctuelles, les actions entreprises par Andry Rajoelina visent uniquement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10601">à</DiscourseConnective> freiner le processus pour retarder la restauration de l'ordre constitutionnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10054" docOffset="65">
      <en>I am referring here to the removal of the prime minister appointed after the Maputo Accords, the withdrawal from the negotiation process with the political groupings and the recent decision to hastily organise elections without taking into account previous agreements.</en>
      <fr>Je fais référence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10700">à</DiscourseConnective> la destitution du Premier ministre désigné au lendemain des accords de Maputo, au retrait du processus de négociation avec les groupes politiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10848">et</DiscourseConnective> à la décision récente d'organiser des élections à la hâte en faisant fi des accords passés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10942">auparavant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10323" docOffset="66">
      <en>I believe that this is an attempt to create a veneer of legality and legitimise a regime which has come to power following a coup d'état, which Rajoelina cannot deny.</en>
      <fr>Selon moi, cette démarche vise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10985">à</DiscourseConnective> installer un semblant de légalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11021">et</DiscourseConnective> à légitimer un régime qui doit son accès au pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11076">à</DiscourseConnective> un coup d'état, ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11097">que</DiscourseConnective> Rajoelina ne peut nier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10490" docOffset="67">
      <en>It is obvious that the only way of ensuring that constitutional order is restored is to fully enforce the Maputo and Addis Ababa Accords.</en>
      <fr>De toute évidence, la restauration de l'ordre constitutionnel passe impérativement par la mise en œuvre complète des accords de Maputo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11260">et</DiscourseConnective> d'Addis-Abeba.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10628" id="223" name="Martin Kastler">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10628" docOffset="68">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, I would just like to draw your attention to the fact that all the groups have endorsed this motion for a resolution.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, je tiens juste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11321">à</DiscourseConnective> attirer votre attention sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11359">que</DiscourseConnective> tous les groupes ont soutenu cette proposition de résolution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10764" docOffset="69">
      <en>That is <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10772" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> it should be, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10789" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> this topic is very important.</en>
      <fr>Il ne pourrait en être autrement, vu l'importance capitale de cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10827" docOffset="70">
      <en>In contrast to the previous speakers, I would like to say that we must ensure that we do not merely promote freedom of expression and freedom of the press in this country, <Alignment alignment="11670" annotation_id="10999">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10999" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that we <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11011" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> actively demand them, <Alignment alignment="33427" annotation_id="11038">
          <Alignment alignment="11826" annotation_id="11038">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11038" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">now that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> we are examining ways that we could help things proceed towards a, hopefully, peaceful election.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11503">Au contraire</DiscourseConnective> des précédents orateurs, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11550">à</DiscourseConnective> souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11562">que</DiscourseConnective> nous ne devons pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11585">simplement</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir la liberté d'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11631">et</DiscourseConnective> la liberté des médias dans ce pays, <Alignment alignment="10999" annotation_id="11670">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11670" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> devons les requérir activement, <Alignment alignment="13007" annotation_id="11707">
          <Alignment alignment="11038" annotation_id="11707">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11707" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">à l'heure où</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> nous étudions les possibilités d'aboutir, espérons-le, à une élection pacifique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11144" docOffset="71">
      <en>We have to ensure that we, as Europeans, establish freedom of the press in all areas, with all the financial assistance that is needed to make that possible.</en>
      <fr>Nous, Européens, devons faire en sorte d'établir la liberté des médias dans tous les domaines en apportant toutes les ressources financières requises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11951">à</DiscourseConnective> cette fin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11302" docOffset="72">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="11964" annotation_id="11305">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11305" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have to provide full support and endeavour to act together to provide financial assistance, within the scope of the agreements which we have with this country.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11305" annotation_id="11964">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11964" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De même</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous devons faire preuve d'un soutien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12011">total</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12017">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une volonté d'agir ensemble afin d'apporter une aide financière, conformément aux accords passés avec ce pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11470" id="224" name="Eija-Riitta Korhola">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11470" docOffset="73">
      <en>(FI) Mr President, it is intolerable to follow the situation in Madagascar, where power is in the hands of a person who took over the country using violent means and who rules it in the same brutal manner, and whose position the international community has not recognised.</en>
      <fr>(FI) Monsieur le Président, nous ne pouvons tolérer la situation de Madagascar, où le pouvoir repose entre les mains d'une personne qui a pris le pays par la violence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12300">et</DiscourseConnective> le dirige avec la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12321">même</DiscourseConnective> brutalité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12337">et</DiscourseConnective> dont la position n'est pas reconnue par la communauté internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11743" docOffset="74">
      <en>That is why I am using the word 'person' and not 'president'.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12410">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> j'utilise le terme "personne" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12455">et</DiscourseConnective> non "président".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11805" docOffset="75">
      <en>The majority of the population in Madagascar live below the poverty line: 7 000 children are suffering from serious malnutrition, <Alignment alignment="1424" annotation_id="11935">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11935" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the situation is only worsening with the political crisis.</en>
      <fr>La majorité de la population de Madagascar vit sous le seuil de pauvreté: 7 000 enfants souffrent de malnutrition grave, <Alignment alignment="2143" annotation_id="12596">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12596" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la situation empire sous l'effet de la crise politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11998" docOffset="76">
      <en>For that reason, it is important that we, along with the rest of the international community, increase the amount of humanitarian aid to Madagascar.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12666">donc</DiscourseConnective>, de concert avec le reste de la communauté internationale, d'intensifier l'aide humanitaire en faveur de Madagascar.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12147" docOffset="77">
      <en>It is, <Alignment alignment="28060" annotation_id="12154">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12154" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, vitally important to investigate and solve the political murders that have taken place, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12255" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> that must be left to an independent, impartial agency.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12154" annotation_id="12788">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12788" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">De plus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il est absolument essentiel d'enquêter sur les crimes politiques perpétrés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12872">et</DiscourseConnective> de les élucider. Cette mission doit être confiée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12924">à</DiscourseConnective> une agence indépendante impartiale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12314" docOffset="78">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="30302" annotation_id="12314">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12314" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Unless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that happens, it will be difficult to build trust and take steps towards democracy.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12314" annotation_id="12962">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12962" sense="Expansion.Alternative">Sans</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> quoi, il sera difficile d'instaurer la confiance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13016">et</DiscourseConnective> de progresser vers la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12405" docOffset="79">
      <en>It must be a priority that Madagascar's four political factions can sit down at the negotiating table to agree on what to do to enable democratic elections to take place this year.</en>
      <fr>La réunion des quatre factions politiques de Madagascar autour de la table des négociations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13145">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> la tenue d'élections démocratiques cette année doit être une priorité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12586" docOffset="80">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="28251" annotation_id="12592">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12592" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> crucial that Madagascar does not conclude agreements on natural resources <Alignment alignment="15513" annotation_id="12671">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12671" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it has a government with a mandate from the people.</en>
      <fr>Il importe <Alignment alignment="818" annotation_id="13237">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13237" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13247">que</DiscourseConnective> Madagascar ne conclue aucun accord sur les ressources naturelles <Alignment alignment="12671" annotation_id="13316">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13316" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> disposer d'un gouvernement élu par le peuple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12730" id="225" name="Michael Gahler">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12730" docOffset="81">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, on the subject of Madagascar, it is good that we can report that it is not just the European Union that is concerned about this country's compliance with Article 96 of The Cotonou Agreement, <Alignment alignment="13578" annotation_id="12940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12940" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the African Union and SADC, as regional organisations, have <Alignment alignment="22848" annotation_id="13009">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13009" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> taken the position that another coup d'état in Africa is unacceptable.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13399">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne Madagascar, il convient d'observer que l'Union européenne n'est pas la seule <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13495">à</DiscourseConnective> se soucier de la conformité de ce pays avec l'article 96 de l'accord de Cotonou, <Alignment alignment="12940" annotation_id="13578">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13578" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13583">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union africaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13605">et</DiscourseConnective> la SADC, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13617">au même titre que</DiscourseConnective> des organisations régionales, ont <Alignment alignment="13009" annotation_id="13669">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13669" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> affirmé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13687">que</DiscourseConnective> tout autre coup d'état <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13714">en</DiscourseConnective> Afrique serait inacceptable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13085" docOffset="82">
      <en>For the African Union and for the regional organisations, it is a relatively new thing, not only to make these kinds of decisions, but also to implement them and to take action.</en>
      <fr>Le fait de prendre ce genre de décisions, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13788">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> de les mettre en œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13822">et</DiscourseConnective> d'agir, est relativement inédit pour l'Union africaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13880">et</DiscourseConnective> les organisations régionales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13263" docOffset="83">
      <en>I hope that <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13275" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> the International Contact Group meets again in Addis Ababa, a week today, on 18 February, all the participating parties will fulfil their tasks and powers, and ensure that any agreement reached in Maputo is <Alignment alignment="13515" annotation_id="13487">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13487" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> implemented.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13922">que</DiscourseConnective> le Groupe de contact international se réunira à nouveau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13982">à</DiscourseConnective> Addis-Abeba dans une semaine, le 18 février, que toutes les parties prenantes seront à la hauteur de leurs missions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14100">et</DiscourseConnective> de leurs pouvoirs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14122">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'elles veilleront <Alignment alignment="13487" annotation_id="14145">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14145" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à la mise en œuvre de l'accord convenu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14194">à</DiscourseConnective> Maputo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13505" docOffset="84">
      <en>That is my appeal to all the participants.</en>
      <fr>Tel est l'appel que je lance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14233">à</DiscourseConnective> tous les participants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13548" id="226" language="FR" name="Viviane Reding">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13548" docOffset="85">
      <en>Mr President, may I start by highlighting our very great concern about the obstacles which are preventing the Maputo agreements from being implemented.</en>
      <fr>vice-présidente de la Commission. - Monsieur le Président, laissez-moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14329">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> souligner notre grande préoccupation au sujet des blocages qui empêchent la mise en œuvre des accords de Maputo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13700" docOffset="86">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="14455" annotation_id="13700">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13700" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the crisis started <Alignment alignment="14135" annotation_id="13725">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13725" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="19532" annotation_id="13729">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13729" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> consultations with Madagascar were opened under Article 96 of the Cotonou Agreement, the Commission has actively supported mediation efforts by the international community, which have translated into considerable progress <Alignment alignment="14728" annotation_id="13957">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13957" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which, unfortunately, have still not resulted in an effective transition process.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13700" annotation_id="14455">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14455" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Depuis</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le début de la crise <Alignment alignment="13725" annotation_id="14483">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14483" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="13729" annotation_id="14486">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14486" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">depuis</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'ouverture des consultations avec Madagascar en vertu de l'article 96 de l'accord de Cotonou, la Commission a soutenu activement les efforts de médiation de la communauté internationale, qui se sont traduits par des avancées notables <Alignment alignment="13957" annotation_id="14728">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14728" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14738">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, n'ont pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14765">encore</DiscourseConnective> abouti <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14779">à</DiscourseConnective> un processus de transition effectif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14043" docOffset="87">
      <en>We are very worried <Alignment alignment="14844" annotation_id="14063">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14063" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, rather than making progress, we are slipping backwards <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14127" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> there is a clear risk of returning to where we started in March 2009.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes très inquiets <Alignment alignment="3023" annotation_id="14844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14844" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ici, on n'avance pas, on recule, avec un risque manifeste de retour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14916">à</DiscourseConnective> la case départ de mars 2009.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14201" docOffset="88">
      <en>You will agree that this may of course result in a deterioration in the political and human rights situation and in clashes between Malagasies.</en>
      <fr>Vous conviendrez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14964">que</DiscourseConnective> cela peut forcément entraîner une aggravation de la situation politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15040">et</DiscourseConnective> des droits de l'homme, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15066">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que des affrontements entre Malgaches.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14345" docOffset="89">
      <en>We have clearly indicated, on numerous occasions, that we reject any unilateral process which results in hastily organised elections that will not bring about a lasting solution to the crisis.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons clairement indiqué, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15142">à</DiscourseConnective> maintes reprises, notre rejet de tout processus unilatéral débouchant sur des élections organisées à la hâte et n'apportant aucune solution durable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15292">à</DiscourseConnective> la crise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14538" docOffset="90">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9152" annotation_id="14538">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14538" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, to reply to the question raised by the honourable Member, I would note that we are not prepared to support such a process either politically or financially.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14538" annotation_id="15304">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15304" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15310">pour</DiscourseConnective> répondre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15324">à</DiscourseConnective> la question de l'honorable parlementaire, j'indiquerai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15381">que</DiscourseConnective> nous ne sommes pas prêts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15410">à</DiscourseConnective> accompagner, ni politiquement ni même financièrement, un tel processus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14706" docOffset="91">
      <en>The initiative currently being taken by the President of the African Union Commission is our last hope.</en>
      <fr>L'initiative prise actuellement par le président de la Commission de l'Union africaine nous laisse un dernier espoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14810" docOffset="92">
      <en>We are prepared to evaluate, together with the international community within an international contact group, the response of Malagasy movements and, depending on the situation, to present proposals for decisions to the Council under Article 96 of the Cotonou Agreement.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes prêts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15620">à</DiscourseConnective> évaluer, conjointement avec la communauté internationale au sein du groupe de contact international, la réponse des mouvances malgaches <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15758">et</DiscourseConnective>, en fonction de la situation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15791">à</DiscourseConnective> présenter des propositions de décision au Conseil au titre de l'article 96 de l'accord de Cotonou.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15081" docOffset="93">
      <en>In the event of a negative decision, this should not affect projects which directly benefit the population <Alignment alignment="16015" annotation_id="15188">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15188" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we shall continue and, <Alignment alignment="16275" annotation_id="15215">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15215" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> necessary, increase humanitarian aid for the vulnerable populations.</en>
      <fr>Dans le cas d'une décision négative, celle-ci ne devrait pas affecter les projets bénéficiant directement à la population, <Alignment alignment="5663" annotation_id="16015">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16015" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous poursuivrons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16036">et</DiscourseConnective> accroîtrons, <Alignment alignment="3336" annotation_id="16052">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16052" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nécessaire, l'aide humanitaire en faveur des populations vulnérables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15287" docOffset="94">
      <en>Finally, may I assure you, Mr President, of the Commission's active, patient and persevering commitment to finding an amicable way out of the crisis.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16137">finalement</DiscourseConnective> vous assurer, Monsieur le Président, de l'engagement actif, patient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16216">et</DiscourseConnective> persévérant de la Commission dans la recherche d'une solution consensuelle de sortie de crise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15437" id="227" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15437" docOffset="95">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15459" docOffset="96">
      <en>The vote will take place at the end of the debate.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16351">à</DiscourseConnective> la fin des débats.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
