<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>36.</en>
    <fr>36.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Consequences of the entry into force of the Treaty of Lisbon for ongoing interinstitutional decision-making procedures (</en>
    <fr>Conséquences de l'entrée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur du traité de Lisbonne sur les procédures décisionnelles interinstitutionnelles en cours (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="125" id="060" name="Takis Hatzigeorgiou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="125" docOffset="2">
      <en>(EL) Just a couple of seconds to explain the withdrawal of our amendment: we have withdrawn our amendment in the absolute and firm conviction that the Conference of Presidents, which is to examine the issue, will take very serious account of the spirit and letter of our amendment.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Laissez-moi quelques secondes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="165">pour</DiscourseConnective> expliquer le retrait de notre amendement: nous avons retiré notre amendement parce que nous sommes fermement convaincus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="290">que</DiscourseConnective> la Conférence des présidents, qui doit examiner la question, tiendra compte avec beaucoup de sérieux de l'esprit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="407">et</DiscourseConnective> de la lettre de notre amendement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="407" docOffset="3">
      <en>I would remind the House that we call in our amendment for the Commission to examine the change to the regulation on direct trade between the European Union and areas of Cyprus which are not under the control of the Republic of Cyprus.</en>
      <fr>Je rappelle à l'Assemblée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="470">que</DiscourseConnective> nous retirons notre amendement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="505">pour que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission examine les modifications apportées au règlement sur le commerce direct entre l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="625">et</DiscourseConnective> les zones de Chypre qui ne sont pas sous le contrôle de la République de Chypre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
