<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>3.</en>
    <fr>3.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>EC-West African Economic and Monetary Union air services agreement (</en>
    <fr>Accord CE/Union Économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30">et</DiscourseConnective> Monétaire Ouest Africaine: services aériens (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="72" docOffset="2">
    <en>Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>
      <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="79">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="89" id="131" name="Dieter-Lebrecht Koch">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="89" docOffset="3">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, by adopting my report, we will be voting for an agreement which will manage to bring about the approximation of the laws under 47 existing bilateral air services agreements concluded between the individual Member States of the EU and the individual countries of the West African Economic and Monetary Union.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="130">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="144">en</DiscourseConnective> adoptant mon rapport, nous voterons en faveur d'un accord qui adaptera les lois relevant des 47 accords bilatéraux existants relatifs aux accords de services aériens conclus entre les différents États membres de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="364">et</DiscourseConnective> les différents pays de l'Union économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="409">et</DiscourseConnective> monétaire ouest-africaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="438" docOffset="4">
      <en>In so doing, we are ensuring the application of applicable EU law, preventing discrimination and barriers to market access and cutting red tape.</en>
      <fr>Nous garantirons ainsi l'application de la législation européenne applicable, en évitant toute discrimination, en levant les obstacles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="574">à</DiscourseConnective> l'accès au marché <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="594">et</DiscourseConnective> en réduisant les lourdeurs administratives.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="583" docOffset="5">
      <en>Please vote 'yes'!</en>
      <fr>Je vous prie donc de voter "oui"!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
