<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>One-minute speeches (Rule 150)</en>
    <fr>Interventions d'une minute (article 150 du règlement)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="31" id="203" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="31" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle les interventions d'une minute sur des questions politiques importantes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="108" id="204" name="Czesław Adam Siekierski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="108" docOffset="2">
      <en>(PL) Madam President, today is the 61st anniversary of Schuman's declaration.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Madame la Présidente, c'est aujourd'hui le 61e anniversaire de la déclaration de Schuman.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="186" docOffset="3">
      <en>Many official celebrations, festivals and parades are taking place to commemorate the anniversary.</en>
      <fr>Des célébrations, festivals <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="274">et</DiscourseConnective> parades à caractère officiel ont lieu en grand nombre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="331">pour</DiscourseConnective> commémorer cet anniversaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="285" docOffset="4">
      <en>Do not let the celebratory mood blind us to the problems with which the EU is currently wrestling.</en>
      <fr>Ne laissons pas cette ambiance festive masquer les problèmes auxquels l'UE est actuellement confrontée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="384" docOffset="5">
      <en>Firstly, we must reply to the question whether the national self-interest which has appeared in the negotiations over the next financial perspective is in accordance with the calls for solidarity of our founding fathers?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="469">Tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective>, nous devons répondre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="504">à</DiscourseConnective> la question de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="528">si</DiscourseConnective> l'intérêt national qui s'est manifesté dans le cadre des négociations sur la prochaine perspective financière est conforme aux appels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="665">à</DiscourseConnective> la solidarité lancés par nos pères fondateurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="605" docOffset="6">
      <en>Secondly, are initiatives which reverse European integration, such as the latest initiative to restrict the Schengen area, compatible with the spirit of Europe?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="714">Ensuite</DiscourseConnective>, les initiatives contraires à l'intégration européenne, telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="785">que</DiscourseConnective> la dernière initiative visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="819">à</DiscourseConnective> limiter l'espace Schengen, sont-elles compatibles avec l'esprit européen?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="766" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="27390" annotation_id="766">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="766" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Finally</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, does the current crisis in the euro area and the lack of solidarity of Member States in tackling it present a threat to the success of this ambitious project?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="168" annotation_id="895">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="895" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la crise actuelle de la zone euro <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="936">et</DiscourseConnective> le manque de solidarité des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="981">pour</DiscourseConnective> y remédier compromettent-ils la réussite de ce projet ambitieux?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="934" docOffset="8">
      <en>Unfortunately, there are many more examples pointing to a crisis in European integration.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1051">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, bien d'autres d'exemples indiquent une crise de l'intégration européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1024" docOffset="9">
      <en>On this anniversary, let us take the opportunity to reflect seriously on what to do to stop these detrimental tendencies, and to return to proper, dynamic integration in the future.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1142">À</DiscourseConnective> l'occasion de cet anniversaire, profitons-en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1189">pour</DiscourseConnective> réfléchir sérieusement sur ce qu'il convient de faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1248">pour</DiscourseConnective> mettre un terme à ces dangereuses tendances, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1298">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1301">pour</DiscourseConnective> renouer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1314">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir avec une intégration adéquate et dynamique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1206" docOffset="10">
      <en>Let us renew the spirit of Europe according to the ideas of Robert Schuman, <Alignment alignment="17673" annotation_id="1282">
          <Alignment alignment="20119" annotation_id="1282">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1282" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the successes we have had so far in our common project do not fall by the wayside.</en>
      <fr>Renouvelons l'esprit européen conformément aux idées de Robert Schuman, <Alignment alignment="5682" annotation_id="1441">
          <Alignment alignment="14869" annotation_id="1441">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1441" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">pour que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> les succès que notre projet commun a connus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1494">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> présent ne soient pas vains.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1373" id="205" name="Csaba Sándor Tabajdi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1373" docOffset="11">
      <en>(HU) Madam President, on Europe Day, I would like to speak about the Community idea.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Madame la Présidente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1558">en</DiscourseConnective> cette Journée de l'Europe, je voudrais évoquer l'idée communautaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1458" docOffset="12">
      <en>The legislative package on economic governance represents a new chapter in the life of the Union.</en>
      <fr>Le paquet législatif de gouvernance économique représente un nouveau chapitre dans la vie de l'Union.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1556" docOffset="13">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1732" annotation_id="1556">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1556" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> observed and enforced, the new system of economic policy governance might finally encourage the Member States of the European Union to establish responsible economic policies.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="20581" annotation_id="1732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1732" sense="Contingency.Condition">S'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il est respecté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1750">et</DiscourseConnective> appliqué, le nouveau système de politique économique pourrait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1815">finalement</DiscourseConnective> encourager les États membres de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1877">à</DiscourseConnective> instaurer des politiques économiques responsables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1735" docOffset="14">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="32015" annotation_id="1735">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1735" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this is only one of the conditions of stability of Europe.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11983" annotation_id="1930">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1930" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ce n'est là <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1953">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une des conditions nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1987">à</DiscourseConnective> la stabilité de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1803" docOffset="15">
      <en>The democratic regression recently seen in several Member States is a disturbing phenomenon.</en>
      <fr>La régression démocratique observée récemment dans plusieurs États membres est un phénomène perturbant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1896" docOffset="16">
      <en>The governments of certain Member States have crossed the boundaries of the rule of law, which were previously considered to be inviolable; they are restricting the freedom of the press, which is essential for the implementation of real democracy.</en>
      <fr>Les gouvernements de certains d'entre eux ont transgressé l'état de droit, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2194">auparavant</DiscourseConnective> considéré comme inviolable; ils limitent la liberté de la presse, essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2283">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place d'une véritable démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2144" docOffset="17">
      <en>The European Commission and the Council should openly combat democratic regression; <Alignment alignment="29506" annotation_id="2228">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2228" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commission and the Council do not take action against the democratic deficit in the Union, it will result in severe problems.</en>
      <fr>La Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2355">et</DiscourseConnective> le Conseil devraient ouvertement lutter contre la régression démocratique; <Alignment alignment="5341" annotation_id="2433">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2433" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils ne prennent pas des mesures contre le déficit démocratique dans l'Union, de graves problèmes surgiront.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2361" docOffset="18">
      <en>Thank you for your attention.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie de votre attention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2391" id="206" name="Filiz Hakaeva Hyusmenova">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2391" docOffset="19">
      <en>(FR) Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, EUR 976 billion have been allocated by the European Union for the period 2007-2013.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, chers collègues, 976 milliards d'euros sont attribués par l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2679">pour</DiscourseConnective> la période 2007-2013.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2519" docOffset="20">
      <en>A large proportion of that amount has been awarded to programmes for which subsidies need to be requested from the European Commission.</en>
      <fr>Une grande partie de ce montant est affectée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2751">à</DiscourseConnective> des programmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2768">pour</DiscourseConnective> lesquels il faut demander des subventions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2815">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2655" docOffset="21">
      <en>A Bulgarian study has shown that the funding for the majority of the approved projects has gone to three or four European countries, with very few of the others participating.</en>
      <fr>Une étude bulgare a montré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2870">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2875">pour</DiscourseConnective> la plupart des projets approuvés, les bénéficiaires sont trois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2943">à</DiscourseConnective> quatre pays européens, avec une très faible participation des autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2831" docOffset="22">
      <en>Unfortunately, the Commission does not have a summary of these findings and their causes, or of the added value of these programmes, <Alignment alignment="55846" annotation_id="2964">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2964" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I fear that this will not be taken into account in the next financial framework.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3015">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, la Commission ne dispose pas d'une synthèse de ces faits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3089">et</DiscourseConnective> de leurs causes, ni de la valeur ajoutée de ces programmes, <Alignment alignment="16045" annotation_id="3152">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3152" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je crains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3165">que</DiscourseConnective> cela ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3177">soit</DiscourseConnective> pas pris en compte dans le prochain cadre financier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3049" docOffset="23">
      <en>The Commission pledged to apply the principles of transparency and equal treatment in these programmes.</en>
      <fr>La Commission s'est engagée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3263">à</DiscourseConnective> appliquer dans ces programmes les principes de transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3325">et</DiscourseConnective> d'égalité de traitement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3153" docOffset="24">
      <en>That <Alignment alignment="3367" annotation_id="3158">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3158" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> means doing more to promote opportunities and ensuring fairer access to information.</en>
      <fr>Cela signifie <Alignment alignment="3158" annotation_id="3367">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3367" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une plus grande promotion des opportunités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3420">et</DiscourseConnective> une plus grande égalité dans l'accès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3460">à</DiscourseConnective> l'information.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3248" docOffset="25">
      <en>I am convinced that the Commission should take steps to promote programmes among interested Europeans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3350" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">while</DiscourseConnective> catering for the needs of beneficiaries from new acceding countries.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3496">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission devrait prendre des mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3542">pour</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir des programmes parmi les Européens intéressés en tenant compte des besoins des bénéficiaires en provenance de nouveaux pays adhérents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3425" id="207" name="Marina Yannakoudakis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3425" docOffset="26">
      <en>Madam President, last week, I met a man in my local church who was arranging his son's memorial service. His 37-year old son had died the previous year of cancer.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, la semaine dernière, j'ai rencontré un homme, dans l'église de mon quartier, qui organisait une messe commémorative à la mémoire de son fils, âgé de 37 ans et décédé l'année dernière d'un cancer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3588" docOffset="27">
      <en>No parent should have to go through the pain of losing a child.</en>
      <fr>Aucun parent ne devrait connaître la douleur de perdre un enfant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3652" docOffset="28">
      <en>As a mother, I can think of nothing worse.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3985">tant que</DiscourseConnective> mère, je ne peux rien imaginer de pire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3695" docOffset="29">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1760" annotation_id="3695">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3695" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have over 2 000 parents, brothers, mothers and sisters in Cyprus who are suffering every day <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3795" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> they wonder about the fate of their loved one.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="25222" annotation_id="4034">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4034" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4040">à</DiscourseConnective> Chypre, plus de 2 000 parents, frères, mères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4087">et</DiscourseConnective> sœurs souffrent chaque jour en se demandant ce qu'il advient de leurs proches.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3845" docOffset="30">
      <en>In 1963-64, civil unrest, and the subsequent Turkish invasion and occupation of Cyprus in 1974, resulted in approximately 2 000 Turkish as well as Greek Cypriots going missing.</en>
      <fr>Les troubles civils de 1963-1964 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4202">et</DiscourseConnective> l'invasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4216">et</DiscourseConnective> l'occupation de Chypre par la Turquie en 1974 ont causé la disparition d'environ 2 000 Chypriotes turcs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4323">et</DiscourseConnective> grecs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4022" docOffset="31">
      <en>Their fate is unknown, <Alignment alignment="30681" annotation_id="4045">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4045" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in 1981, the Committee on Missing Persons was set up and funded primarily by the EU.</en>
      <fr>On ignore leur sort, <Alignment alignment="12829" annotation_id="4354">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4354" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4357">en</DiscourseConnective> 1981, le Comité des personnes disparues a été créé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4411">et</DiscourseConnective> financé essentiellement par l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4134" docOffset="32">
      <en>The work they have done in this area has brought peace to many families.</en>
      <fr>Le travail qu'il a accompli dans ce domaine a apporté la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4510">à</DiscourseConnective> de nombreuses familles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4207" docOffset="33">
      <en>There is much more work for them to do, with over one and a half thousand people still missing.</en>
      <fr>Il lui reste encore beaucoup <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4565">à</DiscourseConnective> faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4573">puisque</DiscourseConnective> plus de 1 500 personnes sont toujours portées disparues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4303" docOffset="34">
      <en>I urge this House to support the work of the CMP, and to support Written Declaration 10 which is humanitarian in its objectives and seeks to bring peace and remembrance and reconciliation to these families.</en>
      <fr>Je prie instamment cette Assemblée de soutenir le travail du CPD, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4704">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la déclaration écrite 10 dont les objectifs sont humanitaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4776">et</DiscourseConnective> qui cherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4791">à</DiscourseConnective> apporter la paix, le souvenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4823">et</DiscourseConnective> la réconciliation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4844">à</DiscourseConnective> ces familles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4510" id="208" name="Michail Tremopoulos">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4510" docOffset="35">
      <en>(EL) Madam President, today is Europe Day <Alignment alignment="32937" annotation_id="4552">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4552" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it reminds us of the objectives on which the European Union must be based: a deepening of the European institutions and a common economic policy which, in our opinion, will set socially fair prosperity and viability as its priorities.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Madame la Présidente, c'est aujourd'hui la Journée de l'Europe <Alignment alignment="2479" annotation_id="4928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4928" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle nous rappelle les objectifs sur lesquels l'Union européenne doit se fonder: un approfondissement des institutions européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5062">et</DiscourseConnective> une politique économique commune dont les priorités seront, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5125">à</DiscourseConnective> notre avis, une prospérité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5154">et</DiscourseConnective> une durabilité bénéfiques d'un point de vue social.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4791" docOffset="36">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="48646" annotation_id="4791">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4791" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the agreement on the euro is fundamentally a move in the wrong direction, <Alignment alignment="5299" annotation_id="4874">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4874" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it does no more than impose the traditional economic orthodoxy.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6747" annotation_id="5209">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5209" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le pacte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5229">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'euro constitue foncièrement un pas dans la mauvaise direction, <Alignment alignment="22086" annotation_id="5299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5299" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il ne fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5317">qu'</DiscourseConnective>imposer la doctrine économique traditionnelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4941" docOffset="37">
      <en>Attempts to link the euro to constant cutbacks in the social state and constant pressure on wages and pensions in the long term risk eroding not only political cohesion, but also the European ideal.</en>
      <fr>Les tentatives d'associer l'euro <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5400">à</DiscourseConnective> de constantes réductions dans le système social <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5450">et</DiscourseConnective> à de constantes pressions sur les salaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5496">et</DiscourseConnective> les retraites risquent à long terme d'affaiblir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5547">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> la cohésion politique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5584">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5589">également</DiscourseConnective> l'idéal européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5140" docOffset="38">
      <en>In response to this, we Greens propose the agreement on viable prosperity: integrated fiscal convergence, a truly interventionist and ambitious European budget and mainstreaming of the social and environmental dimensions.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5617">Pour</DiscourseConnective> réagir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5629">à</DiscourseConnective> cela, nous les Verts proposons l'accord sur la prospérité durable: une convergence fiscale intégrée, un budget européen véritablement interventionniste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5783">et</DiscourseConnective> ambitieux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5796">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que l'intégration des dimensions sociale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5843">et</DiscourseConnective> environnementale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5362" docOffset="39">
      <en>That is why we want to pave the way to move in a different direction.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5864">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous voulons être les pionniers d'une nouvelle orientation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5432" docOffset="40">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="62357" annotation_id="5432">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5432" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, no one is entitled to take life-changing decisions without consulting the public.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5491" annotation_id="5939">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5939" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, personne n'a le droit de prendre des décisions aussi audacieuses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6015">sans</DiscourseConnective> interroger le public.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5523" docOffset="41">
      <en>The only solution is fundamental dialogue with and direct recourse to the public.</en>
      <fr>La seule solution consiste à mener un dialogue fondamental avec les citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6119">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6122">à</DiscourseConnective> les consulter directement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5605" docOffset="42">
      <en>The intransigence, in the past, of those who handled the European Constitution prevented us from institutionalising European referenda.</en>
      <fr>L'intransigeance dont ont fait preuve par le passé les responsables de la constitution européenne nous a empêchés d'institutionnaliser les référendums européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5741" docOffset="43">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="42100" annotation_id="5741">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5741" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we can find alternative solutions, provided that we have the political will.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5741" annotation_id="6313">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6313" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous pouvons trouver des alternatives, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6357">pour autant que</DiscourseConnective> nous en ayons la volonté politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5827" docOffset="44">
      <en>We owe it to Europe and its future.</en>
      <fr>Nous le devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6424">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6435">et</DiscourseConnective> à son avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5863" id="209" name="Georgios Toussas">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5863" docOffset="45">
      <en>(EL) Madam President, today is the 66th anniversary of the major anti-fascist grassroots victory on 9 May 1945, <Alignment alignment="6592" annotation_id="5975">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5975" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the fascist-imperialist axis between Germany, Japan and Italy and their allies was crushed.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Madame la Présidente, aujourd'hui nous célébrons le 66e anniversaire de la grande victoire populaire du 9 mai 1945 contre le fascisme, <Alignment alignment="5975" annotation_id="6592">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6592" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'axe fasciste-impérialiste entre l'Allemagne, le Japon, l'Italie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6666">et</DiscourseConnective> leurs alliés a été anéanti.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6072" docOffset="46">
      <en>We honour the dead, the tortured workers, men and women, who fought to crush fascism within the ranks of the communist parties, the national freedom fighters and the anti-fascist movements.</en>
      <fr>Nous rendons hommage aux morts, aux travailleurs torturés, hommes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6763">et</DiscourseConnective> femmes, qui ont combattu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6791">pour</DiscourseConnective> écraser le fascisme dans les rangs des partis communistes, les combattants pour la liberté nationale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6897">et</DiscourseConnective> les mouvements antifascistes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6262" docOffset="47">
      <en>The organising forces behind the major grassroots victory against the fascist-imperialist axis were the communist parties, with the heroic fight by the people of the Soviet Union altering the course of the war, at a cost of over 20 million dead, thousands injured, villages and towns destroyed and razed to the ground and the destruction of its economy.</en>
      <fr>Les forces à l'origine de la grande victoire populaire contre l'axe fasciste-impérialiste étaient les partis communistes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7052">et</DiscourseConnective> le peuple de l'Union soviétique qui s'est battu héroïquement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7116">et</DiscourseConnective> a changé le cours de la guerre, au prix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7159">de plus</DiscourseConnective> de vingt millions de morts, de milliers de blessés, de villages <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7231">et</DiscourseConnective> de villes entièrement rasés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7262">et</DiscourseConnective> de la destruction de son économie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6616" docOffset="48">
      <en>It is a brazen insult to the millions of dead and injured, the victims of fascist and Nazi bestiality in Greece and Europe as a whole, for the European Union to try and wipe out and falsify history: to turn 9 May from a day of anti-fascist grassroots victory into a vulgar celebration as Europe Day, a day which celebrates the European monopolies.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne insulte gravement les millions de morts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7359">et</DiscourseConnective> de blessés, les victimes de la bestialité fasciste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7413">et</DiscourseConnective> nazie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7422">en</DiscourseConnective> Grèce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7431">et</DiscourseConnective> dans toute l'Europe en tentant d'effacer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7475">et</DiscourseConnective> de déformer l'histoire et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7504">en</DiscourseConnective> faisant du 9 mai, journée de la victoire populaire contre le fascisme, la Journée de l'Europe, vulgaire célébration prônant les monopoles européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6964" docOffset="49">
      <en>Today, the working classes and the poor grassroots classes are again suffering one of the worst capitalist crises.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, les classes ouvrières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7691">et</DiscourseConnective> les classes populaires pauvres connaissent à nouveau l'une des pires crises capitalistes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7079" docOffset="50">
      <en>They face the biggest attack since the end of the Second World War ...</en>
      <fr>Elles sont confrontées à la plus grande attaque <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7832">depuis</DiscourseConnective> la fin de la Seconde Guerre mondiale...</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7150" docOffset="51">
      <en>(The President cut off the speaker)</en>
      <fr>(La Présidente retire la parole à l'orateur)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7186" id="210" name="Gerard Batten">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7186" docOffset="52">
      <en>Madam President, one of my constituents in London has informed me of serious allegations against a Mr Vladimir Perisic, <Alignment alignment="35972" annotation_id="7306">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7306" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> known as Dr Vladmir De Rothschild, who claims to be a medical doctor and a specialist surgeon.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, l'un de mes électeurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7973">à</DiscourseConnective> Londres m'a informé de graves allégations émises à l'encontre d'un certain M. Vladimir Perisic, <Alignment alignment="4693" annotation_id="8071">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8071" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> connu sous le nom de Dr Vladmir De Rothschild, affirmant être docteur en médecine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8163">et</DiscourseConnective> chirurgien spécialisé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7406" docOffset="53">
      <en>It is alleged that Mr Perisic is not medically qualified, is not registered with the General Medical Council, <Alignment alignment="53529" annotation_id="7516">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7516" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that he uses his spurious medical credentials to defraud vulnerable people.</en>
      <fr>On prétend <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8200">que</DiscourseConnective> M. Perisic n'a aucune compétence médicale, qu'il n'est pas inscrit au Conseil général de la médecine, <Alignment alignment="7516" annotation_id="8306">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8306" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8309">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il utilise de fausses références médicales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8355">pour</DiscourseConnective> escroquer des personnes vulnérables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7596" docOffset="54">
      <en>He allegedly claims to have met David Cameron and persuaded the Department of Health to consider his proposal for an NHS voucher scheme.</en>
      <fr>Il affirme avoir soi-disant rencontré David Cameron <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8449">et</DiscourseConnective> persuadé le Département de la santé d'examiner sa proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8514">pour</DiscourseConnective> un régime d'attestation du système de soins de santé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7733" docOffset="55">
      <en>As a result of this, an article featuring him recently appeared, in good faith, in a national Sunday newspaper.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8573">À</DiscourseConnective> la suite de cela, un article le concernant a été récemment publié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8641">en</DiscourseConnective> toute bonne foi dans un journal national du dimanche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7845" docOffset="56">
      <en>This could give him further spurious legitimacy to dupe those in need of serious medical care.</en>
      <fr>Cette publication pourrait renforcer davantage sa fausse légitimité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8766">pour</DiscourseConnective> abuser des patients nécessitant des soins médicaux importants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7940" docOffset="57">
      <en>He is potentially a dangerous risk to the public.</en>
      <fr>Il représente une menace potentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8871">pour</DiscourseConnective> le public.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7990" docOffset="58">
      <en>Mr Perisic should be investigated by the relevant UK authorities and the appropriate action taken <Alignment alignment="9024" annotation_id="8088">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8088" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the allegations are found to be true.</en>
      <fr>M. Perisic devrait faire l'objet d'une enquête par les autorités britanniques compétentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8977">et</DiscourseConnective> des mesures adéquates devraient être prises <Alignment alignment="3681" annotation_id="9024">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9024" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les allégations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9043">s'</DiscourseConnective>avèrent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8129" docOffset="59">
      <en>The national press might <Alignment alignment="30491" annotation_id="8154">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8154" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> decide to play a useful role in investigating this matter.</en>
      <fr>La presse nationale pourrait <Alignment alignment="4140" annotation_id="9083">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9083" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> décider de jouer un rôle utile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9124">en</DiscourseConnective> enquêtant sur cette affaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8218" id="211" name="Corneliu Vadim Tudor">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8218" docOffset="60">
      <en>(RO) Madam President, it is a well-known fact that wherever officials from the International Monetary Fund have been, large popular uprisings have occurred.</en>
      <fr>(RO) Madame la Présidente, il est notoire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9198">que</DiscourseConnective> partout où les responsables du Fonds monétaire international se sont rendus, des soulèvements populaires massifs se sont produits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8375" docOffset="61">
      <en>At the moment, these despotic bureaucrats are imposing a ridiculous agreement on Romania whereby between 150 and 200 of the country's existing 400 hospitals will be closed down.</en>
      <fr>Actuellement, ces bureaucrates tyranniques imposent un accord ridicule <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9404">à</DiscourseConnective> la Roumanie, visant à fermer entre 150 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9445">et</DiscourseConnective> 200 hôpitaux sur les 400 que compte le pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8553" docOffset="62">
      <en>Seventy-one hospitals have been closed so far, resulting in the deaths of innocent people.</en>
      <fr>Jusqu'à présent, 71 hôpitaux ont été fermés, entraînant ainsi la mort d'innocents.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8644" docOffset="63">
      <en>The alleged reason for this is outrageous.</en>
      <fr>La raison invoquée est scandaleuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8687" docOffset="64">
      <en>These hospitals are supposedly unprofitable.</en>
      <fr>Ces hôpitaux ne sont soi-disant pas rentables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8732" docOffset="65">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9659" annotation_id="8732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8732" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, there is nowhere in the world where hospitals generate money <Alignment alignment="9240" annotation_id="8802">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8802" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they provide a different kind of benefit.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8732" annotation_id="9659">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9659" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il n'existe aucun endroit dans le monde où les hôpitaux génèrent de l'argent <Alignment alignment="8802" annotation_id="9747">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9747" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils fournissent un autre type d'avantage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8847" docOffset="66">
      <en>This is why, alarmed at this act of genocide, I lodged a criminal complaint against the IMF's representative in Romania, Jeffrey Franks, as well as against the local henchmen.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9796">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>, alarmé par ce massacre, j'ai déposé une plainte contre le représentant du FMI <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9890">en</DiscourseConnective> Roumanie, Jeffrey Franks, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9919">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que contre les hommes de main locaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9023" docOffset="67">
      <en>I appeal to the European Parliament and World Health Organisation to take a stance on this to prevent a Member State of the European Union turning into an extermination camp.</en>
      <fr>Je demande au Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9996">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'Organisation mondiale de la santé de prendre position pour empêcher qu'un État membre de l'Union européenne ne devienne un camp d'extermination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9198" docOffset="68">
      <en>At present, Big Finance, which is attempting to introduce a new world order, is exterminating us, but tomorrow they could <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9320" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> exterminate you.</en>
      <fr>Actuellement, les grands organismes financiers, qui tentent d'instaurer un nouvel ordre mondial, sont en train de nous exterminer, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10279">mais</DiscourseConnective> demain cela pourrait être votre tour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9342" docOffset="69">
      <en>I cherish the hope that the IMF does not want to replace al-Qaeda.</en>
      <fr>J'espère sincèrement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10343">que</DiscourseConnective> le FMI ne veut pas remplacer Al-Qaïda.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9409" id="212" name="Iuliu Winkler">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9409" docOffset="70">
      <en>(HU) Madam President, we, the members of the Hungarian community in Romania, imagine the Europe of the future as the Europe of the regions and communities, in which the Roma communities, too, can find their home.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Madame la Présidente, nous, membres de la communauté hongroise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10454">en</DiscourseConnective> Roumanie, imaginons l'Europe du futur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10495">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe des régions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10522">et</DiscourseConnective> des communautés, où les communautés roms, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10567">également</DiscourseConnective>, peuvent être chez elles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9622" docOffset="71">
      <en>Today, on Europe Day, the President of Parliament has said: 'We should not retreat behind the borders of our inner circles; let us fight the challenges in unity'.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10616">en</DiscourseConnective> cette Journée de l'Europe, le Président du Parlement a déclaré: "Nous ne devrions pas nous retrancher derrière les frontières de nos cercles restreints; relevons les défis dans l'unité".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9785" docOffset="72">
      <en>I have been following with concern the flare-up of tensions in Transylvania, where the small communities are turning inwards as a result of tension, harassment or fear, shutting out the communities living together with them.</en>
      <fr>J'ai suivi avec inquiétude l'embrasement des tensions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10860">en</DiscourseConnective> Transylvanie, où les petites communautés, accablées par les tensions, les harcèlements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10950">et</DiscourseConnective> la peur, se referment sur elles-mêmes et excluent les communautés vivant avec elles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10010" docOffset="73">
      <en>It is evident in a European region that the future of the Roma community lies not in short-sighted part-measures, but in prospective action by Europe which is founded on solidarity and dialogue.</en>
      <fr>Il est évident que, dans une région européenne, l'avenir de la communauté rom ne réside pas dans des mesures partielles irréfléchies, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11172">mais</DiscourseConnective> dans une action européenne tournée vers l'avenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11226">et</DiscourseConnective> fondée sur la solidarité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11254">et</DiscourseConnective> le dialogue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10205" docOffset="74">
      <en>The Roma integration strategy being prepared under the direction of the Hungarian Presidency may create the Europe of the future for the Roma communities as well.</en>
      <fr>La stratégie pour l'intégration des Roms préparée sous l'égide de la Présidence hongroise peut créer l'Europe du futur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11389">pour</DiscourseConnective> les communautés roms <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11415">également</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10368" docOffset="75">
      <en>It is the responsibility of the Commission, Parliament, the Member States, the competent authorities and every local community concerned, and all of us, to make this a reality.</en>
      <fr>Il appartient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11440">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission, au Parlement, aux États membres, aux autorités compétentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11516">et</DiscourseConnective> à chaque communauté locale concernée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11557">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à nous tous, d'en faire une réalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10545" id="213" name="Ioan Enciu">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10545" docOffset="76">
      <en>(RO) Madam President, the health service reform proposed by the current Romanian Government is continuing the series of counter-reforms which are leading this country slowly, but surely towards a real social catastrophe.</en>
      <fr>(RO) Madame la Présidente, la réforme du système de santé proposée par le gouvernement roumain actuel poursuit la série de contre-réformes menant ce pays, lentement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11768">mais</DiscourseConnective> sûrement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11783">à</DiscourseConnective> une véritable catastrophe sociale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10766" docOffset="77">
      <en>The intention behind the so-called health reform proposed by the Boc government in Bucharest is to shut down hospitals, reduce investment in medical equipment and make thousands of nurses and doctors unemployed, which are all drastic measures implemented in a medical service already suffering from a chronic lack of resources.</en>
      <fr>La soi-disant réforme de la santé proposée par le gouvernement Boc <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11887">à</DiscourseConnective> Bucarest vise en réalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11914">à</DiscourseConnective> fermer des hôpitaux, réduire les investissements dans les équipements médicaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11995">et</DiscourseConnective> licencier des milliers d'infirmières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12035">et</DiscourseConnective> de docteurs. Toutes ces mesures draconiennes sont appliquées dans un système médical souffrant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12133">déjà</DiscourseConnective> d'un manque chronique de ressources.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11094" docOffset="78">
      <en>Romania is in last place in the European league table for the quality and quantity of medical services.</en>
      <fr>La Roumanie occupe la dernière place dans les statistiques européennes relatives à la qualité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12269">et</DiscourseConnective> à la quantité des services médicaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11198" docOffset="79">
      <en>Even deeper cuts to healthcare services are a serious attack on human life and integrity.</en>
      <fr>Des réductions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12324">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus sévères dans les services de soins de santé portent gravement préjudice <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12408">à</DiscourseConnective> la vie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12417">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'intégrité humaines.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11288" docOffset="80">
      <en>The so-called reform proposed by the Boc government is a direct attack on the rights provided for in the EU Charter of Fundamental Rights.</en>
      <fr>La prétendue réforme proposée par le gouvernement Boc est une atteinte directe aux droits prévus par la Charte des droits fondamentaux de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11427" docOffset="81">
      <en>On behalf of Romania's citizens, I call on the European Commission to take a stance and block these inhumane measures which are jeopardising lives and basic rights.</en>
      <fr>Au nom des citoyens roumains, je demande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12629">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne de prendre position <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12676">et</DiscourseConnective> de mettre un terme à ces mesures inhumaines qui mettent en danger des vies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12754">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les droits fondamentaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11592" id="214" name="Ivo Vajgl">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11592" docOffset="82">
      <en>(SL) Madam President, the agreement reached last week by the Palestinians, that is, by senior representatives of Fatah and Hamas, in which the new interim Egyptian Government was actively involved, opens up new opportunities for the resumption or, <Alignment alignment="10392" annotation_id="11840">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11840" sense="Expansion.Restatement">rather</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the commencement of a genuine Palestinian-Israeli dialogue on peace and coexistence on the basis of the mutual recognition principle.</en>
      <fr>(SL) Madame la Présidente, l'accord conclu la semaine dernière par les Palestiniens, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12874">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir, par les hauts représentants du Fatah <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12921">et</DiscourseConnective> du Hamas, auquel le nouveau gouvernement intérimaire égyptien a activement participé, ouvre de nouvelles perspectives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13042">pour</DiscourseConnective> la reprise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13059">ou</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="11840" annotation_id="13062">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13062" sense="Expansion.Restatement">plutôt</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le commencement d'un véritable dialogue israélo-palestinien sur la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13142">et</DiscourseConnective> la coexistence sur la base du principe de reconnaissance mutuelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11982" docOffset="83">
      <en>I hope that the Israeli Government will rightly value the opportunities this Palestinian agreement brings.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13221">que</DiscourseConnective> le gouvernement israélien évaluera correctement les possibilités qu'offre cet accord palestinien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12089" docOffset="84">
      <en>It is wrong to doubt the additional value of Palestinian unification and the agreement on democratic elections.</en>
      <fr>On a tort de mettre en doute la valeur additionnelle de l'unification palestinienne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13407">et</DiscourseConnective> l'accord sur des élections démocratiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12201" docOffset="85">
      <en>For this reason, the statements made by Prime Minister Netanyahu that the authorities in Ramallah should choose between Israel and Hamas are of no benefit either to peace or to the finding of a solution, or to the realisation of the project whereby the two states would live side by side in a spirit of mutual respect.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13452">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>, les déclarations du Premier ministre Netanyahu selon lesquelles les autorités de Ramallah devraient choisir entre Israël <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13589">et</DiscourseConnective> le Hamas ne servent ni la paix ni la perspective d'une solution, pas plus que la réalisation du projet où deux États vivraient côte à côte dans un esprit de respect mutuel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12520" docOffset="86">
      <en>It is right that the democratic changes that are taking place in the Arab world should provide the bedrock for new structures, those of safety, coexistence and development.</en>
      <fr>Il est vrai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13777">que</DiscourseConnective> les changements démocratiques qui se produisent dans le monde arabe devraient jeter les bases de nouvelles structures, celles de la sécurité, de la coexistence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13941">et</DiscourseConnective> du développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12693" id="215" name="Ryszard Czarnecki">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12693" docOffset="87">
      <en>(PL) Madam President, I am taking the floor once again on a very painful matter for Poles in Lithuania.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Madame la Présidente, je m'exprime encore une fois sur une question très douloureuse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14052">pour</DiscourseConnective> les Polonais de Lituanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12797" docOffset="88">
      <en>In this country, only 7% of the population are Poles, <Alignment alignment="11031" annotation_id="12851">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12851" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in certain areas of course, there are more.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce pays, 7 % de la population seulement sont Polonais, <Alignment alignment="262" annotation_id="14143">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14143" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans certaines régions, bien entendu, ils sont plus nombreux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12899" docOffset="89">
      <en>It is very disappointing that before 2004, <Alignment alignment="14341" annotation_id="12942">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12942" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Lithuania became a member of the European Union, the Polish minority had more rights than it has now.</en>
      <fr>Il est très décevant de constater <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14244">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14247">avant</DiscourseConnective> 2004, <Alignment alignment="7196" annotation_id="14259">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14259" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la Lituanie est devenue membre de l'Union européenne, la minorité polonaise avait plus de droits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14362">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle n'en a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14377">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13049" docOffset="90">
      <en>It is a paradox that there has been a regression, especially in educational matters, writing surnames in Polish and the rights and privileges of Poles living in Lithuania.</en>
      <fr>Cette régression est paradoxale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14422">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> dans les domaines de l'enseignement, de l'écriture des patronymes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14503">en</DiscourseConnective> polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14515">et</DiscourseConnective> des droits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14529">et</DiscourseConnective> privilèges des Polonais vivant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14563">en</DiscourseConnective> Lituanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13221" docOffset="91">
      <en>I believe that the European Parliament, which is rightly vocal on behalf of various ethnic minorities in Europe and internationally, should <Alignment alignment="43293" annotation_id="13361">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13361" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> stand up for the Polish minority in Lithuania.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14585">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen, porte-parole légitime des diverses minorités ethniques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14667">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14677">et</DiscourseConnective> dans le monde, devrait <Alignment alignment="17110" annotation_id="14703">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14703" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> défendre la minorité polonaise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14744">en</DiscourseConnective> Lituanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13413" id="216" name="Tatjana Ždanoka">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13413" docOffset="92">
      <en>Madam President, my request to make a one-minute speech on the withdrawal of democratic rights to vote in elections and stand for election in Spain was sent to the Secretariat last Wednesday, at which time the Supreme Court, at the request of the Spanish Government, had banned the Bildu electoral coalition formed by two legal parties, Eusko Alkartasuna and Alternatiba, as well as independent candidates.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, ma demande d'intervention d'une minute sur le retrait des droits démocratiques de voter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14872">et</DiscourseConnective> de se présenter aux élections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14905">en</DiscourseConnective> Espagne a été envoyée au secrétariat mercredi dernier, lorsque la Cour suprême, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14988">à</DiscourseConnective> la demande du gouvernement espagnol, avait interdit la coalition électorale Bildu composée de deux partis légaux, Eusko Alkartasuna <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15122">et</DiscourseConnective> Alternatiba, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15138">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que de candidats indépendants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13820" docOffset="93">
      <en>As a member of the Basque Friendship Group 'Toward a peace process in the Basque Country', I was among those signing the declaration aimed at requesting the Spanish Government to reconsider its position and take all necessary measures to ensure that the elections held on 22 May respect basic democratic principles.</en>
      <fr>En <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15178">tant que</DiscourseConnective> membre de l'amicale basque "Vers un processus de paix dans le pays basque", je faisais partie des signataires de la déclaration visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15322">à</DiscourseConnective> demander au gouvernement espagnol de reconsidérer sa position <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15386">et</DiscourseConnective> de prendre toutes les mesures nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15431">pour</DiscourseConnective> garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15445">que</DiscourseConnective> les élections du 22 mai respectent les principes démocratiques fondamentaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14136" docOffset="94">
      <en>Last Friday, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14149" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">meanwhile</DiscourseConnective>, by a decision of the Spanish Constitutional Court, Bildu was allowed to stand for election.</en>
      <fr>Entretemps, vendredi dernier, Bildu a été autorisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15578">à</DiscourseConnective> se présenter aux élections, par décision de la Cour constitutionnelle espagnole.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14252" docOffset="95">
      <en>I very much welcome this decision and wish to express my hope that the elections held on 22 May in the Basque Country will be conducted in accordance with all international standards relating to democracy and electoral law.</en>
      <fr>Je me réjouis vivement de cette décision <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15702">et</DiscourseConnective> souhaite exprimer l'espoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15732">que</DiscourseConnective> les élections du 22 mai au Pays basque se dérouleront conformément à toutes les normes internationales relatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15849">à</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15865">et</DiscourseConnective> au droit électoral.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14476" id="217" name="Rui Tavares">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14476" docOffset="96">
      <en>(PT) Mr President, I am Parliament's rapporteur for refugees and I should say that this mission has, in recent times, become a depressing one, if not at times macabre.</en>
      <fr>(PT) Madame la Présidente, je suis rapporteur du Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15947">pour</DiscourseConnective> les réfugiés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15965">et</DiscourseConnective> je dirais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15978">que</DiscourseConnective> cette mission est récemment devenue déprimante, voire même parfois macabre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14644" docOffset="97">
      <en>Last month, I informed the House about the deaths of more than 100 refugees off the coast of Lampedusa, <Alignment alignment="31457" annotation_id="14748">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14748" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> now, still reeling from the shock of learning of the disappearance of 600 refugees who were leaving Libya, we learn of more than 60 who died in full view of the ships of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) and several European navies.</en>
      <fr>Le mois dernier, j'ai informé l'Assemblée du décès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16109">de plus</DiscourseConnective> de 100 réfugiés près des côtes de Lampedusa, <Alignment alignment="13016" annotation_id="16162">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16162" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aujourd'hui, alors que nous ne sommes pas encore remis du choc de la disparition de 600 réfugiés qui quittaient la Libye, nous apprenons que plus de 60 sont morts sous les yeux des bateaux de l'Organisation du traité de l'Atlantique Nord (OTAN) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16410">et</DiscourseConnective> de plusieurs flottes européennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14997" docOffset="98">
      <en>Let us not think that nothing can be done about these tragedies.</en>
      <fr>Il ne faut pas croire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16469">qu'</DiscourseConnective>on ne peut rien faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16494">pour</DiscourseConnective> éviter ces tragédies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15062" docOffset="99">
      <en>There is a lot to do, that we must do, <Alignment alignment="44321" annotation_id="15101">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15101" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that we are obliged to do by the international conventions that we have signed.</en>
      <fr>Il y a beaucoup de choses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16547">à</DiscourseConnective> faire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16556">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons faire, <Alignment alignment="24242" annotation_id="16579">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16579" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16582">que</DiscourseConnective> nous sommes tenus de faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16613">en</DiscourseConnective> vertu des conventions internationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16654">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons signées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15185" docOffset="100">
      <en>I will give three examples in the 20 seconds I have left.</en>
      <fr>Je citerai trois exemples pendant les vingt secondes qui me restent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15243" docOffset="101">
      <en>The Council should conclude the codecision procedure regarding the resettlement of refugees that this Parliament voted for <Alignment alignment="16869" annotation_id="15366">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15366" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that provided for emergency mechanisms for use on these occasions.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil devrait conclure la procédure de codécision en matière de réinstallation des réfugiés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16844">que</DiscourseConnective> ce Parlement a votée <Alignment alignment="3838" annotation_id="16869">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16869" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui prévoit des mécanismes d'urgence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16909">à</DiscourseConnective> utiliser dans ces situations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15437" docOffset="102">
      <en>A proposal should be tabled for a humanitarian corridor to remove from Libya refugees recognised as such by the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR), <Alignment alignment="43511" annotation_id="15602">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15602" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> NATO should comply with its mandate of protecting civilians, from Resolution 1973, which means carrying out high-sea rescues.</en>
      <fr>Il faut présenter une proposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16975">pour</DiscourseConnective> la création d'un couloir humanitaire permettant d'évacuer les réfugiés libyens reconnus en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17071">tant que</DiscourseConnective> tels par le Haut-commissariat des Nations unies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17128">pour</DiscourseConnective> les réfugiés (HCR), <Alignment alignment="15602" annotation_id="17153">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17153" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'OTAN devrait respecter son mandat de protection civile, conformément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17227">à</DiscourseConnective> la résolution 1973, à savoir conduire des opérations de sauvetage en haute mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15732" docOffset="103">
      <en>Failure to help, let us not forget, is a crime and should not happen in our name.</en>
      <fr>La non-assistance, ne l'oublions pas, est un crime, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17361">et</DiscourseConnective> ne devrait pas exister <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17387">en</DiscourseConnective> notre nom.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15814" id="218" name="Anna Záborská">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15814" docOffset="104">
      <en>(SK) Madam President, the Duff Report on the European elections has not, in the end, appeared on the agenda for this part-session.</en>
      <fr>(SK) Madame la Présidente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17428">en fin de compte</DiscourseConnective>, le rapport Duff sur les élections européennes ne figure pas à l'ordre du jour de cette période de session.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15945" docOffset="105">
      <en>Let us use this time to consider it and <Alignment alignment="17594" annotation_id="15985">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15985" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> reject it next month.</en>
      <fr>Profitons de ce délai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17575">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'examiner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17591">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="30" annotation_id="17594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17594" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le rejeter dans un mois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16012" docOffset="106">
      <en>The idea of a ​​transnational list is absurd.</en>
      <fr>L'idée d'une liste transnationale est absurde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16058" docOffset="107">
      <en>I have several questions: Why would Slovak, German or Italian electors vote for people they cannot understand without an interpreter?</en>
      <fr>J'ai plusieurs questions: pourquoi des électeurs slovaques, allemands <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17744">ou</DiscourseConnective> italiens voteraient-ils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17771">pour</DiscourseConnective> des gens qu'ils ne peuvent pas comprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17818">sans</DiscourseConnective> interprète?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16192" docOffset="108">
      <en>How will their elected MEPs <Alignment alignment="17895" annotation_id="16220">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16220" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> represent them <Alignment alignment="3313" annotation_id="16240">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16240" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they cannot even read letters sent to them by their constituents?</en>
      <fr>Comment leurs députés européens élus les représenteront-ils <Alignment alignment="17973" annotation_id="17895">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17895" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="11225" annotation_id="17903">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17903" sense="Contingency.Condition">s'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils ne peuvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17920">même</DiscourseConnective> pas lire le courrier qui leur est envoyé par leurs électeurs?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16309" docOffset="109">
      <en>How many times is a Greek MEP going to meet his Slovak voters?</en>
      <fr>Combien de fois un député européen grec rencontrera-t-il ses électeurs slovaques?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16372" docOffset="110">
      <en>What are they going to discuss?</en>
      <fr>De quoi parleront-ils?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16404" docOffset="111">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="6954" annotation_id="16404">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16404" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Besides</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, only large Member States will benefit from a pan-European list.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="22677" annotation_id="18092">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18092" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, seuls les grands États membres bénéficieront d'une liste paneuropéenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16477" docOffset="112">
      <en>Approval of this report would vindicate all the Eurosceptics' claims that the European Union harbours ambitions to become a multinational state.</en>
      <fr>Approuver ce rapport reviendrait à justifier toutes les revendications des eurosceptiques selon lesquelles l'Union européenne nourrit l'ambition de devenir un État multinational.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16622" docOffset="113">
      <en>It will call into question the democratic legitimacy of this Parliament and alienate citizens from the European project even more.</en>
      <fr>Cela mettra <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18369">en</DiscourseConnective> doute la légitimité démocratique de ce Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18421">et</DiscourseConnective> exclura <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18432">encore</DiscourseConnective> davantage les citoyens du projet européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16753" id="219" name="Spyros Danellis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16753" docOffset="114">
      <en>(EL) Madam President, I wish to comment on the need to safeguard the transparency and efficacy of the Climate Fund.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Madame la Présidente, je souhaite m'exprimer sur la nécessité de sauvegarder la transparence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18580">et</DiscourseConnective> l'efficacité du Fonds pour le climat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16869" docOffset="115">
      <en>One of the most tangible results of negotiations on climate change in Cancún was the agreement on a Green Climate Fund, with unprecedented financing in the order of USD 100 billion.</en>
      <fr>L'un des résultats les plus concrets des négociations sur le changement climatique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18704">à</DiscourseConnective> Cancún a été l'accord sur un Fonds vert pour le climat, bénéficiant d'un financement sans précédent de l'ordre de 100 milliards de dollars.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17051" docOffset="116">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="41437" annotation_id="17051">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17051" sense="Comparison.Contrast">While</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the transitional committee set up within the framework of the UN is preparing the final form of the Fund, <Alignment alignment="23899" annotation_id="17163">
          <Alignment alignment="26794" annotation_id="17163">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17163" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> it can obtain a final seal of approval in Durban at the end of the year, questions relating to the design of this unique and extremely important instrument remain unanswered.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4873" annotation_id="18846">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18846" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la commission de transition créée dans le cadre des Nations unies prépare la version finale du Fonds, <Alignment alignment="18265" annotation_id="18958">
          <Alignment alignment="1707" annotation_id="18958">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18958" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">pour qu'</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>il puisse être définitivement approuvé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19005">à</DiscourseConnective> Durban <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19014">à</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'année, des questions liées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19055">à</DiscourseConnective> la conception de cet instrument unique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19096">et</DiscourseConnective> extrêmement important restent sans réponse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17346" docOffset="117">
      <en>The Fund must be a carefully designed vehicle that will provide effective financing for adjustment to climate change in the developing world.</en>
      <fr>Le Fonds doit être un vecteur conçu avec prudence qui fournira un financement efficace permettant aux pays en développement de s'adapter au changement climatique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17488" docOffset="118">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="56265" annotation_id="17488">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17488" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, both the recent criminal attacks on the Community emissions trading system (EU ETS) and the information in the recent report by Transparency International on corruption in climate funding are causes for concern, not only <Alignment alignment="37275" annotation_id="17718">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17718" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> huge amounts of money are at risk, but <Alignment alignment="19657" annotation_id="17765">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17765" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, more importantly, <Alignment alignment="20241" annotation_id="17789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17789" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a global fight which, unlike others, may not be open to repeat efforts, is at risk.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="26652" annotation_id="19306">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19306" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il faut s'inquiéter des récentes attaques criminelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19371">à</DiscourseConnective> l'encontre du système d'échange de quotas d'émission de l'Union européenne (SCEQE) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19456">et</DiscourseConnective> des informations du récent rapport fourni par l'agence Transparency International sur la corruption liée au financement pour le climat, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19595">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="30592" annotation_id="19609">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19609" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'énormes montants sont menacés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19652">mais</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="20128" annotation_id="19657">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19657" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, et c'est plus important, <Alignment alignment="12673" annotation_id="19693">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19693" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>une lutte mondiale est compromise dans laquelle, contrairement à d'autres, nous n'aurons peut-être pas de deuxième chance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17881" id="220" name="Sergej Kozlík">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17881" docOffset="119">
      <en>(SK) Madam President, in 1990, József Antall declared himself Prime Minister of all Hungarians, including Hungarians living outside Hungary.</en>
      <fr>(SK) Madame la Présidente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19852">en</DiscourseConnective> 1990, József Antall s'est présenté comme Premier ministre de tous les Hongrois, y compris de ceux vivant en-dehors de la Hongrie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18022" docOffset="120">
      <en>Today, Viktor Orbán has gone even further.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, Viktor Orbán a été <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20017">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus loin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18065" docOffset="121">
      <en>A new constitution has been adopted, committing Hungary to the idea of a single Hungarian nation consisting of all Hungarians, which is taken to mean all persons belonging to the Hungarian ethnic group, whatever their citizenship.</en>
      <fr>Une nouvelle constitution a été adoptée, associant la Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20097">à</DiscourseConnective> l'idée d'une nation hongroise unique composée de tous les Hongrois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20167">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir de toutes les personnes appartenant au groupe ethnique hongrois, quelle que soit leur citoyenneté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18296" docOffset="122">
      <en>Contrary to international law, according to which the promotion and protection of a national minority is the responsibility of the State in which that minority lives, this constitution <Alignment alignment="22576" annotation_id="18481">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18481" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> stipulates that Hungary is responsible for the fate of Hungarians abroad.</en>
      <fr>Contrairement au droit international, selon lequel la promotion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20339">et</DiscourseConnective> la protection d'une minorité nationale incombe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20389">à</DiscourseConnective> l'État où vit la minorité, cette constitution dispose <Alignment alignment="546" annotation_id="20445">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20445" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20455">que</DiscourseConnective> la Hongrie est responsable du sort des Hongrois à l'étranger.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18560" docOffset="123">
      <en>The new Hungarian constitution <Alignment alignment="6313" annotation_id="18591">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18591" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> supports efforts to establish the collective, ethnically-based self-government of Hungarian minorities living abroad.</en>
      <fr>La nouvelle constitution hongroise soutient <Alignment alignment="9401" annotation_id="20565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20565" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les efforts visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20594">à</DiscourseConnective> établir l'autogouvernement collectif, basé sur l'appartenance ethnique des minorités hongroises vivant à l'étranger.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18714" docOffset="124">
      <en>The provisions of the Hungarian constitution may be a way of meddling in the internal affairs of foreign states and of breeding tension between Hungary and neighbouring countries.</en>
      <fr>Les dispositions prévues dans la constitution hongroise peuvent être le moyen de s'immiscer dans les affaires internes d'États étrangers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20850">et</DiscourseConnective> d'engendrer des tensions entre la Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20895">et</DiscourseConnective> les pays voisins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18894" docOffset="125">
      <en>This is at odds with the spirit of a democratic Europe.</en>
      <fr>C'est contraire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20932">à</DiscourseConnective> l'esprit d'une Europe démocratique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18950" id="221" name="François Alfonsi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18950" docOffset="126">
      <en>(FR) Madam President, I wish to express our relief following the decision by the Spanish Constitutional Court to allow the lists submitted by the Bildu coalition to be included in the Basque Country's democratic elections.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, je vais exprimer ici notre soulagement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21031">après</DiscourseConnective> la décision du tribunal constitutionnel d'Espagne qui a validé la participation des listes déposées par la coalition Bildu aux élections démocratiques du pays basque.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19173" docOffset="127">
      <en>This decision was taken on appeal.</en>
      <fr>Cette décision est intervenue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21234">en</DiscourseConnective> appel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19208" docOffset="128">
      <en>It <Alignment alignment="21251" annotation_id="19211">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19211" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> overturned the decision of the Supreme Court, which had again banned the Basque nationalist left from standing in elections.</en>
      <fr>Elle a <Alignment alignment="10421" annotation_id="21251">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21251" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> annulé la décision du tribunal suprême qui avait, encore une fois, prononcé l'interdiction faite à la gauche nationaliste basque de se présenter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21401">à</DiscourseConnective> des élections.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19346" docOffset="129">
      <en>Would it have been acceptable, at the very heart of the European Union, for citizens to have been deprived again of the right to vote for candidates whom they wished to support?</en>
      <fr>Au cœur même de l'Union européenne aurait-il été acceptable que des citoyens soient à nouveau privés du droit de voter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21537">pour</DiscourseConnective> les listes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21553">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils souhaitent soutenir?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19524" docOffset="130">
      <en>Fortunately, Spain has chosen to stop travelling down this very dangerous road for European democracy.</en>
      <fr>L'Espagne a fort heureusement renoncé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21619">à</DiscourseConnective> continuer sur ces chemins extrêmement périlleux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21669">pour</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19627" docOffset="131">
      <en>We can only be pleased about that, <Alignment alignment="44777" annotation_id="19662">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19662" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must call on Bildu to fulfil the objectives to which it has committed itself: an end to all political violence in the Basque Country and the disbandment of ETA.</en>
      <fr>On ne peut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21711">que s'</DiscourseConnective>en féliciter <Alignment alignment="20262" annotation_id="21730">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21730" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demander <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21742">à</DiscourseConnective> Bildu d'accomplir les objectifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21776">pour</DiscourseConnective> lesquels elle s'est engagée, à savoir la fin de toute violence politique au pays basque <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21869">et</DiscourseConnective> la fin de l'ETA.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19830" docOffset="132">
      <en>A new political climate is gradually emerging.</en>
      <fr>Un cadre politique nouveau voit progressivement le jour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19877" docOffset="133">
      <en>Dialogue is difficult, <Alignment alignment="35238" annotation_id="19900">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19900" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a desire for peace has been very clearly expressed.</en>
      <fr>Le dialogue est difficile <Alignment alignment="14635" annotation_id="21972">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21972" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une volonté de paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21997">s'</DiscourseConnective>est affirmée de façon très nette.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19956" docOffset="134">
      <en>I should like the European Parliament to continue to pay close attention to this important development, <Alignment alignment="22942" annotation_id="20060">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20060" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Basque Country is at the very heart of Europe.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite que le Parlement européen reste très attentif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22091">à</DiscourseConnective> cette évolution importante <Alignment alignment="20060" annotation_id="22120">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22120" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le pays basque est au cœur même de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20119" docOffset="135">
      <en>It is essential for Europe that this peace process, which comes 10 years after the Northern Ireland one, receives support <Alignment alignment="50340" annotation_id="20241">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20241" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that it can <Alignment alignment="57401" annotation_id="20257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20257" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> run its course.</en>
      <fr>Il est essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22186">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22200">que</DiscourseConnective> ce processus de paix, 10 ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22233">après</DiscourseConnective> celui d'Irlande du Nord, soit soutenu <Alignment alignment="20241" annotation_id="22277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22277" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22280">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il puisse <Alignment alignment="18419" annotation_id="22293">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22293" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aller à son terme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20278" id="222" name="Catherine Stihler">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20278" docOffset="136">
      <en>Madam President, for 12 years, I have been asking the Commission and the Council a question which has remained unanswered, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20401" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> they claim it is hypothetical.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22345">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 12 ans, je pose à la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22384">et</DiscourseConnective> au Conseil une question restée sans réponse, parce qu'ils l'estiment vaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20435" docOffset="137">
      <en>On Thursday, the people of Scotland voted in the Scottish parliamentary elections <Alignment alignment="46816" annotation_id="20517">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20517" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Scottish National Party won an overall majority of seats.</en>
      <fr>Jeudi, le peuple écossais a voté aux élections parlementaires écossaises <Alignment alignment="13911" annotation_id="22536">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22536" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parti national écossais a remporté une majorité de sièges écrasante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20583" docOffset="138">
      <en>The prospect of a referendum on Scottish independence is now not a matter of 'if', but rather of 'when'.</en>
      <fr>Il ne s'agit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22624">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> plus de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22650">si</DiscourseConnective> un référendum sur l'indépendance de l'Écosse aura lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22708">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22713">quand</DiscourseConnective> il aura lieu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20688" docOffset="139">
      <en>Under these new circumstances, I <Alignment alignment="67261" annotation_id="20721">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20721" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ask the Commission and the Council, once again, whether, <Alignment alignment="60296" annotation_id="20788">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20788" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> part of an existing EU Member State should choose to separate, the new state would remain a member of the EU, <Alignment alignment="22949" annotation_id="20901">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20901" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whether it would have to reapply for membership.</en>
      <fr>Dans ce nouveau contexte, je demande <Alignment alignment="20721" annotation_id="22770">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22770" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22784">encore</DiscourseConnective> à la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22807">et</DiscourseConnective> au Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22821">si</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="15210" annotation_id="22825">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22825" sense="Contingency.Condition">dans l'hypothèse où</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une partie d'un État membre de l'UE choisissait de se séparer, le nouvel État resterait membre de l'UE, <Alignment alignment="14350" annotation_id="22949">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22949" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22952">s'</DiscourseConnective>il devrait se représenter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22980">à</DiscourseConnective> l'adhésion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20953" docOffset="140">
      <en>The people of Scotland deserve a clear answer to a clear question.</en>
      <fr>Le peuple écossais mérite une réponse claire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23039">à</DiscourseConnective> une question claire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="21020" id="223" name="Pat the Cope Gallagher">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="21020" docOffset="141">
      <en>(GA) Madam President, I refer to the fires we had in my home county - Donegal - and elsewhere in Ireland last weekend, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21139" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> we had fires which destroyed forests, land, fences and wildlife.</en>
      <fr>(GA) Madame la Présidente, je fais référence aux incendies que nous avons connus dans mon comté - Donegal - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23170">et</DiscourseConnective> ailleurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23182">en</DiscourseConnective> Irlande le weekend dernier, qui ont détruit des forêts, des terres, des clôtures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23266">et</DiscourseConnective> une partie de la faune et de la flore.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21209" docOffset="142">
      <en>I want to pay particular tribute to the fire services who were out working without sleep for three days or so, and to members of the defence forces - those who were working on the ground or in helicopters.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite rendre un hommage tout particulier aux services des pompiers qui ont travaillé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23399">sans</DiscourseConnective> interruption pendant trois jours à peu près, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23449">et</DiscourseConnective> aux membres des forces de protection - ceux qui ont travaillé au sol <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23521">ou</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23524">en</DiscourseConnective> hélicoptère.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21415" docOffset="143">
      <en>They made every effort to control the fire.</en>
      <fr>Ils ont fait tout leur possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23572">pour</DiscourseConnective> lutter contre les incendies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21459" docOffset="144">
      <en>I am heartened by the response of the local community - young people, farmers, business people - who came out to help, along with the police and the civil defence forces.</en>
      <fr>Je trouve du réconfort dans la réaction de la communauté locale - les jeunes, les agriculteurs, les entrepreneurs - qui nous est venue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23741">en</DiscourseConnective> aide, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23750">et</DiscourseConnective> de la police <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23766">et</DiscourseConnective> des forces de protection civile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21630" docOffset="145">
      <en>Now we need to learn lessons from this. We must now put an emergency plan in place <Alignment alignment="33064" annotation_id="21713">
          <Alignment alignment="8324" annotation_id="21713">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21713" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> not a minute is lost <Alignment alignment="24225" annotation_id="21742">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21742" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> something similar happens again.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23814">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> tirer les leçons de cette catastrophe et élaborer immédiatement un plan d'urgence <Alignment alignment="11980" annotation_id="23907">
          <Alignment alignment="18407" annotation_id="23907">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23907" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin de</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> ne pas perdre une minute <Alignment alignment="5856" annotation_id="23940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23940" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une situation similaire devait se reproduire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21778" docOffset="146">
      <en>I am saying this, <Alignment alignment="33020" annotation_id="21796">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21796" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, to thank all those people.</en>
      <fr>Je m'exprime <Alignment alignment="21994" annotation_id="24002">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24002" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24007">pour</DiscourseConnective> remercier tous ces gens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="21834" id="224" name="Monika Smolková">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="21834" docOffset="147">
      <en>(SK) Madam President, a hundred years ago, our forefathers fought for an eight-hour working day, a dignified life and better working conditions.</en>
      <fr>(SK) Madame la Présidente, il y a 100 ans, nos ancêtres ont lutté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24103">pour</DiscourseConnective> la journée de huit heures, une vie digne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24149">et</DiscourseConnective> de meilleures conditions de travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21979" docOffset="148">
      <en>A labour code is a piece of legislation under which a state provides a system of fundamental social rights for workers.</en>
      <fr>Un code du travail est un élément législatif en vertu duquel un État fournit aux travailleurs un système de droits sociaux fondamentaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22099" docOffset="149">
      <en>The current government in Slovakia is preparing an amendment to its Labour Code that will increase working time to 56 hours per week and overtime from the current 400 hours to 560 hours.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement slovaque actuel prépare un amendement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24380">à</DiscourseConnective> son code du travail qui portera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24414">le temps de</DiscourseConnective> travail <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24434">à</DiscourseConnective> 56 heures par semaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24458">et</DiscourseConnective> les heures supplémentaires de 400 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24495">à</DiscourseConnective> 560 heures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22286" docOffset="150">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24509" annotation_id="22286">
          <Alignment alignment="24509" annotation_id="22286">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22286" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, it places workers at a disadvantage, creates uncertainty for those in employment, and reduces financial support for those who lose their jobs.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9228" annotation_id="24509">
          <Alignment alignment="20558" annotation_id="24509">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24509" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, il désavantage les travailleurs, crée de l'incertitude dans le secteur de l'emploi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24603">et</DiscourseConnective> réduit le soutien financier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24634">à</DiscourseConnective> ceux qui ont perdu leur travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22442" docOffset="151">
      <en>Paradoxically, the new rules are <Alignment alignment="7433" annotation_id="22475">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22475" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> destabilising for employers.</en>
      <fr>Paradoxalement, les nouvelles règles déstabilisent <Alignment alignment="25937" annotation_id="24720">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24720" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les employeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22509" docOffset="152">
      <en>Trade unions have taken to the streets to voice their opposition to the Labour Code amendment.</en>
      <fr>Les syndicats sont descendus dans la rue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24787">pour</DiscourseConnective> exprimer leur opposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24817">à</DiscourseConnective> l'amendement au code du travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22604" docOffset="153">
      <en>The European Parliament declared 2010 the year for combating poverty.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen a décrété 2010 Année de lutte contre la pauvreté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22674" docOffset="154">
      <en>All of Europe is fighting against poverty.</en>
      <fr>Toute l'Europe lutte contre la pauvreté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22717" docOffset="155">
      <en>The Slovak Government will fuel unemployment and increase poverty with this Labour Code.</en>
      <fr>Par son code du travail, le gouvernement slovaque alimentera le chômage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25037">et</DiscourseConnective> augmentera la pauvreté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="22806" id="225" name="Ramon Tremosa i Balcells">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="22806" docOffset="156">
      <en>(ES) Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, I should today like to report the death on Sunday of the activist for Cuban human rights, Juan Wilfredo Soto García, <Alignment alignment="8453" annotation_id="22967">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22967" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I should <Alignment alignment="36930" annotation_id="22980">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22980" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to express my sincere sympathy to his family.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Madame la Présidente, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25100">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais aujourd'hui évoquer le décès dimanche dernier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25173">à</DiscourseConnective> Cuba, du militant des droits de l'homme Juan Wilfredo Soto García, <Alignment alignment="22967" annotation_id="25242">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25242" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je souhaite <Alignment alignment="2554" annotation_id="25257">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25257" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> exprimer mes sincères condoléances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25302">à</DiscourseConnective> sa famille.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23036" docOffset="157">
      <en>The Cuban Government's official story is that his death was caused by pancreatitis, <Alignment alignment="25403" annotation_id="23120">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23120" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, according to dissidents inside Cuba, Juan Soto's death was caused by a beating from the police force of Castro's communist regime.</en>
      <fr>Selon la version officielle du gouvernement cubain, sa mort est due à une pancréatite, <Alignment alignment="28802" annotation_id="25403">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25403" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> selon les dissidents à Cuba, Juan Soto est mort sous les coups des forces de police du régime communiste de Castro.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23256" docOffset="158">
      <en>Guillermo Fariñas, last year's winner of the Sakharov Human Rights Prize, has accused the Cuban regime and, in particular, the First Secretary of the Communist Party, Raúl Castro, of Juan Soto's death.</en>
      <fr>Guillermo Fariñas, le lauréat du Prix Sakharov pour les droits de l'homme l'année dernière, a accusé le régime cubain <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25642">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25646">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>, le Premier secrétaire du Parti communiste, Raúl Castro, de la mort de Juan Soto.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23458" docOffset="159">
      <en>It is likely that Raúl Castro incited his followers to use violence against the opposition during the recently finished Sixth Congress of the Communist Party of Cuba, <Alignment alignment="50375" annotation_id="23625">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23625" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Cuban dissidents point to him as bearing responsibility for this latest murder.</en>
      <fr>Il est probable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25759">que</DiscourseConnective> Raúl Castro ait incité ses partisans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25800">à</DiscourseConnective> utiliser la violence contre l'opposition pendant le sixième congrès du Parti communiste de Cuba, qui s'est récemment terminé, <Alignment alignment="25725" annotation_id="25928">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25928" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les dissidents cubains le désignent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25967">comme</DiscourseConnective> responsable de ce dernier meurtre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23709" docOffset="160">
      <en>I should like to condemn the death of Juan Soto García, and to denounce the lack of freedom and democracy in Cuba.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais condamner la mort de Juan Soto García, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26059">et</DiscourseConnective> dénoncer l'absence de liberté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26092">et</DiscourseConnective> de démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26109">à</DiscourseConnective> Cuba.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="23824" id="226" name="Estelle Grelier">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="23824" docOffset="161">
      <en>(FR) Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, as you know, the European food aid programme for the most deprived persons in the EU was urgently introduced during the exceptionally cold winter of 1986, then enshrined the following year in the common agricultural policy.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, chers collègues, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26156">comme</DiscourseConnective> vous le savez, le programme européen d'aide aux plus démunis a été mis en place dans l'urgence lors de l'hiver exceptionnellement froid de 1986, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26307">puis</DiscourseConnective> institutionnalisé l'année suivante dans le cadre de la politique agricole commune.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24092" docOffset="162">
      <en>This programme has become vital for 13 million Europeans who have little job security.</en>
      <fr>Ce dispositif est devenu vital <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26426">pour</DiscourseConnective> 13 millions d'Européens qui connaissent la grande précarité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24179" docOffset="163">
      <en>It eases the strain on their food budget through distributions by charities and social services, and adds up to a mere EUR 1 per European per year in aid.</en>
      <fr>Ce programme permet de soulager leur budget alimentaire par l'intermédiaire des distributions réalisées par les associations caritatives et les services sociaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24334" docOffset="164">
      <en>Together with the Federation of Food Banks, Secours populaire, the Red Cross and Restos du Coeur in France, I am concerned about the future of this programme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24492" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective> the European Court of Justice called into question its funding within the framework of the CAP.</en>
      <fr>Cette aide représente seulement un coût d'un euro par Européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26717">et</DiscourseConnective> par an. Avec la fédération des banques alimentaires, le secours populaire, la Croix-Rouge <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26810">et</DiscourseConnective> les restos du cœur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26832">en</DiscourseConnective> France, je suis inquiète pour l'avenir de ce programme suite à la remise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26908">en</DiscourseConnective> cause par la Cour de justice européenne de son financement dans le cadre de la PAC.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24594" docOffset="165">
      <en>Our Parliament has often emphasised the fundamental nature of the right to food.</en>
      <fr>Notre Assemblée a souvent souligné le caractère fondamental du droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27064">à</DiscourseConnective> l'alimentation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24675" docOffset="166">
      <en>Our institutions made 2010 the European Year for Combating Poverty and Social Exclusion.</en>
      <fr>Nos institutions ont fait de l'année 2010 l'Année européenne de la lutte contre la pauvreté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27174">et</DiscourseConnective> l'exclusion sociale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24764" docOffset="167">
      <en>To cite legal ambiguity as an excuse for dismantling, <Alignment alignment="16597" annotation_id="24818">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24818" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> some Member States are trying to do, a food aid programme that has proved its worth would be disastrous not only for the people concerned but also for Europe's credibility and image.</en>
      <fr>Prendre prétexte d'ambiguïté juridique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27237">pour</DiscourseConnective> démanteler, <Alignment alignment="18880" annotation_id="27254">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27254" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cherchent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27270">à</DiscourseConnective> le faire certains États membres, un dispositif d'aide alimentaire qui a fait ses preuves serait désastreux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27379">pour</DiscourseConnective> les populations concernées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27411">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27422">pour</DiscourseConnective> la crédibilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27442">et</DiscourseConnective> l'image de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25004" docOffset="168">
      <en>That is why I call on the Commission to take the political measures necessary to safeguard, preserve and strengthen that programme.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27466">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>, j'invite la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27505">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre les mesures politiques nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27550">pour</DiscourseConnective> sécuriser, pérenniser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27577">et</DiscourseConnective> renforcer ce programme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="25136" id="227" name="Iliana Malinova Iotova">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="25136" docOffset="169">
      <en>(BG) Madam President, the Romanian border control forces have been detaining illegally for more than 10 days a Bulgarian fishing vessel and its captain, Hristo Spasov, apprehended 20 miles east of Romania's Black Sea coast, an area outside the country's territorial waters.</en>
      <fr>(BG) Madame la Présidente, les forces contrôlant les frontières roumaines ont détenu illégalement pendant plus de dix jours un bateau de pêche bulgare <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27755">et</DiscourseConnective> son capitaine, Hristo Spasov, appréhendé 20 miles à l'est des côtes roumaines de la mer Noire, une zone située en-dehors des eaux territoriales du pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25410" docOffset="170">
      <en>Equal access to the European Union's waters and resources is one of the basic principles of the common fisheries policy.</en>
      <fr>L'égalité d'accès aux eaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27938">et</DiscourseConnective> aux ressources de l'Union européenne est l'un des principes fondamentaux de la politique commune de la pêche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25531" docOffset="171">
      <en>This principle is confirmed by Council Regulation (EC) No 2371/2002.</en>
      <fr>Ce principe est confirmé par le règlement (CE) nº 2371/2002 du Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25600" docOffset="172">
      <en>Following the accession of Bulgaria and Romania to the European Union, both countries' marine areas are part of the pan-European waters <Alignment alignment="52974" annotation_id="25736">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25736" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the regulations are directly applicable in their national legislations.</en>
      <fr>Consécutivement à l'adhésion de la Bulgarie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28167">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Roumanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28185">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne, les zones maritimes des deux pays font partie des eaux paneuropéennes <Alignment alignment="19781" annotation_id="28277">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28277" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les règlements sont directement applicables dans leurs législations nationales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25812" docOffset="173">
      <en>The Bulgarian authorities have forwarded all the necessary documents to their Romanian counterparts, certifying that the vessel is entered in the European Union register and has all the permits for fishing in the Black Sea's waters.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités bulgares ont transmis tous les documents nécessaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28427">à</DiscourseConnective> leurs homologues roumains, certifiant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28467">que</DiscourseConnective> le bateau est inscrit au registre de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28527">et</DiscourseConnective> possède toutes les autorisations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28563">pour</DiscourseConnective> pêcher dans les eaux de la mer Noire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26045" docOffset="174">
      <en>In spite of this, there has been no progress on the Romanian side. The sole response has been that only Romanian legislation and the country's constitution are applicable.</en>
      <fr>Malgré cela, rien n'a bougé du côté roumain, l'unique réponse étant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28674">que</DiscourseConnective> seules la législation roumaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28709">et</DiscourseConnective> la constitution du pays sont applicables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26217" docOffset="175">
      <en>We express our deep concern that equal access to European Union waters continues to be a huge problem for professional fishermen.</en>
      <fr>Nous exprimons notre grande inquiétude quant au fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28807">que</DiscourseConnective> l'égalité d'accès aux eaux de l'Union européenne reste un problème de taille <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28888">pour</DiscourseConnective> les pêcheurs professionnels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26347" docOffset="176">
      <en>We call on our fellow MEPs from Romania and the Commission, as guardian of the Treaties, to intervene as mediators to resolve the matter.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28937">à</DiscourseConnective> nos collègues roumains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28962">et</DiscourseConnective> à la Commission, en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28985">tant que</DiscourseConnective> gardienne des traités, d'intervenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29030">comme</DiscourseConnective> médiateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29047">pour</DiscourseConnective> débloquer la situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="26485" id="228" name="Monika Flašíková Beňová">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="26485" docOffset="177">
      <en>(SK) Madam President, yesterday, we commemorated the end of the Second World War and today we celebrate Europe Day.</en>
      <fr>(SK) Madame la Présidente, hier, nous avons commémoré la fin de la Seconde guerre mondiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29167">et</DiscourseConnective> aujourd'hui nous célébrons la Journée de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26601" docOffset="178">
      <en>It has to be said that the European Union constitutes a very distinctive and unique model, built primarily on democracy and the coexistence of nations in the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Il faut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29229">dire que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne constitue un modèle très spécifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29293">et</DiscourseConnective> unique, fondé essentiellement sur la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29344">et</DiscourseConnective> la coexistence de nations dans l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="26775" docOffset="179">
      <en>At a time <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26785" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> we are commemorating such a significant anniversary, it is all the more dispiriting for us that, just a few days beforehand, the Hungarian Parliament, and later the President of Hungary, sign a constitution that runs counter to the fundamental principles of democracy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29398">Alors que</DiscourseConnective> nous célébrons un anniversaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29439">si</DiscourseConnective> important, nous sommes d'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29467">autant</DiscourseConnective> plus découragés qu'il y a quelques jours à peine, le parlement hongrois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29547">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29550">ensuite</DiscourseConnective> le président hongrois, ont signé une constitution allant à l'encontre des principes fondamentaux de la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27059" docOffset="180">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="9846" annotation_id="27065">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27065" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> unfortunate <Alignment alignment="10260" annotation_id="27082">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27082" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Hungarian Government, and Hungary as a country, currently holds the Presidency of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>C'est d'<Alignment alignment="27065" annotation_id="29681">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29681" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">autant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> plus regrettable <Alignment alignment="27082" annotation_id="29705">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29705" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le gouvernement hongrois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29735">et</DiscourseConnective> la Hongrie en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29752">tant que</DiscourseConnective> pays, est actuellement en charge de la Présidence de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27196" docOffset="181">
      <en>Viktor Orbán, as the Hungarian prime minister, has ridden roughshod over fundamental democratic principles.</en>
      <fr>Viktor Orbán, Premier ministre hongrois, a foulé au pied les principes démocratiques fondamentaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27304" docOffset="182">
      <en>Not only has he refused to cooperate with the opposition in the adoption of this basic law of his country, <Alignment alignment="50539" annotation_id="27411">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27411" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, because of the way the constitution has been conceived, he has very fundamentally undermined the rights of minorities, <Alignment alignment="21290" annotation_id="27535">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27535" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> destabilised good neighbourly relations between EU Member States.</en>
      <fr>Il a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29938">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> refusé de coopérer avec l'opposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29989">pour</DiscourseConnective> adopter cette loi essentielle de son pays, <Alignment alignment="27411" annotation_id="30037">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30037" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, étant donné la manière dont la constitution a été conçue, il a sapé les bases mêmes des droits des minorités, <Alignment alignment="14906" annotation_id="30153">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30153" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> déstabilisé les relations de bon voisinage entre les États membres de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27605" docOffset="183">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="44268" annotation_id="27607">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27607" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> hope that the Venice Commission's findings will be directed towards the adoption by this Parliament of a resolution demonstrating that the Fidesz government is bad for Hungary.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <Alignment alignment="27607" annotation_id="30241">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30241" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les conclusions de la commission de Venise recommanderont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30312">à</DiscourseConnective> ce Parlement d'adopter une résolution démontrant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30363">que</DiscourseConnective> le gouvernement Fidesz nuit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30395">à</DiscourseConnective> la Hongrie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="27794" id="229" name="Silvia-Adriana Ţicău">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="27794" docOffset="184">
      <en>(RO) Madam President, every year, 9 May is celebrated as Europe Day <Alignment alignment="44672" annotation_id="27862">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27862" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I take this opportunity to extend my best wishes to all European citizens.</en>
      <fr>(RO) Madame la Présidente, chaque année, le 9 mai est célébré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30471">comme</DiscourseConnective> la Journée de l'Europe <Alignment alignment="13822" annotation_id="30500">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30500" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je profite de cette occasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30532">pour</DiscourseConnective> transmettre mes meilleurs vœux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30568">à</DiscourseConnective> tous les citoyens européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="27941" docOffset="185">
      <en>In his declaration of 9 May 1950, Robert Schuman, the French foreign minister, indicated that Europe would not be built all at once or based on a single plan, but through specific achievements which would primarily generate genuine solidarity.</en>
      <fr>Dans sa déclaration du 9 mai 1950, Robert Schuman, ministre français des affaires étrangères, affirmait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30703">que</DiscourseConnective> "l'Europe ne se fera pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30732">d'un coup</DiscourseConnective> ni dans une construction d'ensemble. Elle se fera par des réalisations concrètes créant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30830">d'abord</DiscourseConnective> une solidarité de fait."</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28185" docOffset="186">
      <en>The aim of the Schuman Plan was to merge markets, modernise and expand the production of coal and steel, as well as improve and establish equal living standards for workers in these industrial sectors.</en>
      <fr>L'objectif du Plan Schuman consistait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30901">à</DiscourseConnective> fusionner les marchés, à moderniser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30939">et</DiscourseConnective> développer la production du charbon <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30978">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'acier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30993">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à améliorer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31014">et</DiscourseConnective> établir des conditions de vie égales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31054">pour</DiscourseConnective> les travailleurs dans ces secteurs industriels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28387" docOffset="187">
      <en>Nowadays, Member States are facing economic, financial and social crises, creating the need more than ever for solidarity and respect for the Union's basic principles.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, les États membres traversent des crises économiques, financières <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31185">et</DiscourseConnective> sociales, créant plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31210">que</DiscourseConnective> jamais un besoin de solidarité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31245">et</DiscourseConnective> de respect <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31259">pour</DiscourseConnective> les principes fondamentaux de l'Union.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28555" docOffset="188">
      <en>I call for the barriers preventing the free movement of Romanian and Bulgarian workers to be lifted.</en>
      <fr>Je demande qu'on lève les barrières empêchant la libre circulation des travailleurs roumains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31396">et</DiscourseConnective> bulgares.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="28656" docOffset="189">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="39136" annotation_id="28658">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28658" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> request support from Member States for a new industrial policy and a new innovation policy capable of creating jobs which will provide European citizens with a decent living.</en>
      <fr>Je demande <Alignment alignment="20700" annotation_id="31420">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31420" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31430">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres soutiennent une nouvelle politique industrielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31500">et</DiscourseConnective> une nouvelle politique d'innovation capables de créer des emplois qui assureront aux citoyens européens des conditions de vie décentes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="28838" id="230" name="Kinga Göncz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="28838" docOffset="190">
      <en>(HU) Madam President, <Alignment alignment="31666" annotation_id="28860">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28860" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want to obtain results in the Roma strategy, we have to simultaneously improve the educational, employment, healthcare, and housing situation, and combat anti-Romanyism, hate speech, and discrimination against the Roma people.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Madame la Présidente, <Alignment alignment="3705" annotation_id="31666">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31666" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous voulons que la stratégie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31699">pour</DiscourseConnective> les Roms produise des résultats, nous devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31749">simultanément</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la situation en matière d'éducation, d'emploi, de soins de santé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31838">et</DiscourseConnective> de logement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31854">et</DiscourseConnective> lutter contre le sentiment anti-rom, les discours de haine, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31917">et</DiscourseConnective> la discrimination contre les Roms.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29093" docOffset="191">
      <en>Neither of these can be efficient <Alignment alignment="5712" annotation_id="29127">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29127" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we ignore the other.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17180" annotation_id="31955">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31955" sense="Contingency.Condition">Pour</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être efficaces, ces éléments ne peuvent être considérés séparément.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29151" docOffset="192">
      <en>The Roma strategy of the Commission concentrates only on one side, the social tasks, <Alignment alignment="44968" annotation_id="29236">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29236" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> even in that respect, it shifts responsibility primarily to the Member States.</en>
      <fr>La stratégie de la Commission pour les Roms se concentre uniquement sur un aspect, les tâches sociales, <Alignment alignment="29236" annotation_id="32132">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32132" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et même</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> sur ce point, elle transfère la responsabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32187">d'abord</DiscourseConnective> aux États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29319" docOffset="193">
      <en>Unfortunately, it barely mentions the necessity of combating anti-Romanyism, the human rights dimension of the issue.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32214">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, elle évoque à peine la nécessité de combattre les discriminations anti-roms, qui, dans ce cas, représente l'aspect lié aux droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29437" docOffset="194">
      <en>The Commission did not raise its voice <Alignment alignment="33911" annotation_id="29476">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29476" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> paramilitary groups were threatening the Roma citizens in the Hungarian Gyöngyöspata for weeks, <Alignment alignment="15033" annotation_id="29577">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29577" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Hungarian Government took action only <Alignment alignment="31618" annotation_id="29623">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29623" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the tension and the provocation escalated into violence.</en>
      <fr>La Commission ne s'est pas exprimée <Alignment alignment="29476" annotation_id="32409">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32409" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des groupes paramilitaires ont menacé, des semaines durant, les citoyens Roms dans le village hongrois de Gyöngyöspata, <Alignment alignment="6513" annotation_id="32537">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32537" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le gouvernement hongrois n'a pris des mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32586">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        <Alignment alignment="9567" annotation_id="32589">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32589" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">une fois que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les tensions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32615">et</DiscourseConnective> les provocations ont dégénéré en violences.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29685" docOffset="195">
      <en>I fear that <Alignment alignment="12970" annotation_id="29697">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29697" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europe does not show willingness to play a greater role in the improvement of the situation of the Roma people than what was mentioned in the Commission Communication, similar situations will occur again and again.</en>
      <fr>Je crains <Alignment alignment="29697" annotation_id="32672">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32672" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Europe ne montre pas sa volonté de jouer un rôle plus actif dans l'amélioration de la situation des Roms <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32786">que</DiscourseConnective> celui décrit dans la communication de la Commission, des situations semblables se reproduiront sans fin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29915" docOffset="196">
      <en>It is not yet too late to make changes.</en>
      <fr>Il n'est pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32908">encore</DiscourseConnective> trop tard <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="32925">pour</DiscourseConnective> procéder à des changements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="29955" docOffset="197">
      <en>We would like to hear the speech of Commissioner Viviane Reding on these issues.</en>
      <fr>Nous voudrions entendre l'intervention de la commissaire Viviane Reding sur ces questions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="30036" id="231" name="Teresa Riera Madurell">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="30036" docOffset="198">
      <en>(ES) Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to ask for your attention to remind you that this year has been proclaimed the International Year of Chemistry, in commemoration of Marie Curie being awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry exactly 100 years ago.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Madame la Présidente, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33085">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je voudrais demander votre attention et vous rappeler <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33153">que</DiscourseConnective> cette année a été proclamée Année internationale de la chimie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33220">en</DiscourseConnective> hommage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33231">à</DiscourseConnective> Marie Curie, lauréate du prix Nobel de Chimie il y a exactement 100 ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30305" docOffset="199">
      <en>With the slogan 'Chemistry - Our life, Our future', it is about making society more aware of chemistry's contribution to our well-being.</en>
      <fr>Le slogan "La chimie: notre vie, notre avenir" vise à sensibiliser davantage la société à la contribution de la chimie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33425">à</DiscourseConnective> notre bien-être.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30442" docOffset="200">
      <en>Chemistry has made possible vaccines and antibiotics that have doubled our life expectancy, <Alignment alignment="4908" annotation_id="30534">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30534" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is key to developing new energy sources and improving food.</en>
      <fr>La chimie a permis de mettre au point les vaccins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33494">et</DiscourseConnective> les antibiotiques qui ont doublé notre espérance de vie, <Alignment alignment="23185" annotation_id="33554">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33554" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> est essentielle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33573">pour</DiscourseConnective> développer de nouvelles sources d'énergie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33620">et</DiscourseConnective> améliorer les aliments.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30601" docOffset="201">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="29382" annotation_id="30601">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30601" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the chemistry industry is a strategic sector in Europe, with 25 000 companies that employ, directly or indirectly, five million people.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="20472" annotation_id="33647">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33647" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'industrie chimique est un secteur stratégique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33705">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe, regroupant 25 000 entreprises qui emploient, directement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33773">ou</DiscourseConnective> indirectement, cinq millions de personnes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30750" docOffset="202">
      <en>We in Parliament must, <Alignment alignment="9008" annotation_id="30773">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30773" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, do everything we can to make the International Year of Chemistry a success <Alignment alignment="28135" annotation_id="30859">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30859" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="53570" annotation_id="30868">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30868" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Marie Curie said, 'now is the time to understand more, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="30926" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective> we may fear less'.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="5429" annotation_id="33831">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33831" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, au Parlement, faire tout notre possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33877">pour que</DiscourseConnective> l'Année internationale de la chimie soit un succès <Alignment alignment="25794" annotation_id="33937">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33937" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="6592" annotation_id="33948">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="33948" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'a dit Marie Curie, "dans la vie, rien n'est à craindre, tout est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="34021">à</DiscourseConnective> comprendre".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="30953" docOffset="203">
      <en>Celebrating this year is a good time to take that on board.</en>
      <fr>La célébration de cette année est le moment opportun d'en tenir compte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="31013" id="232" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="31013" docOffset="204">
      <en>That concludes the item.</en>
      <fr>Ce point de l'ordre du jour est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
