<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>8.</en>
    <fr>8.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Regulation applying a scheme of generalised tariff preferences (vote)</en>
    <fr>Règlement appliquant un schéma de préférences tarifaires généralisées (vote)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="73" id="106" language="FR" name="Yannick Jadot">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="73" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, I should like to table an oral amendment to this amendment, deleting two parts of the amendment, namely the words 'by the Colombian army' and 'on Colombia'.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. - Monsieur le Président, je souhaiterais déposer un amendement oral sur cet amendement, en supprimant deux parties de l'amendement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="240">soit</DiscourseConnective> les termes "par l'armée colombienne" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="282">et</DiscourseConnective> "sur la Colombie".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="244" docOffset="3">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="244" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>, the amendment reads as follows: 'considers that the alarming news concerning the killings of trade unionists in Colombia, as well <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="385" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> the news recently received and now confirmed by Colombia's public prosecutor that mass graves containing the bodies of hundreds of people killed in recent years have been discovered in the region of La Macarena, are sufficient evidence to enable the Commission to open an investigation in accordance with the regulation.'</en>
      <fr>Du coup, l'amendement se lit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="333">comme</DiscourseConnective> tel: "estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="352">que</DiscourseConnective> les nouvelles alarmantes concernant l'assassinat de syndicalistes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="422">en</DiscourseConnective> Colombie, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="435">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les nouvelles reçues récemment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="476">et</DiscourseConnective> désormais confirmées par le procureur général de Colombie, selon lesquelles des fosses communes contenant des centaines de corps de personnes tuées ces dernières années ont été découvertes dans la région de la Macarena, constituent des motifs suffisants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="733">pour</DiscourseConnective> permettre à la Commission d'ouvrir une enquête conformément au règlement."</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
