<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Civilian-military cooperation and the development of civilian-military capabilities (short presentation)</en>
    <fr>Coopération civilo-militaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29">et</DiscourseConnective> développement des capacités civilo-militaires (brève présentation)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="105" id="242" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="105" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the report by Christian Ehler, on behalf of the Committee on Foreign Affairs, on civilian-military cooperation and the development of civilian-military capabilities.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de Christian Ehler, au nom de la commission des affaires étrangères, sur la coopération civilo-militaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="239">et</DiscourseConnective> le développement des capacités civilo-militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="288" id="243" language="DE" name="Christian Ehler">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="288" docOffset="2">
      <en>Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, at an international level, the Member States of the European Union have undertaken to make a significant contribution to civil and military crisis management capabilities throughout the world.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="348">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, au niveau international, les États membres de l'Union européenne se sont engagés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="443">à</DiscourseConnective> apporter une contribution importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="482">à</DiscourseConnective> la gestion de crise au niveau militaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="524">et</DiscourseConnective> civil dans le monde entier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="534" docOffset="3">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24812" annotation_id="534">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="534" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in many cases, we simply pay lip-service to this undertaking, which is formulated several times in the Helsinki Headline Goal as well as elsewhere.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="534" annotation_id="555">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="555" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, dans bon nombre de cas, nous avons manifesté un intérêt de pure forme envers cet engagement, formulé à plusieurs reprises dans l'objectif global d'Helsinki, entre autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="691" docOffset="4">
      <en>Let me put it in black and white: 25% of the positions approved by the Member States for the European Union's currently active civil missions, such as EULEX or EUPOL, are unfilled.</en>
      <fr>Je vais être clair: 25 % des postes approuvés par les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="805">pour</DiscourseConnective> les missions civiles actuelles de l'Union européenne, telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="871">qu'</DiscourseConnective>EULEX <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="880">ou</DiscourseConnective> EUPOL, sont vacants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="872" docOffset="5">
      <en>The objectives and structures for the civil and military capabilities of the European Union repeatedly formulated by the Member States could hardly be further from reality.</en>
      <fr>Les objectifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="918">et</DiscourseConnective> les structures des capacités militaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="961">et</DiscourseConnective> civiles de l'Union européenne, sans cesse formulés par les États membres, pourraient difficilement être plus éloignés de la réalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1045" docOffset="6">
      <en>That is why the European Parliament has decided to produce an own-initiative report on the development of civil and military structures and coordination in the European Union.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1097">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen a décidé d'élaborer un rapport d'initiative sur le développement des structures civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1222">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1236">et</DiscourseConnective> sur la coordination au sein de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1221" docOffset="7">
      <en>Specifically: Parliament once again states in this report that the particular civil and military capabilities of the European Union are one of the most important instruments in its foreign policy and common security and defence policy.</en>
      <fr>Pour être plus précis, le Parlement a une fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1337">encore</DiscourseConnective> énoncé dans ce rapport <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1367">que</DiscourseConnective> les capacités civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1393">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires spécifiques de l'Union européenne comptent parmi les instruments les plus importants de sa politique étrangère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1518">et</DiscourseConnective> de sa politique de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1549">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense commune.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1457" docOffset="8">
      <en>We have taken an unusual route in facing up to Parliament's responsibilities in the context of the Lisbon process.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous sommes engagés sur une voie inhabituelle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1623">en</DiscourseConnective> endossant les responsabilités du Parlement dans le cadre du processus de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1572" docOffset="9">
      <en>We did not start with a report, but <Alignment alignment="21405" annotation_id="1608">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1608" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">instead</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> began by creating the empirical basis for this report.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'avons pas débuté par un rapport, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1749">mais</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="8417" annotation_id="1754">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1754" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">plutôt</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1761">en</DiscourseConnective> créant une base empirique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1790">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce dernier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1671" docOffset="10">
      <en>We have formulated very specific proposals based on these figures, which is why we have the support of the broad majority of the Committee on Foreign Affairs: on a strategic level, we have made concrete proposals for the establishment of a structure of equal partnership between the military and civilian arms of the new European External Action Service; <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2026" sense="Comparison.Concession">while</DiscourseConnective>, on an operative level, we have resolved to establish a permanent European headquarters, to be staffed with personnel by the Member States, to deal with the issue of creating an attractive system of incentives for national experts to participate in such operations and the build-up of personnel reserves for the future.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons présenté des propositions très particulières basées sur ces chiffres, c'est pourquoi nous avons recueilli le soutien d'une large majorité de la commission des affaires étrangères: d'un point de vue stratégique, nous avons avancé des propositions concrètes pour la mise en place d'une structure de partenariat égal entre les branches civile et militaire du nouveau service européen pour l'action extérieure; tandis que d'un point de vue opérationnel, nous avons décidé d'établir un état major européen permanent, dont le personnel sera fourni par les États membres. Il visera à mettre en place un système attrayant, qui encourage les experts nationaux à participer à de telles opérations, et à créer une réserve de personnel pour l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2352" docOffset="11">
      <en>We have made specific proposals for the training of civil and military personnel.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons présenté des propositions spécifiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2606">pour</DiscourseConnective> la formation du personnel civil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2643">et</DiscourseConnective> militaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2434" docOffset="12">
      <en>There are concrete proposals for how start-up missions are to be financed, <Alignment alignment="2744" annotation_id="2509">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2509" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the establishment of a start-up fund according to Article 41 of the treaty.</en>
      <fr>Plusieurs propositions concrètes indiquent comment financer les missions de lancement, <Alignment alignment="65" annotation_id="2744">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2744" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> en instaurant un fonds de lancement, conformément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2806">à</DiscourseConnective> l'article 41 du traité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2598" docOffset="13">
      <en>Proposals are on the table for the instruments of crisis management, in particular, the question of greater future cooperation between police and military forces.</en>
      <fr>Des propositions sont sur la table <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2867">pour</DiscourseConnective> les instruments de gestion de crise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2909">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> la question d'une plus grande coopération à venir entre les forces de police <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3001">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2761" docOffset="14">
      <en>One example of this is the European policing troop.</en>
      <fr>Les troupes de police européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3050">en</DiscourseConnective> sont un bon exemple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2813" docOffset="15">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8869" annotation_id="2813">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2813" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the question arises as to how these two instruments can be linked together in specific operational cases <Alignment alignment="27760" annotation_id="2927">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2927" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> how we can manage the issue of separating purely military and civil operations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2813" annotation_id="3074">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3074" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il reste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3094">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir comment combiner ces instruments lors d'opérations spécifiques <Alignment alignment="2927" annotation_id="3166">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3166" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> comment résoudre la question de séparer les opérations purement militaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3244">ou</DiscourseConnective> civiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3011" docOffset="16">
      <en>We have made proposals for the future of the battle groups.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons également avancé des propositions concernant l'avenir des groupements tactiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3071" docOffset="17">
      <en>We are calling for a new approach to this issue.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons une nouvelle approche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3385">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3120" docOffset="18">
      <en>We want to see the battle groups being financed in accordance with the Athena mechanism.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3413">que</DiscourseConnective> les groupements tactiques soient financés selon le mécanisme ATHENA.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3209" docOffset="19">
      <en>We are calling for the further development of the capabilities of the battle groups in line with the Oslo directives, the strengthening of the ability of the battle groups to secure civil missions, and a widening of the definition of the missions of the battle groups.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3501">à</DiscourseConnective> ce que les capacités des groupements tactiques soient davantage développées conformément aux directives d'Oslo, à ce que leur aptitude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3638">à</DiscourseConnective> assurer les missions civiles soit renforcée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3684">et</DiscourseConnective> à ce que la définition de leurs missions soit élargie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3478" docOffset="20">
      <en>We are considering the issue of research and technology, the question of dual use, and the inclusion of civil and military missions in the security research programme as part of the European Union's research programme.</en>
      <fr>Nous étudions les questions de la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3786">et</DiscourseConnective> de la technologie et du double usage, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3827">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que l'inclusion des missions civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3870">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires dans le programme de recherche sur la sécurité en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3934">tant que</DiscourseConnective> partie intégrante du programme de recherche de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3697" docOffset="21">
      <en>We are dealing with concrete questions in relation to equipment and stockpiling, as well as international cooperation with the United Nations and NATO.</en>
      <fr>Nous traitons des questions concrètes concernant l'équipement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4072">et</DiscourseConnective> le stockage, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4088">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la coopération internationale avec les Nations unies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4151">et</DiscourseConnective> l'OTAN.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3849" docOffset="22">
      <en>Our main concern here is the avoidance of duplication, the improved use of existing structures, the question of the consolidation of shared air transport capacities and the question of the implementation of the Berlin Plus Agreements for improved cooperation between the two organisations in the event of a crisis.</en>
      <fr>Notre principale préoccupation à ce sujet est d'éviter la duplication, d'améliorer l'utilisation des structures existantes, de consolider les moyens communs de transport aérien <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4339">et</DiscourseConnective> de mettre en œuvre les accords "Berlin Plus" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4387">pour</DiscourseConnective> améliorer la coopération entre les deux organisations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4446">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de crise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4164" docOffset="23">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8546" annotation_id="4164">
          <Alignment alignment="2156" annotation_id="4164">
            <Alignment alignment="20580" annotation_id="4164">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4164" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, Parliament has lived up to its new tasks and obligations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1678" annotation_id="4463">
          <Alignment alignment="4164" annotation_id="4463">
            <Alignment alignment="3063" annotation_id="4463">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4463" sense="Expansion.Restatement">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, le Parlement a respecté ses nouvelles tâches <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4528">et</DiscourseConnective> obligations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4238" docOffset="24">
      <en>The report was supported by a broad majority from all groups in the Committee on Foreign Affairs <Alignment alignment="12936" annotation_id="4335">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4335" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we see it as an important contribution to the future establishment of civil and military structures in the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport a été soutenu par une large majorité de tous les groupes de la commission des affaires étrangères, <Alignment alignment="4335" annotation_id="4654">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4654" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> représente à nos yeux une contribution importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4707">à</DiscourseConnective> la mise en place future des structures civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4756">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires au sein de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4462" id="244" name="Csanád Szegedi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4462" docOffset="25">
      <en>(HU) Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, the first and most important point we must clarify is whether we consider it important for civilian and military forces to work together appropriately.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Madame la Présidente, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4837">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, le premier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4862">et</DiscourseConnective> le plus important des points que nous devons clarifier consiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4929">à</DiscourseConnective> déterminer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4942">si</DiscourseConnective> la collaboration appropriée des forces civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4992">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires revêt une importance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4658" docOffset="26">
      <en>For me personally and for my party, Jobbik - The Movement for a Better Hungary - the answer is clearly yes: we consider cooperation between civilians and military authorities to be important.</en>
      <fr>Selon moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5038">et</DiscourseConnective> mon parti, Jobbik - le Mouvement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5074">pour</DiscourseConnective> une meilleure Hongrie - la réponse est clairement affirmative: nous estimons que la coopération entre les autorités civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5203">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires est importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4850" docOffset="27">
      <en>Now, a very good example of this in Hungary was the Magyar Gárda (Hungarian Guard), which was founded in 2007 and was able to work well - <Alignment alignment="4820" annotation_id="4988">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4988" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you will - with the military authorities, be that in floodwater defences, in helping the victims of the red sludge flood, in giving blood or distributing bread, <Alignment alignment="5586" annotation_id="5152">
          <Alignment alignment="761" annotation_id="5152">
            <Alignment alignment="5586" annotation_id="5152">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5152" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in other words</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, in social matters.</en>
      <fr>À présent, un excellent exemple hongrois illustrant mes propos est la Magyar Gárda (la Garde hongroise), qui a été fondée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5355">en</DiscourseConnective> 2007 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5363">et</DiscourseConnective> est capable de bien collaborer, <Alignment alignment="1020" annotation_id="5398">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5398" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'on veut, avec les autorités militaires. Elle intervient pour protéger contre les eaux de crue, aider les victimes de l'inondation de boue rouge, donner du sang <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5563">ou</DiscourseConnective> distribuer du pain, <Alignment alignment="5152" annotation_id="5586">
          <Alignment alignment="5152" annotation_id="5586">
            <Alignment alignment="5152" annotation_id="5586">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5586" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, dans les affaires sociales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5187" docOffset="28">
      <en>You may rightly ask what reward they have received - state honours or recognition perhaps?</en>
      <fr>Vous vous demandez peut-être et à juste titre quelle a été récompense? Les honneurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5718">ou</DiscourseConnective> la reconnaissance de l'État?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5278" docOffset="29">
      <en>They have received nothing, <Alignment alignment="18902" annotation_id="5306">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5306" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> instead of thanking these people for their self-sacrifice, the Hungarian Government made the baffling decision to disband the Hungarian Guard.</en>
      <fr>Non, elle n'a rien reçu, <Alignment alignment="5306" annotation_id="5775">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5775" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5778">au lieu de</DiscourseConnective> remercier ses membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5811">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur dévouement, le gouvernement hongrois a pris la décision déconcertante de dissoudre la Garde hongroise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5453" docOffset="30">
      <en>For this reason, in order that we may start cooperation between civilian and military forces, we need to honour individuals who participate in organisations like the Hungarian Guard.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5924">Ainsi</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5931">afin que</DiscourseConnective> nous puissions instaurer la coopération entre les forces civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6005">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires, il convient d'honorer les citoyens qui prennent part <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6073">à</DiscourseConnective> des organisations telles que la Garde hongroise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5636" docOffset="31">
      <en>People who wish to take part in such organisations out of a love for their country and nation, protecting their environment, must be allowed to work and must be valued members of society.</en>
      <fr>Les individus qui souhaitent s'investir dans de telles organisations par amour <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6203">pour</DiscourseConnective> leur pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6218">et</DiscourseConnective> leur nation, protégeant ainsi leur environnement, doivent être autorisés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6294">à</DiscourseConnective> le faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6305">et</DiscourseConnective> considérés comme des membres précieux de la société.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="5824" id="245" name="Martin Ehrenhauser">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="5824" docOffset="32">
      <en>(DE) Madam President, the combination of civil and military powers is nothing new.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Madame la Présidente, l'association des pouvoirs civils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6422">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires n'a rien de nouveau.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5907" docOffset="33">
      <en>Take, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5913" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>, the Command Centre, which has been in place in Council for some time now.</en>
      <fr>Prenons l'exemple du centre de commande, mis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6502">en</DiscourseConnective> place au Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6522">depuis</DiscourseConnective> un certain temps.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6000" docOffset="34">
      <en>Military and civil information has already been collated here.</en>
      <fr>Les informations civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6572">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires y sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6593">déjà</DiscourseConnective> collectées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6063" docOffset="35">
      <en>The Situation Centre is now to move to the External Action Service.</en>
      <fr>Le centre de situation va à présent être transféré vers le service pour l'action extérieure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6131" docOffset="36">
      <en>I think it important to emphasise above all that the European Union has gained a high profile on the international front for its civil mechanisms, something that has brought the European Union a great deal of positive recognition.</en>
      <fr>Selon moi, nous devons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6726">avant</DiscourseConnective> tout souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6747">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne a acquis une position très <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6797">en</DiscourseConnective> vue au niveau international <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6828">pour</DiscourseConnective> ses mécanismes civils, ce qui lui a valu une grande reconnaissance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6362" docOffset="37">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="18850" annotation_id="6362">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6362" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I believe we need a clear separation of civil and military powers.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6362" annotation_id="6901">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6901" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, j'estime que nous devons clairement séparer les pouvoirs civils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6976">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6438" docOffset="38">
      <en>At this point I would like to pick up on something that Mr Szegedi mentioned a moment ago.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6991">À</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet, je souhaiterais poursuivre sur un élément mentionné par M. Szegedi voici un moment déjà.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6529" docOffset="39">
      <en>I would like to express my grave misgivings about the march organised by the Hungarian Jobbik party in Austria's Burgenland province recently, at which rifles and fixed bayonets were in evidence.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaiterais exprimer mes craintes sérieuses concernant la marche récemment organisée par le parti hongrois Jobbik dans la province autrichienne de Burgenland, lors de laquelle des armes à feu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7288">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que des baïonnettes au canon ont été observées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6725" docOffset="40">
      <en>I do not believe that this is in any way acceptable.</en>
      <fr>Je ne peux pas croire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7364">que</DiscourseConnective> cette situation puisse être acceptée de quelque manière qu'il soit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6778" docOffset="41">
      <en>I would like to express my clear opposition to such actions.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaite faire part de mon opposition catégorique contre de telles actions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6839" docOffset="42">
      <en>There can be little doubt that they run contrary to the European spirit.</en>
      <fr>Il ne fait aucun doute <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7538">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles vont à l'encontre de l'esprit européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6912" docOffset="43">
      <en>(The speaker agreed to take a blue card question under Rule 149(8))</en>
      <fr>(L'orateur accepte de répondre à une question "carton bleu" (article 149, paragraphe 8, du règlement))</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6980" id="246" name="Csanád Szegedi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6980" docOffset="44">
      <en>(HU) Madam President, I would like a very, very short answer.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Madame la Présidente, je souhaiterais très brièvement répondre à cette question. Les propos tenus par le député ne sont que des mensonges.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7042" docOffset="45">
      <en>What my fellow Member says is simply a lie.</en>
      <fr>Le parti Jobbik - le Mouvement pour une meilleure Hongrie - tout comme la Garde hongroise n'ont jamais commis aucun délit, ce que tout un chacun peut facilement vérifier, et n'ont jamais entravé la loi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7086" docOffset="46">
      <en>Neither Jobbik - The Movement for a Better Hungary - nor the Hungarian Guard has ever committed any crime - anyone can easily check this out - and has never defied any law, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7259" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="8037" annotation_id="7263">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7263" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is simply part of neoliberal political propaganda which tries to show them in a bad light, for neither the Hungarian Guard nor members of Jobbik have ever come into any conflict with the law, <Alignment alignment="10181" annotation_id="7470">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7470" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we intend to continue to act in accordance with the law.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4311" annotation_id="8037">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8037" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces propos relèvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8072">simplement</DiscourseConnective> de la propagande politique néolibérale, qui tente de les montrer sous un angle défavorable. Aucun membre du parti Jobbik ou de la Garde hongroise n'a été <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8237">en</DiscourseConnective> conflit avec la loi, <Alignment alignment="7470" annotation_id="8261">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8261" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons bien l'intention de continuer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8305">à</DiscourseConnective> agir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8312">en</DiscourseConnective> toute légalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7531" id="247" name="Martin Ehrenhauser">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7531" docOffset="47">
      <en>(DE) Madam President, I never suggested that the Jobbik party had been guilty of criminal wrongdoing.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Madame la Présidente, jamais je n'ai insinué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8381">que</DiscourseConnective> le parti Jobbik était coupable de méfaits criminels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7633" docOffset="48">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="8438" annotation_id="7633">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7633" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I did claim that a targeted mobilisation took place with rifles and fixed bayonets in Burgenland.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4111" annotation_id="8438">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8438" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, j'ai effectivement déclaré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8476">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une mobilisation ciblée avait eu lieu avec des armes à feu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8538">et</DiscourseConnective> des baïonnettes au canon dans la province de Burgenland.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7740" docOffset="49">
      <en>You have not denied that this was indeed the case.</en>
      <fr>Vous n'avez pas nié les faits.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7791" id="248" name="Maria Damanaki">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7791" docOffset="50">
      <en>Member of the Commission. - Madam President, I will focus on the report, <Alignment alignment="3347" annotation_id="7864">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7864" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is an extremely useful and important report.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, je vais me concentrer sur le rapport, <Alignment alignment="7864" annotation_id="8689">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8689" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">puisqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il est d'une importance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8720">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une utilité extrêmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7918" docOffset="51">
      <en>I would like to thank Mr Ehrenhauser for his contribution.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaiterai remercier M. Ehrenhauser d'y avoir contribué.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7977" docOffset="52">
      <en>The report is useful <Alignment alignment="4565" annotation_id="7998">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7998" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it rightly focuses on the key element of civil-military cooperation, which is exactly the Commission's priority.</en>
      <fr>Ce rapport est utile <Alignment alignment="7998" annotation_id="8829">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8829" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il se concentre à juste titre sur l'élément principal de la coopération civilo-militaire, ce qui est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8939">précisément</DiscourseConnective> la priorité de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8119" docOffset="53">
      <en>It deals with the main points related to the EU's comprehensive approach in crisis management.</en>
      <fr>Il traite des points principaux liés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9018">à</DiscourseConnective> l'approche globale de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9047">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de gestion de crise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8214" docOffset="54">
      <en>The establishment of the European External Action Service is the exact expression of this priority.</en>
      <fr>La mise en place du service européen pour l'action extérieure est l'expression exacte de cette priorité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8314" docOffset="55">
      <en>The very concept of the service that the High Representative is putting in place points in the same direction as the one suggested in the report, in particular, through the inclusion of the structures of the Common Security and Defence Policy in the External Action Service.</en>
      <fr>Le concept <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9195">même</DiscourseConnective> du service <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9211">que</DiscourseConnective> la haute représentante est en train de mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9261">en</DiscourseConnective> place suit la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9278">même</DiscourseConnective> direction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9293">que</DiscourseConnective> celui suggéré dans le rapport, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9328">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> grâce à l'inclusion des structures de la politique de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9406">et</DiscourseConnective> défense commune dans le service pour l'action extérieure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8589" docOffset="56">
      <en>We fully support the development of civilian capabilities in order to have a proper balance between resources.</en>
      <fr>Nous soutenons pleinement le développement des capacités civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9532">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>équilibrer adéquatement les ressources.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8700" docOffset="57">
      <en>The appropriate modalities for recruitment are now agreed, <Alignment alignment="26917" annotation_id="8759">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8759" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> appropriate expertise can be brought into the External Action Service.</en>
      <fr>Les modalités de recrutement appropriées sont à présent approuvées, <Alignment alignment="8759" annotation_id="9647">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9647" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">de sorte que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le service pour l'action extérieure peut bénéficier des compétences adéquates.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8834" docOffset="58">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7938" annotation_id="8834">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8834" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> everyone knows, this was not possible before.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4643" annotation_id="9739">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9739" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez, cela n'était pas possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9786">auparavant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8883" docOffset="59">
      <en>A number of points in the report have been taken into account, <Alignment alignment="9862" annotation_id="8946">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8946" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> specific actions have been launched. This relates, in particular, to fostering civil-military synergies, better usability of the EU battle groups, training, financing, and cooperation with key partners, in particular, NATO and the United Nations.</en>
      <fr>Plusieurs éléments de ce rapport ont été pris en considération, <Alignment alignment="8946" annotation_id="9862">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9862" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des actions spécifiques ont été entreprises, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9910">notamment</DiscourseConnective> pour ce qui est d'encourager les synergies civilo-militaires, une plus grande utilité des groupements tactiques de l'UE, la formation, le financement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10070">et</DiscourseConnective> la coopération avec les principaux partenaires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10121">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> l'OTAN <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10143">et</DiscourseConnective> les Nations unies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9197" docOffset="60">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="25265" annotation_id="9200">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9200" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> support the reinforcement of relations between the EU and the United Nations.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9200" annotation_id="10165">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10165" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous soutenons le renforcement des relations entre l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10231">et</DiscourseConnective> les Nations unies.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9283" docOffset="61">
      <en>We have already done a lot together.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10264">déjà</DiscourseConnective> réalisé un beau parcours ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9320" docOffset="62">
      <en>The High Representative again met with the UN Secretary General in Lisbon last Saturday.</en>
      <fr>La haute représentante s'est à nouveau entretenue avec le secrétaire générale des Nations unies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10400">à</DiscourseConnective> Lisbonne samedi dernier.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9409" docOffset="63">
      <en>The relationship between the EU and NATO is an important issue, as was illustrated just yesterday at the NATO summit in Lisbon.</en>
      <fr>La relation entre l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10450">et</DiscourseConnective> l'OTAN revêt une importance considérable, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10495">comme</DiscourseConnective> l'a montré hier le sommet de l'OTAN <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10537">à</DiscourseConnective> Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9537" docOffset="64">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="10564" annotation_id="9540">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9540" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> favour implementing all practical measures which can reinforce concrete cooperation between the EU and NATO and ensure, in particular, cooperation <Alignment alignment="17040" annotation_id="9692">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9692" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> both are deployed in the same theatre.</en>
      <fr>Nous soutenons <Alignment alignment="9540" annotation_id="10564">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10564" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la mise en œuvre de toutes les mesures pratiques qui peuvent renforcer la coopération concrète entre l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10680">et</DiscourseConnective> l'OTAN, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10691">et</DiscourseConnective> garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10703">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> la coopération <Alignment alignment="983" annotation_id="10733">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10733" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les deux organisations déploient leurs forces au <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10790">même</DiscourseConnective> endroit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9736" docOffset="65">
      <en>The Commission and the High Representative herself are looking forward to working together with the European Parliament on this important issue of civil-military cooperation.</en>
      <fr>La Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10818">et</DiscourseConnective> la haute représentante en personne se réjouissent de collaborer avec le Parlement européen sur la question importante de la coopération civilo-militaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9911" id="249" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9911" docOffset="66">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9933" docOffset="67">
      <en>The vote will take place on Tuesday, 23 November 2010.</en>
      <fr>Le vote aura lieu mardi 23 novembre 2010.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9988" docOffset="68">
      <en>Written statements (Rule 149)</en>
      <fr>Déclarations écrites (article 149)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10018" id="992" language="PL" name="Krzysztof Lisek">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10018" docOffset="69">
      <en>Civil-military cooperation and the development of civil-military potential is one of the most important components of the common security and defence policy.</en>
      <fr>La coopération civilo-militaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11103">et</DiscourseConnective> le développement du potentiel civilo-militaire est un des composants les plus importants de la politique de sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11223">et</DiscourseConnective> de défense commune.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10176" docOffset="70">
      <en>Unfortunately, many aspects relating thereto remain at the planning stage.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11246">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, de nombreux aspects y afférents ne restent qu'au stade de projet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10251" docOffset="71">
      <en>In discussions on the subject, Member States agree that significant resources should be provided for this.</en>
      <fr>Lors de discussions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11349">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet, les États membres ont admis que <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11393">pour</DiscourseConnective> y parvenir, d'importantes ressources devraient être allouées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10358" docOffset="72">
      <en>In reality, the plans have not been implemented <Alignment alignment="17580" annotation_id="10406">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10406" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we still do not have fully formed structures.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11460">En réalité</DiscourseConnective>, les projets n'ont pas été mis en œuvre, <Alignment alignment="6787" annotation_id="11512">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11512" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous n'avons toujours pas élaboré complètement des structures.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10456" docOffset="73">
      <en>In view of the growing threat posed by natural disasters, terrorist acts and conflicts beyond the borders of the EU, I hope that this report will contribute to the exploitation of civil-military potential and civil-military cooperation.</en>
      <fr>Au vu de la menace grandissante que représentent les catastrophes naturelles, les actes terroristes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11678">et</DiscourseConnective> les conflits au-delà des frontières de l'UE, j'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11735">que</DiscourseConnective> ce rapport contribuera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11762">à</DiscourseConnective> l'exploitation du potentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11792">et</DiscourseConnective> de la coopération civilo-militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10693" docOffset="74">
      <en>The report contains practical recommendations in this field, inter alia, with reference to the creation of civil-military structures within the European External Action Service, the use of battlegroups and the European Gendarmerie Force, optimisation of crisis management and the use of funds from the next framework programme.</en>
      <fr>Le rapport comporte des recommandations pratiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11882">à</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet, renvoyant entre autres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11918">à</DiscourseConnective> la création de structures civilo-militaires au sein du service européen pour l'action extérieure, à l'utilisation des groupements tactiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12060">et</DiscourseConnective> de la force de gendarmerie européenne, à l'optimisation de la gestion de crise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12142">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'utilisation des fonds issu du prochain programme-cadre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11021" docOffset="75">
      <en>The aim of all this is to make better use of funds <Alignment alignment="14139" annotation_id="11072">
          <Alignment alignment="12262" annotation_id="11072">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11072" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> civil-military cooperation may fully materialise.</en>
      <fr>L'objectif de tout cela est de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12236">mieux</DiscourseConnective> utiliser les fonds, <Alignment alignment="11863" annotation_id="12262">
          <Alignment alignment="9837" annotation_id="12262">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12262" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de sorte que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> la coopération civilo-militaire puisse pleinement se concrétiser.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11130" docOffset="76">
      <en>A further significant aim is to avoid duplication of efforts during missions where NATO is participating in tandem with European forces.</en>
      <fr>Un autre objectif important est d'éviter la duplication des efforts lors des missions auxquelles l'OTAN participe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12455">en</DiscourseConnective> tandem avec les forces européennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11267" docOffset="77">
      <en>I hope that the report will be a significant incentive to start working towards the formation of effective civil-military structures.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12503">que</DiscourseConnective> le rapport donnera une impulsion importante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12551">pour</DiscourseConnective> débuter la mise en place de structures civilo-militaires efficaces.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11401" docOffset="78">
      <en>Baroness Ashton should ensure that the suggestions contained in the report are implemented as quickly as possible.</en>
      <fr>Mme Ashton devrait veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12656">que</DiscourseConnective> les propositions avancées dans ce rapport soient mises en œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12724">aussi</DiscourseConnective> rapidement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12741">que</DiscourseConnective> possible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11516" id="250" language="RO" name="Petru Constantin Luhan">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11516" docOffset="79">
      <en>The European Union must respond rapidly in crisis situations, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11578" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thereby</DiscourseConnective> necessitating more efficient coordination of its civilian and military structures.</en>
      <fr>l'Union européenne doit répondre rapidement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12799">en</DiscourseConnective> situation de crise, ce qui nécessite une coordination plus efficace de ses structures civiles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12896">et</DiscourseConnective> militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11669" docOffset="80">
      <en>Setting up a permanent EU operational headquarters, placed alongside the Civilian Planning and Conduct Capability, would maximise the benefits of civil-military coordination.</en>
      <fr>L'instauration d'un état-major opérationnel permanent de l'UE, aux côtés de la capacité civile de planification <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13023">et</DiscourseConnective> de conduite, maximiserait les avantages de la coordination civilo-militaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11844" docOffset="81">
      <en>With regard to the request in the report for Member States to make available civilian capabilities in order to achieve real progress as quickly as possible, I want to stress that, on the civilian front, Romania actively contributes to fulfilling the Civilian Headline Goal 2010.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13103">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la demande formulée dans le rapport, selon laquelle les États membres devraient mettre leurs capacités civiles à la disposition de l'UE de sorte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13267">à</DiscourseConnective> accomplir un réel progrès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13295">aussi</DiscourseConnective> vite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13306">que</DiscourseConnective> possible, je souhaite souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13342">que</DiscourseConnective>, sur le plan civil, la Roumanie contribue activement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13399">à</DiscourseConnective> l'accomplissement de l'objectif global civil 2010.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12123" docOffset="82">
      <en>As a result of its considerable involvement in EU civilian missions, Romania has achieved third place in the European rankings in terms of participating in such missions and contributing sound and varied expertise through its police officers, military police officers, soldiers, diplomats, judges and human rights experts.</en>
      <fr>De par son engagement considérable dans les missions civiles de l'UE, la Roumanie se hisse à la troisième place du classement européen pour avoir participé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13608">à</DiscourseConnective> de telles missions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13629">et</DiscourseConnective> apporté des compétences solides <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13664">et</DiscourseConnective> variées au travers de ses officiers de police, officiers de police militaire, soldats, diplomates, juges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13772">et</DiscourseConnective> experts en droits de l'homme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12446" docOffset="83">
      <en>Romania is <Alignment alignment="6387" annotation_id="12457">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12457" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> at an advanced stage in the process of adopting a national civilian capabilities strategy.</en>
      <fr>La Roumanie est <Alignment alignment="12457" annotation_id="13821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13821" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13831">à</DiscourseConnective> un stade avancé du processus d'adoption d'une stratégie nationale en matière de capacités civiles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
