<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>2.</en>
    <fr>2.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>European Globalisation Adjustment Fund: ES/Region of Valencia (</en>
    <fr>Mobilisation du Fonds européen d'ajustement à la mondialisation: ES/Comunidad Valenciana (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="67" docOffset="2">
    <en>- Before the vote:</en>
    <fr>- <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="96">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="86" id="154" language="IT" name="Barbara Matera">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="86" docOffset="3">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, in the current context of economic crisis, one of the biggest problems that advanced economies are having to face is precisely that of unemployment, a threat that has reached the alarming level of 10% of the euro area.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="142">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="156">en</DiscourseConnective> ces temps de crise économique, l'un des plus graves problèmes auxquels doivent faire face les économies développées est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="279">précisément</DiscourseConnective> celui du chômage, une menace qui a atteint le seuil critique de 10 % dans la zone euro.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="341" docOffset="4">
      <en>The European institutions and, above all, the European Commission, in its draft budget for 2011, have introduced a series of measures to support the economic recovery, including supplementing the European Globalisation Adjustment Fund, for which I am rapporteur, and which is being called upon for four important mobilisation requests, on which we are about to vote.</en>
      <fr>Les institutions européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="408">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="411">surtout</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne, dans son projet de budget <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="471">pour</DiscourseConnective> 2010, ont introduit une série de mesures visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="524">à</DiscourseConnective> soutenir la reprise économique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="558">notamment</DiscourseConnective> un renforcement du Fonds européen d'ajustement à la mondialisation, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="636">pour</DiscourseConnective> lequel je suis rapporteure, un Fonds auquel nous faisons appel pour répondre à quatre importantes demandes de mobilisation, au sujet desquelles nous allons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="797">à</DiscourseConnective> présent voter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="708" docOffset="5">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="823" annotation_id="710">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="710" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> believe that the procedures for mobilising this fund should be streamlined, in order to respond quickly to workers whose companies have been hit by the economic crisis <Alignment alignment="1016" annotation_id="888">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="888" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> who have been affected by their companies' relocation processes.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <Alignment alignment="789" annotation_id="823">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="823" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il convient de rationaliser les procédures de mobilisation de ce fonds, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="907">afin de</DiscourseConnective> pouvoir aider rapidement les travailleurs dont les sociétés ont été touchées par la crise économique <Alignment alignment="700" annotation_id="1016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1016" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui ont été affectés par les processus de délocalisation de celles-ci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="957" docOffset="6">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="1101" annotation_id="959">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="959" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> urge my fellow Members to promote this fund within the individual Member States.</en>
      <fr>Je demande <Alignment alignment="3" annotation_id="1101">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1101" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> instamment à mes confrères de promouvoir ce fonds dans leurs États membres d'origine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
