<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Welcome</en>
    <fr>Souhaits de bienvenue</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="8" id="050" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8" docOffset="1">
      <en>Colleagues, I welcome the delegation from the EEA-EFTA Parliaments, that is our colleagues from Iceland, Liechtenstein and Norway, as well as the observers from the Swiss Federal Assembly, who are in the official gallery.</en>
      <fr>Chers collègues, je voudrais souhaiter la bienvenue à la délégation des parlements EEE/AELE, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="115">à</DiscourseConnective> savoir nos collègues d'Islande, du Liechtenstein <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="166">et</DiscourseConnective> de Norvège <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="180">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les observateurs de l'Assemblée fédérale suisse, qui ont pris place dans la tribune officielle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="230" docOffset="2">
      <en>It is a pleasure for me to welcome this delegation to the European Parliament in Strasbourg, where they will participate in the 35th EEA JPC meeting today and tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>C'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="292">pour</DiscourseConnective> moi un plaisir d'accueillir cette délégation au Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="364">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg, où ils participeront, aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="412">et</DiscourseConnective> demain, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="423">à</DiscourseConnective> la 35e réunion de la commission parlementaire mixte de l'EEE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="399" docOffset="3">
      <en>I hope that the well-established work of the EEA JPC this week will be productive and will contribute to enhanced parliamentary cooperation, as well as to ensuring democratic parliamentary supervision within the EEA.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="496">que</DiscourseConnective> le travail régulier de cette commission parlementaire mixte sera productif cette semaine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="589">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'il contribuera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="610">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la coopération parlementaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="651">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à garantir un contrôle démocratique parlementaire au sein de l'EEE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="616" docOffset="4">
      <en>Welcome, colleagues.</en>
      <fr>Soyez les bienvenus, chers collègues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
