<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Containers lost at sea and compensation (debate)</en>
    <fr>Conteneurs perdus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18">en</DiscourseConnective> mer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25">et</DiscourseConnective> indemnisation (débat)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="49" id="036" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="49" docOffset="1">
      <en>The next item is the debate on the oral question to the Commission on containers lost at sea and compensation by Brian Simpson, on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism - B7-0469/2010).</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle le débat sur la question orale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="105">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sur les conteneurs perdus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="147">en</DiscourseConnective> mer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="154">et</DiscourseConnective> l'indemnisation de Brian Simpson, au nom de la commission des transports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="230">et</DiscourseConnective> du tourisme - B7-0469/2010).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="246" id="037" name="Brian Simpson">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="246" docOffset="2">
      <en>author. - Mr President, <Alignment alignment="15201" annotation_id="270">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="270" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you said, I speak this morning on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism on an issue that has been overlooked for so long, namely containers falling from ships at sea.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="14889" annotation_id="300">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="300" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous l'avez dit, je prends la parole ce matin au nom de la commission des transports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="391">et</DiscourseConnective> du tourisme sur un sujet qui a été trop longtemps négligé: les conteneurs perdus en mer par des navires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="451" docOffset="3">
      <en>It is amazing to me that, in this modern day and age, thousands of these containers go missing each year, with the great majority of them falling off the ships into our oceans.</en>
      <fr>Je trouve incroyable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="520">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à notre époque des milliers de ces conteneurs disparaissent chaque année, la plupart tombant des navires dans nos océans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="628" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is estimated that a staggering 10 000 containers are lost at sea each year.</en>
      <fr>On estime au chiffre ahurissant de 10 000, le nombre de conteneurs perdus chaque année <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="732">en</DiscourseConnective> mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="707" docOffset="5">
      <en>It would appear to us that shipping lines and insurers are quite happy to accept this figure and do nothing about it.</en>
      <fr>Les compagnies maritimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="765">et</DiscourseConnective> les assureurs semblent être satisfaits de ce chiffre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="821">et</DiscourseConnective> ne font rien pour remédier à la situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="825" docOffset="6">
      <en>In European waters, 2 000 containers a year are lost at sea, <Alignment alignment="36962" annotation_id="886">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="886" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this figure would appear to be rising year on year.</en>
      <fr>Chaque année, 2 000 conteneurs sont perdus dans les eaux européennes, <Alignment alignment="8991" annotation_id="937">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="937" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ce chiffre paraît augmenter d'année en année.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="942" docOffset="7">
      <en>These containers are a menace to navigation, they could pollute the seas with both toxic and non-toxic materials, <Alignment alignment="30060" annotation_id="1056">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1056" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they leave local authorities with large clean-up costs.</en>
      <fr>Ces conteneurs constituent une menace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1024">pour</DiscourseConnective> la navigation, ils risquent de polluer les eaux avec des substances toxiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1106">et</DiscourseConnective> non toxiques, <Alignment alignment="20464" annotation_id="1123">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1123" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils laissent aux autorités locales des frais de nettoyage considérables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1116" docOffset="8">
      <en>The Transport Committee is now demanding action to reduce this figure and is sending a signal to the maritime industry that we are not prepared to tolerate this state of affairs much longer.</en>
      <fr>La commission des transports exige <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1234">à présent que</DiscourseConnective> des mesures soient prises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1274">pour</DiscourseConnective> réduire ce chiffre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1299">et</DiscourseConnective> envoie un signal au secteur maritime pour lui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1348">dire que</DiscourseConnective> nous ne sommes pas disposés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1385">à</DiscourseConnective> tolérer cette situation plus longtemps.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1307" docOffset="9">
      <en>The MARIN Institute in the Netherlands found the main reasons for container stack collapses were faulty lashings, overweight containers and faulty stowage.</en>
      <fr>L'institut MARIN aux Pays-Bas a trouvé que les principales causes des effondrements de piles de conteneurs résidaient dans un matériel de saisissage défectueux, dans des conteneurs en surpoids <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1620">et</DiscourseConnective> dans un mauvais arrimage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1463" docOffset="10">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="12954" annotation_id="1463">
          <Alignment alignment="1649" annotation_id="1463">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1463" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, crews on larger container ships have difficulty in assessing <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1537" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> severe loads are moving forward and/or aft due to weather conditions, which can amplify vertical acceleration in these areas beyond the vessel's actual design specifications.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13431" annotation_id="1649">
          <Alignment alignment="9901" annotation_id="1649">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1649" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En outre</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, les équipages des navires de grandes dimensions ont du mal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1718">à</DiscourseConnective> évaluer les mouvements de charges importantes vers l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1773">avant</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1779">et</DiscourseConnective> vers l'arrière qui se produisent du fait des conditions climatiques, ce qui peut amplifier l'accélération verticale au-delà des limites prévues lors de la conception du navire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1717" docOffset="11">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1959" annotation_id="1717">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1717" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Moreover</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the absence of a strict liability compensation convention for non-toxic substances leaves local government picking up the cost of the clean-up.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1717" annotation_id="1959">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1959" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'absence de convention en matière d'indemnisation et de responsabilité objective <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2055">pour</DiscourseConnective> les substances non toxiques signifie que les autorités locales doivent supporter les coûts de nettoyage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1871" docOffset="12">
      <en>Parliament is now demanding that shipping companies accept their responsibilities on this issue.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement exige désormais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2194">que</DiscourseConnective> les compagnies de transport maritime assument leurs responsabilités sur cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1968" docOffset="13">
      <en>We would like to see the Commission becoming more proactive in solving this unacceptable state of affairs.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaiterions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2305">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission prenne davantage d'initiatives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2354">pour</DiscourseConnective> résoudre cette situation inacceptable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2075" docOffset="14">
      <en>Today I am asking the Commission to study the results obtained by the Lashing@sea project and to come forward with proposals to improve container lashing procedures and equipment.</en>
      <fr>Je demande aujourd'hui à la Commission d'examiner les résultats du projet Lashing@sea <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2484">et</DiscourseConnective> de présenter des propositions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2517">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>améliorer les procédures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2549">et</DiscourseConnective> les équipements de saisissage des conteneurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2255" docOffset="15">
      <en>Secondly, we would like to see action to ensure that all containers are correctly weighed in port and correctly stowed <Alignment alignment="37856" annotation_id="2374">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2374" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a ship sets sail for sea, as well as fitting automated beacons to aid container location.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2598">Deuxièmement</DiscourseConnective>, nous souhaiterions que des mesures soient prises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2661">pour</DiscourseConnective> garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2675">que</DiscourseConnective> tous les conteneurs sont correctement pesés dans le port <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2736">et</DiscourseConnective> arrimés convenablement <Alignment alignment="6292" annotation_id="2762">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2762" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le navire ne prenne la mer, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2800">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2803">que</DiscourseConnective> les vaisseaux sont équipés de balises à activation automatique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2870">pour</DiscourseConnective> faciliter la localisation des conteneurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2471" docOffset="16">
      <en>Thirdly, we are asking the Commission to look at the compensation regime <Alignment alignment="3007" annotation_id="2544">
          <Alignment alignment="59994" annotation_id="2544">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2544" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> local and regional authorities are not left short-changed.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2917">Troisièmement</DiscourseConnective>, nous demandons à la Commission de se pencher sur le régime d'indemnisation <Alignment alignment="21288" annotation_id="3007">
          <Alignment alignment="2544" annotation_id="3007">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3007" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> les autorités locales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3038">et</DiscourseConnective> régionales ne soient pas laissées pour compte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2611" docOffset="17">
      <en>Finally, I want to return to the obligations of the wider maritime industry to get their act together.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3088">Pour finir</DiscourseConnective>, je veux revenir aux obligations du secteur maritime au sens large <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3166">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'amener à se ressaisir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2714" docOffset="18">
      <en>I appreciate that containers will be lost in severe storms.</en>
      <fr>Je comprends <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3209">que</DiscourseConnective> des conteneurs soient perdus lors de fortes tempêtes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2774" docOffset="19">
      <en>What I cannot accept is that containers are lost due to shoddy workmanship, or to containers being overloaded or incorrectly stacked, or because of a laissez-faire attitude to this problem by the industry at large.</en>
      <fr>Je ne peux pas accepter, en revanche, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3305">que</DiscourseConnective> des conteneurs soient perdus en raison de négligences humaines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3372">ou</DiscourseConnective> parce qu'ils sont surchargés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3404">ou</DiscourseConnective> mal empilés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3420">ou encore</DiscourseConnective> en raison de la nonchalance de l'ensemble du secteur vis-à-vis de ce problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2989" docOffset="20">
      <en>Containers falling off ships are dangerous.</en>
      <fr>Les conteneurs qui tombent des navires sont dangereux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3033" docOffset="21">
      <en>Losing 20 000 of them a year is unacceptable.</en>
      <fr>Perdre 20 000 conteneurs chaque année est inadmissible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3079" docOffset="22">
      <en>Lives are being put at risk, which is why we are demanding action.</en>
      <fr>Des vies sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3634">en</DiscourseConnective> danger et <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3647">c'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> nous exigeons que des mesures soient prises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3146" docOffset="23">
      <en>The maritime industry seems unwilling to act.</en>
      <fr>Le secteur maritime ne semble pas disposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3749">à</DiscourseConnective> agir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3192" docOffset="24">
      <en>Maybe we should.</en>
      <fr>Peut-être devrions-nous le faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3209" id="038" language="GA" name="Máire Geoghegan-Quinn">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3209" docOffset="25">
      <en>Mr President, I am grateful to Mr Simpson for raising this crucial issue which is of interest to many Members of this Parliament and <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3342" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> to the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je remercie M. Simpson d'avoir soulevé cette question cruciale qui intéresse de nombreux députés de ce Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3927">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3366" docOffset="26">
      <en>The Commission welcomes the results of the Lashing@Sea project.</en>
      <fr>(EN) La Commission salue les résultats du projet Lashing@Sea.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3430" docOffset="27">
      <en>It is primarily the role of the International Maritime Organisation to tackle the issue of containers lost at sea, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3545" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> this is regulated at an international level.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4014">En</DiscourseConnective> vertu des règlementations internationales, la question des conteneurs perdus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4094">en</DiscourseConnective> mer est essentiellement du ressort de l'Organisation maritime internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3593" docOffset="28">
      <en>The Commission will <Alignment alignment="31124" annotation_id="3613">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3613" sense="Comparison.Contrast">nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> work together with Member States to promote actions to adopt internationally agreed procedures within the structures of the International Maritime Organisation.</en>
      <fr>La Commission travaillera <Alignment alignment="13026" annotation_id="4201">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4201" sense="Comparison.Contrast">néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avec les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4234">pour</DiscourseConnective> promouvoir des actions visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4269">à</DiscourseConnective> adopter des procédures concertées au niveau international au sein des structures de l'OMI.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3787" docOffset="29">
      <en>On the second question of overweight and incorrectly stowed containers, there are no EU rules governing the weighing of containers <Alignment alignment="18307" annotation_id="3918">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3918" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> loading them on ships or procedures covering stowage or lashing.</en>
      <fr>Concernant la deuxième question sur la surcharge <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4411">et</DiscourseConnective> le mauvais arrimage des conteneurs, il n'existe pas de règles européennes régissant la pesée des conteneurs <Alignment alignment="11584" annotation_id="4522">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4522" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils soient chargés sur les navires, ni de procédures concernant l'arrimage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4606">ou</DiscourseConnective> le saisissage.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3990" docOffset="30">
      <en>This matter is regulated at national level or through international agreements.</en>
      <fr>Ces questions sont régulées au niveau national <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4671">ou</DiscourseConnective> au moyen d'accords internationaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4070" docOffset="31">
      <en>The Commission does not plan at this stage to take a legislative initiative concerning this issue.</en>
      <fr>La Commission n'envisage pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4738">à</DiscourseConnective> ce stade de prendre d'initiative législative sur ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4169" docOffset="32">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="4799" annotation_id="4169">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4169" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this could change <Alignment alignment="3769" annotation_id="4196">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4196" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> international discussions are not successful <Alignment alignment="887" annotation_id="4244">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4244" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are increased problems with the stability of ships, the strength of ships or losses of containers.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11823" annotation_id="4799">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4799" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, cela pourrait changer <Alignment alignment="6287" annotation_id="4832">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4832" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les discussions internationales n'aboutissaient pas <Alignment alignment="4244" annotation_id="4887">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4887" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que les problèmes de stabilité et de résistance des navires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4950">ou</DiscourseConnective> de pertes de conteneurs augmentaient.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4353" docOffset="33">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7854" annotation_id="4353">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4353" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> presenting any new proposal, the Commission would need to fully assess the impact such a measure would have on shipping operators.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4353" annotation_id="4991">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4991" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Avant de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> présenter de nouvelles propositions, la Commission devrait évaluer parfaitement l'impact qu'une telle mesure pourrait avoir sur les transporteurs maritimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4491" docOffset="34">
      <en>Today the Commission does not have sufficient information concerning this specific matter.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, la Commission n'a pas suffisamment d'information sur ce sujet précis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4582" docOffset="35">
      <en>Concerning the third issue of tracking systems to locate containers at sea, this possibility could be further explored.</en>
      <fr>Concernant la troisième question sur les systèmes de traçabilité permettant de localiser les conteneurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5344">en</DiscourseConnective> mer, cette possibilité pourrait être explorée plus avant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4702" docOffset="36">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5405" annotation_id="4702">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4702" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, equipping millions of containers with tracking devices would be costly <Alignment alignment="17417" annotation_id="4782">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4782" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a proper assessment of the benefits must be carried out <Alignment alignment="5568" annotation_id="4842">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4842" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> taking a final decision to make such tracking systems mandatory.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6910" annotation_id="5405">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5405" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, équiper des millions de conteneurs avec des dispositifs de repérage risque d'être coûteux, <Alignment alignment="11075" annotation_id="5507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5507" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une évaluation adéquate des avantages doit être effectuée <Alignment alignment="2474" annotation_id="5568">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5568" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant d'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>arrêter une décision qui rende ces systèmes obligatoires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4914" docOffset="37">
      <en>The Commission could <Alignment alignment="5657" annotation_id="4935">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4935" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> assess the feasibility of clarifying the provisions of Directive 2002/59/EC that established the Community vessel traffic monitoring system <Alignment alignment="29393" annotation_id="5080">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5080" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which obliges the Member States to ensure that the master of a ship reports to responsible coastal stations any sight of containers drifting at sea.</en>
      <fr>La Commission pourrait <Alignment alignment="10915" annotation_id="5657">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5657" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> évaluer la possibilité de clarifier les dispositions de la directive 2002/59/CE qui établit un système communautaire de suivi du trafic des navires, <Alignment alignment="12194" annotation_id="5816">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5816" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> oblige les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5844">à</DiscourseConnective> veiller à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5859">que</DiscourseConnective> les capitaines de navires signalent aux centres côtiers la vue de tout conteneur dérivant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5953">en</DiscourseConnective> mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5233" docOffset="38">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="11194" annotation_id="5233">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5233" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the option to ensure the traceability of the containers is to be explored, the cost of such measures should be taken into account.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12476" annotation_id="5961">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5961" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la traçabilité des conteneurs devait être envisagée, les coûts d'une telle mesure devraient être pris en considération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5367" docOffset="39">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28823" annotation_id="5367">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5367" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, such an option could be considered in the framework of the potential development of the traceability of the containers for logistics and security purposes.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="24124" annotation_id="6084">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6084" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, cette option devrait être envisagée dans le cadre du développement potentiel de la traçabilité des conteneurs à des fins de logistique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6230">et</DiscourseConnective> de sécurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5532" docOffset="40">
      <en>Finally, concerning compensation for the damage caused by lost containers; this can be addressed under Directive 2009/20/EC concerning maritime insurance, <Alignment alignment="17946" annotation_id="5687">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5687" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Directive 2005/35/EC concerning maritime pollution and sanctions in the event of offences covers cases <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5794" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> oil-polluting substances have been dumped into the sea.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6246">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, la question de l'indemnisation des dommages causés par les conteneurs perdus pourrait être abordée dans le cadre de la directive 2009/20/CE qui est relative à l'assurance maritime, <Alignment alignment="804" annotation_id="6434">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6434" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de la directive 2005/35/CE qui concerne la pollution maritime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6499">et</DiscourseConnective> les sanctions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6516">en</DiscourseConnective> cas d'infraction, et qui couvre les cas de rejet d'hydrocarbures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6584">ou</DiscourseConnective> de substances nocives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6609">en</DiscourseConnective> mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5855" docOffset="41">
      <en>Directive 2004/35/EC concerning environmental liability <Alignment alignment="39618" annotation_id="5911">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5911" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> establishes strict liability for operators who cause damage to the environment through the transportation by sea of dangerous goods or polluting goods.</en>
      <fr>La directive 2004/35/CE relative à la responsabilité environnementale établit <Alignment alignment="5911" annotation_id="6695">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6695" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la responsabilité objective des exploitants qui causent des dommages environnementaux en transportant des substances dangereuses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6834">ou</DiscourseConnective> polluantes par voie maritime.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6068" docOffset="42">
      <en>Such operators are obliged to remedy the damage caused to protected species and natural habitats.</en>
      <fr>Ces exploitants sont tenus de réparer les dommages causés aux espèces protégées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6947">et</DiscourseConnective> aux habitats naturels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6166" docOffset="43">
      <en>Additional measures to put in place a compensation regime for damages caused by lost containers would need to be closely assessed against the proportionality principle justifying EU action.</en>
      <fr>Toutes mesures supplémentaires visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7011">à</DiscourseConnective> mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7020">en</DiscourseConnective> place un régime d'indemnisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7055">pour</DiscourseConnective> les dommages causés par des conteneurs perdus devraient être examinées attentivement à la lumière du principe de proportionnalité justifiant l'action de l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6356" docOffset="44">
      <en>The Commission believes that at this stage the work of the IMO to improve standards should be the priority.</en>
      <fr>La Commission estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7240">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à ce stade, le travail de l'OMI <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7275">pour</DiscourseConnective> améliorer les normes devraient être la priorité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6464" id="040" language="FR" name="Dominique Riquet">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6464" docOffset="45">
      <en>Mr President, Commissioner, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6492" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> Mr Simpson pointed out, several thousand containers are lost each year in European waters, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6586" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> they pose a very significant risk on two counts: they pose a pollution risk, which has been widely discussed, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6700" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6704" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6710" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> a number of them do not sink but often float between two bodies of water in which they are difficult to locate, they pose a major risk to the safe passage of ships, whether they be cargo ships or, in particular, the smallest fishing or recreational vessels. The result, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6988" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> we know, is serious accidents that endanger human lives.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE. - Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, comme M. Simpson l'a rappelé, plusieurs milliers de conteneurs sont perdus chaque année dans les eaux européennes et représentent un danger très important à deux titres: en termes de pollution, ce qui a été largement évoqué, mais aussi, car un certain nombre d'entre eux ne coulent pas et flottent souvent entre deux eaux où ils sont difficilement repérables, ils représentent un danger majeur pour la sécurité de la navigation, qu'il s'agisse de la navigation de commerce d'ailleurs mais surtout des plus petites unités de pêche ou de plaisance avec, on le sait, des accidents graves qui mettent en jeu la vie humaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7048" docOffset="46">
      <en>This is <Alignment alignment="40435" annotation_id="7056">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7056" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an extremely serious problem, <Alignment alignment="36849" annotation_id="7096">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7096" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Commission seems to be saying that either it does not have the information to act, <Alignment alignment="42892" annotation_id="7187">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7187" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it believes that, in view of the existing arrangements, certain measures must be applied.</en>
      <fr>Cela représente <Alignment alignment="7056" annotation_id="8035">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8035" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un problème extrêmement sérieux, <Alignment alignment="2803" annotation_id="8073">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8073" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'entends bien que la Commission nous répond que <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8125">soit</DiscourseConnective> elle n'a pas les renseignements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8162">pour</DiscourseConnective> agir, <Alignment alignment="5972" annotation_id="8173">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8173" sense="Expansion.Alternative">soit</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8190">que</DiscourseConnective> dans l'état des dispositifs existants, un certain nombre de mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8262">s'</DiscourseConnective>appliquent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7280" docOffset="47">
      <en>In reality, that is not the case: nothing whatsoever is being done about this situation.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8276">En réalité</DiscourseConnective>, il n'en est rien, cette situation est en déshérence complète.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7369" docOffset="48">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="7282" annotation_id="7372">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7372" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> want real measures to be proposed. We want preventive measures, by which I mean measures relating to container loading and stowage methods and to the scope to build into containers - <Alignment alignment="10961" annotation_id="7565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7565" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this can be done in satisfactory economic conditions - a beacon that will enable lost containers to be located and, <Alignment alignment="8724" annotation_id="7685">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7685" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, either avoided by vessels - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7724" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective> saving human lives - or retrieved <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7763" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> they contain toxic substances.</en>
      <fr>Nous souhaitons <Alignment alignment="7372" annotation_id="8366">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8366" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que des mesures effectives soient proposées, à la fois préventives, c'est-à-dire sur les modalités de chargement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8484">et</DiscourseConnective> d'arrimage des conteneurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8513">et</DiscourseConnective> sur la capacité qu'il y a d'intégrer aux conteneurs, <Alignment alignment="4670" annotation_id="8569">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8569" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on peut le faire dans des conditions économiques satisfaisantes, une balise qui permette, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8662">d'une part</DiscourseConnective>, de localiser le conteneur lorsqu'il est perdu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8720">et</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="8233" annotation_id="8724">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8724" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8730">soit</DiscourseConnective> de l'éviter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8747">à</DiscourseConnective> la navigation - et on épargnera des vies humaines-, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8801">soit</DiscourseConnective> de le récupérer s'il contient des produits toxiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7797" docOffset="49">
      <en>In the event that toxic or highly toxic substances are present, this beacon must <Alignment alignment="7698" annotation_id="7878">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7878" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be able to emit an agreed signal to enable the environmental risk to be anticipated and contained.</en>
      <fr>Il faut <Alignment alignment="7947" annotation_id="8867">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8867" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que cette balise puisse émettre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8910">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de produits toxiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8938">ou</DiscourseConnective> hautement toxiques, un signal convenu qui permette de prévoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9003">et</DiscourseConnective> contenir le risque environnemental.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7982" docOffset="50">
      <en>Lastly, this beacon must be of use in identifying the owners of containers, <Alignment alignment="9106" annotation_id="8058">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8058" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is a real issue of liability that has been raised in the oral question.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9042">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, cette balise doit permettre d'identifier le propriétaire <Alignment alignment="15974" annotation_id="9106">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9106" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il y a un vrai sujet de responsabilité qui a été soulevé lors de la question orale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8142" docOffset="51">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17912" annotation_id="8142">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8142" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Indeed</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, not knowing who the owners are and not being able, <Alignment alignment="9262" annotation_id="8201">
          <Alignment alignment="41774" annotation_id="8201">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8201" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, to identify and locate containers means that nothing can be established with regard to recovery and compensation for damage.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8142" annotation_id="9194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9194" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">En effet</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'absence de propriétaire connu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9236">et</DiscourseConnective> l'absence, d'ailleurs, <Alignment alignment="10652" annotation_id="9262">
          <Alignment alignment="19975" annotation_id="9262">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9262" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en fait</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, de capacité d'identifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9296">et</DiscourseConnective> de retrouver les conteneurs font <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9332">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9337">à</DiscourseConnective> la fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9347">pour</DiscourseConnective> la récupération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9368">et</DiscourseConnective> la réparation des dommages, rien n'est établi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8335" docOffset="52">
      <en>We strongly urge the Commission not to just conclude that we do not have the resources <Alignment alignment="14568" annotation_id="8422">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8422" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the existing resources are sufficient, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8469" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective> that is not the case: there is an issue of environmental safety, <Alignment alignment="2711" annotation_id="8542">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8542" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there are <Alignment alignment="41109" annotation_id="8556">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8556" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> lives at stake, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8577" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> we must remember that.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons très fermement à la Commission de ne pas se contenter de constater <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9500">que</DiscourseConnective> nous n'avons pas les moyens <Alignment alignment="6127" annotation_id="9532">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9532" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9535">que</DiscourseConnective> les moyens existants suffisent, ce n'est pas le cas, il y a une sécurité environnementale, <Alignment alignment="8865" annotation_id="9630">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9630" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il y a <Alignment alignment="2960" annotation_id="9642">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9642" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des vies <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9657">en</DiscourseConnective> jeu, il faut le rappeler.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8604" id="041" language="NL" name="Saïd El Khadraoui">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8604" docOffset="53">
      <en>Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, on behalf of my group I would like to second the comments and questions put forward by the Chair of the Committee on Transport and Tourism, Mr Simpson.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9741">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, au nom de mon groupe, je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9786">à</DiscourseConnective> appuyer les commentaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9813">et</DiscourseConnective> les questions formulés par le président de la commission des transports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9888">et</DiscourseConnective> du tourisme, M. Simpson.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8806" docOffset="54">
      <en>The loss of containers - as well as their contents, of course, <Alignment alignment="15132" annotation_id="8869">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8869" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we must not forget that we are <Alignment alignment="10016" annotation_id="8906">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8906" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> talking about that - is without doubt an underestimated and neglected problem.</en>
      <fr>La perte des conteneurs - et, bien sûr, de leurs contenus, <Alignment alignment="20438" annotation_id="9975">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9975" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il ne faut pas oublier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10002">que</DiscourseConnective> cela fait <Alignment alignment="996" annotation_id="10016">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10016" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> partie de notre discussion - est assurément un problème sous-estimé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10094">et</DiscourseConnective> négligé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8990" docOffset="55">
      <en>As has been said, this concerns as many as 2 000 containers a year in European waters alone, with all the consequences for the environment, consequences possibly for the crews, for other ships and for the coastal regions, which of course are fairly often left with the task of clearing up the debris.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10106">Comme</DiscourseConnective> cela a été dit, cela concerne chaque année 2 000 conteneurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10172">pour</DiscourseConnective> les seules eaux européennes, avec toutes les conséquences environnementales et les conséquences éventuelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10285">pour</DiscourseConnective> les équipages, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10305">pour</DiscourseConnective> les autres navires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10329">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10332">pour</DiscourseConnective> les régions côtières qui, bien souvent, se retrouvent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10391">à</DiscourseConnective> devoir nettoyer les débris.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9291" docOffset="56">
      <en>This is <Alignment alignment="10431" annotation_id="9299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9299" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an issue that we must tackle.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10424">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit <Alignment alignment="25283" annotation_id="10431">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10431" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'un problème auquel nous devons nous attaquer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9339" docOffset="57">
      <en>There are various reasons for this problem: bad weather, speed, poor securing and stacking of containers, excessive weight, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9463" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> so on. My group believes that this problem has a European dimension which justifies an initiative by the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Il y a plusieurs raisons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10519">à</DiscourseConnective> ce problème: le mauvais temps, la vitesse, les défaillances de l'arrimage ou de l'empilement, la surcharge, etc. Mon groupe estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10652">que</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet a une dimension européenne qui justifie une initiative de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9584" docOffset="58">
      <en>We should not stand back passively and wait for International Maritime Organization (IMO) measures.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne devrions pas rester en retrait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10777">et</DiscourseConnective> attendre les mesures de l'Organisation maritime internationale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9684" docOffset="59">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23988" annotation_id="9684">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9684" sense="Expansion.Restatement">In particular</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, initiatives could be taken to register such incidents and raise awareness of this issue in European ports.</en>
      <fr>Des initiatives devraient être prises <Alignment alignment="5201" annotation_id="10882">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10882" sense="Expansion.Restatement">notamment</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10892">pour</DiscourseConnective> enregistrer ces incidents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10923">et</DiscourseConnective> sensibiliser les ports européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10959">à</DiscourseConnective> cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9806" docOffset="60">
      <en>In the context of the social dialogue - the European social dialogue in the port sector - the Commission could <Alignment alignment="30750" annotation_id="9917">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9917" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> broach the subject and propose solutions such as new procedures for loading containers or modified training.</en>
      <fr>Dans le contexte du dialogue social - du dialogue social européen dans le secteur portuaire - la Commission pourrait <Alignment alignment="19158" annotation_id="11094">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11094" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aborder le sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11121">et</DiscourseConnective> proposer des solutions telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11154">que</DiscourseConnective> de nouvelles procédures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11182">pour</DiscourseConnective> le chargement des conteneurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11216">ou</DiscourseConnective> des modifications à apporter aux formations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10031" docOffset="61">
      <en>Mr Riquet has emphasised, <Alignment alignment="36576" annotation_id="10057">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10057" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I too believe, that it is very wise to ensure that containers are traceable: not only in this context but also in the context of monitoring the entire logistics chain.</en>
      <fr>M. Riquet a souligné, <Alignment alignment="24183" annotation_id="11286">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11286" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je partage son avis, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11310">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il serait très judicieux d'assurer la traçabilité des conteneurs, pas uniquement dans ce contexte, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11412">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11417">également</DiscourseConnective> dans le cadre de la surveillance du processus logistique dans son ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10229" docOffset="62">
      <en>Commissioner, I <Alignment alignment="33878" annotation_id="10245">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10245" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> expect some slightly more concrete initiatives over the coming months and years.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Commissaire, j'attends <Alignment alignment="10245" annotation_id="11536">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11536" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des initiatives un peu plus concrètes dans les mois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11603">et</DiscourseConnective> les années à venir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10336" id="042" name="Gesine Meissner">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10336" docOffset="63">
      <en>on behalf of the ALDE Group. - (DE) Mr President, Mrs Geoghegan-Quinn, the arrival of a container full of trainers on an island somewhere, which was received enthusiastically by the residents, has in the past made headline news.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe ALDE. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Madame Geoghegan-Quinn, il y a quelques années, l'arrivée d'un conteneur de chaussures de sport sur une île lointaine, accueilli avec enthousiasme par la population locale, avait fait les gros titres des journaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10565" docOffset="64">
      <en>In another case, a contingent of rubber ducks floated ashore.</en>
      <fr>Il y a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11900">également</DiscourseConnective> l'exemple d'un contingent de canards en caoutchouc qui est venu s'échouer sur la côte.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10627" docOffset="65">
      <en>These are, of course, the pleasant examples of ships' cargoes going missing, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10704" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective> the fact is that in many cases lost containers can cause serious damage.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12000">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit, bien évidemment, d'exemples sympathiques de pertes de cargaisons maritimes. Toutefois, dans de nombreux cas, les conteneurs perdus peuvent causer de graves dommages.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10781" docOffset="66">
      <en>It has become clear that we must do something about this.</en>
      <fr>Il est devenu clair <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12194">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons faire quelque chose à ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10839" docOffset="67">
      <en>The Dutch Government was concerned about this problem and set up an investigation to find out why it was happening.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement néerlandais était préoccupé par ce problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12302">et</DiscourseConnective> il a lancé une étude <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12326">pour</DiscourseConnective> comprendre pourquoi cela arrivait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10955" docOffset="68">
      <en>The investigation identified a number of causes.</en>
      <fr>L'étude a identifié un certain nombre de causes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11004" docOffset="69">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11004" sense="Comparison.Concession">Although</DiscourseConnective> there are EU regulations which specify how cargoes should be secured <Alignment alignment="6863" annotation_id="11082">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11082" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="47852" annotation_id="11086">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11086" sense="Comparison.Concession">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> all ships have the manual containing the regulations on board, only 46% of ships have their cargoes properly lashed down.</en>
      <fr>En dépit de l'existence de réglementations européennes spécifiant de quelle manière les cargaisons doivent être arrimées, <Alignment alignment="11034" annotation_id="12537">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12537" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="11086" annotation_id="12540">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12540" sense="Comparison.Concession">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tous les navires disposent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12576">à</DiscourseConnective> bord d'un manuel contenant ces réglementations, seuls 46 % des vaisseaux fixent correctement leurs chargements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11217" docOffset="70">
      <en>This means that we do not need any new rules.</en>
      <fr>Cela signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12704">que</DiscourseConnective> nous n'avons pas besoin de règles supplémentaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11263" docOffset="71">
      <en>You were right about that, Mrs Geoghegan-Quinn.</en>
      <fr>Vous aviez raison sur ce point Madame Geoghegan-Quinn.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11311" docOffset="72">
      <en>In many cases, the weight of the cargo has not been correctly balanced.</en>
      <fr>Dans de nombreux cas, le poids de la cargaison n'a pas été réparti correctement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11383" docOffset="73">
      <en>Another reason is that many crews in the short sea shipping sector unlash cargoes <Alignment alignment="58023" annotation_id="11465">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11465" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they have reached their destination to speed up the unloading process.</en>
      <fr>Par ailleurs, dans le secteur du transport maritime à courte distance, beaucoup d'équipages détachent les cargaisons <Alignment alignment="11465" annotation_id="13012">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13012" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant d'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>avoir atteint leur destination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13051">afin d'</DiscourseConnective>accélérer le processus de déchargement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11543" docOffset="74">
      <en>Stacking errors can <Alignment alignment="13131" annotation_id="11563">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11563" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be a cause of the problem, together with old or damaged equipment.</en>
      <fr>Les erreurs d'empilement peuvent <Alignment alignment="8169" annotation_id="13131">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13131" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être à l'origine du problème, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13171">de même que</DiscourseConnective> les équipements anciens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13207">ou</DiscourseConnective> endommagés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11635" docOffset="75">
      <en>All of this can, of course, have a major impact on the environment.</en>
      <fr>Tout cela peut, bien évidemment, avoir un impact considérable sur l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11703" docOffset="76">
      <en>Around 70% of items lost from ships at sea sink to the bottom, <Alignment alignment="45582" annotation_id="11766">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11766" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this gives rise to the question of what damage they are causing on the sea bed.</en>
      <fr>Près de 70 % des objets perdus en mer coulent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13351">jusqu'au</DiscourseConnective> fond, <Alignment alignment="3712" annotation_id="13366">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13366" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela pose la question des dommages qu'ils causent au fond marin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11850" docOffset="77">
      <en>A total of 15% of the goods reach land.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13441">Au total</DiscourseConnective>, 15 % des produits échouent sur les côtes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11890" docOffset="78">
      <en>The remaining 15% float around in the ocean and obviously represent a major hazard for other ships, platforms and the environment.</en>
      <fr>Les 15% restants flottent dans l'océan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13532">et</DiscourseConnective> représentent un danger majeur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13565">pour</DiscourseConnective> les autres navires, les plates-formes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13608">et</DiscourseConnective> l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12021" docOffset="79">
      <en>This means that <Alignment alignment="52441" annotation_id="12037">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12037" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> accidents happen at sea we must investigate the extent to which containers were involved.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13628">En d'autres termes</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="3916" annotation_id="13648">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13648" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des accidents surviennent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13682">en</DiscourseConnective> mer, nous devons examiner dans quelle mesure des conteneurs pourraient être impliqués.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12132" docOffset="80">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13791" annotation_id="12132">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12132" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we need to speak to shipping companies and port operators to ensure that they comply with the regulations.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons parler <Alignment alignment="19080" annotation_id="13791">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13791" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> avec les compagnies maritimes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13829">et</DiscourseConnective> les opérateurs portuaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13858">pour</DiscourseConnective> nous assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13876">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils respectent bien les règlementations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12244" docOffset="81">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13920" annotation_id="12244">
          <Alignment alignment="60500" annotation_id="12244">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12244" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, regular inspections must be made.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="22677" annotation_id="13920">
          <Alignment alignment="12244" annotation_id="13920">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13920" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, des inspections doivent être faites régulièrement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12291" docOffset="82">
      <en>Two thousand containers really are too many <Alignment alignment="42724" annotation_id="12335">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12335" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I think that carrying out feasibility studies would take too long.</en>
      <fr>Deux mille conteneurs est un nombre vraiment trop élevé, <Alignment alignment="4798" annotation_id="14042">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14042" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14054">que</DiscourseConnective> réaliser des études de faisabilité prendrait trop de temps.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12406" docOffset="83">
      <en>We must take immediate action, <Alignment alignment="2364" annotation_id="12437">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12437" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the situation simply cannot go on <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12479" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> it is.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons prendre des mesures immédiates <Alignment alignment="27820" annotation_id="14161">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14161" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette situation ne peut tout bonnement pas durer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12489" id="044" name="Jaroslav Paška">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12489" docOffset="84">
      <en>on behalf of the EFD Group. - (SK) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12524" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective> I see it, the solution to the problem of compensation for damage caused by containers lost at sea lies in having well-organised relations between three parties: the owner of the transported goods, the shipping company and the insurance company.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe EFD. - (SK) Je pense que la solution au problème de l'indemnisation des dommages causés par des conteneurs perdus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14346">en</DiscourseConnective> mer tient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14359">à</DiscourseConnective> la bonne organisation des relations entre trois parties: le propriétaire des marchandises transportées, la compagnie de transport maritime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14500">et</DiscourseConnective> la compagnie d'assurance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12772" docOffset="85">
      <en>The operator, the shipping company and the crew in particular are responsible for the security of goods at sea.</en>
      <fr>L'exploitant, la compagnie maritime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14565">et</DiscourseConnective> l'équipage sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14584">notamment</DiscourseConnective> responsables de la sécurité des marchandises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14639">en</DiscourseConnective> mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12884" docOffset="86">
      <en>The crew is <Alignment alignment="45662" annotation_id="12896">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12896" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> responsible for preventing the containers from falling off or sliding from the vessel into the sea, that is, for compliance with the international regulations in force, and for ensuring the safe shipping of goods in international maritime transport.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14647">En</DiscourseConnective> vertu des réglementations internationales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14692">en</DiscourseConnective> vigueur, l'équipage est <Alignment alignment="22604" annotation_id="14719">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14719" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> chargé d'empêcher que les conteneurs ne tombent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14777">ou</DiscourseConnective> ne glissent du navire dans la mer, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14815">et</DiscourseConnective> d'assurer la sécurité de l'acheminement des biens dans le transport maritime international.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13151" docOffset="87">
      <en>In my opinion, the first step we ought to consider <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13202" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">while</DiscourseConnective> tackling this issue is ensuring compliance with the regulations on securing goods <Alignment alignment="9219" annotation_id="13290">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13290" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> putting to sea.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14910">À</DiscourseConnective> mon avis, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14922">pour</DiscourseConnective> aborder cette question il convient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14962">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> de garantir l'application des règlements visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15023">à</DiscourseConnective> sécuriser les marchandises <Alignment alignment="6943" annotation_id="15052">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15052" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles ne prennent la mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13313" docOffset="88">
      <en>I think this is the central issue in this matter.</en>
      <fr>Je pense qu'il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15102">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de la question centrale dans cette affaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13363" docOffset="89">
      <en>Only <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13368" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective> should we try to find new, complementary regulations for the transportation of goods.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est qu'à partir de là que nous devrions essayer de trouver de nouvelles réglementations complémentaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15262">pour</DiscourseConnective> le transport de marchandises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13459" docOffset="90">
      <en>Only <Alignment alignment="7793" annotation_id="13464">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13464" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">after</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we know the actual starting position <Alignment alignment="37227" annotation_id="13507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13507" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the situation concerning compliance with the regulations should we seek amendments to regulations which are already established for international shipping and, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13671" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> the case may be, for the European Union too.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est qu'<Alignment alignment="13464" annotation_id="15309">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15309" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Succession">une fois que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous connaitrons la situation de départ réelle <Alignment alignment="13507" annotation_id="15369">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15369" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la façon dont les réglementations sont respectées que nous devrions chercher <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15449">à</DiscourseConnective> modifier les règlements qui existent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15488">déjà</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15493">pour</DiscourseConnective> le transport maritime international <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15534">et</DiscourseConnective>, probablement aussi, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15558">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13719" id="045" name="Jim Higgins">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13719" docOffset="91">
      <en>(GA) Mr President, my colleague Brian Simpson has raised very important questions, <Alignment alignment="2109" annotation_id="13802">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13802" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I have to say that I am not at all happy with the response I received from the Commissioner.</en>
      <fr>(GA) Monsieur le Président, mon collègue Brian Simpson a soulevé des questions importantes <Alignment alignment="5147" annotation_id="15674">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15674" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je dois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15685">dire que</DiscourseConnective> je ne suis pas du tout satisfait des réponses apportées par la commissaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13899" docOffset="92">
      <en>Is she willing or ready to do anything about it <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13947" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> regards the introduction of a law?</en>
      <fr>A-t-elle l'intention de faire quelque chose en ce qui concerne l'introduction d'une législation? Y est-elle seulement disposée?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13985" docOffset="93">
      <en>This is a hugely important issue <Alignment alignment="15952" annotation_id="14018">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14018" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I commend my colleague, Brian Simpson, for raising it <Alignment alignment="32638" annotation_id="14076">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14076" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="16018" annotation_id="14084">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14084" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you look at the statistics things are actually getting worse.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Il s'agit d'une question extrêmement importante, <Alignment alignment="11491" annotation_id="15952">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15952" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je félicite mon collègue Brian Simpson de l'avoir soulevée <Alignment alignment="8591" annotation_id="16014">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16014" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="3230" annotation_id="16018">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16018" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous regardez les statistiques, la situation est, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16071">en fait</DiscourseConnective>, en train de s'aggraver.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14149" docOffset="94">
      <en>Approximately 50% of the world's shipping tonnage carries non-toxic substances as bulk goods.</en>
      <fr>Le transport de substances non toxiques telles que des marchandises en vrac représente environ 50 % du tonnage mondial.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14243" docOffset="95">
      <en>There has been a rapid increase in the worldwide container ship fleet - which has grown by 140% from 32.6 million to 78.3 million gross tonnes since 1984 - <Alignment alignment="23152" annotation_id="14399">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14399" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the problem needs to be regulated.</en>
      <fr>La flotte mondiale des porte-conteneurs a connu une augmentation rapide - elle a augmenté de 140 %, passant de 32,6 millions de tonnes brutes à 78,3 millions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16382">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 1984 - <Alignment alignment="20207" annotation_id="16396">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16396" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le problème doit faire l'objet d'une réglementation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14438" docOffset="96">
      <en>There is <Alignment alignment="14848" annotation_id="14447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14447" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a problem in relation to increased speed, <Alignment alignment="44383" annotation_id="14494">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14494" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> these container carriers travel at a much faster speed than bulk carriers.</en>
      <fr>Il y a <Alignment alignment="8887" annotation_id="16459">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16459" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un problème lié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16485">à</DiscourseConnective> l'augmentation de la vitesse <Alignment alignment="26586" annotation_id="16516">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16516" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces porte-conteneurs naviguent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16551">à</DiscourseConnective> une vitesse bien supérieure à celle des vraquiers.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14577" docOffset="97">
      <en>They are now travelling at speeds of 27 knots, which is a huge speed in terms of the possibility of crashes or impacts, collisions and so on. So there is a huge problem there as well.</en>
      <fr>Ils se déplacent désormais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16631">à</DiscourseConnective> la vitesse de 27 nœuds, ce qui est une vitesse prodigieuse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16692">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de possibilité d'accidents, d'impacts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16740">ou</DiscourseConnective> de collisions, etc. Il y a donc un gros problème sur ce point <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16805">également</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14761" docOffset="98">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="38550" annotation_id="14761">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14761" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we have the problem in relation to the actual age of the fleets themselves.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14761" annotation_id="16816">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16816" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous avons le problème de l'âge réel des flottes elles-mêmes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14842" docOffset="99">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="45111" annotation_id="14842">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14842" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you look at the age of the fleets carrying containers, the bulk of them are in the category of 19-24 years old, which means that there is a major problem from the point of view of actual structural defects.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4982" annotation_id="16887">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16887" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous examinez l'âge des flottes de porte-conteneurs, vous constatez que la majorité d'entre elles se situent dans la catégorie 19-24 ans, ce qui signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17049">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il y a un vrai problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17076">en</DiscourseConnective> termes de défauts structurels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15054" docOffset="100">
      <en>What we need is a legislative initiative.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons besoin d'une initiative législative.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15096" docOffset="101">
      <en>We cannot allow a laissez-faire attitude.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pouvons pas accepter le laisser-faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15138" docOffset="102">
      <en>What we <Alignment alignment="17216" annotation_id="15146">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15146" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> need is a strict liability convention, <Alignment alignment="31554" annotation_id="15190">
          <Alignment alignment="53821" annotation_id="15190">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15190" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> ships travelling though EU waters will automatically have to foot the bill for non-intentional toxic releases into the sea due to the loss of containers.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="15146" annotation_id="17216">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17216" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> besoin d'une convention sur la responsabilité objective <Alignment alignment="23718" annotation_id="17282">
          <Alignment alignment="15190" annotation_id="17282">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17282" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> les navires qui circulent dans les eaux européennes paient automatiquement la note des rejets toxiques non intentionnels causés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17419">en</DiscourseConnective> mer par la perte des conteneurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15352" docOffset="103">
      <en>What I am saying in essence is that we need action <Alignment alignment="9716" annotation_id="15403">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15403" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the situation is getting progressively worse <Alignment alignment="10" annotation_id="15456">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15456" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="41125" annotation_id="15461">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15461" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Mr Simpson has pointed out, in the bulk of cases of accidents we are talking about human error in terms of the way containers are tied down, dealt with and so on, <Alignment alignment="61914" annotation_id="15627">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15627" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we really need to take the shipping companies on.</en>
      <fr>Ce que je veux dire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17476">en</DiscourseConnective> substance, c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17496">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il nous faut prendre des mesures <Alignment alignment="3795" annotation_id="17532">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17532" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la situation empire peu à peu <Alignment alignment="15456" annotation_id="17572">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17572" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que, <Alignment alignment="12299" annotation_id="17580">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17580" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que l'a fait valoir M. Simpson, dans la majorité des cas, les accidents sont le fruit d'une erreur humaine liée à l'arrimage, à la manutention etc. <Alignment alignment="17456" annotation_id="17734">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17734" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il est vraiment nécessaire d'obtenir la coopération des compagnies maritimes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15680" id="047" name="Inés Ayala Sender">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15680" docOffset="104">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, exactly eight years ago this November, the Prestige, an oil tanker carrying 70 000 tonnes of crude oil, suffered an accident off the coast of Galicia causing a leak through which the tanker spilled 20 000 tonnes of oil.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, cela fera exactement huit ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17885">en</DiscourseConnective> novembre que le Prestige, un pétrolier transportant 70 000 tonnes de pétrole brut, a eu, au large des côtes de la Galice, un accident qui a provoqué une fuite à la suite de laquelle 20 000 tonnes de pétrole se sont déversées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15919" docOffset="105">
      <en>This initial leak, combined with the misjudged decisions of the Minister of Public Works at the time, Mr Álvarez-Cascos, resulted in an absolute disaster and the worst ecological, social and economic tragedy ever to affect the Galician coasts.</en>
      <fr>Cette fuite initiale combinée aux décisions inadaptées du ministre de l'équipement de l'époque, M. Álvarez-Cascos, a abouti <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18238">à</DiscourseConnective> une véritable catastrophe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18266">et</DiscourseConnective> à la pire tragédie écologique, sociale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18308">et</DiscourseConnective> économique qu'aient jamais connue les côtes galiciennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16163" docOffset="106">
      <en>One of the possible causes considered to explain the leak was precisely the presence of lost containers floating on the sea surface at the mercy of the waves and storms.</en>
      <fr>L'une des causes possibles évoquées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18404">pour</DiscourseConnective> expliquer la fuite était justement la présence de conteneurs perdus flottant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18486">à</DiscourseConnective> la surface de la mer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18509">à</DiscourseConnective> la merci des vagues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18531">et</DiscourseConnective> des tempêtes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16333" docOffset="107">
      <en>These containers are potential projectiles that can be thrust against the hulls of all kinds of ships, including oil tankers like the Prestige but also passenger ships, ferries or cruise ships.</en>
      <fr>Ces conteneurs constituent potentiellement des projectiles qui peuvent venir frapper les coques de tous types de navires, y compris de pétroliers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18694">comme</DiscourseConnective> le Prestige, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18713">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> de paquebots, de transbordeurs rouliers de passagers <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18777">ou</DiscourseConnective> de bateaux de croisière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16527" docOffset="108">
      <en>The outcome of the Lashing@Sea project has revealed serious deficiencies and negligence in the different areas concerned, such as lack of training and instruction among loading personnel and stevedores in the ports and also among the ship crews, which are consistently undertrained and undermanned even <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16830" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective> the ships they work on are genuine monsters of the seas.</en>
      <fr>Les résultats du projet Lashing@Sea ont révélé des déficiences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18868">et</DiscourseConnective> des négligences graves dans différents domaines, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18920">notamment</DiscourseConnective> le manque de formation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18953">et</DiscourseConnective> d'instruction du personnel de chargement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18997">et</DiscourseConnective> des manutentionnaires dans les ports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19037">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19041">également</DiscourseConnective> des équipages à bord qui ne sont jamais suffisamment formés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19111">et</DiscourseConnective> qui sont toujours en sous-effectif alors qu'ils travaillent sur des navires qui sont de véritables monstres marins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16894" docOffset="109">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19230" annotation_id="16894">
          <Alignment alignment="28075" annotation_id="16894">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16894" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">In addition</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, the best techniques to secure and trace the containers are, on the whole, insufficiently used, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17002" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> they are frequently overloaded.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="796" annotation_id="19230">
          <Alignment alignment="13559" annotation_id="19230">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19230" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, les techniques les plus performantes de sécurisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19297">et</DiscourseConnective> de traçabilité des conteneurs, qui sont souvent trop chargés, sont dans l'ensemble insuffisamment utilisées.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17038" docOffset="110">
      <en>Lastly, a cost and risk assessment of the new physical effects generated by these monsters of the seas needs to be carried out.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19409">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, il serait opportun de réaliser une évaluation des coûts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19472">et</DiscourseConnective> des risques des nouveaux effets physiques générés par ces monstres marins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17166" docOffset="111">
      <en>These effects include, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17189" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>, the so-called 'parametric resonance effect', which can cause containers to drop from the rear of the ship at a faster rate.</en>
      <fr>Ces effets comprennent entre autres l'effet dit de "résonance paramétrique", lequel est susceptible d'accélérer la chute des conteneurs à l'arrière du navire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17326" docOffset="112">
      <en>This is why we demand that the European Commission undertake immediate preventive measures, more training, instruction and refreshment courses for stevedores and crews.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19709">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>, nous exigeons de la Commission européenne des mesures préventives immédiates, plus de formation, d'instruction <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19836">et</DiscourseConnective> de cours de remise à niveau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19867">pour</DiscourseConnective> les manutentionnaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19894">et</DiscourseConnective> les équipages.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17495" docOffset="113">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="33274" annotation_id="17498">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17498" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demand the implementation of technological safety measures: weight controls in ports, improved lashing equipment and stacking strategies, and adequate marking to locate the containers in case of loss, traceability being one of the services potentially provided by the Galileo project.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons <Alignment alignment="6713" annotation_id="19927">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19927" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la mise en place de mesures technologiques de sécurité: le contrôle du poids dans les ports, l'amélioration des équipements d'arrimage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20072">et</DiscourseConnective> des stratégies d'empilement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20104">et</DiscourseConnective> un marquage adéquat permettant de localiser les conteneurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20166">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de perte, la traçabilité étant un des services potentiels du projet Galileo.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17788" id="048" name="Jörg Leichtfried">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17788" docOffset="114">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, I am glad that the European Commission did not exist in the 15th century. <Alignment alignment="13551" annotation_id="17881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17881" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it had existed, Christopher Columbus and his companions would probably have sailed in the next container, which would promptly have sunk, <Alignment alignment="47777" annotation_id="18022">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18022" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they would never have reached the continent of America.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, je me réjouis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20292">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne n'ait pas existé au XVe siècle car <Alignment alignment="26" annotation_id="20356">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20356" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle avait existé, Christophe Colomb <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20396">et</DiscourseConnective> ses compagnons auraient probablement navigué dans un conteneur, qui aurait rapidement coulé, <Alignment alignment="4887" annotation_id="20492">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20492" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils n'auraient jamais atteint le continent américain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18082" docOffset="115">
      <en>We know what the cause of this problem is.</en>
      <fr>Nous connaissons l'origine du problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18125" docOffset="116">
      <en>We know that something needs to be done about it.</en>
      <fr>Nous savons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20601">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il faut faire quelque chose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18175" docOffset="117">
      <en>What does the Commission say?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20633">Que</DiscourseConnective> dit la Commission?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18205" docOffset="118">
      <en>It says that it is not possible to do anything.</en>
      <fr>Elle dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20665">qu'</DiscourseConnective>on ne peut rien faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18253" docOffset="119">
      <en>This is simply not acceptable.</en>
      <fr>C'est tout <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20702">simplement</DiscourseConnective> inacceptable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18284" docOffset="120">
      <en>We know that inaccurate stowage is the cause, that the containers have faulty lashings, that they are overweight, that they fall into the water even <Alignment alignment="31162" annotation_id="18433">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18433" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the weather is not stormy <Alignment alignment="45023" annotation_id="18464">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18464" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that individual countries with their own regulations cannot change any of this.</en>
      <fr>Nous savons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20739">que</DiscourseConnective> la cause tient à un mauvais arrimage, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20781">que</DiscourseConnective> les conteneurs sont mal fixés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20816">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils sont surchargés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20840">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils tombent à l'eau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20863">même</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="9422" annotation_id="20868">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20868" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le temps est au beau fixe, <Alignment alignment="1175" annotation_id="20903">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20903" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20906">que</DiscourseConnective> les pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20919">et</DiscourseConnective> leurs réglementations nationales ne peuvent rien changer seuls.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18548" docOffset="121">
      <en>Who else should be bringing about change, if not the Commission, which is responsible for ensuring that things like this do not happen in European waters.</en>
      <fr>Qui devrait apporter des changements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21023">si</DiscourseConnective> ce n'est la Commission qui est chargée d'empêcher <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21076">que</DiscourseConnective> ce genre de choses ne se produise dans les eaux européennes?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18703" docOffset="122">
      <en>It is not only the environmental damage that we are concerned about.</en>
      <fr>Les dommages environnementaux ne sont pas notre seule préoccupation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18772" docOffset="123">
      <en>Human lives are <Alignment alignment="21233" annotation_id="18788">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18788" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> being put at risk.</en>
      <fr>Des vies humaines sont <Alignment alignment="25845" annotation_id="21233">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21233" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21243">en</DiscourseConnective> danger.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18812" docOffset="124">
      <en>What would happen <Alignment alignment="37311" annotation_id="18830">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18830" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a small boat with a plastic hull were to ram one of these containers in mid-Atlantic?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21254">Que</DiscourseConnective> se passerait-il <Alignment alignment="8770" annotation_id="21274">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21274" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un petit bateau avec une coque en plastique heurtait un de ces conteneurs au milieu de l'Atlantique?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18919" docOffset="125">
      <en>It would sink.</en>
      <fr>Il coulerait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18934" docOffset="126">
      <en>It would not just be the boat itself that would sink, but also the people on board.</en>
      <fr>Il n'y a pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21405">que</DiscourseConnective> le bateau qui coulerait, les gens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21443">à</DiscourseConnective> bord <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21450">également</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19018" docOffset="127">
      <en>Spending a long period in the water in the middle of the North Atlantic wearing a life jacket is not much fun.</en>
      <fr>Passer un long moment dans l'eau, au milieu de l'Atlantique Nord, avec un gilet de sauvetage n'a rien de très drôle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19129" docOffset="128">
      <en>This is something which we need to take into account.</en>
      <fr>C'est un fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21592">que</DiscourseConnective> nous devons prendre en considération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19183" docOffset="129">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28468" annotation_id="19183">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19183" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I think it is wrong that nothing is happening.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19183" annotation_id="21634">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21634" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je trouve anormal <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21668">que</DiscourseConnective> rien ne bouge.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19241" docOffset="130">
      <en>I believe that the European Commission must introduce regulations as quickly as possible in order to put an end to this situation.</en>
      <fr>Je crois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21696">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission doit introduire des règlements <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21745">aussi</DiscourseConnective> vite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21756">que</DiscourseConnective> possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21769">pour</DiscourseConnective> mettre un terme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21790">à</DiscourseConnective> cette situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19372" docOffset="131">
      <en>It is dangerous, it is wrong <Alignment alignment="7455" annotation_id="19401">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19401" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> something must be done.</en>
      <fr>C'est dangereux, c'est mal <Alignment alignment="6819" annotation_id="21836">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21836" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il faut faire quelque chose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19429" docOffset="132">
      <en>I am calling on the Commission to take urgent action, <Alignment alignment="4744" annotation_id="19483">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19483" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is responsible in this case.</en>
      <fr>J'exhorte la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21892">à</DiscourseConnective> prendre des mesures urgentes <Alignment alignment="409" annotation_id="21923">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21923" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans cette affaire, elle est responsable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19523" id="049" name="Mario Pirillo">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19523" docOffset="133">
      <en>(IT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I consider the question on containers lost at sea, which we are discussing today, to be very important, <Alignment alignment="8542" annotation_id="19668">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19668" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it raises an issue of extraordinary importance above all for the economy of EU coastal regions.</en>
      <fr>(IT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22006">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, je pense que la question des conteneurs perdus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22067">en</DiscourseConnective> mer dont nous discutons aujourd'hui est très importante <Alignment alignment="19668" annotation_id="22126">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22126" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle soulève un problème fondamental <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22167">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'économie des régions côtières de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19770" docOffset="134">
      <en>Hence, I believe the European Commission must strive to create an insurance fund that can provide compensation for any damage caused by the leakage of what are at times hazardous substances from containers lost at sea.</en>
      <fr>Je crois, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22227">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>, que la Commission doit mettre en place un fonds d'assurance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22303">pour</DiscourseConnective> rembourser les dommages causés par la fuite de substances, parfois dangereuses, des conteneurs perdus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22410">en</DiscourseConnective> mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19989" docOffset="135">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="43771" annotation_id="19989">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19989" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Furthermore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it is advisable to raise the maritime safety level through stricter legislation on the control of goods stowage operations and the prevention of the illegal stowage of harmful toxic goods on ships.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19989" annotation_id="22418">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22418" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il est opportun d'augmenter le niveau de sécurité de la navigation maritime grâce à une législation plus sévère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22544">en</DiscourseConnective> matière de contrôle des opérations de chargement de marchandises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22612">et</DiscourseConnective> de prévention des activités illégales de chargement de produits toxiques et nocifs sur les navires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20200" docOffset="136">
      <en>This insurance fund is something that I have already requested on other similar occasions.</en>
      <fr>J'ai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22720">déjà</DiscourseConnective> demandé la création de ce fonds d'assurance lors d'occasions similaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20291" id="050" name="Brian Simpson">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20291" docOffset="137">
      <en>author. - Mr President, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20315" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in short</DiscourseConnective>, I am disappointed with the Commission's response to our oral question.</en>
      <fr>auteur. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais dire brièvement que je suis déçu par la réponse de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22913">à</DiscourseConnective> notre question orale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20396" docOffset="138">
      <en>I appreciate that a world agreement would be ideal <Alignment alignment="22984" annotation_id="20447">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20447" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I appreciate that we need to involve the IMO, <Alignment alignment="23039" annotation_id="20497">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20497" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the IMO has got to be one of the slowest international organisations the world has ever come across.</en>
      <fr>Je comprends <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22950">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un accord mondial serait idéal <Alignment alignment="5465" annotation_id="22984">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22984" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22987">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons besoin de la participation de l'OMI. <Alignment alignment="5957" annotation_id="23039">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23039" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'OMI est l'une des organisations internationales les plus lentes que le monde ait connues.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20602" docOffset="139">
      <en>It works at the pace of a tortoise, <Alignment alignment="16283" annotation_id="20638">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20638" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we want action now.</en>
      <fr>Elle fonctionne au rythme d'une tortue <Alignment alignment="1276" annotation_id="23180">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23180" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous demandons des mesures immédiates.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20662" docOffset="140">
      <en>Commissioner, <Alignment alignment="23252" annotation_id="20676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20676" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I drop 2 000 heavy metal boxes into the sea, deliberately, with a load of materials in, then I would be prosecuted.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Commissaire, <Alignment alignment="12517" annotation_id="23252">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23252" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je fais délibérément tomber en mer 2 000 grosses boîtes métalliques pleines de matériaux, je serais poursuivi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20795" docOffset="141">
      <en>Yet we allow this to happen every year in EU waters.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23366">Pourtant</DiscourseConnective>, nous permettons que cela arrive chaque année dans les eaux européennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20848" docOffset="142">
      <en>I make a plea: you cannot play Pontius Pilot with this and wash your hands of the problem.</en>
      <fr>Je lance un appel: vous ne pouvez pas jouer les Ponce Pilate sur ce sujet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23522">et</DiscourseConnective> vous laver les mains de ce problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20939" docOffset="143">
      <en>It is a problem that is increasing.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23565">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un problème qui va s'amplifiant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20975" docOffset="144">
      <en>It is a serious problem <Alignment alignment="32720" annotation_id="20999">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20999" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is a problem that you have to address.</en>
      <fr>C'est un problème grave <Alignment alignment="13212" annotation_id="23631">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23631" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est un problème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23652">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il vous faut aborder.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21045" docOffset="145">
      <en>It is not a problem you can hide behind, saying 'well, we need to assess this' and 'we need to assess that', or whatever.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est pas un problème derrière lequel vous pouvez vous cacher en disant: "Eh bien, nous devons évaluer ceci" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23789">et</DiscourseConnective> "Nous devons évaluer cela", etc.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21167" docOffset="146">
      <en>You have heard what the Members have said.</en>
      <fr>Vous avez entendu ce que les députés ont dit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21210" docOffset="147">
      <en>Please now get on with trying to sort it out.</en>
      <fr>Efforcez-vous à présent de trouver une solution</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="21256" id="051" language="GA" name="Máire Geoghegan-Quinn">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="21256" docOffset="148">
      <en>Mr President, I am grateful to all Members who participated in this debate <Alignment alignment="50781" annotation_id="21331">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21331" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would like to emphasise that I fully understand the importance of the topic we are discussing <Alignment alignment="58519" annotation_id="21431">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21431" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> how important it is in the opinion of Members that the Commission press ahead with a policy that would resolve this particular matter.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je remercie tous les députés qui ont participé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23989">à</DiscourseConnective> ce débat, <Alignment alignment="18991" annotation_id="24001">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24001" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24013">à</DiscourseConnective> souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24025">que</DiscourseConnective> je comprends tout à fait la dimension du sujet dont nous discutons <Alignment alignment="11285" annotation_id="24096">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24096" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> combien il est important, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24125">pour</DiscourseConnective> les députés, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24143">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission établisse rapidement une politique permettant de résoudre ce problème.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21570" docOffset="149">
      <en>I believe that the debate, and all that everyone has contributed, has shown the importance of the affair.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24241">que</DiscourseConnective> le débat, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24255">et</DiscourseConnective> la contribution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24274">que</DiscourseConnective> chacun y a apportée, a montré à quel point cette question était importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21676" docOffset="150">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="30403" annotation_id="21678">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21678" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> believe the debate showed the importance to be attached to the protection of the environment.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Je crois <Alignment alignment="10471" annotation_id="24368">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24368" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que ce débat a montré l'importance qu'il faut attacher <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24433">à</DiscourseConnective> la protection de l'environnement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21777" docOffset="151">
      <en>Interestingly, the debate has gone from Mrs Meissner's rubber ducks and shoes all the way to Columbus, who folklore says paid a visit to my home port in the west of Ireland.</en>
      <fr>D'une façon intéressante, la discussion est passée des canards en caoutchouc <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24546">et</DiscourseConnective> des chaussures de Mme Meissner à Christophe Colomb qui, selon la légende, serait passé par chez moi, dans l'ouest de l'Irlande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21951" docOffset="152">
      <en>I am very glad that he took that famous voyage!</en>
      <fr>Je me réjouis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24691">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ait effectué ce célèbre voyage!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21999" docOffset="153">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="59105" annotation_id="21999">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21999" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I would like to emphasise again to all of the Members, but <Alignment alignment="46152" annotation_id="22067">
          <Alignment alignment="48798" annotation_id="22067">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22067" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> to Mr Simpson who has taken such a keen interest in this area <Alignment alignment="56238" annotation_id="22143">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22143" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> who has put so much work into it, that we are very serious about this particular issue.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5371" annotation_id="24729">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24729" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Quoiqu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il en soit, je voudrais souligner une fois de plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24787">à</DiscourseConnective> tous les députés et, <Alignment alignment="22067" annotation_id="24810">
          <Alignment alignment="7954" annotation_id="24810">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24810" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24826">à</DiscourseConnective> M. Simpson qui se passionne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24856">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce sujet <Alignment alignment="1582" annotation_id="24870">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24870" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui y a investi tant d'efforts, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24905">que</DiscourseConnective> nous considérons cette question très sérieusement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22235" docOffset="154">
      <en>We are aware of the large increase in the number of containers that are lost <Alignment alignment="60724" annotation_id="22312">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22312" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="57980" annotation_id="22317">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22317" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I said earlier, Commissioner Kallas is looking at this problem.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes conscients de l'augmentation du nombre de conteneurs perdus <Alignment alignment="4615" annotation_id="25032">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25032" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="9999" annotation_id="25036">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25036" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai dit plus tôt, le commissaire Kallas étudie la question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22384" docOffset="155">
      <en>He believes it is not just linked to the lashing of containers but also to overweight containers.</en>
      <fr>Il estime que le problème n'est pas seulement lié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25156">à</DiscourseConnective> l'arrimage des conteneurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25184">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25189">également</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25199">à</DiscourseConnective> leur surcharge.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22482" docOffset="156">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="25281" annotation_id="22488">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22488" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> due sometimes to the strength of the ship which was an issue that was raised, and the age of the ships - an issue raised by Mr Higgins.</en>
      <fr>Parfois il est <Alignment alignment="14517" annotation_id="25232">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25232" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> lié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25246">à</DiscourseConnective> la résistance du navire, point qui a été évoqué précédemment, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25310">et</DiscourseConnective> à son âge, comme cela a été soulevé par M. Higgins.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22629" docOffset="157">
      <en>Safety and protection of the marine environment, <Alignment alignment="20364" annotation_id="22678">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22678" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I said earlier, are very important priorities for the Commission.</en>
      <fr>La sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25377">et</DiscourseConnective> la protection de l'environnement maritime constituent, <Alignment alignment="22678" annotation_id="25435">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25435" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je l'ai <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25449">déjà</DiscourseConnective> dit, des priorités importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25485">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22747" docOffset="158">
      <en>We cannot compromise on those issues <Alignment alignment="10636" annotation_id="22784">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22784" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we, and Commissioner Kallas in particular, will certainly consider whether further action is necessary.</en>
      <fr>Nous ne pouvons pas transiger sur ces questions, <Alignment alignment="5995" annotation_id="25554">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25554" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous, le commissaire Kallas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25585">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>, allons certainement examiner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25630">si</DiscourseConnective> des mesures supplémentaires sont nécessaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22892" docOffset="159">
      <en>I am sure he would be very happy to work closely with you and your committee, Mr Simpson, in coming to a conclusion on that.</en>
      <fr>Je suis convaincue qu'il serait ravi de travailler en étroite collaboration avec vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25765">et</DiscourseConnective> votre commission, Monsieur Simpson, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25804">pour</DiscourseConnective> arriver <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25817">à</DiscourseConnective> une conclusion sur ce sujet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23017" docOffset="160">
      <en>We already have quite a number of tools at our disposal to ensure safety, as well as the prevention of pollution, including from containers lost at sea.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25859">déjà</DiscourseConnective> un certain nombre d'outils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25891">à</DiscourseConnective> notre disposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25911">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer la sécurité et prévenir la pollution, y compris celle qui provient des conteneurs perdus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26013">en</DiscourseConnective> mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23170" docOffset="161">
      <en>With regard to concrete action on the issue, I believe that action at an EU level does not seem necessary at this stage.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26021">En</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne une action concrète sur ce sujet, je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26083">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à ce stade, cela n'est pas nécessaire au niveau européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23291" docOffset="162">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="26144" annotation_id="23291">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23291" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I do take your point that the IMO as an organisation is moving very slowly <Alignment alignment="34343" annotation_id="23375">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23375" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that the Commission needs to get involved to push for quicker solutions.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9454" annotation_id="26144">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26144" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, j'ai bien noté votre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26176">remarque</DiscourseConnective> sur le fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26197">que</DiscourseConnective> l'OMI en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26210">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>organisation fonctionne très lentement, <Alignment alignment="24259" annotation_id="26258">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26258" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26261">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission doit faire tout son possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26308">pour que</DiscourseConnective> des solutions soient trouvées rapidement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23452" docOffset="163">
      <en>I still think, <Alignment alignment="15989" annotation_id="23467">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23467" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I know that Commissioner Kallas feels very strongly, that the adequate forum to discuss these issues is still the IMO, <Alignment alignment="24720" annotation_id="23590">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23590" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I suppose a review of the recent results of the lashing@sea project could be encouraged there.</en>
      <fr>Je continue de penser, <Alignment alignment="23467" annotation_id="26382">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26382" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je sais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26393">que</DiscourseConnective> le commissaire Kallas partage tout à fait cet avis, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26449">que</DiscourseConnective> le forum le plus approprié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26480">pour</DiscourseConnective> discuter de ces questions demeure l'OMI, <Alignment alignment="2464" annotation_id="26526">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26526" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suppose qu'un examen des derniers résultats du projet Lashing@sea pourrait être encouragé dans ce cadre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23689" docOffset="164">
      <en>That project <Alignment alignment="8096" annotation_id="23702">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23702" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> confirms the importance of having a global approach <Alignment alignment="35259" annotation_id="23759">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23759" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are developing procedures and standards <Alignment alignment="49975" annotation_id="23807">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23807" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we keep this level playing field that we talked about earlier between operators from Member States and indeed other states.</en>
      <fr>Ce projet confirme <Alignment alignment="4149" annotation_id="26656">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26656" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'importance d'avoir une approche globale <Alignment alignment="12857" annotation_id="26708">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26708" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">lorsque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous développons des procédures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26748">et</DiscourseConnective> des normes, <Alignment alignment="13716" annotation_id="26763">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26763" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> conserver le degré d'égalité dont nous avons parlé plus tôt entre les exploitants des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26871">et</DiscourseConnective> ceux des autres pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="23939" docOffset="165">
      <en>Let me conclude by emphasising that these issues should first be discussed in the IMO.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26896">Pour conclure</DiscourseConnective>, permettez-moi de souligner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26938">que</DiscourseConnective> ces questions devraient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="26966">tout d'abord</DiscourseConnective> être discutées par l'OMI.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24026" docOffset="166">
      <en>The Commission participates as an observer in the IMO and the Commission prepares positions together with the Member States.</en>
      <fr>La Commission participe en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27032">tant qu'</DiscourseConnective>observateur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27052">à</DiscourseConnective> l'OMI <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27060">et</DiscourseConnective> elle prépare des positions avec les États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24151" docOffset="167">
      <en>I can assure you that I will convey the results of the debate here today to Commissioner Kallas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24247" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> the issue, I know, will be looked at by him and promoted in that context.</en>
      <fr>Je peux vous assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27135">que</DiscourseConnective> je transmettrai les résultats du débat d'aujourd'hui au commissaire Kallas qui, je le sais, examinera le problème dans ce contexte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27270">et</DiscourseConnective> favorisera sa résolution.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="24325" id="053" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="24325" docOffset="168">
      <en>The debate is closed.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24347" docOffset="169">
      <en>Written statements (Rule 149)</en>
      <fr>Déclaration écrite (article 149)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="24377" id="054" language="PL" name="Artur Zasada">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="24377" docOffset="170">
      <en>I would like to offer my congratulations on the decision to take up the subject of containers lost at sea.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27360">à</DiscourseConnective> saluer la décision d'aborder la question des conteneurs perdus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27425">en</DiscourseConnective> mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24484" docOffset="171">
      <en>On 8 February this year, ferries sailing from Poland to Sweden were in immediate danger.</en>
      <fr>Le 8 février dernier, des navires transbordeurs naviguant entre la Pologne et la Suède se sont trouvés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27536">en</DiscourseConnective> danger immédiat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24573" docOffset="172">
      <en>The Finnish freight vessel the Linda was sailing from Rotterdam to St Petersburg, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24655" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="14999" annotation_id="24659">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24659" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> crossing lanes used by Polish and Swedish vessels it lost three containers containing 8.3 tonnes of substances classified as dangerous to the environment, 7 tonnes of products which are hazardous to marine life and 5.5 tonnes of flammable substances.</en>
      <fr>Le bateau finlandais de marchandise Linda naviguait de Rotterdam <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27621">à</DiscourseConnective> Saint-Pétersbourg et, <Alignment alignment="12799" annotation_id="27645">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27645" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>il traversait les voies utilisées par les navires polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27713">et</DiscourseConnective> suédois, il a perdu trois conteneurs renfermant 8,3 tonnes de substances classées dangereuses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27810">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'environnement, 7 tonnes de produits nocifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27860">pour</DiscourseConnective> la vie marine <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27879">et</DiscourseConnective> 5,5 tonnes de substances inflammables.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24916" docOffset="173">
      <en>Fortunately, this time it was possible to avert a tragedy.</en>
      <fr>Par chance, il a été possible, cette fois, d'éviter une tragédie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="24975" docOffset="174">
      <en>I agree that all containers should be weighed in port and correctly stowed <Alignment alignment="61925" annotation_id="25050">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25050" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vessels head to sea.</en>
      <fr>Je suis favorable à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28010">que</DiscourseConnective> tous les conteneurs soient pesés dans les ports <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28062">et</DiscourseConnective> correctement arrimés <Alignment alignment="13102" annotation_id="28086">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28086" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le navire ne prenne la mer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25078" docOffset="175">
      <en>This is, <Alignment alignment="28124" annotation_id="25087">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25087" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, a long-term plan.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13177" annotation_id="28124">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28124" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28138">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un projet à long terme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25114" docOffset="176">
      <en>The plan for today is for the Commission to introduce a regulation which provides for particular supervision of containers with substances classified as hazardous.</en>
      <fr>Le projet <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28181">pour</DiscourseConnective> aujourd'hui est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28202">que</DiscourseConnective> la Commission introduise une réglementation qui prévoie un contrôle spécifique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28285">pour</DiscourseConnective> les conteneurs comportant des substances classées dangereuses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="25278" docOffset="177">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23842" annotation_id="25278">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25278" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I would like to ask the Commission a question: when may we expect the first action on this matter?</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="25278" annotation_id="28353">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28353" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je voudrais poser une question à la Commission: <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="28417">quand</DiscourseConnective> peut-on espérer une première mesure sur ce sujet?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
