<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Transportation of horses for slaughter in the European Union (written declaration)</en>
    <fr>Transport des chevaux destinés à l'abattage dans l'Union européenne (déclaration écrite)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="83" id="012" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="83" docOffset="1">
      <en>I would like to inform you that Written Declaration 0054/2009 by Mrs Lynne, Mrs Jędrzejewska and Mr Schlyter on the transportation of horses for slaughter in the European Union was signed today, 24 February 2010, by a majority of Parliament's component Members. <Alignment alignment="1506" annotation_id="345">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="345" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in accordance with Rule 124(4) of the Rules of Procedure, it will be forwarded to its addressees and published with the names of its signatories in the Texts Adopted of the sitting of 25 February 2010.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais vous informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="115">que</DiscourseConnective> la déclaration écrite 0054/2009 déposée par les députés Elizabeth Lynne, Sidonia Elżbieta Jędrzejewska <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="222">et</DiscourseConnective> Carl Schlyter sur le transport de chevaux destinés à l'abattage dans l'Union européenne a recueilli aujourd'hui, 24 février 2010, les signatures de la majorité des membres qui composent le Parlement et qu'elle sera <Alignment alignment="345" annotation_id="440">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="440" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, conformément à l'article 123, paragraphes 3 et 4, du règlement, transmise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="530">à</DiscourseConnective> ses destinataires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="550">et</DiscourseConnective> publiée dans les textes adoptés de la séance du 25 février 2010, avec indication au procès-verbal des noms des signataires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="558" docOffset="2">
      <en>We would like to thank the authors for submitting this declaration.</en>
      <fr>Nous voudrions remercier les auteurs d'avoir déposé cette déclaration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="626" id="013" name="Elizabeth Lynne">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="626" docOffset="3">
      <en>author. - Mr President, it is great news that we have achieved the right number of signatures.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, je suis ravie d'apprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="797">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons obtenu le nombre de signatures requis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="721" docOffset="4">
      <en>Thank you everyone for signing this written declaration.</en>
      <fr>Je remercie toutes les personnes qui ont signé cette déclaration écrite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="778" id="014" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="778" docOffset="5">
      <en>I would like to inform you that I did not have the possibility of signing this declaration, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="870" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I am ready to do it immediately.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais vous informer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="950">que</DiscourseConnective> je n'ai pas eu la possibilité de signer cette déclaration et que je suis disposé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1035">à</DiscourseConnective> le faire immédiatement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
