<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>12.</en>
    <fr>12.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4" docOffset="1">
    <en>Closure of the accounts of the European Police College for the financial year 2008</en>
    <fr>Clôture des comptes du collège européen de police <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="54">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'exercice 2008</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="87" id="112" name="Véronique Mathieu">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="87" docOffset="2">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, on 7 October 2010 Parliament adopted by 618 votes to 0, with 7 abstentions, a decision to refuse to grant discharge to the European Police College for the financial year 2008.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, le 7 octobre 2010, le Parlement a adopté par 618 voix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="169">pour</DiscourseConnective>, aucune contre et 7 abstentions, une décision de refus de décharge au Collège européen de police <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="271">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'exercice 2008.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="304" docOffset="3">
      <en>In accordance with Parliament's Rules of Procedure, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="356" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> discharge is not granted, a formal proposal to close the accounts shall be submitted at a subsequent part-session.</en>
      <fr>Selon le règlement du Parlement, dans les cas où la décharge n'est pas accordée, une proposition formelle de clôture des comptes est présentée lors d'une session ultérieure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="474" docOffset="4">
      <en>The decision put to the vote today is <Alignment alignment="232238" annotation_id="512">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="512" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a technical measure designed to close the accounts for the financial year in question, not the granting of discharge.</en>
      <fr>La décision soumise au vote aujourd'hui est <Alignment alignment="512" annotation_id="511">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="511" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une mesure technique, destinée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="547">à</DiscourseConnective> clôturer l'exercice concerné et non un octroi de décharge.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="640" docOffset="5">
      <en>I wanted to make that clear.</en>
      <fr>Je tenais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="618">à</DiscourseConnective> préciser ce point.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
