<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes</en>
    <fr>Corrections <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12">et</DiscourseConnective> intentions de vote: voir procès-verbal</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="56" docOffset="1">
    <en>(The sitting was suspended at 13.05 and resumed at 15.00)</en>
    <fr>(La séance, suspendue à 13 h 05, est reprise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="99">à</DiscourseConnective> 15 heures)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="114" id="282" name="Raül Romeva i Rueda">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="114" docOffset="2">
      <en>(FR) I should just like to communicate some information I received a moment ago to the House.</en>
      <fr>Je veux juste communiquer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="138">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Assemblée une information que je viens d'apprendre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="208" docOffset="3">
      <en>For some weeks now, a new and unprecedented phenomenon has been occurring around certain large occupied towns in Western Sahara, that is to say, more than 12 000 Saharawi men, women and children are, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="408" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> we speak, deserting their towns and moving into tents in the vicinity of Laayoune, Smara and Boujdour.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="194">Depuis</DiscourseConnective> quelques semaines, un phénomène nouveau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="241">et</DiscourseConnective> sans précédent se déroule autour de certaines grandes villes occupées du Sahara occidental, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="336">c'est-à-dire que</DiscourseConnective> plus de 12 000 Sahraouis, hommes, femmes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="394">et</DiscourseConnective> enfants sont littéralement en train de vider leurs villes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="455">et</DiscourseConnective> de s'installer dans des tentes dans les environs de Laayoune, Smara <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="526">et</DiscourseConnective> Boujdour.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="514" docOffset="4">
      <en>The movements, which are steadily increasing, appear to be a new way of protesting against the unbearable political and socioeconomic situation of the indigenous inhabitants of these territories.</en>
      <fr>Les mouvements qui ne cessent de croître se présentent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="594">comme</DiscourseConnective> une nouvelle façon de protester contre la situation intenable, tant sur le plan politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="690">que</DiscourseConnective> socioéconomique, des habitants autochtones de ces territoires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="710" docOffset="5">
      <en>I am saying this today and right now <Alignment alignment="369659" annotation_id="747">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="747" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the problem posed by the many violent interventions by the Moroccan regime could worryingly become worse this weekend.</en>
      <fr>Si je dis ça aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="782">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="785">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="67" annotation_id="797">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="797" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">c'est parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le problème des multiples interventions violentes de la part du régime marocain risque de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="903">s'</DiscourseConnective>aggraver de façon préoccupante ce week-end.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="874" docOffset="6">
      <en>That is why I call on Parliament to be ready to react depending on how the situation unfolds.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="949">C'est pourquoi</DiscourseConnective> je demande au Parlement d'être prêt <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1000">à</DiscourseConnective> réagir en fonction de l'évolution de la situation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="968" id="283" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="968" docOffset="7">
      <en>I will take it into account.</en>
      <fr>Je prendrai cela en considération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="997" docOffset="8">
      <en>It was of course a point of order and the situation in Western Sahara <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1067" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> the situation in Morocco are not what we are supposed to be talking about this afternoon.</en>
      <fr>Il s'agissait, bien sûr, d'une motion de procédure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1139">et</DiscourseConnective> nous ne sommes pas censés discuter de la situation au Sahara occidental ni de la situation au Maroc cet après-midi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1161" docOffset="9">
      <en>I will, <Alignment alignment="319" annotation_id="1169">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1169" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, take note of what you said.</en>
      <fr>Je prends <Alignment alignment="401" annotation_id="1268">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1268" sense="Comparison.Contrast">cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> bonne note de ce que vous avez dit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
