<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>5.</en>
    <fr>5.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Improvements in the safety and health at work of pregnant workers and workers who have recently given birth or are breastfeeding (</en>
    <fr>Amélioration de la sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="31">et</DiscourseConnective> de la santé des travailleuses enceintes, accouchées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="86">ou</DiscourseConnective> allaitantes au travail (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="134" id="149" name="Carl Schlyter">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="134" docOffset="2">
      <en>(SV) There are several translation errors in the Swedish version of this report.</en>
      <fr>(SV) Nous avons relevé plusieurs erreurs de traduction dans la version suédoise du rapport.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="215" docOffset="3">
      <en>Among other things, there is confusion between the terms barnledighet (parental leave) and mammaledighet (maternity leave).</en>
      <fr>Entre autres, il y a une confusion entre les termes barnledighet (congé parental) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="288">et</DiscourseConnective> mammaledighet (congé de maternité).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="339" docOffset="4">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="327" annotation_id="339">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="339" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in Amendment 125 in particular, there is a very serious translation error.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3" annotation_id="327">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="327" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'amendement 125 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="349">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> présente une très grave erreur de traduction.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="423" docOffset="5">
      <en>The Swedish version of Amendment 125 states that paternity leave should be on full pay. It does not say this in other versions.</en>
      <fr>La version suédoise de l'amendement 125 indique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="458">que</DiscourseConnective> le congé de paternité devrait être entièrement rémunéré, ce que n'indiquent pas les autres versions linguistiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="551" docOffset="6">
      <en>This means that there is no difference between Amendment 50 and Amendment 125 in the Swedish version.</en>
      <fr>Cela signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="591">que</DiscourseConnective> la version suédoise ne fait aucune différence entre l'amendement 50 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="663">et</DiscourseConnective> l'amendement 125.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="653" docOffset="7">
      <en>It would be good <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="670" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> this could be corrected.</en>
      <fr>Il serait opportun de corriger cette erreur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
