<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Voting time (continued)</en>
    <fr>Heure des votes (suite)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="24" id="090" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="24" docOffset="1">
      <en>Before the vote, we will hear speeches from the chairs of the political groups on the election of the new Commission.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24">Avant</DiscourseConnective> le vote, nous écouterons les discours des présidents des groupes politiques sur l'élection de la nouvelle Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="142" id="091" language="FR" name="Joseph Daul">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="142" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, Mr López Garrido, President of the Commission, thank you for giving me the opportunity to say why I firmly believe, on behalf of the Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats), that Mr Barroso and his College of Commissioners, assisted by members of staff from the Commission, will be equal to the challenges that they face.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe PPE. - Monsieur le Président, Messieurs les Présidents du Conseil et de la Commission, je vous remercie de me donner l'occasion de dire pourquoi je crois fermement, au nom du groupe PPE, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="352">que</DiscourseConnective> José Manuel Barroso <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="376">et</DiscourseConnective> son collège de commissaires, assistés de collaborateurs de la Commission, seront <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="460">à</DiscourseConnective> la hauteur des enjeux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="497" docOffset="3">
      <en>Europe was born of an international crisis <Alignment alignment="35327" annotation_id="540">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="540" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, for the first time in 60 years, it is facing a new international crisis that is of a different type <Alignment alignment="11948" annotation_id="645">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="645" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that is undoubtedly serious and dangerous.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe est née d'une crise mondiale <Alignment alignment="540" annotation_id="523">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="523" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="527">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="549">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 60 ans, elle affronte une nouvelle crise globale d'un autre type <Alignment alignment="645" annotation_id="621">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="621" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, sans nul doute, grave <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="649">et</DiscourseConnective> dangereuse.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="692" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is overcoming it, <Alignment alignment="45864" annotation_id="713">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="713" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are not yet out of the woods.</en>
      <fr>Elle est en train de la surmonter, <Alignment alignment="713" annotation_id="699">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="699" sense="Comparison.Contrast">même si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne sommes pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="726">encore</DiscourseConnective> tirés d'affaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="755" docOffset="5">
      <en>The euro has done its job as a monetary shield; there will never be enough words to say how much we owe it: the automatic stabilisers, those famous solidarity mechanisms, which are too ...</en>
      <fr>L'euro a joué son rôle de bouclier monétaire, on ne dira jamais assez ce qu'on lui doit: les stabilisateurs automatiques, ces fameux mécanismes de solidarité, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="909">que</DiscourseConnective> l'on a trop...</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="944" docOffset="6">
      <en>You have benefited a great deal from them, my friends!</en>
      <fr>Vous en avez largement profité, les amis!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="999" docOffset="7">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1010" docOffset="8">
      <en>Where would you be now without the solidarity stabilisers?</en>
      <fr>Dans quelle situation seriez-vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1023">s'</DiscourseConnective>il n'y avait pas les stabilisateurs de solidarité?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1069" docOffset="9">
      <en>Too often they have been regarded as a burden weighing down our economies, <Alignment alignment="30786" annotation_id="1144">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1144" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they have done a great deal to keep the European model afloat. An attractive, much-copied model to which our fellow citizens are rightly attached, <Alignment alignment="39856" annotation_id="1295">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1295" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which is being called into question by new challenges.</en>
      <fr>On les a trop souvent considérés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1109">comme</DiscourseConnective> un boulet pesant sur nos économies <Alignment alignment="11772" annotation_id="1150">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1150" sense="Comparison.Contrast">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils ont été pour beaucoup dans la solidité du modèle européen, un modèle qui attire, qui est copié, et auquel nos concitoyens sont justement attachés, <Alignment alignment="15287" annotation_id="1304">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1304" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un modèle remis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1325">en</DiscourseConnective> cause par de nouveaux défis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1354" docOffset="10">
      <en>The world has become multipolar, but not in the way we dreamed; we dreamed that it would be idealistic, peaceful and multilateral.</en>
      <fr>Le monde est devenu multipolaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1391">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas comme on le rêvait: idéaliste, pacifié <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1439">et</DiscourseConnective> multilatéral.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1485" docOffset="11">
      <en>No, the world has become one of competition, of a struggle - a peaceful one, certainly, but a fierce one - to impose one's model on the others.</en>
      <fr>Non, c'est bien d'une compétition qu'il s'agit, d'une lutte - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1518">certes</DiscourseConnective> pacifique, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1536">mais</DiscourseConnective> farouche - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1552">pour</DiscourseConnective> imposer son modèle aux autres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1629" docOffset="12">
      <en>In the face of this challenge, the Union, which has so many tools at its disposal, must not waste them.</en>
      <fr>Face <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1593">à</DiscourseConnective> cet enjeu, l'Union, qui dispose de tant d'atouts, ne doit pas les gâcher.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1733" docOffset="13">
      <en>It must remain true to itself, by embracing ideas and people, and by pioneering the fight against global warming, <Alignment alignment="8738" annotation_id="1847">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1847" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it must <Alignment alignment="13801" annotation_id="1859">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1859" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> arm itself with the resources to compete.</en>
      <fr>Elle doit rester elle-même, championne de l'ouverture aux idées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1733">et</DiscourseConnective> aux hommes, pionnière de la lutte contre le réchauffement climatique, <Alignment alignment="9969" annotation_id="1806">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1806" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle doit <Alignment alignment="1357" annotation_id="1821">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1821" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> s'armer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1835">pour</DiscourseConnective> la compétition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1906" docOffset="14">
      <en>That is, I know, what the new Commission is going to strive to achieve with us.</en>
      <fr>C'est, je le sais, ce à quoi la nouvelle Commission va s'atteler avec nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1986" docOffset="15">
      <en>We all know about Europe's weaknesses: demographics, lack of future expenditure, industrial challenges, government deficit, weak economic governance.</en>
      <fr>Nous connaissons tous les faiblesses de l'Europe: démographie, insuffisance des dépenses d'avenir, défis industriels, déficit public, faible gouvernance économique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2136" docOffset="16">
      <en>That is one more reason why we should make the most of our tools: the euro and monetary policy, technological achievements, industrial flagships, agricultural potential to guarantee the food security of our 500 million fellow citizens.</en>
      <fr>Raison <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2104">de plus</DiscourseConnective> pour valoriser nos atouts: euro <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2144">et</DiscourseConnective> politique monétaire, prouesses technologiques, fleurons de l'industrie, potentiel agricole <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2238">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer la sécurité alimentaire de nos 500 millions de concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2372" docOffset="17">
      <en>To this end, I expect the Commission to show imagination and leadership in the European legislation that we will be called on to adopt.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2311">Pour</DiscourseConnective> cela, j'attends de la Commission qu'elle fasse preuve d'imagination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2384">et</DiscourseConnective> de leadership dans les législations européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2435">que</DiscourseConnective> nous serons amenés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2458">à</DiscourseConnective> adopter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2508" docOffset="18">
      <en>I expect it to defend European interests, to demand reciprocity from our partners and to have no hesitation in resorting to the legal means at its disposal in the event of violations.</en>
      <fr>J'attends d'elle qu'elle défende les intérêts européens, qu'elle exige la réciprocité de la part de nos partenaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2585">et</DiscourseConnective> qu'elle n'hésite pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2609">à</DiscourseConnective> recourir aux moyens légaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2638">à</DiscourseConnective> sa disposition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2655">en</DiscourseConnective> cas de manquements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2692" docOffset="19">
      <en>Commissioners, it is your responsibility, with us, with the Council, to complete the internal market.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames et Messieurs les commissaires, il vous appartient, avec nous, avec le Conseil, d'achever le marché intérieur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2794" docOffset="20">
      <en>To do so, we must break taboos such as those of taxation and of the social dimension.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2797">Pour</DiscourseConnective> cela, il nous faut briser les tabous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2839">comme</DiscourseConnective> celui de la fiscalité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2867">et</DiscourseConnective> du social.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2880" docOffset="21">
      <en>The Member States can no longer act as though these two areas are restricted and untouchable competences, beyond the scope of common action.</en>
      <fr>Les États membres ne peuvent plus faire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2921">comme si</DiscourseConnective> ces deux domaines étaient des compétences réservées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2982">et</DiscourseConnective> intouchables, hors de portée de l'action commune.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3021" docOffset="22">
      <en>At the same time, <Alignment alignment="19977" annotation_id="3039">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3039" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we must be much more forceful with regard to the external challenges: security and defence, but also trade, technological and industrial standards, and environmental standards.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3039" annotation_id="3035">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3035" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il faut, dans le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3057">même</DiscourseConnective> temps, redoubler de force sur les défis extérieurs: sécurité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3123">et</DiscourseConnective> défense, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3135">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> normes commerciales, technologiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3182">ou</DiscourseConnective> industrielles, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3200">et</DiscourseConnective> normes environnementales.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3225" docOffset="23">
      <en>Europe must defend its values, peace and the prosperity of its citizens.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe doit assurer la défense de ses valeurs, la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3286">et</DiscourseConnective> la prospérité de ses concitoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3298" docOffset="24">
      <en>Europe must be an international player and not merely an area of prosperity and of law.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe doit être un acteur global <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3359">et</DiscourseConnective> pas seulement un simple espace de prospérité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3407">et</DiscourseConnective> de droit.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3386" docOffset="25">
      <en>It must not deprive itself of the tools that come with its power.</en>
      <fr>Elle ne doit pas se priver elle-même des outils de sa puissance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3452" docOffset="26">
      <en>The PPE Group expects the Commission to work effectively on all these fronts, at the same time.</en>
      <fr>Le groupe PPE attend de la Commission un travail efficace sur tous ces fronts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3563">à</DiscourseConnective> la fois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3548" docOffset="27">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="44833" annotation_id="3548">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3548" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it does so - and I have no reason to doubt it - it will always have the support of the PPE Group.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3548" annotation_id="3574">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3574" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle le fait - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3592">et</DiscourseConnective> je n'ai pas de raison d'en douter -, elle trouvera toujours le groupe PPE à ses côtés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3649" docOffset="28">
      <en>Mr Barroso, the PPE Group has faith in you; it asks you to be bold, to reform.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président Barroso, le groupe PPE vous fait confiance, il vous invite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3763">à</DiscourseConnective> l'audace, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3775">à</DiscourseConnective> la réforme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3728" docOffset="29">
      <en>It asks you to be far-sighted, for the benefit of the cause that brings us together: the creation of political Europe.</en>
      <fr>Il vous demande de voir loin, au service de la cause qui nous rassemble: la réalisation de l'Europe politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3847" docOffset="30">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3858" id="092" language="DE" name="Martin Schulz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3858" docOffset="31">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament has not made its decision lightly.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, le groupe de l'Alliance progressiste des Socialistes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4012">et</DiscourseConnective> Démocrates au Parlement européen n'a pas pris sa décision à la légère.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4022" docOffset="32">
      <en>We voted on the President of the Commission five months ago in this House <Alignment alignment="6252" annotation_id="4096">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4096" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="15612" annotation_id="4100">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4100" sense="Comparison.Concession">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we did not give him our support <Alignment alignment="7641" annotation_id="4141">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4141" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, he received the majority vote.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons voté sur le président de la Commission il y a cinq mois dans ce Parlement <Alignment alignment="9223" annotation_id="4171">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4171" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <Alignment alignment="4100" annotation_id="4174">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4174" sense="Comparison.Concession">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne l'ayons pas soutenu <Alignment alignment="4141" annotation_id="4211">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4211" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il a reçu le vote de la majorité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4178" docOffset="33">
      <en>On the basis of this majority, which regrettably rested on people who are actually not in favour of the Treaty of Lisbon, he has presented a College to us and today we are to assess this College.</en>
      <fr>Sur la base de cette majorité, qui reposait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4296">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> sur des opposants au traité de Lisbonne, il nous a présenté un collège <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4383">et</DiscourseConnective> aujourd'hui nous devons évaluer ce collège.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4374" docOffset="34">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="4442" annotation_id="4380">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4380" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> necessary for us to assess this College.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons <Alignment alignment="5184" annotation_id="4442">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4442" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> évaluer ce collège.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4426" docOffset="35">
      <en>There are two options open to us: we can go and divide this House into those on the Right and those on the Left.</en>
      <fr>Deux options se présentent: nous pouvons diviser cette Assemblée entre ceux de la droite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4561">et</DiscourseConnective> ceux de la gauche.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4539" docOffset="36">
      <en>These two groups have conflicting ideologies and must vote <Alignment alignment="23709" annotation_id="4598">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4598" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">accordingly</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</en>
      <fr>Ces deux groupes ont des idéologies opposées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4628">et</DiscourseConnective> ils doivent voter <Alignment alignment="13670" annotation_id="4649">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4649" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">en conséquence</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4611" docOffset="37">
      <en>That is one option.</en>
      <fr>Voilà une option.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4631" docOffset="38">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="24523" annotation_id="4631">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4631" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this is not the way that Europe works.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2894" annotation_id="4683">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4683" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ce n'est pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4707">comme ça</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4716">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe fonctionne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4679" docOffset="39">
      <en>We do not have a majority in this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Nous n'avons pas de majorité dans ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4725" docOffset="40">
      <en>The Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) does not have a majority in this Parliament either, nor has the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe.</en>
      <fr>Le groupe du Parti populaire européen (Démocrates-Chrétiens) n'a pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4858">non plus</DiscourseConnective> de majorité au sein de ce Parlement, pas plus que le groupe Alliance des démocrates <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4951">et</DiscourseConnective> des libéraux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4967">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4912" docOffset="41">
      <en>Europe is not an entity in which any political force whatsoever can alone cobble together a majority and say that Europe will now be governed in a particular way.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe n'est pas une entité où n'importe quelle force politique peut obtenir à elle seule une majorité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5087">et</DiscourseConnective> déclarer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5099">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe sera désormais dirigée de manière déterminée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5075" docOffset="42">
      <en>Europe is a permanent compromise.</en>
      <fr>L'Europe est un compromis permanent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5109" docOffset="43">
      <en>That is what sometimes makes it so cumbersome and also so difficult to understand.</en>
      <fr>C'est ce qui la rend parfois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5224">si</DiscourseConnective> pesante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5235">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5238">si</DiscourseConnective> difficile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5251">à</DiscourseConnective> comprendre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5192" docOffset="44">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17119" annotation_id="5192">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5192" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, better a permanent compromise, which leads to successes and more social justice, than an ideological battle that ultimately fizzles out without any tangible results.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="5192" annotation_id="5265">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5265" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5276">mieux</DiscourseConnective> vaut un compromis permanent, qui conduit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5323">à</DiscourseConnective> des succès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5336">et</DiscourseConnective> à une plus grande justice sociale, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5374">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une bataille idéologique qui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5407">en fin de compte</DiscourseConnective>, ne débouche sur aucun <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5447">résultat</DiscourseConnective> tangible.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5367" docOffset="45">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5378" docOffset="46">
      <en>It is <Alignment alignment="58320" annotation_id="5384">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5384" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> very difficult for us to weigh up the benefits.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13760" annotation_id="5485">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5485" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, il nous est très difficile d'évaluer les avantages.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5442" docOffset="47">
      <en>Of course, we all enjoy a tussle.</en>
      <fr>Bien sûr, nous aimons tous une mêlée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5476" docOffset="48">
      <en>I, too, enjoy arguing principles with fellow Members from other groups, <Alignment alignment="19067" annotation_id="5548">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5548" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Europe <Alignment alignment="17517" annotation_id="5559">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5559" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> needs tangible results.</en>
      <fr>Moi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5595">aussi</DiscourseConnective>, j'aime discuter de principes avec mes collègues d'autres groupes <Alignment alignment="22322" annotation_id="5667">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5667" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Europe a <Alignment alignment="5559" annotation_id="5683">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5683" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> besoin de résultats tangibles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5588" docOffset="49">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="37040" annotation_id="5591">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5591" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> asked ourselves what we, as Social Democrats - as Socialists and Democrats - can call for and get accepted.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous sommes <Alignment alignment="5591" annotation_id="5741">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5741" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demandés ce que nous, sociaux-démocrates - socialistes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5805">et</DiscourseConnective> démocrates - pouvons demander <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5838">et</DiscourseConnective> faire accepter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5709" docOffset="50">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="26384" annotation_id="5712">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5712" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> defined criteria.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="22551" annotation_id="5868">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5868" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> défini des critères.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5735" docOffset="51">
      <en>One criterion was that we wanted the political force that is the second-strongest force in Europe to be represented on a higher level in this Commission.</en>
      <fr>Un critère était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5912">que</DiscourseConnective> nous voulions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5930">que</DiscourseConnective> la deuxième force politique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5962">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5972">soit</DiscourseConnective> représentée au plus niveau dans cette Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5889" docOffset="52">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="17902" annotation_id="5892">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5892" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> wanted the High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy <Alignment alignment="40941" annotation_id="5973">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5973" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we succeeded in getting this post in place.</en>
      <fr>Nous voulions <Alignment alignment="10529" annotation_id="6041">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6041" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">dès lors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la création d'un poste de haut représentant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6094">pour</DiscourseConnective> les affaires étrangères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6123">et</DiscourseConnective> la politique de sécurité <Alignment alignment="5973" annotation_id="6151">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6151" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous avons réussi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6172">à</DiscourseConnective> l'obtenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6021" docOffset="53">
      <en>I would like to say something with regard to the person holding this post.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais dire quelque chose <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6216">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard de la personne occupant ce poste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6096" docOffset="54">
      <en>Baroness Ashton must not allow herself to be called a communist in this Parliament by a man who, in France, has been convicted of denying the Holocaust.</en>
      <fr>La baronne Ashton ne doit pas se laisser traiter de communiste dans ce Parlement par un homme qui a été condamné <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6373">en</DiscourseConnective> France pour négationnisme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6249" docOffset="55">
      <en>Baroness Ashton has our full support.</en>
      <fr>La baronne Ashton bénéficie de notre appui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6446">total</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6287" docOffset="56">
      <en>(Sustained applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements soutenus)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6308" docOffset="57">
      <en>We asked whether we could introduce a social impact assessment into European Union legislation as a regulatory mechanism.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous sommes demandé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6506">si</DiscourseConnective> nous pouvions introduire une évaluation de l'impact social dans la législation de l'Union européenne en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6613">tant que</DiscourseConnective> mécanisme de réglementation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6430" docOffset="58">
      <en>For us, the question was whether measures - such as the Services Directive in the past - could still be set in motion at all.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6651">Pour</DiscourseConnective> nous, la question était de savoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6690">si</DiscourseConnective> des mesures - telles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6714">que</DiscourseConnective> la directive "services" par le passé - pouvaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6767">encore</DiscourseConnective> être mises <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6785">en</DiscourseConnective> œuvre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6556" docOffset="59">
      <en>No, we wanted a mechanism for examining any measures that this Commission is to take in terms of their impact on the social security systems of the Member States <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6718" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective> they are taken.</en>
      <fr>Non, nous voulions un mécanisme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6827">pour</DiscourseConnective> examiner au préalable l'impact sur les systèmes de sécurité sociale des États membres de toutes les mesures <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6940">que</DiscourseConnective> prendra cette Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6741" docOffset="60">
      <en>This was incorporated.</en>
      <fr>Cela a été incorporé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6764" docOffset="61">
      <en>We wanted - <Alignment alignment="18726" annotation_id="6776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6776" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, for me, this is a quantum leap in European policy - the legislative resolutions of this Parliament to be turned into the Commission's own legislative initiatives within a year.</en>
      <fr>Nous voulions - <Alignment alignment="14679" annotation_id="7008">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7008" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7011">pour</DiscourseConnective> moi, il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7024">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un bond en avant prodigieux dans la politique européenne - que les résolutions législatives de ce Parlement deviennent des initiatives législatives propres de la Commission dans un délai d'un an.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6958" docOffset="62">
      <en>That is a huge step forward, <Alignment alignment="10645" annotation_id="6987">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6987" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it means that the right of initiative of this Parliament, which unfortunately does not exist, will be secured by indirect means.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7232">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'un énorme pas en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7258">avant</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="6987" annotation_id="7264">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7264" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cela signifie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7282">que</DiscourseConnective> le droit d'initiative de ce Parlement, qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7329">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> n'existe pas, sera acquis par des moyens indirects.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7124" docOffset="63">
      <en>We see this as significant progress.</en>
      <fr>Nous estimons qu'il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7417">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit là d'un progrès significatif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7161" docOffset="64">
      <en>Ultimately, as the second-strongest force in this Parliament and also as a group without which no qualified majority would be possible in this House, we wanted to be represented in the Commission.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7454">Enfin</DiscourseConnective>, en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7464">tant que</DiscourseConnective> deuxième force dans ce Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7506">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7509">également</DiscourseConnective> en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7522">tant que</DiscourseConnective> groupe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7538">sans</DiscourseConnective> lequel aucune majorité qualifiée ne serait possible dans cette Assemblée, nous voulions être représentés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7648">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7358" docOffset="65">
      <en>Three of the seven vice-presidents are Social Democrats.</en>
      <fr>Trois des sept vice-présidents sont sociaux-démocrates.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7415" docOffset="66">
      <en>In this respect, you have largely accommodated us.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7721">À cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, vous avez amplement satisfait notre demande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7466" docOffset="67">
      <en>In recent weeks and months, we have voiced many concerns, including in our debate this morning.</en>
      <fr>Au cours des semaines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7801">et</DiscourseConnective> des mois écoulés, nous avons exprimé de nombreuses inquiétudes, y compris dans notre débat de ce matin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7562" docOffset="68">
      <en>In weighing up these concerns against the progress made, we decided to offer you our support for the next five years.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7908">En</DiscourseConnective> comparant ces inquiétudes aux progrès réalisés, nous avons décidé de vous accorder notre appui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8006">pour</DiscourseConnective> les cinq années à venir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7680" docOffset="69">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="9568" annotation_id="7680">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7680" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I say 'you', I mean the College of Commissioners.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="7615" annotation_id="8036">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8036" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je dis "vous", je veux dire le collège des commissaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7735" docOffset="70">
      <en>You can count on our support <Alignment alignment="26835" annotation_id="7764">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7764" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you take seriously what I say to you: Europe will either be a social Europe <Alignment alignment="24971" annotation_id="7843">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7843" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it will fail.</en>
      <fr>Vous pouvez compter sur notre appui <Alignment alignment="10201" annotation_id="8135">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8135" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous prenez au sérieux ce que je vous dis: l'Europe sera une Europe sociale <Alignment alignment="5437" annotation_id="8214">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8214" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ne sera pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7860" docOffset="71">
      <en>It is our joint responsibility to ensure that it becomes a more social Europe.</en>
      <fr>Il est de notre responsabilité commune de nous assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8285">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle devienne une Europe plus sociale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7939" docOffset="72">
      <en>The S&amp;D Group will support this Commission.</en>
      <fr>Le groupe S&amp;D appuiera cette Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7983" docOffset="73">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7994" id="093" name="Guy Verhofstadt">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7994" docOffset="74">
      <en>on behalf of the ALDE Group. - Mr President, my group will offer its support to the European Commission.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, mon groupe offrira son appui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8439">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8099" docOffset="75">
      <en>The Alliance of Liberals and Democrats is a responsible group <Alignment alignment="40406" annotation_id="8161">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8161" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we firmly believe that the next five years will be so critical for the European Union and European citizens that we will need a Commission that will have broad pro-European support in this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>L'Alliance des démocrates <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8493">et</DiscourseConnective> des libéraux représente un groupe responsable <Alignment alignment="6807" annotation_id="8542">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8542" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous croyons fermement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8568">que</DiscourseConnective> les cinq prochaines années seront à ce point critiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8627">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8651">et</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8677">que</DiscourseConnective> nous aurons besoin d'une Commission jouissant d'un large appui pro-européen dans ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8366" docOffset="76">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7532" annotation_id="8366">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8366" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> let me <Alignment alignment="25505" annotation_id="8377">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8377" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be very clear.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8366" annotation_id="8776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8776" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, permettez-moi <Alignment alignment="8377" annotation_id="8801">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8801" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'être très clair.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8397" docOffset="77">
      <en>Our support is conditional, more so than during the last five years.</en>
      <fr>Notre appui est conditionnel, encore plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8872">qu'</DiscourseConnective>au cours des cinq dernières années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8466" docOffset="78">
      <en>We expect the new European Commission to be the engine of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Nous attendons de la nouvelle Commission européenne qu'elle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8971">soit</DiscourseConnective> le moteur de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8544" docOffset="79">
      <en>We want a Commission with a bolder, more ambitious and more integrated economic and social approach, a Commission that is at the forefront of such a strategy - a strategy that can force Member States to do what they have to do.</en>
      <fr>Nous voulons une Commission suivant une approche économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9069">et</DiscourseConnective> sociale plus audacieuse, plus ambitieuse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9113">et</DiscourseConnective> plus intégrée, une Commission qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9150">soit</DiscourseConnective> au centre d'une telle stratégie - une stratégie pouvant obliger les États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9237">à</DiscourseConnective> faire ce qu'ils doivent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8772" docOffset="80">
      <en>I think that, certainly in the eurozone, we have to recognise that there is a great need for a true economic and social pillar next to the existing monetary pillar.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9273">que</DiscourseConnective>, certainement dans la zone euro, nous devons reconnaître la nécessité absolue d'un réel pilier économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9383">et</DiscourseConnective> social, outre le pilier monétaire existant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8937" docOffset="81">
      <en>The problems in the eurozone today are clear proof of the failure of the weak approach that we have followed over the last 10 years with the so-called open coordination method.</en>
      <fr>Les problèmes que connaît aujourd'hui la zone euro sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9486">la preuve</DiscourseConnective> manifeste de l'échec de l'approche médiocre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9540">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons suivie durant les 10 dernières années avec ce qu'on appelle la méthode ouverte de coordination.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9114" docOffset="82">
      <en>The same is true in other areas - on climate change, on foreign policy and on defence policy.</en>
      <fr>La <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9654">même</DiscourseConnective> chose est vraie dans d'autres domaines - concernant le changement climatique, la politique étrangère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9760">et</DiscourseConnective> la politique de défense.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9208" docOffset="83">
      <en>The basic assumption behind this new bold approach is the recognition that <Alignment alignment="18036" annotation_id="9283">
          <Alignment alignment="9878" annotation_id="9283">
            <Alignment alignment="9878" annotation_id="9283">
              <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9283" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">in fact</DiscourseConnective>
            </Alignment>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment>, in the multipolar world of tomorrow, Europe cannot play a significant role without being more effective and without further deepening its own integration in the near future.</en>
      <fr>L'hypothèse de base derrière cette nouvelle approche audacieuse consiste à reconnaître <Alignment alignment="9283" annotation_id="9875">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9875" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">qu'en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> fait, dans le monde multipolaire de demain, l'Europe ne peut jouer un rôle significatif <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9969">sans</DiscourseConnective> être plus efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9993">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9996">sans</DiscourseConnective> approfondir davantage sa propre intégration dans un proche avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9466" docOffset="84">
      <en>We expect you to embrace this assumption and to come forward with clear, firm and ambitious proposals and reforms in all these fields.</en>
      <fr>Nous attendons de vous que vous adoptiez cette hypothèse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10125">et</DiscourseConnective> que vous fassiez des propositions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10162">et</DiscourseConnective> des réformes claires, fermes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10194">et</DiscourseConnective> ambitieuses dans tous ces domaines.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9601" docOffset="85">
      <en>We expect that, to achieve this, the Commission will use the right of initiative to its full potential.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10247">que</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10252">à</DiscourseConnective> cette fin, la Commission recourra pleinement au droit d'initiative.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9705" docOffset="86">
      <en>I am clearly talking about the Commission as a whole, working as a college, as a cohesive political body pushing European integration forward.</en>
      <fr>Je parle explicitement de la Commission dans son ensemble, fonctionnant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10394">comme</DiscourseConnective> un collège, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10412">comme</DiscourseConnective> un organe politique cohérent faisant avancer l'intégration européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9848" docOffset="87">
      <en>A strong Commission may be helpful, <Alignment alignment="10526" annotation_id="9884">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9884" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a strong Commission in that respect is indispensable.</en>
      <fr>Une Commission forte peut être utile <Alignment alignment="11363" annotation_id="10526">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10526" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une Commission forte <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10552">à cet égard</DiscourseConnective> est indispensable.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9942" docOffset="88">
      <en>The Lisbon Treaty offers new tools and has enhanced our capacity for action.</en>
      <fr>Le traité de Lisbonne offre de nouveaux outils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10630">et</DiscourseConnective> a amélioré notre capacité d'action.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10019" docOffset="89">
      <en>High Representative Ashton, we ask you to use these new tools.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Haute représentante Ashton, nous vous demandons d'utiliser ces nouveaux outils.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10082" docOffset="90">
      <en>We expect more from a High Representative than we have seen until now.</en>
      <fr>Nous attendons plus d'une haute représentante que ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10812">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons vu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10830">jusqu'à</DiscourseConnective> présent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10153" docOffset="91">
      <en>Your role demands it <Alignment alignment="17692" annotation_id="10174">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10174" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the European Union requires it.</en>
      <fr>Votre rôle le requiert <Alignment alignment="5739" annotation_id="10870">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10870" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne l'exige.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10210" docOffset="92">
      <en>Take the opportunities.</en>
      <fr>Saisissez les occasions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10234" docOffset="93">
      <en>The lesson we learned from Haiti is an example.</en>
      <fr>L'enseignement que nous avons tiré de Haïti en est un exemple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10282" docOffset="94">
      <en>Put the report to establish a European civil protection force on the Council table immediately.</en>
      <fr>Mettez immédiatement sur la table du Conseil le rapport visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11052">à</DiscourseConnective> établir une force de protection civile européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10378" docOffset="95">
      <en>Having said that, my group will support this Commission, with its strong liberal presence, <Alignment alignment="25591" annotation_id="10469">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10469" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are prepared to offer our commitment to advance the European cause with her.</en>
      <fr>Cela étant dit, mon groupe soutiendra cette Commission, avec sa forte présence libérale, <Alignment alignment="5608" annotation_id="11194">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11194" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous sommes disposés à nous engager <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11233">à</DiscourseConnective> faire avancer la cause européenne avec elle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10553" docOffset="96">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10564" id="094" language="FR" name="Daniel Cohn-Bendit">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10564" docOffset="97">
      <en>Mr President, you know very well that the Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance will not vote for this Commission, <Alignment alignment="23934" annotation_id="10684">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10684" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, at the same time, we are offering you our ideas, our imagination and our European determination.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. - Monsieur le Président, vous savez très <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11368">bien que</DiscourseConnective> le groupe des Verts ne votera pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11411">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette Commission <Alignment alignment="3429" annotation_id="11433">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11433" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11437">en même temps</DiscourseConnective>, nous vous proposons nos idées, notre imagination <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11501">et</DiscourseConnective> notre détermination européennes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10786" docOffset="98">
      <en>Mr Barroso, do not play the game of saying that those who fail to vote for the Commission are against Europe.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur Barroso, ne jouez pas au jeu de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11578">dire que</DiscourseConnective> ceux qui ne votent pas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11610">pour</DiscourseConnective> la Commission sont contre l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10896" docOffset="99">
      <en>Not with us, the European Greens.</en>
      <fr>Pas avec nous, Verts européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10930" docOffset="100">
      <en>You can play that game with others, but not with us.</en>
      <fr>Ça, vous pouvez le jouer avec d'autres, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11723">mais</DiscourseConnective> pas avec nous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10983" docOffset="101">
      <en>We propose to cooperate unconditionally with you <Alignment alignment="11797" annotation_id="11032">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11032" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you wish to make progress on a European tax system.</en>
      <fr>Nous vous proposons une collaboration sans objections <Alignment alignment="11032" annotation_id="11797">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11797" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez avancer sur une fiscalité européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11087" docOffset="102">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13834" annotation_id="11087">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11087" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you wish Europe to have its own resources, we will support you against the Member States' defence of their economic sovereignty.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="11087" annotation_id="11850">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11850" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez des ressources européennes propres, nous serons avec vous contre le souverainisme économique des États.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11219" docOffset="103">
      <en>I will name them: whether it be Germany, or France, we will support you.</en>
      <fr>Et je les nomme: <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11986">que</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11993">soit</DiscourseConnective> l'Allemagne, que ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12018">soit</DiscourseConnective> la France, nous serons avec vous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11292" docOffset="104">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="15368" annotation_id="11292">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11292" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you wish to be the guardians of the treaties - there are, <Alignment alignment="16854" annotation_id="11353">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11353" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, negotiations taking place today within the Council aimed at returning the refugees to Libya, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11459" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> we ask the Council to tell us what the legal basis of those negotiations is.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="23890" annotation_id="12057">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12057" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez être les garants des Traités - il y a <Alignment alignment="3115" annotation_id="12110">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12110" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une négociation aujourd'hui au sein du Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12169">pour</DiscourseConnective> remettre les réfugiés en Libye -, nous demandons au Conseil de nous dire quelle est la base juridique de ces négociations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11540" docOffset="105">
      <en>Will Parliament be part of the ordinary legislative procedure?</en>
      <fr>Est-ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12304">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement sera en codécision?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11603" docOffset="106">
      <en>The Council tells us: 'you will be told that at the end of the negotiations'.</en>
      <fr>Le Conseil nous dit: "on vous dira ça <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12379">à</DiscourseConnective> la fin des négociations".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11681" docOffset="107">
      <en>That is impossible; it is the Commission's responsibility to intervene to ensure that the European institutions are informed of the legal basis of those negotiations.</en>
      <fr>C'est impossible, c'est à la Commission d'intervenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12460">pour que</DiscourseConnective> les institutions européennes soient informées sur la base juridique de ces négociations.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11848" docOffset="108">
      <en>I can give you a whole host of examples.</en>
      <fr>Je peux vous donner des tas d'exemples.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11889" docOffset="109">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21548" annotation_id="11889">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11889" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you want to make progress on climate change, <Alignment alignment="12652" annotation_id="11937">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11937" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you want Europe to go further than the three times twenty, <Alignment alignment="9944" annotation_id="11999">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11999" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you want to get closer to 30%, you will have the support of the entire Verts/ALE Group.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2207" annotation_id="12598">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12598" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez avancer sur la dégradation climatique, <Alignment alignment="12465" annotation_id="12652">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12652" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez que l'Europe aille plus loin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12696">que</DiscourseConnective> les trois fois 20, <Alignment alignment="11999" annotation_id="12719">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12719" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous allez vers 30 %, vous aurez la collaboration de tout le groupe des Verts européens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12090" docOffset="110">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="36675" annotation_id="12090">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12090" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you want to go further in the field of financial regulation after the financial crisis, you will have our full support.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12090" annotation_id="12811">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12811" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez aller plus loin dans la régulation des finances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12874">après</DiscourseConnective> la crise financière, vous aurez toute notre collaboration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12213" docOffset="111">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="39310" annotation_id="12213">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12213" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you and your Commission want to go further with regard to the protection of Europe, you will have our support.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="374" annotation_id="12939">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12939" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez, avec votre Commission, aller plus loin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12994">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne la protection de l'Europe, vous aurez notre collaboration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12327" docOffset="112">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="13072" annotation_id="12327">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12327" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you want to solve the Cyprus problem, you will have our support.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18661" annotation_id="13072">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13072" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez régler le problème de Chypre, vous aurez notre collaboration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12395" docOffset="113">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7650" annotation_id="12395">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12395" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you want to see an end, finally, to this crazy situation in which a country such as Greece - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12491" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> I said earlier - spends 4.3% of its GDP on defence, you will have our support.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="2365" annotation_id="13149">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13149" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous voulez <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13164">qu'</DiscourseConnective>on arrête <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13177">enfin</DiscourseConnective> cette folie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13195">qu'</DiscourseConnective>un pays <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13206">comme</DiscourseConnective> la Grèce - je l'ai dit tout à l'heure - dépense 4,3 % de son PIB <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13277">pour</DiscourseConnective> la défense, vous aurez notre collaboration.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12573" docOffset="114">
      <en>You will have it unconditionally!</en>
      <fr>Vous l'aurez sans condition!</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12607" docOffset="115">
      <en>For this reason, Mr Barroso, I am saying that we will vote 'No' now, <Alignment alignment="13425" annotation_id="12676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12676" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that we may be making a mistake.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13355">Pour</DiscourseConnective> cela, Monsieur Barroso, je dis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13391">que</DiscourseConnective> nous votons "non" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13413">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="12676" annotation_id="13425">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13425" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13430">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pouvons nous tromper.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12713" docOffset="116">
      <en>We know that we made a mistake last time where Mr Dimas was concerned.</en>
      <fr>Nous savons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13473">que</DiscourseConnective> nous nous sommes trompés la dernière fois <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13519">pour</DiscourseConnective> M. Dimas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12784" docOffset="117">
      <en>We made a mistake, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12803" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> we admit it.</en>
      <fr>Nous nous sommes trompés, nous l'avouons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12820" docOffset="118">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="40850" annotation_id="12820">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12820" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="52948" annotation_id="12831">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12831" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you can live up to our dreams, and not live up to the expectations that we have of you following today, we will say frankly that we made a mistake, <Alignment alignment="21978" annotation_id="12982">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12982" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will support you.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="12820" annotation_id="13576">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13576" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="12831" annotation_id="13582">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13582" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous êtes à la hauteur de nos rêves, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13622">et</DiscourseConnective> non pas à la hauteur de ce que vous avez démontré aujourd'hui, nous dirons franchement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13712">que</DiscourseConnective> nous nous sommes trompés, <Alignment alignment="3084" annotation_id="13742">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13742" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous serons à vos côtés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13007" docOffset="119">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13018" id="095" name="Timothy Kirkhope">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13018" docOffset="120">
      <en>on behalf of the ECR Group. - Mr President, some Member States believe the nomination of a Commissioner is a useful opportunity to sort out a domestic problem or settle a political debt.</en>
      <fr>au nom du groupe ECR. - (EN) Monsieur le Président, certains États membres pensent que la nomination d'un commissaire est une occasion utile de résoudre un problème national <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13963">ou</DiscourseConnective> de régler une dette politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13205" docOffset="121">
      <en>The European Commission should bring together the most talented and effective political leaders from across Europe, people with experience and competence to help it address the enormous challenges we face.</en>
      <fr>La Commission européenne devrait rassembler les dirigeants politiques les plus talentueux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14087">et</DiscourseConnective> les plus efficaces de toute l'Europe, des personnes expérimentées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14156">et</DiscourseConnective> compétentes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14171">pour</DiscourseConnective> aider à relever les défis de taille auxquels nous sommes confrontés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13411" docOffset="122">
      <en>After years of institutional wrangling, Europe needs to refocus its efforts on delivering results in areas where it can add value to the work of the Member States, <Alignment alignment="38407" annotation_id="13575">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13575" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> where our fellow citizens expect the nations of Europe to cooperate.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14245">Après</DiscourseConnective> des années de disputes institutionnelles, l'Europe a besoin de recentrer ses efforts sur la recherche de résultats dans des domaines où elle peut apporter une valeur ajoutée au travail des États membres, <Alignment alignment="13575" annotation_id="14455">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14455" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> où nos concitoyens s'attendent à ce que les nations d'Europe coopèrent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13648" docOffset="123">
      <en>It must support efforts to nurture fragile economic recovery and to generate growth and jobs, <Alignment alignment="43302" annotation_id="13742">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13742" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> has to play a leading role in tackling energy security and climate change.</en>
      <fr>Elle doit soutenir les efforts visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14568">à</DiscourseConnective> nourrir la relance économique fragile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14608">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14611">à</DiscourseConnective> générer la croissance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14635">et</DiscourseConnective> l'emploi, <Alignment alignment="4464" annotation_id="14648">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14648" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> doit jouer un rôle majeur dans l'amélioration de la sécurité énergétique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14724">et</DiscourseConnective> la lutte contre le changement climatique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13821" docOffset="124">
      <en>It must propose central reforms to the European budget and many of the key expenditure programmes.</en>
      <fr>Elle doit proposer des réformes centrales au budget européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14830">et</DiscourseConnective> bon nombre des programmes de dépenses majeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13920" docOffset="125">
      <en>In Mr Barroso, we have the right leader to take the Commission forward.</en>
      <fr>Avec M. Barroso, nous avons le bon dirigeant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14925">pour</DiscourseConnective> faire avancer la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13992" docOffset="126">
      <en>In his political guidelines, he outlines an ambitious agenda to focus on the issues that matter, an agenda which, in general, we support.</en>
      <fr>Dans ses orientations politiques, il expose un programme ambitieux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15026">pour</DiscourseConnective> se concentrer sur les matières importantes, un programme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15088">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans l'ensemble, nous soutenons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14130" docOffset="127">
      <en>Every single Member State should have backed his efforts by sending the strongest possible nominee as Commissioner, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14246" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> in some cases, he has been badly let down.</en>
      <fr>Alors que chaque État membre aurait dû appuyer ses efforts <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15185">en</DiscourseConnective> envoyant le meilleur candidat possible au poste de commissaire, certains l'ont laissé tomber.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14293" docOffset="128">
      <en>Of course he must back every member of his team - we would expect nothing less from a leader in his position - <Alignment alignment="18195" annotation_id="14404">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14404" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in organising his team, <Alignment alignment="6201" annotation_id="14433">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14433" sense="Comparison.Contrast">although</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we question some portfolios, he has probably done his best with what he has got.</en>
      <fr>Naturellement, il doit soutenir chaque membre de son équipe - nous n'attendrions rien de moins d'un leader dans sa position - <Alignment alignment="8220" annotation_id="15408">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15408" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, concernant l'organisation de son équipe, <Alignment alignment="8559" annotation_id="15453">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15453" sense="Comparison.Contrast">bien que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous mettions en doute certains portefeuilles, il a probablement fait de son <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15539">mieux</DiscourseConnective> avec ce qu'il avait.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14523" docOffset="129">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="28118" annotation_id="14523">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14523" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whilst some nominees are excellent and performed well in the hearings, others are mediocre and made a poor impression.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="14523" annotation_id="15566">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15566" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15577">tandis que</DiscourseConnective> certains candidats désignés sont excellents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15632">et</DiscourseConnective> s'en sont bien sortis lors des auditions, d'autres sont médiocres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15701">et</DiscourseConnective> n'ont pas fait bonne impression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14646" docOffset="130">
      <en>Some distanced themselves from his own political guidelines.</en>
      <fr>Certains se sont distanciés de ses propres orientations politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14707" docOffset="131">
      <en>Mr President, <Alignment alignment="15828" annotation_id="14721">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14721" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the vote is favourable, we will, of course, engage constructively with every Commissioner <Alignment alignment="15937" annotation_id="14814">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14814" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we still hope to be positively surprised, but please let us at least have an annual assessment by this Parliament of the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, <Alignment alignment="14721" annotation_id="15828">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15828" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le vote est favorable, nous nous engagerons naturellement de manière constructive avec chaque commissaire <Alignment alignment="14814" annotation_id="15937">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15937" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous espérons toujours être agréablement surpris, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15990">mais</DiscourseConnective> s'il vous plaît laissez-nous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16024">au moins</DiscourseConnective> avoir une évaluation annuelle de la Commission par ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14951" docOffset="132">
      <en>This is still a fundamentally flawed process and one we cannot endorse fully.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16101">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit toujours d'un processus fondamentalement imparfait auquel nous ne pouvons souscrire pleinement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15029" docOffset="133">
      <en>For these reasons, the European Conservatives and Reformists will today abstain on this vote.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16204">Pour</DiscourseConnective> ces raisons, les Conservateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16240">et</DiscourseConnective> Réformistes européens s'abstiendront de voter aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15123" docOffset="134">
      <en>Some groups are disunited; we are united in that position.</en>
      <fr>Certains groupes sont désunis, nous, nous sommes unis dans cette position.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15182" id="096" language="DE" name="Lothar Bisky">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15182" docOffset="135">
      <en>Mr President, Mr Barroso, ladies and gentlemen, my group <Alignment alignment="5039" annotation_id="15239">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15239" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> participated actively in the hearings of the candidates.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, Monsieur Barroso, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16427">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, mon groupe a <Alignment alignment="15239" annotation_id="16454">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16454" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> participé activement aux auditions des candidats.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15301" docOffset="136">
      <en>Some of them made a thoroughly positive impression on us.</en>
      <fr>Certains d'entre eux nous ont laissé une très bonne impression.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15359" docOffset="137">
      <en>We are less enthusiastic about the new arrangement of many of the portfolios.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes moins enthousiastes quant au nouvel aménagement de nombreux portefeuilles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15437" docOffset="138">
      <en>That <Alignment alignment="33072" annotation_id="15442">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15442" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> includes the rather mysterious - although perhaps soon to be less mysterious - area of responsibility of the High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, who is <Alignment alignment="16870" annotation_id="15624">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15624" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Vice-President of the Commission.</en>
      <fr>Cela inclut <Alignment alignment="15442" annotation_id="16677">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16677" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le domaine de compétences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16713">plutôt</DiscourseConnective> mystérieux - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16733">quoique</DiscourseConnective> peut-être <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16751">bientôt</DiscourseConnective> moins mystérieux - de la haute représentante <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16804">pour</DiscourseConnective> les affaires étrangères <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16833">et</DiscourseConnective> la politique de sécurité, qui est <Alignment alignment="21559" annotation_id="16870">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16870" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vice-présidente de la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15663" docOffset="139">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="41712" annotation_id="15663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15663" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we found many of the candidates disappointing in terms of their specialist knowledge.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="15663" annotation_id="16914">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16914" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous avons trouvé beaucoup de candidats décevants concernant leurs connaissances spécialisés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15758" docOffset="140">
      <en>In this regard, all of our questions related primarily to political projects.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17019">À cet égard</DiscourseConnective>, toutes nos questions portaient essentiellement sur les projets politiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15836" docOffset="141">
      <en>In what direction should the European integration process go?</en>
      <fr>Dans quelle direction devrait aller le processus d'intégration européenne?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15898" docOffset="142">
      <en>Which measures are most important to the Commission candidate?</en>
      <fr>Quelles mesures sont les plus importantes aux yeux du candidat?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15961" docOffset="143">
      <en>There were far too many vague answers to these questions and answers that, politically speaking, we do not support.</en>
      <fr>Il y a eu beaucoup trop de réponses vagues <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17289">à</DiscourseConnective> ces questions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17305">et</DiscourseConnective> des réponses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17321">que</DiscourseConnective>, politiquement parlant, nous n'approuvons pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16077" docOffset="144">
      <en>Despite claims of a more social Europe, they persisted in advocating a route towards deregulation, privatisation or the flexicurity concept.</en>
      <fr>Malgré les revendications d'une Europe plus sociale, ils persistaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17442">à</DiscourseConnective> plaider en faveur de la dérèglementation, de la privatisation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17506">ou</DiscourseConnective> du concept de flexicurité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16218" docOffset="145">
      <en>The flexibility of workers was the top priority <Alignment alignment="29721" annotation_id="16266">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16266" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> social security was right at the bottom.</en>
      <fr>La flexibilité des travailleurs figurait au sommet des priorités <Alignment alignment="11912" annotation_id="17601">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17601" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la sécurité sociale se trouvait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17644">tout en</DiscourseConnective> bas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16311" docOffset="146">
      <en>Climate protection is on the agenda, <Alignment alignment="14951" annotation_id="16348">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16348" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are not seeing a move away from coal-powered generation of electricity or from nuclear power.</en>
      <fr>La protection du climat est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17685">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre du jour <Alignment alignment="21323" annotation_id="17703">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17703" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne voyons aucune mesure mise en œuvre pour abandonner la production d'électricité à partir du charbon <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17815">ou</DiscourseConnective> l'énergie nucléaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16449" docOffset="147">
      <en>I do not see the EU taking a leading role in climate protection and in development aid.</en>
      <fr>Je ne vois pas l'UE jouer un rôle majeur dans la protection du climat <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17909">et</DiscourseConnective> dans l'aide au développement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16537" docOffset="148">
      <en>Nothing has been said about consistent disarmament, especially with regard to nuclear weapons within Europe.</en>
      <fr>Rien n'a été dit sur le désarmement cohérent, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17988">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> concernant les armes nucléaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18035">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16646" docOffset="149">
      <en>Mr Barroso, Mr President, as much as I appreciate the candidates coming forward for the hearing, my group is unable to give your College a positive vote.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur Barroso, Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18087">bien que</DiscourseConnective> j'apprécie les candidats présentés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18131">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'audition, mon groupe n'est pas en mesure de voter en faveur de votre collège aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16800" id="097" name="Nigel Farage">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16800" docOffset="150">
      <en>on behalf of the EFD Group. - Mr President, in generations to come, children will be told a story.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, dans les générations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18272">à</DiscourseConnective> venir, on racontera une histoire aux enfants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16899" docOffset="151">
      <en>They will be told that once upon a time, Europe was divided; there was a big wall down the middle of it <Alignment alignment="32513" annotation_id="17003">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17003" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the people in the East were very poor <Alignment alignment="6315" annotation_id="17045">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17045" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they had no democracy, <Alignment alignment="21204" annotation_id="17072">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17072" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they lived under an evil system called Communism that killed millions of its own people.</en>
      <fr>On leur racontera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18338">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il était une fois, une Europe divisée; il y avait une grand mur érigé au milieu <Alignment alignment="17003" annotation_id="18421">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18421" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les gens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18433">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Est étaient très pauvres <Alignment alignment="10681" annotation_id="18462">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18462" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ne connaissaient pas la démocratie, <Alignment alignment="11706" annotation_id="18501">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18501" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils vivaient dans un système maléfique appelé le communisme qui tuait ses habitants par millions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17165" docOffset="152">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="23515" annotation_id="17165">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17165" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, joy of joys, the wall came down <Alignment alignment="30490" annotation_id="17202">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17202" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we finished up with 27 nations, <Alignment alignment="13773" annotation_id="17238">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17238" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> those people lived in democracy <Alignment alignment="35680" annotation_id="17274">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17274" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> 500 million people lived in peace...</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17165" annotation_id="18602">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18602" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, bonheur suprême, le mur tomba <Alignment alignment="16269" annotation_id="18643">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18643" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous nous retrouvèrent avec 27 nations, <Alignment alignment="17238" annotation_id="18686">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18686" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ces gens vécurent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18707">en</DiscourseConnective> démocratie <Alignment alignment="9044" annotation_id="18721">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18721" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> 500 millions de personnes vécurent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18759">en</DiscourseConnective> paix...</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17315" docOffset="153">
      <en>( Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17327" docOffset="154">
      <en>There is more.</en>
      <fr>Il y a une suite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17342" docOffset="155">
      <en>I promise you, there is more.</en>
      <fr>Je vous le promets, il y a une suite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17372" docOffset="156">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17383" docOffset="157">
      <en>Well, I must say that is the first time I have ever received such applause <Alignment alignment="38023" annotation_id="17458">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17458" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I am tempted, Mr Verhofstadt, to sit down <Alignment alignment="28698" annotation_id="17504">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17504" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <Alignment alignment="19029" annotation_id="17509">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17509" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I may, sadly, the story continues.</en>
      <fr>Et bien, je dois avouer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18888">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est la première fois que je reçois de tels applaudissements <Alignment alignment="5926" annotation_id="18954">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18954" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je suis tenté, Monsieur Verhofstadt, de m'asseoir <Alignment alignment="17504" annotation_id="19007">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19007" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19012">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="17509" annotation_id="19029">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19029" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19035">puis</DiscourseConnective> me permettre, l'histoire continue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17547" docOffset="158">
      <en>The politicians in charge became very greedy; they wanted money for themselves <Alignment alignment="8075" annotation_id="17626">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17626" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they wanted power.</en>
      <fr>Les responsables politiques au pouvoir devinrent très gourmands, ils voulaient de l'argent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19166">pour</DiscourseConnective> eux <Alignment alignment="17626" annotation_id="19175">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19175" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils voulaient le pouvoir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17649" docOffset="159">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="46624" annotation_id="17649">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17649" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they resorted to lies and deceit, they staged the most spectacular bureaucratic coup d'état that the world had ever seen.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17649" annotation_id="19204">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19204" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Alors</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ils recoururent aux mensonges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19241">et</DiscourseConnective> aux tromperies, ils mirent en scène le coup d'État bureaucratique le plus spectaculaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19332">que</DiscourseConnective> le monde avait jamais vu.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17774" docOffset="160">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="21447" annotation_id="17774">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17774" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they did not need to use any bullets to do it.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17774" annotation_id="19362">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19362" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ils n'eurent pas besoin d'utiliser la moindre balle <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19425">pour ce faire</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17825" docOffset="161">
      <en>They were much cleverer, much more scheming than that.</en>
      <fr>Ils étaient beaucoup plus intelligents, beaucoup plus comploteurs que ça.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17880" docOffset="162">
      <en>What they did is they put in place a new treaty - it was called the Lisbon Treaty.</en>
      <fr>Ils mirent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19525">en</DiscourseConnective> place un nouveau traité - ils l'appelèrent le traité de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17963" docOffset="163">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="7651" annotation_id="17963">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17963" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Then</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they gave 27 people total unlimited power.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="8378" annotation_id="19594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19594" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">Ensuite</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ils confièrent un pouvoir illimité à 27 personnes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18011" docOffset="164">
      <en>These would have been the people who made all the laws.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19657">s'</DiscourseConnective>agissait des gens qui faisaient toutes les lois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18067" docOffset="165">
      <en>Of course, they already had a flag, <Alignment alignment="7828" annotation_id="18103">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18103" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they already had an anthem, <Alignment alignment="29392" annotation_id="18135">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18135" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they went about building a new state.</en>
      <fr>Bien sûr, ils avaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19730">déjà</DiscourseConnective> un drapeau <Alignment alignment="18103" annotation_id="19746">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19746" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un hymne, <Alignment alignment="18135" annotation_id="19759">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19759" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils procédèrent à la construction d'un nouvel État.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18177" docOffset="166">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="56991" annotation_id="18177">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18177" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they ignored the people.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="15814" annotation_id="19816">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19816" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ils ignorèrent le peuple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18206" docOffset="167">
      <en>What they did, whether they knew it <Alignment alignment="31810" annotation_id="18242">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18242" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not, was to recreate the very evil system that the people in Eastern Europe had lived under before.</en>
      <fr>Ils recréèrent, consciemment <Alignment alignment="18242" annotation_id="19882">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19882" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> non, le <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19893">même</DiscourseConnective> système maléfique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19916">que</DiscourseConnective> les habitants de l'Europe de l'Est avaient connu autrefois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18345" docOffset="168">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="19980" annotation_id="18345">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18345" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the incredible thing was that many of the new bosses had <Alignment alignment="20062" annotation_id="18406">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18406" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> worked for that same evil system before.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18345" annotation_id="19980">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19980" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, ce qui était incroyable était <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20021">que</DiscourseConnective> beaucoup de nouveaux patrons avaient <Alignment alignment="22439" annotation_id="20062">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20062" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> travaillé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20082">pour</DiscourseConnective> ce système maléfique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20108">auparavant</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18452" docOffset="169">
      <en>Well, of course, the plan was flawed <Alignment alignment="20159" annotation_id="18489">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18489" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> their fanciful monetary scheme collapsed.</en>
      <fr>Naturellement, le plan était imparfait <Alignment alignment="18824" annotation_id="20159">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20159" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leur système monétaire fantaisiste s'effondra.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18535" docOffset="170">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18535" sense="Comparison.Contrast">But</DiscourseConnective>, still, the new bosses would not listen to the people.</en>
      <fr>Les nouveaux patrons persistèrent cependant à ne pas écouter le peuple.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18594" docOffset="171">
      <en>No, they made life tougher and tougher: they put tens of millions into poverty; they denied people a say <Alignment alignment="45784" annotation_id="18699">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18699" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in the end, those people had to resort to violence to get back their nation states and their democracies.</en>
      <fr>Non, ils rendirent la vie de plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20315">en plus</DiscourseConnective> dure: ils plongèrent des dizaines de millions de personnes dans la pauvreté, les privèrent de leur droit de regard <Alignment alignment="18699" annotation_id="20438">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20438" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20442">finalement</DiscourseConnective>, ces personnes durent recourir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20484">à</DiscourseConnective> la violence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20498">pour</DiscourseConnective> retrouver leurs États nations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20533">et</DiscourseConnective> leurs démocraties.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18810" docOffset="172">
      <en>The moral of the story is that they had learnt nothing from history.</en>
      <fr>La morale de cette histoire est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20587">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils n'avaient rien appris de l'histoire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18879" docOffset="173">
      <en>Members of the European Parliament, <Alignment alignment="13777" annotation_id="18915">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18915" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">before</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you give this Commission power, remember that 60 years ago, an Iron Curtain came down on Europe <Alignment alignment="20789" annotation_id="19018">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19018" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> now, with this Commission, there is an economic iron fist <Alignment alignment="15545" annotation_id="19080">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19080" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is being felt in Greece today.</en>
      <fr>Chers députés du Parlement européen, <Alignment alignment="8460" annotation_id="20668">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20668" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">avant que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous n'habilitiez cette Commission, rappelez-vous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20728">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il y a 60 ans, un Rideau de fer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20763">s'</DiscourseConnective>est abattu sur l'Europe <Alignment alignment="11176" annotation_id="20789">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20789" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20794">maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, avec cette Commission, il y a une main de fer économique <Alignment alignment="11616" annotation_id="20863">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20863" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle se fait sentir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20886">en</DiscourseConnective> Grèce aujourd'hui.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19118" docOffset="174">
      <en>(The President cut off the speaker)</en>
      <fr>(Le Président retire la parole à l'orateur)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19154" id="098" name="Hans-Peter Martin">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19154" docOffset="175">
      <en>(DE) Mr President, after the fairytale that you have just heard, I would like to return to reality.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20980">après</DiscourseConnective> le conte de fées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21003">que</DiscourseConnective> vous venez d'écouter, je voudrais revenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21049">à</DiscourseConnective> la réalité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19254" docOffset="176">
      <en>My son is seventeen years old and is studying English very intensively, <Alignment alignment="21129" annotation_id="19326">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19326" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he knows that English is the working language, <Alignment alignment="23987" annotation_id="19381">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19381" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> he hopes that it will help him to get an appropriate job.</en>
      <fr>Mon fils a dix-sept ans <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21087">et</DiscourseConnective> étudie l'anglais de manière intensive, <Alignment alignment="20776" annotation_id="21129">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21129" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il sait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21141">que</DiscourseConnective> l'anglais est la langue de travail, <Alignment alignment="21347" annotation_id="21181">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21181" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21194">que</DiscourseConnective> cela l'aidera <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21212">à</DiscourseConnective> trouver un emploi adéquat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19443" docOffset="177">
      <en>He is an enthusiastic European, but is dissatisfied with European politics - and rightly so.</en>
      <fr>C'est un Européen convaincu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21269">mais</DiscourseConnective> mécontent de la politique européenne - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21313">et</DiscourseConnective> avec raison.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19536" docOffset="178">
      <en>In Germany, the magazine Der Spiegel is already writing about widespread political contempt - and rightly so.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21329">En</DiscourseConnective> Allemagne, le magazine Der Spiegel écrit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21373">déjà</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21378">à propos</DiscourseConnective> du mépris politique généralisé - <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21420">et</DiscourseConnective> avec raison.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19646" docOffset="179">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="17118" annotation_id="19646">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19646" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Nevertheless</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, millions of young Europeans want a functional, competent and bold democracy in the 21st century.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="19646" annotation_id="21436">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21436" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Néanmoins</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, des millions de jeunes Européens veulent une démocratie fonctionnelle, compétente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21529">et</DiscourseConnective> audacieuse au XXIe siècle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19757" docOffset="180">
      <en>Yet, what are we being offered here today by the Commission?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21559">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21570">que</DiscourseConnective> nous offre la Commission aujourd'hui?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19818" docOffset="181">
      <en>Are these the competent people - and the best people - that we need?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21612">S'</DiscourseConnective>agit-il des personnes compétentes - des meilleures personnes - dont nous avons besoin?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19887" docOffset="182">
      <en>Those of us up here in the back row represent an independent group of citizens who have played a key role in ensuring that the right-wing radicals in this House do not set up a group once again.</en>
      <fr>Ceux d'entre nous assis ici dans la rangée du fond représentent un groupe indépendant de citoyens qui ont joué un rôle majeur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21827">pour</DiscourseConnective> s'assurer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21842">que</DiscourseConnective> les radicaux de l'extrême droite dans ce Parlement ne refondent pas un groupe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20082" docOffset="183">
      <en>We are passionate pro-Europeans, <Alignment alignment="21634" annotation_id="20115">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20115" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this is precisely why we are extremely disappointed by the people that you have presented us with and by the quality of these people.</en>
      <fr>Nous sommes des pro-Européens passionnés <Alignment alignment="273" annotation_id="21966">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21966" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21977">précisément</DiscourseConnective> la raison pour laquelle nous sommes extrêmement déçus par les candidats <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22061">que</DiscourseConnective> vous nous avez présentés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22090">et</DiscourseConnective> par leur qualité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20253" docOffset="184">
      <en>Would we employ an assistant here who becomes a laughing stock like Günther Oettinger has done on YouTube in 'Oettinger talking English'?</en>
      <fr>Engagerions-nous un assistant ici qui se couvre de ridicule <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22171">comme</DiscourseConnective> Günther Oettinger l'a fait sur YouTube dans "Oettinger talking English"?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20391" docOffset="185">
      <en>Presumably not.</en>
      <fr>Vraisemblablement non.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20407" docOffset="186">
      <en>From the point of view of competence, would we want to deal with an Austrian Commissioner who has not proven himself at all in his area.</en>
      <fr>Du point de vue des compétences, voudrions-nous avoir affaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22335">à</DiscourseConnective> un commissaire autrichien qui n'a pas du tout fait ses preuves dans son domaine?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20544" docOffset="187">
      <en>Mr Barroso, there are very many experienced parliamentarians here in Parliament that you could adorn yourself with.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur Barroso, il y a un très grande nombre de députés expérimentés ici au Parlement dont vous pourriez vous entourer.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20660" docOffset="188">
      <en>You have one of them, <Alignment alignment="16499" annotation_id="20682">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20682" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, in the shape of the Swede, that is true.</en>
      <fr>Vous en avez un, <Alignment alignment="20682" annotation_id="22557">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22557" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, sous la forme du Suédois, c'est vrai.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20736" docOffset="189">
      <en>Yet, why do you not want Mr Karas?</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22608">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>, pourquoi ne voulez-vous pas de M. Karas?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20771" docOffset="190">
      <en>Why have you not taken a German from here, instead of the ones you have?</en>
      <fr>Pourquoi n'avez-vous pas pris un Allemand d'ici, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22709">à la place</DiscourseConnective> de ceux que vous avez?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20844" docOffset="191">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="22743" annotation_id="20844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20844" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you are not allowed to.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="9359" annotation_id="22743">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22743" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous ne le pouvez pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20876" docOffset="192">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="34881" annotation_id="20876">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20876" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, despite the Treaty of Lisbon, we are still restrained, <Alignment alignment="22848" annotation_id="20940">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20940" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are still not so independent that we can make sovereign decisions - you cannot <Alignment alignment="24011" annotation_id="21030">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21030" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> neither can we as Parliament.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="21251" annotation_id="22776">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22776" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, malgré le traité de Lisbonne, nous sommes toujours empêchés, <Alignment alignment="24911" annotation_id="22848">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22848" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne sommes toujours pas assez indépendants pour pouvoir prendre des décisions souveraines - vous ne le pouvez pas <Alignment alignment="7908" annotation_id="22976">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22976" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous ne le pouvons pas non plus en <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23014">tant que</DiscourseConnective> Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21064" docOffset="193">
      <en>Unfortunately, we are <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21086" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective> still not allowed to elect individual commissioners.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23034">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, nous ne sommes toujours pas autorisés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23089">à</DiscourseConnective> élire des commissaires individuels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21144" docOffset="194">
      <en>That is a type of democracy that we had in Austria in the 19th century.</en>
      <fr>C'est le genre de démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23156">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23172">en</DiscourseConnective> Autriche au XIXe siècle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21216" docOffset="195">
      <en>It is not appropriate for the Europe that we need, of which we dream.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est pas le genre de démocratie qui convient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23249">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe dont nous avons besoin, dont nous rêvons.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21286" docOffset="196">
      <en>Please take heed: <Alignment alignment="6929" annotation_id="21304">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21304" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you continue in this way, you will be playing into the hands of the nationalists and, indeed, the opponents of the EU.</en>
      <fr>S'il vous plaît, tenez-en compte: <Alignment alignment="24688" annotation_id="23336">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23336" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous poursuivez dans cette voie, vous deviendrez le jouet des nationalistes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23415">et</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23419">en fait</DiscourseConnective>, des opposants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23442">à</DiscourseConnective> l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21426" docOffset="197">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="31995" annotation_id="21426">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21426" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">Instead</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we need more democracy.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="3863" annotation_id="23450">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23450" sense="Expansion.Alternative.Chosen alternative">Au contraire</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous avons besoin <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23482">de plus</DiscourseConnective> de démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="21459" id="099" name="Bruno Gollnisch">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="21459" docOffset="198">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, my sentiments exactly.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, c'est exactement cela.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21501" docOffset="199">
      <en>I shall be very brief.</en>
      <fr>Je serai très <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23565">bref</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21524" docOffset="200">
      <en>Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, Mr Schulz has referred to me - not by name but precisely enough - as having been found guilty of revisionism by the French courts.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, mes chers collègues, M. Schulz m'a désigné, non pas nommément <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23656">mais</DiscourseConnective> avec suffisamment de précision, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23693">comme</DiscourseConnective> ayant été condamné pour négationnisme par les juridictions françaises.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21691" docOffset="201">
      <en>I would like to tell Mr Schulz that he is mistaken, <Alignment alignment="23815" annotation_id="21743">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21743" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I have at his disposal, and at the disposal of the entire European Parliament Committee on immunities, the momentous decision of the French supreme court, the Court of Cassation, which overturned all the sentences handed down to me <Alignment alignment="40814" annotation_id="21979">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21979" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> which, in its exceptional judgment, declared that I had been prosecuted on the basis of parts of sentences artificially put together to form a statement <Alignment alignment="24222" annotation_id="22136">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22136" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22146" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">furthermore</DiscourseConnective>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22159" sense="Comparison.Contrast">though</DiscourseConnective> cobbled together in this way by my political opponents, this statement did not come within the provisions of the law.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais dire à M. Schulz <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23799">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il se trompe <Alignment alignment="9929" annotation_id="23815">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23815" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23827">à</DiscourseConnective> sa disposition, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23845">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> qu'à celle de toute la commission du Parlement européen chargée des immunités, la décision éclatante de la juridiction suprême française, la Cour de cassation, qui a cassé toutes condamnations me concernant <Alignment alignment="4983" annotation_id="24058">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24058" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qui, dans son arrêt exceptionnel, a déclaré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24105">que</DiscourseConnective> j'avais été poursuivi sur la base de bribes de phrases artificiellement agencées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24190">pour</DiscourseConnective> constituer une déclaration <Alignment alignment="22136" annotation_id="24222">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24222" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24225">qu'</DiscourseConnective>au surplus, même ainsi bricolée par mes adversaires politiques, cette déclaration ne tombait pas sous le coup de la loi.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22284" docOffset="202">
      <en>This is an exceptionally rare decision, <Alignment alignment="24385" annotation_id="22324">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22324" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Court overturned a lower court ruling and decided the case itself, which happens very rarely with the French Court of Cassation.</en>
      <fr>C'est une décision extrêmement rare <Alignment alignment="3105" annotation_id="24385">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24385" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est une cassation sans renvoi devant une autre juridiction. <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24451">Et</DiscourseConnective> ça, c'est très rare de la part de la Cour de cassation française.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22463" docOffset="203">
      <en>This overturning of a ruling and judgment of a case by the Court of Cassation became part of our legal history for the first time during the Dreyfus affair.</en>
      <fr>Cette cassation sans renvoi est arrivée dans notre histoire judiciaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24591">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois dans l'affaire Dreyfus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22620" docOffset="204">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="35291" annotation_id="22620">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22620" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Mr Gollnisch is as innocent as Mr Dreyfus.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="18276" annotation_id="24637">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24637" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, M. Gollnisch est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24670">aussi</DiscourseConnective> innocent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24685">que</DiscourseConnective> M. Dreyfus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22674" docOffset="205">
      <en>(The President interrupted the speaker)</en>
      <fr>(Le Président interrompt l'orateur)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22714" docOffset="206">
      <en>I should like to add something.</en>
      <fr>J'ajoute une chose.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22746" docOffset="207">
      <en>I did not say that Baroness Ashton was a communist.</en>
      <fr>Je n'avais pas dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24776">que</DiscourseConnective> Mme Ashton était communiste.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22798" docOffset="208">
      <en>I said that she was one of those pacifists who Lenin might have called a fellow traveller.</en>
      <fr>J'ai dit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24818">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle avait fait partie de ces pacifistes que peut-être Lénine appelle des compagnons de route.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22889" docOffset="209">
      <en>(The President cut off the speaker)</en>
      <fr>(Le Président retire la parole à l'orateur)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="22925" id="100" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="22925" docOffset="210">
      <en>Thank you.</en>
      <fr>Merci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="22936" docOffset="211">
      <en>It was only supposed to be a personal statement.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'était censé être qu'une intervention pour un fait personnel.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
