<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>3.</en>
    <fr>3.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Parliament's position on the new 2011 Draft Budget <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="54" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> modified by the Council (</en>
    <fr>Position du Parlement sur le nouveau projet de budget 2011 tel que modifié par le Conseil (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="83" id="170" name="Sidonia Elżbieta Jędrzejewska">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="83" docOffset="2">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, I think the Members should be given a word of explanation.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, je pense que les députés ont droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="158">à</DiscourseConnective> un mot d'explication.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="161" docOffset="3">
      <en>We are voting on the draft presented to us by the Council, with no changes, <Alignment alignment="1377" annotation_id="237">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="237" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this draft is exactly the same as the position which the Committee on Budgets adopted last week.</en>
      <fr>Nous votons sur le projet qui nous a été soumis par le Conseil, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="246">sans</DiscourseConnective> amendements, <Alignment alignment="1150" annotation_id="264">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="264" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est exactement la <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="288">même</DiscourseConnective> position que celle adoptée par la commission des budgets la semaine dernière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="342" docOffset="4">
      <en>It is in accord with what we negotiated during the very long negotiations, which lasted for 10 months.</en>
      <fr>Il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="378">en</DiscourseConnective> accord avec le résultat des très longues négociations que nous avons menées, et qui ont duré dix mois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="445" docOffset="5">
      <en>I would like to take this opportunity to thank <Alignment alignment="500" annotation_id="492">
          <Alignment alignment="500" annotation_id="492">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="492" sense="Expansion.Restatement">in particular</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the specialist rapporteurs from the European Parliament committees.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaiterais <Alignment alignment="828" annotation_id="500">
          <Alignment alignment="1017" annotation_id="500">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="500" sense="Expansion.Restatement">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> saisir cette occasion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="537">pour</DiscourseConnective> remercier les rapporteurs spéciaux des commissions du Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="574" docOffset="6">
      <en>Thank you for your unceasing confidence and support.</en>
      <fr>Merci de votre confiance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="641">et</DiscourseConnective> de votre soutien sans failles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="627" docOffset="7">
      <en>Thank you for making it possible for us to adopt the 2011 budget, today, <Alignment alignment="740" annotation_id="700">
          <Alignment alignment="3102" annotation_id="700">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="700" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> it can be put into effect efficiently at the very beginning of January next year.</en>
      <fr>Merci de nous avoir permis d'adopter le budget 2011 aujourd'hui, <Alignment alignment="700" annotation_id="740">
          <Alignment alignment="693" annotation_id="740">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="740" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> nous puissions commencer de le mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="787">en</DiscourseConnective> œuvre efficacement début janvier l'année prochaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="790" id="172" name="Olivier Chastel">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="790" docOffset="8">
      <en>President-in-Office of the Council. - (FR) Mr President, honourable Members, Parliament has <Alignment alignment="1904" annotation_id="882">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="882" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> approved the Council's position on the 2011 draft budget without amendments.</en>
      <fr>président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="852">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil. - Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les parlementaires, le Parlement vient <Alignment alignment="89" annotation_id="962">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="962" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'approuver la position du Conseil sur le projet de budget 2011 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1031">sans</DiscourseConnective> amendements.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="969" docOffset="9">
      <en>Clearly I cannot but be pleased, on behalf of the Council, with our common agreement on the 2011 budget.</en>
      <fr>Je ne peux évidemment, au nom du Conseil, que me féliciter de notre accord commun sur le budget 2011.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1074" docOffset="10">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1085" id="173" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1085" docOffset="11">
      <en>Please listen to this statement.</en>
      <fr>Je vous demanderai de bien vouloir écouter la déclaration que j'ai à faire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1118" docOffset="12">
      <en>It is important.</en>
      <fr>Elle est importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1135" docOffset="13">
      <en>For the first time in history, we have applied the procedure set down in the Treaty of Lisbon.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1267">Pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois dans l'histoire, nous avons appliqué la procédure établie par le traité de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1230" docOffset="14">
      <en>Last year, we followed a simplified procedure.</en>
      <fr>L'année dernière, nous avions appliqué une procédure simplifiée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1277" docOffset="15">
      <en>This was the first time the full procedure of the Treaty of Lisbon has been followed.</en>
      <fr>Cette année, c'était la première fois que nous appliquions la procédure à part entière prévue par le traité de Lisbonne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1363" docOffset="16">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="582259" annotation_id="1363">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1363" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, I would like to make the following statement.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="417" annotation_id="1560">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1560" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, je voudrais faire la déclaration suivante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1420" docOffset="17">
      <en>The European Parliament has adopted the Council's position of 10 December 2010 on the draft general budget which was presented by the Commission on 26 November 2010.</en>
      <fr>Le Parlement européen a adopté la position du Conseil du 10 décembre 2010 sur le projet de budget général qui a été présenté par la Commission le 26 novembre 2010.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1586" docOffset="18">
      <en>The budgetary procedure has been completed in accordance with Article 314 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>La procédure budgétaire a été mise en œuvre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1827">en</DiscourseConnective> vertu de l'article 314 du traité sur le fonctionnement de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1716" docOffset="19">
      <en>In accordance with this article and point 4(a) thereof, I declare that the budget for the year 2011 has been definitively adopted, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1847" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> I will now sign the document officially.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1908">En</DiscourseConnective> vertu de cet article <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1932">et</DiscourseConnective> de son point 4, sous a), je déclare le budget <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1981">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'année 2011 définitivement adopté. Je vais à présent procéder à la signature officielle du document.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
