<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Composition of Parliament</en>
    <fr>Composition du Parlement</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="26" id="013" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="26" docOffset="1">
      <en>Ernst Strasser has submitted his resignation as a Member of the European Parliament with effect from 24 March 2011.</en>
      <fr>Ernst Strasser a présenté sa démission en qualité de député au Parlement européen, avec effet au 24 mars 2011.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="142" docOffset="2">
      <en>Pursuant to Rule 4(1) and (3) of the Rules of Procedure, Parliament has noted his resignation and established the vacancy of his seat from the date previously stated.</en>
      <fr>En vertu de l'article 4, paragraphes 1 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="175">et</DiscourseConnective> 3, du règlement, le Parlement a pris acte de sa démission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="236">et</DiscourseConnective> a constaté la vacance de son siège à compter de la date précitée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="309" docOffset="3">
      <en>Hella Ranner has submitted her resignation as a Member of the European Parliament with effect from 1 April 2011.</en>
      <fr>Hella Ranner a présenté sa démission en qualité de députée au Parlement européen avec effet au 1er avril 2011.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="422" docOffset="4">
      <en>Pursuant to Rule 4(1) and (3) of the Rules of Procedure, Parliament has noted her resignation and established the vacancy of her seat from the date previously stated.</en>
      <fr>En vertu de l'article 4, paragraphes 1 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="455">et</DiscourseConnective> 3, du règlement, le Parlement a pris acte de sa démission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="516">et</DiscourseConnective> a constaté la vacance de son siège à compter de la date précitée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="589" docOffset="5">
      <en>The competent Austrian authorities have informed me that Ernst Strasser will be replaced by Hubert Pirker with effect from 31 March 2011.</en>
      <fr>Les autorités autrichiennes compétentes m'ont signalé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="639">que</DiscourseConnective> Ernst Strasser sera remplacé par Hubert Pirker avec effet au 31 mars 2011.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="727" docOffset="6">
      <en>I would like to welcome our new Member and to remind Members that pursuant to Rule 3(2) of the Rules of Procedure, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="842" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">until</DiscourseConnective> his credentials have been verified <Alignment alignment="3223" annotation_id="883">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="883" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a ruling has been given on any dispute, Hubert Pirker will take his seat in Parliament and on its bodies and enjoy all the rights pertaining thereto, provided that he has previously signed a written declaration that he does not hold any office incompatible with that of Member of the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="727">à</DiscourseConnective> souhaiter la bienvenue à notre nouveau membre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="775">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="778">à</DiscourseConnective> rappeler aux députés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="801">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> vertu de l'article 3, paragraphe 2, du règlement, aussi longtemps que son pouvoir n'a pas été vérifié <Alignment alignment="721" annotation_id="909">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="909" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'il n'a pas été statué sur une contestation éventuelle, Hubert Pirker siègera au Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1005">et</DiscourseConnective> dans ses organes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1025">en</DiscourseConnective> pleine jouissance de ses droits, à la condition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1076">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ait au préalable signé une déclaration écrite selon laquelle il n'exerce pas une fonction incompatible avec celle de député au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1191" id="014" name="Barry Madlener">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1191" docOffset="7">
      <en>(NL) Mr President, I wish to raise a point of order in connection with Mr Strasser and the other Member who have left Parliament because of corrupt behaviour: I would like to ask whether you, Mr President, are going to check whether it is possible to stop their reduced pay, <Alignment alignment="1558" annotation_id="1466">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1466" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it would be outrageous <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1497" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective> anyone who has been involved in corruption here left with reduced pay.</en>
      <fr>(NL) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais juste soulever une motion de procédure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1308">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne M. Strasser, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1340">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que l'autre députée qui ont quitté le Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1394">pour</DiscourseConnective> des faits de corruption. Je voudrais vous demander, Monsieur le Président, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1474">si</DiscourseConnective> vous comptez vérifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1499">s'</DiscourseConnective>il est possible de supprimer leurs traitements minimaux, <Alignment alignment="613" annotation_id="1558">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1558" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il serait scandaleux de permettre à un député accusé de corruption de partir avec un tel traitement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1571" docOffset="8">
      <en>Would you please look into this?</en>
      <fr>Pourriez-vous, je vous prie, examiner cette question?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1604" id="015" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1604" docOffset="9">
      <en>We will answer that question later, <Alignment alignment="1766" annotation_id="1640">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1640" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I was not prepared for it.</en>
      <fr>Nous répondrons à cette question ultérieurement, <Alignment alignment="1068" annotation_id="1766">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1766" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je ne m'y attendais pas.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1670" id="016" name="Antonio Masip Hidalgo">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1670" docOffset="10">
      <en>(ES) Mr President, on a point of order: you earlier referred to a request, on behalf of the whole House, that a state of the United States imprison someone for life rather than executing them.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Monsieur le Président, une motion de procédure: vous avez précédemment parlé d'une demande, formulée au nom de l'ensemble de l'Assemblée, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1938">pour que</DiscourseConnective> l'un des États des États-Unis emprisonne quelqu'un <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1998">à</DiscourseConnective> vie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2004">plutôt que de</DiscourseConnective> l'exécuter.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1863" docOffset="11">
      <en>I should like to request that, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1894" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective> we do indeed request that this sentence be commuted, we do not say 'to the sentence of life imprisonment', particularly given what life imprisonment means in the United States.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaiterais, dans le cadre de notre demande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2078">que</DiscourseConnective> cette condamnation soit commuée, que nous ne déclarions pas "une réclusion à perpétuité", sachant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2180">notamment</DiscourseConnective> ce que signifie une réclusion à perpétuité aux États-Unis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2077" docOffset="12">
      <en>I think it should be phrased as the death penalty being commuted 'to another proportionate sentence'.</en>
      <fr>Il conviendrait, selon moi, de formuler la phrase ainsi: la peine de mort devrait être commuée en "une autre condamnation proportionnelle".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2179" id="017" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2179" docOffset="13">
      <en>Thank you.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2190" docOffset="14">
      <en>This certainly calls for a separate and far-reaching debate.</en>
      <fr>Ce point nécessite sans aucun doute un débat distinct <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2461">et</DiscourseConnective> en profondeur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2251" docOffset="15">
      <en>Finding a solution to this problem is definitely not a simple matter.</en>
      <fr>Trouver une solution <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2500">à</DiscourseConnective> ce problème n'est certainement pas chose facile.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2321" docOffset="16">
      <en>My next announcement is that the competent Austrian bodies have informed me that Hella Ranner will be replaced by Heinz Becker with effect from 1 April 2011.</en>
      <fr>Je dois encore vous annoncer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2580">que</DiscourseConnective> les autorités autrichiennes compétentes m'ont signalé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2638">que</DiscourseConnective> Hella Ranner sera remplacée par Heinz Becker avec effet au 1er avril 2011.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2479" docOffset="17">
      <en>I would like to welcome our new Member and to remind Members that pursuant to Rule 3(2) of the Rules of Procedure, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2594" sense="Temporal.Asynchronous.Precedence">until</DiscourseConnective> his credentials have been verified <Alignment alignment="2908" annotation_id="2635">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2635" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> a ruling has been given on any dispute, Heinz Becker will take his seat in Parliament and on its bodies and enjoy all the rights pertaining thereto, provided that he has previously signed a written declaration that he does not hold any office incompatible with that of Member of the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Je tiens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2726">à</DiscourseConnective> souhaiter la bienvenue à notre nouveau membre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2774">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2777">à</DiscourseConnective> rappeler aux députés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2800">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> vertu de l'article 3, paragraphe 2, du règlement, aussi longtemps que son pouvoir n'a pas été vérifié <Alignment alignment="328" annotation_id="2908">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2908" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> qu'il n'a pas été statué sur une contestation éventuelle, Heinz Becker siègera au Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3003">et</DiscourseConnective> dans ses organes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3023">en</DiscourseConnective> pleine jouissance de ses droits, à la condition <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3074">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il ait au préalable signé une déclaration écrite selon laquelle il n'exerce pas une fonction incompatible avec celle de député au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
