<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>9.</en>
    <fr>9.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>A new Energy Strategy for Europe 2011 - 2020 (</en>
    <fr>Vers une nouvelle stratégie énergétique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="43">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe pour la période 2011-2020 (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="50" id="089" name="Hannes Swoboda">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="50" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, on Tuesday of this week, we voted on the Rapkay report, with a compromise on coal mines.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Monsieur le Président, ce mardi, nous avons voté sur le rapport Rapkay, avec un compromis sur les mines de charbon.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="153" docOffset="3">
      <en>Like it or not, a decision has been made by this Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Que cela nous plaise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="227">ou</DiscourseConnective> non, une décision a été prise par ce Parlement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="214" docOffset="4">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="278" annotation_id="214">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="214" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we were to vote now for something different, it would not be well regarded, especially by the Commission.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="57" annotation_id="278">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="278" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous devions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="294">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> voter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="311">pour</DiscourseConnective> quelque chose de différent, cela ne serait pas bien perçu, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="375">surtout</DiscourseConnective> par la Commission.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="323" docOffset="5">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="366145" annotation_id="323">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="323" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">So</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I suggest that, in Amendment 1 by the PPE Group, we include the word 'uncompetitive' to bring it into line with the Rapkay report.</en>
      <fr>Je suggère <Alignment alignment="203" annotation_id="413">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="413" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="418">que</DiscourseConnective>, dans l'amendement 1 du groupe PPE, nous ajoutions le mot "non concurrentiel" <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="500">pour</DiscourseConnective> plus de cohérence avec le rapport Rapkay.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="457" docOffset="6">
      <en>Whatever your individual opinion, the opinion of this Parliament this week should at least be consistent.</en>
      <fr>Quelle que soit votre opinion individuelle, l'opinion de ce Parlement cette semaine devrait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="639">au moins</DiscourseConnective> être cohérente.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="563" id="090" name="Konrad Szymański">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="563" docOffset="7">
      <en>(PL) Mr President, I would like to inform the Chamber that the amendment tabled by the rapporteur, Mrs Kolarska-Bobińska, brings our text, and the sense of our text, sufficiently into line with yesterday's voting on the Rapkay report.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Monsieur le Président, je voudrais informer l'Assemblée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="725">que</DiscourseConnective> l'amendement présenté par la rapporteure, Mme Kolarska-Bobińska, permet d'aligner suffisamment notre texte sur le vote d'hier sur le rapport Rapkay.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="798" docOffset="8">
      <en>The next part of the oral amendment only weakens the expression and tone of the resolution as regards the use of coal as a source of primary energy in the energy mix in the European Union.</en>
      <fr>La partie suivante de l'amendement oral ne fait qu'affaiblir l'expression <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="952">et</DiscourseConnective> le ton de la résolution concernant l'utilisation du charbon <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1015">comme</DiscourseConnective> source d'énergie primaire dans le bouquet énergétique de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="987" docOffset="9">
      <en>I think there is no need to destroy the consensus that we achieved in the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy by adopting the oral amendment.</en>
      <fr>Je pense qu'il ne faut pas réduire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1133">à</DiscourseConnective> néant le consensus auquel nous sommes parvenus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1182">en</DiscourseConnective> commission de l'industrie, de la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1228">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'énergie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1244">en</DiscourseConnective> adoptant l'amendement oral.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1136" docOffset="10">
      <en>For this reason, I ask that you vote against this amendment.</en>
      <fr>C'est la raison pour laquelle je vous demande de voter contre cet amendement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
