<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>One-minute speeches (Rule 150)</en>
    <fr>Interventions d'une minute (article 150 du règlement)</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="31" id="284" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="31" docOffset="1">
      <en>Τhe next item is one-minute speeches.</en>
      <fr>L'ordre du jour appelle les interventions d'une minute.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="69" id="285" name="Anna Záborská">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="69" docOffset="2">
      <en>- (SK) Madam President, free Sundays should become part of a European standard in the area of employment rights. This was agreed on by representatives of trade unions, civic bodies and Christian groups and churches, which founded the European Sunday Alliance this week in Brussels.</en>
      <fr>- (SK) Madame la Présidente, les dimanches libres devraient constituer une norme européenne dans le domaine des droits du travail, ce qu'ont approuvé les représentants de syndicats, d'organisations de la société civile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="329">et</DiscourseConnective> d'associations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="347">et</DiscourseConnective> églises chrétiennes, qui ont fondé cette semaine, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="400">à</DiscourseConnective> Bruxelles, la European Sunday Alliance (Alliance européenne pour le dimanche).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="351" docOffset="3">
      <en>A free Sunday is important from the perspective of decent employment conditions, <Alignment alignment="23954" annotation_id="432">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="432" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it <Alignment alignment="33844" annotation_id="439">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="439" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> creates an opportunity to build up family relationships, particularly between parents and children.</en>
      <fr>Les dimanches libres sont essentiels <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="518">à</DiscourseConnective> des conditions d'emploi décentes, <Alignment alignment="432" annotation_id="554">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="554" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ils permettent <Alignment alignment="439" annotation_id="574">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="574" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de consolider les relations familiales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="620">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> entre les parents <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="653">et</DiscourseConnective> les enfants.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="544" docOffset="4">
      <en>I am pleased that I was present at the birth of this initiative, just like the two civic associations from Slovakia - the Large Families Club and the Alliance for Sunday.</en>
      <fr>Je suis ravie d'avoir assisté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="699">à</DiscourseConnective> la naissance de cette initiative, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="735">au même titre que</DiscourseConnective> les deux associations slovaques de la société civile (le Club des familles nombreuses <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="839">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Alliance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="853">pour</DiscourseConnective> le dimanche).</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="715" docOffset="5">
      <en>The Commission, in its revision of the Working Time Directive, should take account of the view of the hundreds of organisations from across Europe federated in the newly established alliance, <Alignment alignment="20470" annotation_id="907">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="907" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> such a large association cannot be ignored <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="958" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective> creating laws.</en>
      <fr>Lors de la révision de la directive relative au temps de travail, la Commission devrait tenir compte du point de vue de centaines d'organisations européennes réunies dans cette nouvelle alliance, <Alignment alignment="907" annotation_id="1068">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1068" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> on ne peut ignorer une si grande association dans l'élaboration de la législation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="978" id="286" name="László Tőkés">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="978" docOffset="6">
      <en>(HU) Madam President, in the last few weeks the founders of Szeklerland's Representative Office in Brussels, and the Hungarian community in Romania in general, have had to endure a long chain of attacks and a hostile hysteria campaign from the Romanian political elite.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Madame la Présidente, ces dernières semaines, les fondateurs du bureau de représentation du pays des Sicules <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1269">à</DiscourseConnective> Bruxelles, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1282">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que la communauté hongroise de Roumanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1328">en</DiscourseConnective> général ont subi une longue série d'attaques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1376">et</DiscourseConnective> une vague d'hystérie hostile de la part de l'élite politique roumaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1248" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1248" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Meanwhile</DiscourseConnective>, attempts have been made to force a territorial and administrative reorganisation plan in Romania, which would create eight majority megaregions, forcing the Hungarian majority living in Szeklerland and Partium into absolute minority.</en>
      <fr>Entre-temps, on a tenté d'imposer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1484">en</DiscourseConnective> Roumanie un plan de réorganisation territoriale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1535">et</DiscourseConnective> administrative, qui créerait huit mégarégions majoritaires, contraignant la majorité hongroise vivant dans le pays des Sicules <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1665">et</DiscourseConnective> dans le Partium à devenir une minorité absolue.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1493" docOffset="8">
      <en>Pursuant to the explicit provisions set out in the European Charter of Local Self-Government and the European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages, the Transylvanian Hungarian MEPs from Romania firmly reject this antidemocratic and discriminative method of regional reorganisation of their country.</en>
      <fr>Conformément aux dispositions explicites contenues dans la charte européenne de l'autonomie locale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1815">et</DiscourseConnective> dans la charte européenne des langues régionales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1867">ou</DiscourseConnective> minoritaires, les parlementaires hongrois de Transylvanie, en Roumanie, rejettent fermement cette méthode antidémocratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1993">et</DiscourseConnective> discriminatoire de réorganisation régionale de leur pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1798" docOffset="9">
      <en>We ask for your effective help in the name of the common democratic values of the governing Popular Parties of Romania and Hungary, <Alignment alignment="32537" annotation_id="1930">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1930" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we ask for Parliament's active support for the protection of the Transylvanian Hungarian community.</en>
      <fr>Au nom des valeurs démocratiques communes des partis populaires au pouvoir en Roumanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2141">et</DiscourseConnective> en Hongrie, nous demandons une aide efficace de votre part, <Alignment alignment="1930" annotation_id="2204">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2204" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que le soutien actif du Parlement en faveur de la protection de la communauté hongroise de Transylvanie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2034" id="287" name="Alexander Mirsky">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2034" docOffset="10">
      <en>(LV) Madam President, what do you think the word 'perversion' means?</en>
      <fr>(LV) Madame la Présidente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2342">que</DiscourseConnective> pensez-vous que signifie le mot "perversité"?</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2103" docOffset="11">
      <en>In the dictionary this word means complete distortion.</en>
      <fr>D'après le dictionnaire, ce mot désigne une tendance à faire le mal consciemment par plaisir de nuire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2158" docOffset="12">
      <en>Political perversion means nothing but lies and cynical deception of voters.</en>
      <fr>La perversité politique ne signifie rien d'autre que des mensonges <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2562">et</DiscourseConnective> une tromperie cynique à l'égard des électeurs.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2235" docOffset="13">
      <en>It appears that in Latvia, there has appeared a group of members of parliament who are political perverts.</en>
      <fr>Il semble <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2622">que</DiscourseConnective> la Lituanie a vu naître un groupe de parlementaires empreints de perversité politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2342" docOffset="14">
      <en>The issue is that during the last elections to the Latvian parliament, members of the Saskaņas centrs (Harmony Centre) group promised their Russian-speaking constituents, who in Latvia comprise more than 40% of the population, that they would protect their native language.</en>
      <fr>Le problème est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2729">que</DiscourseConnective>, lors des dernières élections au parlement lituanien, des membres du groupe Saskaņas centrs (centre de l'harmonie) ont promis à leurs électeurs russophones, qui représentent plus de 40 % de la population lituanienne, de protéger leur langue maternelle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2616" docOffset="15">
      <en>Last week, <Alignment alignment="19553" annotation_id="2627">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2627" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, this group voted for increased penalties for those people who fail to use the official state language in the private sector.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17991" annotation_id="2986">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2986" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, la semaine dernière, ce groupe a voté en faveur d'un renforcement des pénalités <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3077">pour</DiscourseConnective> les personnes qui n'utilisent pas la langue officielle de l'État dans le secteur privé.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2761" docOffset="16">
      <en>It turns out that they promise one thing, and do another.</en>
      <fr>Il s'avère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3181">que</DiscourseConnective> leurs actes ne correspondent pas à leurs promesses.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2819" docOffset="17">
      <en>I believe you will agree that that is perversion.</en>
      <fr>Je crois que vous serez d'accord de <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3273">dire qu'</DiscourseConnective>il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3284">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit de perversité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2869" docOffset="18">
      <en>It is possible that Latvia will become the birthplace of a new political movement, the 'Perversion Centre'.</en>
      <fr>Il est possible <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3322">que</DiscourseConnective> la Lituanie devienne le berceau d'un nouveau mouvement politique, à savoir le "centre de la perversité".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2977" docOffset="19">
      <en>Thank you for your attention.</en>
      <fr>Je vous remercie de votre attention.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3007" id="288" name="Nikolaos Salavrakos">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3007" docOffset="20">
      <en>(EL) Madam President, certainly no European, and hence no Greek, likes to go round with a begging bowl.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Madame la Présidente, il est certain qu'aucun Européen, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3529">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3532">donc</DiscourseConnective> aucun Grec, n'apprécie de demander l'aumône.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3111" docOffset="21">
      <en>We Greeks need to understand that we have turned our standard of living back at least 10 years.</en>
      <fr>Nous, les Grecs, devons nous-mêmes comprendre que notre niveau de vie est revenu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3663">à</DiscourseConnective> celui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3671">que</DiscourseConnective> nous connaissions il y a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3700">au moins</DiscourseConnective> dix ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3207" docOffset="22">
      <en>I fear that, unfortunately, the same will happen in other countries too.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3718">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, je crains <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3745">que</DiscourseConnective> cela se produise également dans d'autres pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3280" docOffset="23">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="5077" annotation_id="3280">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3280" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we see that we are being blamed for things which go beyond our responsibilities.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4864" annotation_id="3796">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3796" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, nous constatons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3823">que</DiscourseConnective> nous sommes blâmés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3846">pour</DiscourseConnective> quelque chose qui n'est pas de notre responsabilité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3370" docOffset="24">
      <en>Seventeen captains in Europe, plus as many mates, seventeen budgets, seventeen bond markets and one common currency.</en>
      <fr>Dix-sept capitaines <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3924">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe, plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3940">autant</DiscourseConnective> de seconds, dix-sept budgets, dix-sept marchés obligataires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4007">et</DiscourseConnective> une monnaie unique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3487" docOffset="25">
      <en>The common currency cannot go on like this.</en>
      <fr>Celle-ci ne peut continuer sur cette voie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3531" docOffset="26">
      <en>We need a common economic policy, a single bond market and joint coordination.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons besoin d'une politique économique commune, d'un marché obligataire unique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4158">et</DiscourseConnective> d'une coordination centralisée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3610" docOffset="27">
      <en>Without doubt, fiscal prudence implies a shake-up in the consumer climate.</en>
      <fr>Il ne fait pas de doute que la prudence fiscale implique un bouleversement de l'environnement de consommation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3685" docOffset="28">
      <en>I do not see anything happening in that direction.</en>
      <fr>Je ne vois rien se concrétiser <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4335">en ce sens</DiscourseConnective>.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3736" docOffset="29">
      <en>We need to safeguard the major achievements of the last 65 years, culminating in the single currency, by being more disciplined with ourselves.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons défendre les réalisations majeures des 65 dernières années, dont le point culminant est la monnaie unique, en nous imposant une plus grande autodiscipline.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3880" id="289" name="Nicole Sinclaire">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3880" docOffset="30">
      <en>Madam President, less than a year ago I set up a cross-party petition for a referendum in the UK in respect of membership of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, il y a moins d'un an, j'ai lancé une pétition multipartite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4601">pour</DiscourseConnective> la tenue d'un référendum au Royaume-Uni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4646">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de l'adhésion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4669">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4025" docOffset="31">
      <en>The campaign has attracted high-profile support from across the political spectrum.</en>
      <fr>Cette campagne a bénéficié d'un soutien de premier plan de la part de tout l'éventail politique.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4109" docOffset="32">
      <en>What these people have railed against is the EU obsession of creating a European federal state, ignoring the will of the people and democracy.</en>
      <fr>Toutes ces personnes ont protesté contre l'obsession de l'UE de créer un État fédéral européen en ignorant la volonté des citoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4919">et</DiscourseConnective> la démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4252" docOffset="33">
      <en>One cannot ignore the will of people forever.</en>
      <fr>On ne peut ignorer la volonté des citoyens éternellement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4298" docOffset="34">
      <en>My constituents constantly come to me and say, '<Alignment alignment="5055" annotation_id="4346">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4346" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> are we going to get a say on our membership of the European Union?'</en>
      <fr>Les électeurs de ma circonscription me demandent sans cesse <Alignment alignment="4346" annotation_id="5055">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5055" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous pourrons nous exprimer sur notre adhésion <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5108">à</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4419" docOffset="35">
      <en>The will of the people across Europe has been ignored, a single currency has been created, against the will of the people of Europe, and look what problems have been created.</en>
      <fr>La volonté des citoyens européens a été ignorée, une monnaie unique a été créée, contre la volonté des citoyens européens, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5253">et</DiscourseConnective> nous constatons maintenant les problèmes qui sont apparus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4594" docOffset="36">
      <en>There have been referenda in Member States <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4637" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> they have been ignored.</en>
      <fr>Des États membres ont organisé des référendums qui ont été ignorés.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4665" docOffset="37">
      <en>The people from my constituency, the people across the UK and the people across the European Union are saying, 'Let the people decide'.</en>
      <fr>Les citoyens de ma circonscription, les citoyens du Royaume-Uni <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5447">et</DiscourseConnective> les citoyens de l'Union européenne demandent qu'on laisse les citoyens décider.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4801" docOffset="38">
      <en>The professional politicians have made a mess.</en>
      <fr>Les hommes et femmes politiques professionnels ont semé la pagaille.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4848" docOffset="39">
      <en>Let the people decide.</en>
      <fr>Laissons les citoyens décider.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="4871" id="291" name="Czesław Adam Siekierski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="4871" docOffset="40">
      <en>(PL) Madam President, a Treaty of Good Neighbourship and Friendly Cooperation was signed between Poland and Germany as long ago as 11 June 1991, forming a basis for current relations between the two countries.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Madame la Présidente, le 11 juin 1991, la Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5685">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Allemagne ont signé un traité de bon voisinage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5737">et</DiscourseConnective> de coopération amicale, qui a constitué la base des relations actuelles entre les deux pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5081" docOffset="41">
      <en>Yesterday, on the 20th anniversary of this momentous event, a joint consultation between the Polish and German governments took place in Warsaw, chaired by Mr Tusk, the Polish Prime Minister, and Mrs Merkel, the German Chancellor.</en>
      <fr>Hier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5839">à</DiscourseConnective> l'occasion du 20e anniversaire de cet événement majeur, une consultation entre les gouvernements polonais <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5947">et</DiscourseConnective> allemand a eu lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5969">à</DiscourseConnective> Varsovie, sous la présidence de M. Tusk, le Premier ministre polonais, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6042">et</DiscourseConnective> Mme Merkel, la chancelière allemande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5312" docOffset="42">
      <en>Over 20 ministers and deputy ministers from the individual departments of both states took part in the consultation.</en>
      <fr>Plus de vingt ministres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6107">et</DiscourseConnective> ministres adjoints des différents ministères des deux États ont participé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6184">à</DiscourseConnective> cette consultation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5429" docOffset="43">
      <en>The outcome of the joint meeting is the statement by the governments of the Republic of Poland <Alignment alignment="39770" annotation_id="5524">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="5524" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Federal Republic of Germany entitled 'Neighbours and Partners', together with an attached programme of cooperation for the coming years.</en>
      <fr>La réunion conjointe a donné lieu à une déclaration par les gouvernements de la République de Pologne <Alignment alignment="14209" annotation_id="6308">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6308" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> de la République fédérale d'Allemagne, intitulée "Voisins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6369">et</DiscourseConnective> partenaires", ainsi qu'à l'élaboration d'un programme connexe de coopération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6449">pour</DiscourseConnective> les années à venir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5669" docOffset="44">
      <en>On the occasion of this anniversary, I should like to remind the House of the commitment shown by successive German governments to supporting Polish attempts to join the European Union.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6474">À</DiscourseConnective> l'occasion de cet anniversaire, je voudrais rappeler à cette Assemblée l'engagement pris par les gouvernements allemands successifs de soutenir les démarches de la Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6648">en vue de</DiscourseConnective> rejoindre l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5855" docOffset="45">
      <en>Relations between Poland and Germany are constantly improving, one example of which is the growing volume of trade between the two countries.</en>
      <fr>Les relations entre la Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6719">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Allemagne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6734">s'</DiscourseConnective>améliorent constamment, comme le montre, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6777">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>, l'augmentation des échanges entre ces deux pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="5997" docOffset="46">
      <en>Our economies are among the most dynamic in Europe.</en>
      <fr>Nos économies comptent parmi les plus dynamiques d'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6049" docOffset="47">
      <en>We hope that relations between Poland and Germany will continue to develop, for the good of our citizens and of Europe as a whole.</en>
      <fr>Nous espérons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6912">que</DiscourseConnective> les relations entre la Pologne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6947">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Allemagne continueront de se développer, dans l'intérêt de nos concitoyens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7027">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'Europe dans son ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="6180" id="292" name="Elisabeth Köstinger">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="6180" docOffset="48">
      <en>(DE) Madam President, the European Union needs an effective common agricultural policy to enable it to meet society's demands for high standards and, most importantly, to allow it to play a strong, independent role.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Madame la Présidente, l'Union européenne a besoin d'une politique agricole commune efficace <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7158">pour</DiscourseConnective> pouvoir répondre aux normes élevées exigées par la société <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7222">et</DiscourseConnective>, qui plus est, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7240">pour</DiscourseConnective> pouvoir jouer un rôle fort et indépendant.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6396" docOffset="49">
      <en>Businesses in Europe must remain competitive.</en>
      <fr>Les entreprises européennes doivent rester compétitives.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6442" docOffset="50">
      <en>They are faced with major challenges, including fluctuations in the price of raw materials, high production costs and low income levels.</en>
      <fr>Elles doivent relever d'énormes défis, y compris les fluctuations des prix des matières premières, des coûts de production élevés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7475">et</DiscourseConnective> de faibles niveaux de revenus.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6579" docOffset="51">
      <en>Downward pressure is being exerted on prices by the low production costs and low social, environmental and quality standards in third countries, which cannot be compared with the standards in the EU.</en>
      <fr>Une pression à la baisse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7534">s'</DiscourseConnective>exerce sur les prix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7556">en</DiscourseConnective> raison de l'application de faibles coûts de production <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7614">et</DiscourseConnective> de normes sociales, environnementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7655">et</DiscourseConnective> de qualité peu élevées dans des pays tiers, qui ne sont pas comparables aux normes appliquées dans l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6779" docOffset="52">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6779" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective> new trading relationships are established, it is essential for us to protect European production levels by including safeguard clauses.</en>
      <fr>Lors de l'établissement de nouvelles relations commerciales, il est essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7841">que</DiscourseConnective> nous protégions les niveaux de production européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7897">en</DiscourseConnective> y incluant des clauses de sauvegarde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="6920" docOffset="53">
      <en>Clauses of this kind which are used in an industrial context, <Alignment alignment="28608" annotation_id="6982">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="6982" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in trade agreements with South Korea concerning the car industry, must <Alignment alignment="37413" annotation_id="7065">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7065" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> be applied to agriculture.</en>
      <fr>Ce type de clause qui est employé dans un contexte industriel, <Alignment alignment="1962" annotation_id="8001">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8001" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> dans les accords commerciaux du secteur automobile conclus avec la Corée du Sud, doit <Alignment alignment="9497" annotation_id="8099">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8099" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> être utilisé dans le domaine de l'agriculture.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7097" docOffset="54">
      <en>This is all about establishing a level playing field and equal opportunities for all.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8159">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit d'établir des conditions de concurrence équitables <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8217">et</DiscourseConnective> une égalité des chances <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8244">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7183" docOffset="55">
      <en>Every country should have the right to focus on the concerns of its citizens, including food security, the environment, reservations about genetic modification and the needs of rural areas, in order to support sustainable agriculture in Europe.</en>
      <fr>Chaque pays devrait avoir le droit de se concentrer sur les préoccupations de ses citoyens, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8347">notamment en</DiscourseConnective> matière de sécurité alimentaire, d'environnement, de réserves quant à la modification génétique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8456">et</DiscourseConnective> de besoins des zones rurales, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8489">afin de</DiscourseConnective> soutenir une agriculture durable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8530">en</DiscourseConnective> Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="7428" id="293" name="Ramon Tremosa i Balcells">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="7428" docOffset="56">
      <en>Madam President, last week in the Catalan Parliament some MEPs representing the main political parties of Catalonia made a common stand in defence of our language, Catalan, in the EU and in its institutions.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, la semaine dernière, au parlement catalan, certains parlementaires représentant les principaux partis politiques de Catalogne ont présenté une position commune <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8728">en</DiscourseConnective> faveur de la défense de notre langue, le catalan, dans l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8805">et</DiscourseConnective> au sein de ses institutions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7636" docOffset="57">
      <en>We call again for Catalan to be recognised as an official language in the European Parliament, just <Alignment alignment="43028" annotation_id="7736">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="7736" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> many other Catalan MEPs have been doing over the last 25 years.</en>
      <fr>Nous réitérons notre demande de reconnaissance du catalan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8895">comme</DiscourseConnective> langue officielle au Parlement européen, <Alignment alignment="6682" annotation_id="8942">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8942" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> d'autres députés catalans l'ont fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8985">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 25 ans.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7803" docOffset="58">
      <en>Now there is a new opportunity for the Catalan language, which has been prohibited for centuries in the Spanish state.</en>
      <fr>Il existe aujourd'hui une nouvelle perspective <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9047">pour</DiscourseConnective> la langue catalane, dont l'usage est interdit depuis des siècles dans l'État espagnol.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7922" docOffset="59">
      <en>In a few months Croatia will enter the Union.</en>
      <fr>Dans quelques mois, la Croatie rejoindra l'Union.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="7968" docOffset="60">
      <en>For Croatian to be an official language, the Treaty has to be modified.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9189">Pour que</DiscourseConnective> le croate devienne une langue officielle, il faut modifier le traité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8040" docOffset="61">
      <en>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8040" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">When</DiscourseConnective> that time comes, we will again ask the Spanish Government to allow official status for Catalan in the EU.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9268">À ce moment-là</DiscourseConnective>, nous demanderons à nouveau au gouvernement espagnol d'accorder un statut officiel au catalan dans l'UE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8151" docOffset="62">
      <en>The Spanish Government should bring the Catalan language to the EU just <Alignment alignment="18563" annotation_id="8223">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8223" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the Irish Government did with the Gaelic language some years ago.</en>
      <fr>Le gouvernement espagnol devrait introduire la langue catalane dans l'UE, <Alignment alignment="8223" annotation_id="9462">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9462" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le gouvernement irlandais l'a fait <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9503">pour</DiscourseConnective> le gaélique il y a quelques années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8292" docOffset="63">
      <en>We ask for the support of the European Parliament and the Commission to achieve recognition of Catalan as an official language.</en>
      <fr>Nous demandons le soutien du Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9592">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9612">afin de</DiscourseConnective> parvenir à la reconnaissance du catalan <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9660">comme</DiscourseConnective> langue officielle.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="8420" id="294" name="Spyros Danellis">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="8420" docOffset="64">
      <en>(EL) Madam President, the problem of piracy in the Gulf of Aden, and now in the huge sea area of the Indian Ocean, is still getting worse, despite efforts by EU NAVFOR.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Madame la Présidente, le problème de la piraterie dans le golfe d'Aden, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9762">et</DiscourseConnective> à présent dans l'immense région maritime de l'océan Indien, continue de s'aggraver, en dépit des efforts déployés par l'EU NAVFOR.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8589" docOffset="65">
      <en>The size of the area in which pirates operate makes it hard to deal with the problem of piracy with military resources alone.</en>
      <fr>En raison de la superficie de la zone dans laquelle les pirates agissent, il est difficile de résoudre le problème de la piraterie en n'utilisant que des moyens militaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8715" docOffset="66">
      <en>As such, measures to suppress the problem, <Alignment alignment="41641" annotation_id="8758">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="8758" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> possible within the framework of an ambitious international strategy, must be improved in conjunction with measures to combat its root causes.</en>
      <fr>Il convient donc d'améliorer les mesures destinées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10120">à</DiscourseConnective> éradiquer ce problème, <Alignment alignment="948" annotation_id="10145">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10145" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> possible dans le cadre d'une stratégie internationale ambitieuse, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10214">tout en</DiscourseConnective> les associant à des mesures visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10257">à</DiscourseConnective> combattre les causes profondes de ce phénomène.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="8904" docOffset="67">
      <en>Piracy is rooted in absolute poverty and lack of governance, two permanent features of Somalia over the last 20 years.</en>
      <fr>La piraterie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10320">s'</DiscourseConnective>explique par une pauvreté absolue <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10356">et</DiscourseConnective> par un manque de gouvernance, deux caractéristiques constantes de la Somalie au cours des vingt dernières années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9023" docOffset="68">
      <en>The European Union has the facility to make greater use of the European Development Fund for this purpose.</en>
      <fr>L'Union européenne a la possibilité de recourir davantage au Fonds européen de développement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10566">pour</DiscourseConnective> cette question.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9130" docOffset="69">
      <en>Both the European Union and the United Nations have acquired experience in programmes which have produced real results in Somalia <Alignment alignment="42042" annotation_id="9260">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9260" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that work must be continued and increased.</en>
      <fr>Tant l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10597">que</DiscourseConnective> les Nations unies ont acquis de l'expérience dans des programmes qui ont donné des résultats concrets <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10703">en</DiscourseConnective> Somalie <Alignment alignment="15928" annotation_id="10714">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10714" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il convient de poursuivre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10743">et</DiscourseConnective> de renforcer ce travail.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="9307" id="295" name="Marek Henryk Migalski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="9307" docOffset="70">
      <en>(PL) Madam President, last night Anatoly Bitkov died in Magadan, the principal town of the Kolyma region in Russia.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Madame la Présidente, la nuit dernière, Anatoly Bitkov est décédé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10842">à</DiscourseConnective> Magadan, principale ville de la région de Kolyma, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10894">en</DiscourseConnective> Russie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9423" docOffset="71">
      <en>He was the chief editor of the local television channel 'Kolyma Plyus'.</en>
      <fr>Il était le directeur de la chaîne de télévision locale "Kolyma Plyus".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9495" docOffset="72">
      <en>Without wishing to pre-empt any findings as to whether this was murder or natural death, <Alignment alignment="34962" annotation_id="9584">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9584" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> whether it was a politically motivated murder <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9633" sense="Expansion.Alternative">or</DiscourseConnective> not, it is worth pointing out that this sad event is unfortunately not an exception.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10977">Sans</DiscourseConnective> vouloir conclure anticipativement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11016">à</DiscourseConnective> un meurtre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11029">ou</DiscourseConnective> une mort naturelle, <Alignment alignment="14848" annotation_id="11052">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11052" sense="Expansion.Alternative">ou</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> éventuellement à un meurtre politique, il convient de faire remarquer que ce triste événement n'est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11155">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> pas une exception.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9721" docOffset="73">
      <en>Journalists die in Russia, <Alignment alignment="2476" annotation_id="9748">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="9748" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> journalists investigating political issues die even more frequently.</en>
      <fr>Des journalistes meurent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11215">en</DiscourseConnective> Russie <Alignment alignment="5687" annotation_id="11225">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11225" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> des journalistes qui enquêtent sur des sujets politiques meurent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11293">encore</DiscourseConnective> plus fréquemment.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9821" docOffset="74">
      <en>A great many serious analyses have found that around 200 journalists have died in the Russian Federation over the past 10 years.</en>
      <fr>De nombreuses analyses sérieuses ont permis de conclure <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11374">que</DiscourseConnective> quelque 200 journalistes sont morts dans la Fédération de Russie ces dix dernières années.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="9950" docOffset="75">
      <en>This is the highest-risk profession in Russia today.</en>
      <fr>Le journalisme est aujourd'hui la profession à plus haut risque en Russie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10003" docOffset="76">
      <en>Without freedom and safety for journalists, there can be no freedom of the media, <Alignment alignment="34246" annotation_id="10085">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10085" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> without freedom of the media there can be no democracy.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11544">Sans</DiscourseConnective> la liberté <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11560">et</DiscourseConnective> la sécurité des journalistes, il ne peut y avoir une liberté de presse <Alignment alignment="16812" annotation_id="11634">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11634" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11638">sans</DiscourseConnective> liberté de presse, il ne peut y avoir de démocratie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10145" docOffset="77">
      <en>We should always remember this in our cooperation and collaboration with the Russian Federation.</en>
      <fr>Nous devrions toujours nous en souvenir dans le cadre de notre coopération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11771">et</DiscourseConnective> de notre collaboration avec la Fédération de Russie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="10242" id="296" name="Paul Murphy">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="10242" docOffset="78">
      <en>Madam President, on Saturday I will set sail for Gaza with hundreds of other activists <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10329" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective> part of the Freedom Flotilla 2.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, samedi, je partirai en bateau <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11884">pour</DiscourseConnective> Gaza avec des centaines d'autres militants participant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11944">à</DiscourseConnective> la "Flottille pour la liberté II".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10364" docOffset="79">
      <en>We will be bringing medicine and reconstruction materials that are desperately needed.</en>
      <fr>Nous emporterons des médicaments <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12014">et</DiscourseConnective> des matériaux de reconstruction qui font cruellement défaut.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10451" docOffset="80">
      <en>As a result of Israel's illegal blockade, 300 000 people live on less than a dollar a day <Alignment alignment="32333" annotation_id="10541">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10541" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> there is over 40% unemployment.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12078">En</DiscourseConnective> raison du blocus israélien illégal, 300 000 personnes vivent avec moins d'un dollar par jour <Alignment alignment="6033" annotation_id="12174">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12174" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le taux de chômage <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12196">s'</DiscourseConnective>élève à plus de 40 %.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10577" docOffset="81">
      <en>Catherine Ashton has said that the flotilla is not the right response to the situation in Gaza, <Alignment alignment="17488" annotation_id="10673">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="10673" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the EU's response is to continue to fund, through research grants, the Israeli armaments companies that make the weapons that kill Palestinian civilians.</en>
      <fr>Catherine Ashton a déclaré <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12247">que</DiscourseConnective> la flottille n'est pas la réaction appropriée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12297">à</DiscourseConnective> la situation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12312">à</DiscourseConnective> Gaza, <Alignment alignment="10673" annotation_id="12320">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12320" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la réaction de l'UE est de poursuivre le financement, par des bourses de recherche, des usines d'armement israéliennes qui fabriquent les armes qui tuent les civils palestiniens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10831" docOffset="82">
      <en>Instead of criticising the flotilla, the EU should condemn the threats of violence made against us by the Israel Defence Forces.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12504">Au lieu de</DiscourseConnective> critiquer la flottille, l'UE devrait condamner les menaces de violence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12586">que</DiscourseConnective> les forces de défense israéliennes nous adressent.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="10960" docOffset="83">
      <en>Given the fact that they murdered nine activists on the flotilla last year, these threats have to be taken extremely seriously.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12641">Étant donné qu'</DiscourseConnective>elles ont assassiné l'année dernière neuf militants faisant partie de la flottille, il est impératif de prendre ces menaces au sérieux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11088" docOffset="84">
      <en>The EU should <Alignment alignment="33896" annotation_id="11102">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11102" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> end its complicity with the continuing oppression of the Palestinian people.</en>
      <fr>L'UE devrait <Alignment alignment="10023" annotation_id="12805">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12805" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mettre un terme à sa complicité dans l'oppression permanente du peuple palestinien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="11184" id="297" name="Monika Smolková">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="11184" docOffset="85">
      <en>- (SK) Madam President, two weeks ago in Strasbourg, there was a heated discussion on the Hungarian constitution.</en>
      <fr>- (SK) Madame la Présidente, il y a deux semaines, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12950">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg, une discussion passionnée a eu lieu <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13000">à propos</DiscourseConnective> de la constitution hongroise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11298" docOffset="86">
      <en>Today we <Alignment alignment="17002" annotation_id="11307">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11307" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have the statement of the Venice Commission.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui, nous avons <Alignment alignment="14830" annotation_id="13063">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13063" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la déclaration de la commission de Venise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11357" docOffset="87">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="31229" annotation_id="11365">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11365" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to repeat my warning about the problematic wording of the Hungarian constitution, particularly in the formulation of Section D, which talks about the responsibility of Hungary for all Hungarians, about a single Hungarian nation, about collective rights and about the creation of collective self-governing authorities in other countries, based on the principle of ethnicity.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="17415" annotation_id="13128">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13128" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> réitérer mon avertissement concernant la formulation problématique de la constitution hongroise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13230">notamment</DiscourseConnective> dans la section D, qui porte sur la responsabilité de la Hongrie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13305">pour</DiscourseConnective> tous les Hongrois, sur une nation hongroise unique, sur des droits collectifs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13388">et</DiscourseConnective> sur l'institution d'autorités collectives autonomes dans d'autres pays, sur la base du principe d'ethnicité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11754" docOffset="88">
      <en>The Venice Commission has emphasised the individual nature of human rights, <Alignment alignment="7292" annotation_id="11830">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="11830" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the framework agreement for the protection of ethnic minorities does not assume any collective minority rights.</en>
      <fr>La commission de Venise a souligné le caractère personnel des droits de l'homme, <Alignment alignment="4759" annotation_id="13581">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13581" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'accord-cadre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13600">pour</DiscourseConnective> la protection des minorités ethniques ne couvre aucun droit minoritaire collectif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="11945" docOffset="89">
      <en>The Venice Commission has cast doubt on the principle of democracy by accepting a constitutional law for cultural, religious, ethical, social, economic and financial policy.</en>
      <fr>La commission de Venise a mis en doute le principe de démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13753">en</DiscourseConnective> approuvant une loi constitutionnelle sur une politique culturelle, religieuse, éthique, sociale, économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13864">et</DiscourseConnective> financière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12119" docOffset="90">
      <en>I expect a rapid response from the EU institutions to the opinion of the Venice Commission on the Hungarian constitution.</en>
      <fr>J'attends une réaction rapide des institutions de l'UE <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13934">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avis de la commission de Venise sur la constitution hongroise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="12241" id="298" name="Michail Tremopoulos">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="12241" docOffset="91">
      <en>(EL) Madam President, I wonder <Alignment alignment="44974" annotation_id="12272">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12272" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the economic crisis can be resolved with measures at the expense of the climate.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Madame la Présidente, je me demande <Alignment alignment="8600" annotation_id="14042">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14042" sense="Contingency.Condition">si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la crise économique peut être résolue par des mesures néfastes au climat.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12356" docOffset="92">
      <en>The European Commission, unfortunately, says it can, given that it and Portugal have jointly endorsed a term on reduced guaranteed prices for energy from renewable sources as a lawful measure in the memorandum on the support mechanism.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14119">Malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, la Commission européenne dit que c'est possible, car elle est arrivée à un accord avec le Portugal sur une réduction des prix garantis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14271">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'énergie provenant de sources renouvelables, cette mesure légale faisant partie du protocole relatif au mécanisme de soutien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12592" docOffset="93">
      <en>In Greece, investments in renewable energy are one of the few counterweights to the economic crisis <Alignment alignment="20275" annotation_id="12692">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12692" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the commitment by the outgoing Minister for Environmental Affairs to safeguard guaranteed prices needs to be renewed immediately by her successor.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14403">En</DiscourseConnective> Grèce, les investissements dans les énergies renouvelables constituent l'une des rares compensations de la crise économique <Alignment alignment="13258" annotation_id="14530">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14530" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'engagement pris par la ministre sortante de l'environnement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14595">pour</DiscourseConnective> protéger les prix garantis doit être immédiatement renouvelé par son successeur.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="12843" docOffset="94">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="22533" annotation_id="12843">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="12843" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the debate on a possible exemption for countries with economic problems from the already inadequate European climate targets, the 20-20-20 targets, is a serious absurdity.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="4784" annotation_id="14681">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14681" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le débat sur la possibilité d'exempter les pays qui connaissent des problèmes économiques d'atteindre les objectifs climatiques européens <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14830">déjà</DiscourseConnective> inadéquats (les objectifs 20/20/20) est une véritable absurdité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13024" docOffset="95">
      <en>These choices illustrate an unacceptable attitude endorsed by the Commission; they set entire European policies in stone <Alignment alignment="8460" annotation_id="13145">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13145" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> no one anywhere is held to account.</en>
      <fr>Ces choix illustrent une attitude inacceptable de la part de la Commission: elle scelle dans le béton des politiques européennes entières <Alignment alignment="6598" annotation_id="15038">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15038" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> personne, nulle part, ne doit rendre des comptes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13185" docOffset="96">
      <en>All Europe will achieve with this is to cut the branch it is sitting on.</en>
      <fr>Ainsi, tout ce que l'Europe réussira à faire sera de couper la branche sur laquelle elle est assise.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13258" docOffset="97">
      <en>Climate targets must be increased to the levels called for by scientists <Alignment alignment="23418" annotation_id="13331">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13331" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> special programmes must be designed for countries with economic problems.</en>
      <fr>Les objectifs climatiques doivent être relevés jusqu'aux niveaux demandés par les scientifiques <Alignment alignment="13331" annotation_id="15288">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15288" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> il convient d'élaborer des programmes spéciaux <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15338">pour</DiscourseConnective> les pays qui font face à des problèmes économiques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13409" docOffset="98">
      <en>It is our destiny to find a way out of the impasse and face the economic, social and environmental crisis.</en>
      <fr>Il nous appartient de trouver une issue à cette impasse <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15451">et</DiscourseConnective> de résoudre la crise économique, sociale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15495">et</DiscourseConnective> environnementale.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13516" docOffset="99">
      <en>In the final analysis, fiscal restructuring is one thing <Alignment alignment="30962" annotation_id="13573">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13573" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> an attack on environmental sustainability is another.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15516">En fin de compte</DiscourseConnective>, la restructuration de la fiscalité est une chose <Alignment alignment="10580" annotation_id="15583">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15583" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'atteinte portée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15604">à</DiscourseConnective> la durabilité environnementale en est une autre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="13631" id="299" name="Katarína Neveďalová">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="13631" docOffset="100">
      <en>- (SK) Madam President, Europe and the European Union want to become the most competitive and the best, most advanced economy in the world.</en>
      <fr>- (SK) Madame la Présidente, l'Europe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15693">et</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne veulent devenir l'économie la plus compétitive, la meilleure et la plus avancée au monde.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13771" docOffset="101">
      <en>In order to achieve that, <Alignment alignment="23952" annotation_id="13797">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13797" sense="Comparison.Contrast">however</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, we should not just talk about funding and various related matters, <Alignment alignment="26912" annotation_id="13873">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="13873" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, as the European Union, we should certainly invest more in education, science, research and innovation.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="13797" annotation_id="15805">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15805" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15816">pour</DiscourseConnective> y parvenir, nous ne devrions pas seulement parler de financement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15886">et</DiscourseConnective> d'autres questions connexes, <Alignment alignment="13873" annotation_id="15918">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="15918" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'Union européenne devrait certainement accroître les investissements dans l'enseignement, les sciences, la recherche <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16041">et</DiscourseConnective> l'innovation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="13981" docOffset="102">
      <en>The European Commission very recently published some additional results of research into Member State investments in this area.</en>
      <fr>La Commission européenne a publié tout récemment des résultats supplémentaires de recherches menées sur les investissements effectués par les États membres dans ce domaine.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14109" docOffset="103">
      <en>The countries were divided into four groups, <Alignment alignment="38097" annotation_id="14154">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14154" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> my own country, Slovakia, unfortunately obtained a very unflattering place in only the third group, investing just 0.48% of the original 2% it had committed to investing in science, education and research in Europe 2020.</en>
      <fr>Les pays ont été répartis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16257">en</DiscourseConnective> quatre groupes <Alignment alignment="13815" annotation_id="16275">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16275" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> mon propre pays, la Slovaquie, occupe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16316">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective> une position très peu flatteuse dans le troisième groupe seulement, ses investissements s'élevant à 0,48 % sur les 2 % qu'elle s'était initialement engagée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16488">à</DiscourseConnective> investir dans le domaine des sciences, de l'enseignement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16547">et</DiscourseConnective> de la recherche dans le cadre d'Europe 2020.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14379" docOffset="104">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="16607" annotation_id="14387">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14387" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to ask the EU, the European Parliament, the Commission and the Council to try harder to support Member States, and to push harder for them to invest in this area, <Alignment alignment="41355" annotation_id="14565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="14565" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is only through the money we invest in research, innovation and education that we can really fulfil the objectives of Europe 2020.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="3475" annotation_id="16607">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16607" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> demander à l'UE, au Parlement européen, à la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16668">et</DiscourseConnective> au Conseil de consacrer plus d'efforts au soutien des États membres <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16739">et</DiscourseConnective> de les inciter encore plus <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16769">à</DiscourseConnective> investir dans ce domaine, <Alignment alignment="5700" annotation_id="16797">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16797" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> c'est uniquement grâce aux investissements destinés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16853">à</DiscourseConnective> la recherche, à l'innovation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16884">et</DiscourseConnective> à l'enseignement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16904">que</DiscourseConnective> nous pourrons réellement atteindre les objectifs d'Europe 2020.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="14707" id="300" name="Pat the Cope Gallagher">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="14707" docOffset="105">
      <en>(GA) Madam President, for the last 20 years the Union has taken a central role in encouraging peace and reconciliation in Ireland.</en>
      <fr>(GA) Madame la Présidente, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16999">depuis</DiscourseConnective> vingt ans, l'Union exerce un rôle essentiel dans l'encouragement de la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17082">et</DiscourseConnective> de la réconciliation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17106">en</DiscourseConnective> Irlande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="14838" docOffset="106">
      <en>The Union has given more than EUR 1.3 billion to the Programme for Peace and Reconciliation since 1994 and around EUR 349 million to the International Fund for Ireland.</en>
      <fr>L'Union a octroyé plus de 1,3 milliard d'euros au Programme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17178">pour</DiscourseConnective> la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17191">et</DiscourseConnective> la réconciliation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17212">depuis</DiscourseConnective> 1994 <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17224">et</DiscourseConnective> environ 349 millions d'euros au Fonds international <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17279">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Irlande.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15007" docOffset="107">
      <en>The violent incidents in east Belfast and the murder of Ronan Kerr show how important it is to continue with those schemes which encourage economic and social development on both sides of the border.</en>
      <fr>Les violents incidents qui se sont produits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17339">à</DiscourseConnective> Belfast-Est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17353">et</DiscourseConnective> l'assassinat de Ronan Kerr démontrent qu'il est crucial de poursuivre ces programmes qui favorisent le développement économique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17484">et</DiscourseConnective> social des deux côtés de la frontière.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15207" docOffset="108">
      <en>This week, representatives from the International Fund for Ireland and the Programme for Peace and Reconciliation were here in the European Parliament to speak to the Regional Development Committee on the importance of the support of Parliament and the Union for this programme.</en>
      <fr>Cette semaine, des représentants du Fonds international <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17582">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Irlande <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17597">et</DiscourseConnective> du programme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17613">pour</DiscourseConnective> la paix <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17626">et</DiscourseConnective> la réconciliation se sont rendus dans ce Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17680">pour</DiscourseConnective> discuter avec la commission du développement régional de l'importance du soutien du Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17779">et</DiscourseConnective> de l'Union en faveur de ce programme.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15486" docOffset="109">
      <en>I believe strongly that the European Union and the other international partners should think hard about the issue and make the decision to continue with this worthwhile and effective programme.</en>
      <fr>Je crois fermement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17839">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17862">et</DiscourseConnective> les autres partenaires internationaux devraient sérieusement réfléchir à cette question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17953">et</DiscourseConnective> décider de poursuivre ce programme utile <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17997">et</DiscourseConnective> efficace.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="15680" id="301" name="John Bufton">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="15680" docOffset="110">
      <en>Madam President, farming is the heart of the Welsh economy, yet under increasing EU legislation Welsh farmers are prevented from competing successfully, despite standards being some of the highest in Europe.</en>
      <fr>(EN) Madame la Présidente, l'élevage est au cœur de l'économie galloise, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18083">mais</DiscourseConnective> sous le poids croissant de la législation européenne, les éleveurs gallois n'ont pas la possibilité d'être concurrentiels, malgré les normes, qui sont parmi les plus élevées d'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15888" docOffset="111">
      <en>Under EID regulations, farmers are fined for inaccurate data, despite serious faults with the technology.</en>
      <fr>Conformément aux réglementations relatives à l'identification électronique, les éleveurs reçoivent une amende en cas de données inexactes, malgré les graves défauts que présente la technologie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="15994" docOffset="112">
      <en>I have presented this issue to the Commission on numerous occasions, <Alignment alignment="22757" annotation_id="16063">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="16063" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> have representatives from many Member States.</en>
      <fr>J'ai soumis cette question <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18493">à</DiscourseConnective> la Commission <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18509">à</DiscourseConnective> de nombreuses reprises, <Alignment alignment="434" annotation_id="18535">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18535" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> l'ont fait des représentants de bon nombre d'États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16112" docOffset="113">
      <en>Welsh farmers feel the flawed EID system amounts to a stealth tax.</en>
      <fr>Les éleveurs gallois ont le sentiment que le système d'identification électronique défaillant équivaut <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18704">à</DiscourseConnective> une taxe cachée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16179" docOffset="114">
      <en>On another matter, Welsh cattle under 24 months of age cannot be labelled as Welsh under PGI legislation.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18723">Par ailleurs</DiscourseConnective>, conformément à la législation relative aux IGP, le bétail gallois de moins de 24 mois ne peut recevoir le label gallois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16285" docOffset="115">
      <en>The same is not true in Scotland, where the beef industry can label meat from any age of animal with the country stamp.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est pas le cas <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18878">en</DiscourseConnective> Écosse, où l'industrie bovine peut utiliser le label du pays quel que soit l'âge de l'animal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16405" docOffset="116">
      <en>Wales is producing fantastic beef and must be able to label it as Welsh.</en>
      <fr>Le pays de Galles produit une viande bovine formidable <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19030">et</DiscourseConnective> doit pouvoir lui attribuer le label gallois.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16478" docOffset="117">
      <en>Trade in the global market depends upon a country's produce being promoted.</en>
      <fr>Les échanges sur le marché mondial dépendent de la promotion consacrée aux produits d'un pays.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="16554" docOffset="118">
      <en>These are significant matters for hundreds of farmers in Wales who run high-quality businesses that in many cases have been in families for generations. I demand explanations.</en>
      <fr>C'est une question fondamentale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19205">pour</DiscourseConnective> des centaines d'éleveurs gallois qui gèrent des entreprises d'excellente qualité qui, dans bien des cas, sont des entreprises familiales transmises de génération <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19372">en</DiscourseConnective> génération.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="16730" id="302" name="Oriol Junqueras Vies">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="16730" docOffset="119">
      <en>(ES) Madam President, I wish to express my support for the package of measures designed to strengthen the economic governance of the Union, as well as the measures aimed at clarifying and speeding up the disciplinary procedure for any Member States with an excessive deficit.</en>
      <fr>(ES) Madame la Présidente, je voudrais appuyer l'ensemble de mesures destinées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19466">à</DiscourseConnective> renforcer la gouvernance économique de l'Union, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19516">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que les mesures visant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19545">à</DiscourseConnective> clarifier <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19557">et</DiscourseConnective> à accélérer la procédure disciplinaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19599">à</DiscourseConnective> l'égard des États membres qui présentent un déficit excessif.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17006" docOffset="120">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="29653" annotation_id="17006">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17006" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, the Union should be aware that some Member States are trying to meet the budget demands that Europe makes of them at the cost of destabilising the accounts of sub-state governments.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="17006" annotation_id="19663">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19663" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, l'Union devrait être consciente <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19706">que</DiscourseConnective> certains États membres essaient de satisfaire aux exigences budgétaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19782">que</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe leur impose et que cela entraîne la déstabilisation des comptes des gouvernements infranationaux.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17197" docOffset="121">
      <en>The Spanish State is a paradigmatic example of that: it is attempting to meet requirements by passing its deficit on to the autonomous governments and local councils.</en>
      <fr>L'État espagnol en est un exemple paradigmatique: il tente de répondre aux exigences <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19978">en</DiscourseConnective> déplaçant son déficit vers les gouvernements autonomes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20036">et</DiscourseConnective> les municipalités.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17364" docOffset="122">
      <en>These practices must be condemned, <Alignment alignment="39244" annotation_id="17399">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17399" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they do not enter into the spirit of the EU's Stability and Growth Pact <Alignment alignment="12586" annotation_id="17479">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17479" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, above all, <Alignment alignment="20198" annotation_id="17495">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17495" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> they greatly harm the economic recovery of economically powerful nations such as Catalonia.</en>
      <fr>Ces pratiques sont <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20077">à</DiscourseConnective> condamner <Alignment alignment="18749" annotation_id="20089">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20089" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles ne s'inscrivent pas dans l'esprit du pacte de stabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20160">et</DiscourseConnective> de croissance de l'UE <Alignment alignment="10614" annotation_id="20185">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20185" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20189">surtout</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="3172" annotation_id="20198">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20198" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>elles portent un grave préjudice au redressement économique de nations économiquement puissantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20304">comme</DiscourseConnective> la Catalogne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="17595" id="303" name="Csaba Sógor">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="17595" docOffset="123">
      <en>(HU) Madam President, the EU does not interfere with the administrative affairs of its Member States.</en>
      <fr>(HU) Madame la Présidente, l'UE ne s'immisce pas dans les affaires administratives de ses États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17697" docOffset="124">
      <en>It is important to highlight this, <Alignment alignment="20463" annotation_id="17732">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="17732" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> today some Romanian politicians explain the necessity of administrative reorganisation by claiming that this is the only way Romania can receive more money from the Structural Funds.</en>
      <fr>Il est essentiel de le souligner, <Alignment alignment="17732" annotation_id="20463">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20463" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, aujourd'hui, certains hommes politiques roumains justifient la nécessité d'une réorganisation administrative <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20577">en</DiscourseConnective> affirmant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20590">que</DiscourseConnective> c'est la seule manière pour la Roumanie de recevoir plus d'argent des Fonds structurels.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="17923" docOffset="125">
      <en>The current debate in Romania is about a reform that would create eight NUTS 2 level administrative units from the current 41 counties that are NUTS 3 administrative units, <Alignment alignment="20909" annotation_id="18096">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18096" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ignoring geographical, economic, social and cultural realities.</en>
      <fr>Le débat mené actuellement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20710">en</DiscourseConnective> Roumanie porte sur une réforme qui entraînerait la création de huit unités administratives de niveau NUTS 2 à partir des 41 régions actuelles qui sont des unités administratives de niveau NUTS 3, <Alignment alignment="418" annotation_id="20909">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20909" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> ignorant les caractéristiques géographiques, économiques, sociales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20984">et</DiscourseConnective> culturelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18166" docOffset="126">
      <en>The main debates concern the Romanian Hungarians in particular, <Alignment alignment="29575" annotation_id="18230">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18230" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> this native national community, despite the provisions enshrined in the relevant convention of the Council of Europe, would not represent a majority in any of the new administrative units and would lose its rights to set up a local government.</en>
      <fr>Les principaux débats concernent les Hongrois de Roumanie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21058">en particulier</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="4436" annotation_id="21074">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21074" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> cette communauté ethnique indigène, malgré les dispositions contenues dans la convention correspondante du Conseil de l'Europe, ne représenterait aucune majorité dans les nouvelles unités administratives <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21282">et</DiscourseConnective> perdrait ses droits <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21305">à</DiscourseConnective> la constitution d'un gouvernement local.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18482" docOffset="127">
      <en>The EU has to ensure that Member States not only expect the EU itself to observe the principle of subsidiarity, <Alignment alignment="36349" annotation_id="18594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18594" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that they, too, ensure that decision making takes place as close to the citizens as possible.</en>
      <fr>L'UE doit veiller <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21366">à</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21371">que</DiscourseConnective> les États membres s'attendent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21405">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> à ce que l'UE elle-même respecte le principe de subsidiarité, <Alignment alignment="4142" annotation_id="21481">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21481" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> à ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21497">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils garantissent <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21517">que</DiscourseConnective> les décisions soient prises le plus près possible des citoyens.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="18692" id="304" name="Cristian Silviu Buşoi">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="18692" docOffset="128">
      <en>(RO) Madam President, <Alignment alignment="40213" annotation_id="18714">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18714" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> you are probably aware, the second round of voting took place this weekend in the local elections in Chişinău, in the Republic of Moldova.</en>
      <fr>(RO) Madame la Présidente, <Alignment alignment="11616" annotation_id="21612">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21612" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> vous le savez probablement, le deuxième tour des élections locales a eu lieu ce week-end <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21707">à</DiscourseConnective> Chisinau, dans la République de Moldavie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="18856" docOffset="129">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3594" annotation_id="18856">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18856" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">As</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> was <Alignment alignment="44147" annotation_id="18863">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="18863" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> noted by the OSCE observers, these elections, like those in other locations in the Republic of Moldova, were conducted largely in accordance with European and international standards, marking real progress compared to the parliamentary elections which took place in 2010.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="6044" annotation_id="21751">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21751" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">Comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les observateurs de l'OSCE l'ont <Alignment alignment="18863" annotation_id="21790">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21790" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remarqué, ces élections, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21825">comme</DiscourseConnective> d'autres élections tenues dans d'autres lieux de la République de Moldavie, se sont déroulées dans l'ensemble conformément aux normes européennes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21977">et</DiscourseConnective> internationales, ce qui représente un réel progrès par rapport aux élections parlementaires de 2010.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19140" docOffset="130">
      <en>I can only rejoice at the local election results in the Republic of Moldova, which have strengthened the position of the parties in the Alliance for European Integration, currently in government.</en>
      <fr>Je ne peux que me réjouir des résultats des élections locales organisées dans la République de Moldavie, qui révèlent le renforcement de la position des partis de l'Alliance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22255">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'intégration européenne, qui est actuellement au pouvoir au sein du gouvernement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19336" docOffset="131">
      <en>The results of the elections <Alignment alignment="16013" annotation_id="19365">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19365" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> send a very clear signal from Moldova's citizens that their aspiration to become a prosperous, democratic society and for the Republic of Moldova to be integrated into the European Union is strong and real.</en>
      <fr>Ces résultats reflètent <Alignment alignment="9373" annotation_id="22367">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22367" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> très clairement le souhait ferme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22410">et</DiscourseConnective> réel des citoyens moldaves de constituer une société démocratique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22479">et</DiscourseConnective> prospère et de voir la République de Moldavie rejoindre l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19577" docOffset="132">
      <en>They must <Alignment alignment="22594" annotation_id="19587">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="19587" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> provide encouragement to the parties in the Alliance for European Integration to continue implementing the reforms which they have committed to undertake.</en>
      <fr>Les résultats des élections doivent <Alignment alignment="15115" annotation_id="22594">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22594" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> encourager les partis de l'Alliance <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22636">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'intégration européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22666">à</DiscourseConnective> continuer de mettre en œuvre les réformes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22710">qu'</DiscourseConnective>ils se sont engagés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22733">à</DiscourseConnective> entreprendre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19747" docOffset="133">
      <en>On a personal note, I welcome and am delighted that Dorin Chirtoacă won a new term of office as Mayor of Chişinău.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22749">Pour terminer</DiscourseConnective> par une remarque d'ordre personnel, je me félicite <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22814">et</DiscourseConnective> suis ravi <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22827">que</DiscourseConnective> Dorin Chirtoacă ait pu renouveler son mandat de maire de Chisinau.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="19862" id="305" name="Zbigniew Ziobro">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="19862" docOffset="134">
      <en>(PL) Madam President, public opinion in Poland was shocked recently by an event which took place at six o'clock in the morning.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Madame la Présidente, les citoyens polonais ont été récemment choqués par un événement qui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="22994">s'</DiscourseConnective>est produit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23008">à</DiscourseConnective> six heures du matin.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="19990" docOffset="135">
      <en>Eight armed officials, including six special services agents, forced their way into one of the flats in a tower block.</en>
      <fr>Huit fonctionnaires armés, dont six agents des services spéciaux, sont entrés de force dans un appartement d'une tour d'habitation.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20109" docOffset="136">
      <en>There was nothing strange about this, <Alignment alignment="1518" annotation_id="20147">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20147" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the residents of the block included an individual wanted for drug dealing, an arms trader <Alignment alignment="33832" annotation_id="20243">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20243" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> someone suspected of organising bank robberies.</en>
      <fr>Il n'y avait rien d'étrange <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23191">à</DiscourseConnective> cela, <Alignment alignment="2060" annotation_id="23199">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23199" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> parmi les habitants de cet immeuble se trouvaient une personne recherchée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23277">pour</DiscourseConnective> trafic de drogue, un trafiquant d'armes <Alignment alignment="18211" annotation_id="23322">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23322" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> une personne soupçonnée d'organiser des cambriolages de banques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20295" docOffset="137">
      <en>Yet the victim was none of these people.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23390">Cependant</DiscourseConnective>, la victime n'était aucune de ces personnes.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20336" docOffset="138">
      <en>The block of flats was home to an Internet user, a student who had the courage to describe the current government's actions ironically.</en>
      <fr>L'immeuble à appartements abritait un internaute, un étudiant, qui a eu le courage de décrire avec ironie les actions actuelles du gouvernement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20472" docOffset="139">
      <en>It is highly alarming <Alignment alignment="23301" annotation_id="20494">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20494" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> those in power are so sensitive to criticism, satire and laughter that they send armed officials at six o'clock in the morning to students who use the Internet.</en>
      <fr>Il est extrêmement préoccupant <Alignment alignment="9460" annotation_id="23621">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23621" sense="Contingency.Condition">que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les autorités soient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23646">si</DiscourseConnective> sensibles aux critiques, à la satire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23686">et</DiscourseConnective> aux rires au point d'envoyer des fonctionnaires armés <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23743">à</DiscourseConnective> six heures du matin, à la recherche d'étudiants qui utilisent l'internet.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20658" docOffset="140">
      <en>Such practices should be opposed, particularly here in the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Il convient de s'opposer à ce type de pratiques, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="23868">notamment</DiscourseConnective> ici, au Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="20738" id="306" name="Jacek Olgierd Kurski">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="20738" docOffset="141">
      <en>(PL) Madam President, in 10 days' time Poland will take over the presidency of the European Union, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20837" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="20841" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective> we should keep a close check on what is happening in Poland.</en>
      <fr>(PL) Madame la Présidente, étant donné que dans dix jours la Pologne prendra la Présidence de l'Union européenne, il est judicieux de vérifier de près ce qui se passe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24073">en</DiscourseConnective> Pologne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="20912" docOffset="142">
      <en>The quality of democracy can be measured by the way in which the opposition is treated.</en>
      <fr>Il est possible d'évaluer la qualité de la démocratie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24139">en</DiscourseConnective> observant la manière dont l'opposition est considérée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21000" docOffset="143">
      <en>In Poland, unfortunately, a witch-hunt is being conducted against the opposition, <Alignment alignment="13286" annotation_id="21082">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21082" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the courts have joined in.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24197">En</DiscourseConnective> Pologne, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24209">malheureusement</DiscourseConnective>, une chasse aux sorcières est menée contre l'opposition <Alignment alignment="21082" annotation_id="24281">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24281" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les tribunaux ont rejoint ce mouvement.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21113" docOffset="144">
      <en>In the case involving the former prime minister and leader of the opposition, Jarosław Kaczyński, a court has ordered that he undergo psychiatric tests.</en>
      <fr>Dans l'affaire impliquant l'ancien Premier ministre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24376">et</DiscourseConnective> chef de l'opposition, Jarosław Kaczyński, un tribunal lui a ordonné de se soumettre à des tests psychiatriques.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21266" docOffset="145">
      <en>This is especially mean in view of the fact that the only reason for ordering him to undergo such tests was that he admitted that he had used sedatives after the Smolensk tragedy, in which his brother, sister-in-law and many of his friends died.</en>
      <fr>C'est particulièrement mesquin, car cet ordre était uniquement motivé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24561">par le fait qu'</DiscourseConnective>il a admis avoir utilisé des tranquillisants <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24621">après</DiscourseConnective> la tragédie de Smolensk, dans laquelle son frère, sa belle-sœur <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24691">et</DiscourseConnective> de nombreux amis ont perdu la vie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21512" docOffset="146">
      <en>There was nothing unusual in this, <Alignment alignment="3157" annotation_id="21547">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21547" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it is backed up by the appropriate medical documentation.</en>
      <fr>Cela n'avait rien d'inhabituel, <Alignment alignment="3344" annotation_id="24761">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24761" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le démontre la documentation médicale correspondante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21609" docOffset="147">
      <en>This turn of events is deplorable <Alignment alignment="5039" annotation_id="21643">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21643" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it has a European subtext, <Alignment alignment="28533" annotation_id="21676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21676" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we will see its culmination on 6 July. It is on this date that Jarosław Kaczyński will undergo psychiatric tests, <Alignment alignment="6702" annotation_id="21794">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="21794" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Donald Tusk is to deliver an inauguration speech in Strasbourg for his presidency of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>Ces événements sont regrettables <Alignment alignment="1989" annotation_id="24854">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24854" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>ils <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24867">s'</DiscourseConnective>inscrivent dans un contexte européen <Alignment alignment="3114" annotation_id="24906">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="24906" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> leur point culminant aura lieu le 6 juillet, date à laquelle Jarosław Kaczyński passera les tests psychiatriques, <Alignment alignment="22797" annotation_id="25023">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25023" sense="Comparison.Contrast">tandis que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Donald Tusk prononcera un discours inaugural <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25079">à</DiscourseConnective> Strasbourg, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25093">à</DiscourseConnective> l'occasion de la Présidence de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="21905" docOffset="148">
      <en>I hope that the international community will protest against the abuse of psychiatric tests for political battles, following the model of the Soviet Union and Belarus.</en>
      <fr>J'espère <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25155">que</DiscourseConnective> la communauté internationale protestera contre les abus de tests psychiatriques dans les batailles politiques, comme dans le cas de l'Union soviétique <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="25310">et</DiscourseConnective> de la Biélorussie.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="22073" id="307" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="22073" docOffset="149">
      <en>That concludes the debate on this item.</en>
      <fr>Le débat est clos.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
