<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>6.</en>
    <fr>6.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Innovative financing at a global and European level (</en>
    <fr>Le financement innovant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="27">à</DiscourseConnective> l'échelon européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="48">et</DiscourseConnective> mondial (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="57" id="141" name="Jean-Paul Gauzès">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="57" docOffset="2">
      <en>(FR) Madam President, I regret that there is some confusion in this report by Mrs Podimata, which raises a number of important issues with regard to innovative financing.</en>
      <fr>Madame la Présidente, dans ce rapport Podimata qui soulève un certain nombre de questions importantes <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="163">pour</DiscourseConnective> le financement d'innovations, je regrette une certaine confusion.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="228" docOffset="3">
      <en>I would like to ask the Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament to withdraw the alternative motion it has tabled <Alignment alignment="319" annotation_id="390">
          <Alignment alignment="1870" annotation_id="390">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="390" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> the joint drafting work that has been carried out can be concluded.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais demander au groupe S&amp;D de retirer la motion alternative qu'il a proposée <Alignment alignment="228" annotation_id="319">
          <Alignment alignment="679" annotation_id="319">
            <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="319" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">de manière à ce que</DiscourseConnective>
          </Alignment>
        </Alignment> le travail d'élaboration commune qui a été fait puisse être mené à son bout.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="466" docOffset="4">
      <en>Secondly, I regret that a slightly artificial opposition has emerged on the issue of a tax on financial transactions <Alignment alignment="531" annotation_id="583">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="583" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that there are two very similar amendments.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="416">En second lieu</DiscourseConnective>, je regrette <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="444">qu'</DiscourseConnective>une opposition un peu factice soit intervenue sur la question de la taxe financière <Alignment alignment="505" annotation_id="531">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="531" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="534">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il y ait deux amendements qui soient très proches l'un de l'autre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="631" docOffset="5">
      <en>I regret that, <Alignment alignment="619" annotation_id="646">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="646" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">as a result</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Parliament cannot express its overwhelming support for this tax in conditions that are reasonable with regard to Europe's competitiveness.</en>
      <fr>Je regrette <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="616">qu'</DiscourseConnective>
        <Alignment alignment="1442" annotation_id="619">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="619" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Parlement ne puisse pas manifester de façon massive son approbation <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="696">à</DiscourseConnective> cette taxe dans des conditions qui soient des conditions raisonnables au regard de la compétitivité de l'Europe.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="798" id="142" name="Martin Schulz">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="798" docOffset="6">
      <en>(DE) Madam President, I can tell Mr Gauzès this: yes, we intend withdrawing this draft for an alternative resolution.</en>
      <fr>(DE) Madame la Présidente, je dirai ceci à M. Gauzès: oui, nous comptons retirer notre proposition de résolution alternative.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="916" docOffset="7">
      <en>I recommended this to my group for a very simple reason: The following amendment, which has been signed by 120 Members from all groups, shows that proposals regarding a financial transaction tax are not the preserve of any one group, whether the socialists, conservatives, the Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) or the Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance.</en>
      <fr>Je l'ai conseillé <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="955">à</DiscourseConnective> mon groupe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="969">pour</DiscourseConnective> une raison toute simple: l'amendement a été signé par cent vingt députés de tous les groupes politiques, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1079">preuve que</DiscourseConnective> les propositions de taxe sur les transactions financières ne sont pas l'apanage d'un groupe, que ce soit le groupe des socialistes, les conservateurs, le Parti populaire européen (Démocrates-Chrétiens) <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1292">ou</DiscourseConnective> le groupe Verts/Alliance libre européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1303" docOffset="8">
      <en>The point is that we are making an institutional proposal and issuing an institutional signal that this House is capable of saying on a cross-party basis: 'We want the private sector to pay its share in dealing with the burden of the crisis'.</en>
      <fr>C'est une proposition institutionnelle qui envoie un signal institutionnel selon lequel la présente Assemblée est capable de dire, tous partis confondus: "Nous voulons que le secteur privé paie sa part dans la gestion de la crise".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1546" docOffset="9">
      <en>This is not a socialist demand, or a PPE Group demand; it is our common wish.</en>
      <fr>Ce n'est pas une requête socialiste <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1606">ou</DiscourseConnective> une demande émanant du groupe PPE.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1624" docOffset="10">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="3783" annotation_id="1624">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1624" sense="Contingency.Condition">If</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we manage to express this today on an institutional basis, then this will be a major success for the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>C'est notre volonté à tous. <Alignment alignment="928" annotation_id="1672">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1672" sense="Contingency.Condition">Si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous parvenons à l'exprimer aujourd'hui, sur une base institutionnelle, le Parlement européen aura remporté une belle victoire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1749" docOffset="11">
      <en>This is why we are withdrawing this motion.</en>
      <fr>Voila pourquoi nous retirons la proposition.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1793" docOffset="12">
      <en>(Applause)</en>
      <fr>(Applaudissements)</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="1804" id="143" name="Rodi Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="1804" docOffset="13">
      <en>(EL) Madam President, yesterday in plenary, the Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) put forward another proposal which could constitute a compromise.</en>
      <fr>(EL) Madame la Présidente, hier, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1900">en</DiscourseConnective> plénière, le groupe du Parti populaire européen (Démocrates-Chrétiens) a déposé un autre projet, qui pourrait constituer un compromis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1977" docOffset="14">
      <en>It was: could it be made clear that resources will be channelled to the EU budget and the support mechanism?</en>
      <fr>Nous y demandions si l'on pouvait garantir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2081">que</DiscourseConnective> des ressources ainsi engrangées alimentent le budget européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2147">et</DiscourseConnective> le mécanisme de soutien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2086" docOffset="15">
      <en>We tabled the subject for debate yesterday <Alignment alignment="3458" annotation_id="2129">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2129" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we are waiting for a reply, <Alignment alignment="2265" annotation_id="2161">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2161" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so that</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we can reach a compromise and send a positive message to the EU institutions.</en>
      <fr>Nous avions mis ce thème <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2200">à</DiscourseConnective> l'ordre du jour du débat d'hier <Alignment alignment="461" annotation_id="2234">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2234" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> nous attendons une réponse, <Alignment alignment="2161" annotation_id="2265">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2265" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">afin de</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> pouvoir conclure un compromis <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2303">et</DiscourseConnective> envoyer un signe positif aux institutions de l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
