<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>Second European Roma Summit (motions for resolutions tabled): see Minutes</en>
    <fr>Deuxième sommet européen sur les Roms (propositions de résolution déposées): voir procès-verbal</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="74" docOffset="1">
    <en>* * *</en>
    <fr>* * *</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="80" id="077" name="Bruno Gollnisch">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="80" docOffset="2">
      <en>(FR) Mr President, through a ruling given on 19 March, the Court of Justice of the European Union has just declared that the majority of our Parliament violated a clear rule of law by refusing to defend my immunity on the basis of Article 10 of the international protocol, <Alignment alignment="402" annotation_id="353">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="353" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> requested by my foreign colleagues, led by Mr Romagnoli.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, par un arrêt qui a été rendu le 19 mars, la Cour de justice de l'Union européenne vient de déclarer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="225">que</DiscourseConnective> la majorité de notre Parlement avait violé une règle de droit caractérisée <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="304">en</DiscourseConnective> refusant de défendre mon immunité sur le fondement de l'article 10 du protocole international, <Alignment alignment="608" annotation_id="402">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="402" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que l'en avaient prié mes collègues étrangers conduits par le député Luca Romagnoli.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="413" docOffset="3">
      <en>This request was made <Alignment alignment="504477" annotation_id="435">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="435" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I was the victim of violent political, professional and legal persecution for the crime of 'telling journalists who were interviewing me on revisionism and the history of the Second World War that these questions were a matter for historians to debate'.</en>
      <fr>Cette demande avait été formulée <Alignment alignment="435" annotation_id="526">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="526" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> j'étais l'objet de violentes persécutions politiques, professionnelles <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="607">et</DiscourseConnective> judiciaires <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="622">pour</DiscourseConnective> le crime "d'avoir répondu aux journalistes m'interrogeant sur le révisionnisme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="706">et</DiscourseConnective> l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="711">histoire de</DiscourseConnective> la Seconde Guerre mondiale <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="750">que</DiscourseConnective> ces questions relevaient du débat des historiens".</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="694" docOffset="4">
      <en>This is in paragraph 108 of the ruling.</en>
      <fr>Il <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="808">s'</DiscourseConnective>agit du paragraphe 108 de l'arrêt.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="734" docOffset="5">
      <en>The Court states, and I quote: 'Since the aim of the protocol is to grant rights to the Members of the European Parliament, it follows that by failing to give a verdict on the basis of Article 10, Parliament violated a rule of law in a sufficiently clear manner'.</en>
      <fr>Je le cite, je cite la Cour: "<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="875">Dès lors que</DiscourseConnective> le protocole a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="903">pour</DiscourseConnective> objet de conférer des droits aux membres du Parlement, il s'ensuit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="975">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> s'abstenant de se prononcer sur la base de l'article 10, le Parlement a violé de manière suffisamment caractérisée une règle de droit."</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="998" docOffset="6">
      <en>It is true that the Court is not complying with my request for indemnity <Alignment alignment="3058" annotation_id="1071">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1071" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> it believes that the French Court of Appeal and its 11 judges found me totally and definitively innocent.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1117">Certes</DiscourseConnective>, la Cour ne fait pas droit <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1151">à</DiscourseConnective> ma demande d'indemnité <Alignment alignment="160" annotation_id="1176">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1176" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">car</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> elle estime <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1192">que</DiscourseConnective> la Cour de cassation française <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1227">et</DiscourseConnective> ses onze magistrats m'ont totalement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1267">et</DiscourseConnective> définitivement innocenté.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1185" docOffset="7">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="1312" annotation_id="1185">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1185" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Consequently</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, it believes that I can no longer cite prejudice.</en>
      <fr>Elle considère, <Alignment alignment="1185" annotation_id="1312">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1312" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">par conséquent</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1328">que</DiscourseConnective> je ne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1338">puis</DiscourseConnective> plus faire état d'un préjudice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1248" docOffset="8">
      <en>The fact remains that it is ordering our Parliament to pay two thirds of the legal costs.</en>
      <fr>Il n'en reste pas moins <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1399">qu'</DiscourseConnective>elle condamne notre Parlement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1432">à</DiscourseConnective> payer les deux tiers des frais de justice.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1338" docOffset="9">
      <en>This decision <Alignment alignment="1502" annotation_id="1352">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1352" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> constitutes a scathing rejection of the partisan tactics that deprived me of parliamentary immunity.</en>
      <fr>Cette décision constitue <Alignment alignment="174" annotation_id="1502">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1502" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> un désaveu cinglant des manœuvres partisanes qui m'ont privé de l'immunité parlementaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1463" docOffset="10">
      <en>Under pressure, the rapporteur resorted to a crude procedural trick.</en>
      <fr>Sous la pression, le rapporteur avait eu recours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1646">à</DiscourseConnective> un grossier artifice de procédure.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1532" docOffset="11">
      <en>This decision sets a precedent of which members of the national right in the European Parliament, whose freedom of expression is constantly under attack, will be able to take advantage in future.</en>
      <fr>Cette décision constitue un précédent, dont les députés de droite nationale au Parlement européen, constamment attaqués dans leur liberté d'expression, pourront se prévaloir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1857">à</DiscourseConnective> l'avenir.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
