<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>1.</en>
    <fr>1.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Amendment of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union with regard to a stability mechanism for Member States whose currency is the euro (</en>
    <fr>Modification du traité sur le fonctionnement de l'Union européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="70">en</DiscourseConnective> ce qui concerne un mécanisme de stabilité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="115">pour</DiscourseConnective> les États membres dont la monnaie est l'euro (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="152" id="036" name="Elmar Brok">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="152" docOffset="2">
      <en>rapporteur. - (DE) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, this European stability mechanism is necessary in order to provide enduring legal assurance <Alignment alignment="327" annotation_id="299">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="299" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in order to guarantee solidarity with countries that are having problems, but also in order to secure the euro, guarantee the necessary budgetary discipline and enable a joint response to growth challenges.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (DE) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="218">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, ce mécanisme de stabilité européen est nécessaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="282">pour</DiscourseConnective> assurer une certitude juridique durable <Alignment alignment="1692" annotation_id="327">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="327" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="330">pour</DiscourseConnective> garantir la solidarité avec les pays connaissant des problèmes, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="399">mais</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="404">également</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="414">pour</DiscourseConnective> sécuriser l'euro, garantir la nécessaire discipline budgétaire <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="482">et</DiscourseConnective> favoriser une réponse européenne commune aux enjeux liés à la croissance.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="510" docOffset="3">
      <en>In view of the time that an ordinary procedure would have taken, and <Alignment alignment="623" annotation_id="579">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="579" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> in order to avoid a referendum in some Member States, this can only be regulated by a simplified Treaty revision procedure.</en>
      <fr>Considérant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="571">le temps qu'</DiscourseConnective>aurait pris une procédure ordinaire, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="620">et</DiscourseConnective> <Alignment alignment="579" annotation_id="623">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="623" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">aussi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="629">pour</DiscourseConnective> éviter la tenue d'un référendum dans certains États membres, cette question ne peut être réglée que par une procédure simplifiée de révision du traité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="708" docOffset="4">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="786" annotation_id="708">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="708" sense="Comparison.Contrast">However</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, Parliament is saying that this should not become the usual procedure <Alignment alignment="882" annotation_id="786">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="786" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> that we should actually proceed here in accordance with the ordinary Treaty revision procedure.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="708" annotation_id="786">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="786" sense="Comparison.Contrast">Toutefois</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, le Parlement déclare <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="818">que</DiscourseConnective> cette option ne devrait pas devenir la procédure habituelle <Alignment alignment="1155" annotation_id="882">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="882" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="885">qu'en</DiscourseConnective> fait nous devrions procéder en cette matière conformément à la procédure ordinaire de révision du traité.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="886" docOffset="5">
      <en>The original proposals stated that this should be a purely intergovernmental method in which the Commission had hardly any role and the European Parliament no role whatsoever.</en>
      <fr>Les propositions originales indiquaient <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1037">qu'</DiscourseConnective>il devrait s'agir d'une méthode purement intergouvernementale où la Commission jouerait un rôle insignifiant <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1149">et</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen aucun rôle du tout.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1062" docOffset="6">
      <en>Today we are able to report that, further to the negotiations that we have held with the Commission, the European Central Bank, the President of the European Council and the President of the Euro Group, in almost all matters concerning models, tests and decision bases, all aspects concerned with defining a framework and proposing a regulation for this in a Community procedure, it has so far been accepted by the European Council, by the Council of Finance Ministers, that the European Parliament can <Alignment alignment="10429" annotation_id="1565">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1565" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> play a part in this process and will play a role in such matters.</en>
      <fr>Aujourd'hui nous pouvons annoncer <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1228">qu'</DiscourseConnective>à la suite de nos négociations avec la Commission, la Banque centrale européenne, le président du Conseil européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1346">et</DiscourseConnective> le président de l'Eurogroupe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1379">pour</DiscourseConnective> presque tous les sujets concernant les modèles, les tests <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1442">et</DiscourseConnective> les motifs de décision, tous les aspects impliquant la définition d'un cadre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1522">et</DiscourseConnective> la proposition d'un règlement selon une procédure communautaire, il a été accepté jusqu'ici par le Conseil européen, par le Conseil des ministres des finances, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1685">que</DiscourseConnective> le Parlement européen peut <Alignment alignment="1565" annotation_id="1716">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1716" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> intervenir dans ce processus et qu'il jouera un rôle dans ces questions.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1636" docOffset="7">
      <en>We were <Alignment alignment="1799" annotation_id="1644">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1644" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">thus</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> not too pleased initially, <Alignment alignment="1851" annotation_id="1676">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1676" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I believe that <Alignment alignment="2784" annotation_id="1695">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1695" sense="Contingency.Condition">if</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Community institutions are used <Alignment alignment="1920" annotation_id="1730">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1730" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> we can start using intergovernmental procedures as in the past, then <Alignment alignment="2027" annotation_id="1803">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1803" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">when</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the time is right it will be easy to arrive at a clear Community policy.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="1799">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1799" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">Ainsi</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, au départ nous n'étions pas très satisfaits, <Alignment alignment="560" annotation_id="1851">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1851" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je pense <Alignment alignment="1842" annotation_id="1865">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1865" sense="Contingency.Condition">que si</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les institutions communautaires sont impliquées <Alignment alignment="1488" annotation_id="1920">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1920" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> que nous pouvons commencer à appliquer des procédures intergouvernementales <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1999">comme</DiscourseConnective> dans le passé, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2020">alors</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="1803" annotation_id="2027">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2027" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">quand</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le bon moment sera venu, il sera facile de parvenir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2085">à</DiscourseConnective> une politique clairement communautaire.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1881" docOffset="8">
      <en>
        <Alignment alignment="2127" annotation_id="1881">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1881" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Since</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the institutional conditions are now in place, we can propose to you that we approve this Treaty revision procedure from the European Council and set it in motion.</en>
      <fr>
        <Alignment alignment="1881" annotation_id="2127">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2127" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">Puisque</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> les conditions institutionnelles sont désormais remplies, nous pouvons vous proposer d'approuver cette procédure de révision du traité élaborée par le Conseil européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2303">et</DiscourseConnective> de la mettre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2319">en</DiscourseConnective> œuvre.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2051" docOffset="9">
      <en>We <Alignment alignment="2340" annotation_id="2054">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2054" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">therefore</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> tabled such amendments with the unanimous approval of the Committee on Constitutional Affairs.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons <Alignment alignment="2054" annotation_id="2340">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2340" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">donc</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> déposé des amendements en ce sens avec l'approbation unanime de la commission des affaires constitutionnelles.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2159" docOffset="10">
      <en>We need to realise that our interpretations have <Alignment alignment="2507" annotation_id="2208">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2208" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> been accepted and confirmed by letters from the President of the Euro Group and the Commissioner for Monetary Affairs, as well as by a letter from the President of the European Council.</en>
      <fr>Nous devons comprendre <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2479">que</DiscourseConnective> nos interprétations ont <Alignment alignment="1663" annotation_id="2507">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2507" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> été acceptées <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2531">et</DiscourseConnective> confirmées par des lettres du président de l'Eurogroupe <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2590">et</DiscourseConnective> du commissaire aux affaires monétaires, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2633">ainsi</DiscourseConnective> que par une lettre du président du Conseil européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="2399" docOffset="11">
      <en>I believe that this provides a reliable basis for our adopting this now in order to secure the euro, which has been a great success for Europe, and to move forward together.</en>
      <fr>Je pense <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2701">que</DiscourseConnective> cela constitue une base solide <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2736">pour que</DiscourseConnective> nous adoptions ce mécanisme <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2773">maintenant</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2784">afin de</DiscourseConnective> sécuriser l'euro, qui a été un grand succès <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2836">pour</DiscourseConnective> l'Europe, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2851">et</DiscourseConnective> d'aller de l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2867">avant</DiscourseConnective> ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="2573" id="037" name="Roberto Gualtieri">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="2573" docOffset="12">
      <en>rapporteur. - (IT) Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, in the report that we are about to vote for, we still have reservations over the decision to adopt a revision of the Treaty on the intergovernmental character of the mechanism, <Alignment alignment="3129" annotation_id="2805">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2805" sense="Comparison.Contrast">but</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> at the same time we are in favour, <Alignment alignment="3174" annotation_id="2844">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2844" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">because</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - <Alignment alignment="4963" annotation_id="2854">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2854" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">as</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> Mr Brok explained - the negotiations that we conducted allowed us to achieve important objectives that relate mainly to the fact that the conditionalities associated with the assistance will be determined by a regulation, hence by a codecision procedure.</en>
      <fr>rapporteur. - (IT) Monsieur le Président, Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2934">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, dans le rapport sur lequel nous allons voter, nous avons <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3005">encore</DiscourseConnective> des réserves sur la décision d'adopter une révision du traité <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3074">à</DiscourseConnective> cause du caractère intergouvernemental du mécanisme, <Alignment alignment="2805" annotation_id="3129">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3129" sense="Comparison.Contrast">mais</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3134">en même temps</DiscourseConnective> nous y sommes favorables, <Alignment alignment="2529" annotation_id="3174">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3174" sense="Contingency.Cause.Reason">parce que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> - <Alignment alignment="2854" annotation_id="3186">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3186" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">comme</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> M. Brok l'a expliqué - les négociations <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3232">que</DiscourseConnective> nous avons menées nous ont permis d'atteindre des objectifs importants liés principalement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3327">au fait</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3335">que</DiscourseConnective> les conditions associées à l'assistance financière seront déterminées par un règlement, donc par une procédure de codécision.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3112" docOffset="13">
      <en>It is therefore fair to vote in favour <Alignment alignment="3498" annotation_id="3151">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3151" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">and</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> I would like to thank the many fellow MEPs who have contributed to this result and mention the privilege of working with Mr Brok, Mr Pirillo's extremely useful advice and also the work of the two rapporteurs from the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs (ECON): Mr Scicluna and Mr Gauzès, Mr Schade, Mrs Häfner and the group coordinators and of course the chairmen of the groups that have given us such significant political support, thank you.</en>
      <fr>Il est <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3472">donc</DiscourseConnective> juste de voter <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3492">pour</DiscourseConnective>, <Alignment alignment="3151" annotation_id="3498">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3498" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">et</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> je voudrais remercier les nombreux collègues qui ont contribué <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3564">à</DiscourseConnective> ce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3569">résultat</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3578">et</DiscourseConnective> souligner le privilège de travailler avec M. Brok, les conseils extrêmement utiles de M. Pirillo <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3678">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3681">également</DiscourseConnective> le travail des deux rapporteurs de la commission des affaires économiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3765">et</DiscourseConnective> monétaires (ECON): M. Scicluna <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3799">et</DiscourseConnective> M. Gauzès, M. Schade, Mme Häfner <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3835">et</DiscourseConnective> le groupe des coordinateurs <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="3866">et</DiscourseConnective>, bien sûr, les présidents des groupes qui nous ont apporté un soutien politique si important. Merci.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
  <Speaker annotation_id="3606" id="038" name="President">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="3606" docOffset="14">
      <en>I would like to welcome the President of the European Commission and the Vice-President of the Commission who are here with us, and also the President-in-Office of the Council.</en>
      <fr>J'ai l'honneur d'accueillir le président de la Commission européenne <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4039">et</DiscourseConnective> le vice-président de la Commission qui sont ici avec nous, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4101">et</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4104">également</DiscourseConnective> le Président <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4127">en</DiscourseConnective> exercice du Conseil.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3783" docOffset="15">
      <en>We have some very important voting, we know that very well, so thank you for your presence at such an important moment.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons un vote très important, nous le savons parfaitement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4215">alors</DiscourseConnective> je vous remercie <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4238">pour</DiscourseConnective> votre présence <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4258">à</DiscourseConnective> un moment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4270">aussi</DiscourseConnective> important.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3903" docOffset="16">
      <en>Ladies and gentlemen, you will be able to comment on the vote tomorrow.</en>
      <fr>Mesdames <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4296">et</DiscourseConnective> Messieurs, vous pourrez commenter le vote demain.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3975" docOffset="17">
      <en>Now is not the time for explanations of vote, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4021" sense="Contingency.Cause.Result">so</DiscourseConnective> please do not make such comments.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4349">Maintenant</DiscourseConnective>, ce n'est pas le moment des explications de vote, je vous prie donc d'éviter de tels commentaires.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="4058" docOffset="18">
      <en>Tomorrow after the vote there will be a time for comments on all the issues - those from today and from tomorrow together.</en>
      <fr>Demain, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4467">après</DiscourseConnective> le vote, il y aura un moment <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4502">pour</DiscourseConnective> les commentaires sur toutes les questions, celles d'aujourd'hui <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="4571">et</DiscourseConnective> celles de demain, ensemble.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
