<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="translator.xsl"?>

<DOCUMENT>
  <ParallelChunk annotation_id="0" docOffset="0">
    <en>2.</en>
    <fr>2.</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="3" docOffset="1">
    <en>Law applicable to divorce and legal separation (</en>
    <fr>Loi applicable au divorce <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="29">et</DiscourseConnective> à la séparation de corps (</fr>
  </ParallelChunk>
<Speaker annotation_id="52" id="185" language="PL" name="Tadeusz Zwiefka">
    <ParallelChunk annotation_id="52" docOffset="2">
      <en>Mr President, a couple of months ago, the European Parliament gave the Council consent for the first time to set in motion an enhanced cooperation procedure.</en>
      <fr>Monsieur le Président, il y a quelques mois, le Parlement européen a <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="128">pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois donné au Conseil son consentement <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="184">pour</DiscourseConnective> la mise <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="197">en</DiscourseConnective> œuvre d'une procédure de coopération renforcée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="210" docOffset="3">
      <en>For the first time in the history of the European Union.</en>
      <fr>
        <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="248">Pour</DiscourseConnective> la première fois dans l'<DiscourseConnective annotation_id="277">histoire de</DiscourseConnective> l'Union européenne.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="267" docOffset="4">
      <en>This is an extremely important step, which opens up a completely new basis for cooperation between a group of Member States of the European Union in situations in which it is not possible to achieve the consent of all 27 Member States.</en>
      <fr>C'est une avancée extrêmement importante, qui instaure une base totalement nouvelle de coopération entre un groupe d'États membres de l'Union européenne dans les situations où il n'est pas possible d'obtenir le consentement de l'ensemble des 27 États membres.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="503" docOffset="5">
      <en>This is a very important decision.</en>
      <fr>C'est une décision très importante.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="538" docOffset="6">
      <en>We have confirmed, today, that this procedure works well.</en>
      <fr>Nous avons confirmé, aujourd'hui, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="639">que</DiscourseConnective> cette procédure fonctionne bien.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="596" docOffset="7">
      <en>I would like to express my very sincere thanks to the Council in particular for the position it adopted as part of its work with the European Parliament.</en>
      <fr>Je souhaiterais exprimer mes remerciements les plus sincères au Conseil, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="749">en particulier</DiscourseConnective> <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="764">pour</DiscourseConnective> la position qu'il a adoptée dans le cadre de son travail avec le Parlement européen.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="750" docOffset="8">
      <en>It is an example of perfect interinstitutional cooperation.</en>
      <fr>C'est un exemple de coopération interinstitutionnelle parfaite.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="810" docOffset="9">
      <en>During work on this resolution, Parliament featured only as a consultative body, <Alignment alignment="1026" annotation_id="891">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="891" sense="Comparison.Contrast">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> the frequency of meetings and the inclusion by the Council of all the proposals which were put forward by the European Parliament and voted on by the Committee on Legal Affairs - their inclusion in the final document - is a perfect example which augurs well for the enhanced cooperation procedure for the future.</en>
      <fr>Au cours des travaux sur cette résolution, le Parlement n'est intervenu qu'en qualité d'organe consultatif, <Alignment alignment="891" annotation_id="1026">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1026" sense="Comparison.Contrast">alors que</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> la fréquence des réunions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1062">et</DiscourseConnective> l'inclusion par le Conseil de toutes les propositions soumises par le Parlement européen <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1154">et</DiscourseConnective> votées par la commission des affaires juridiques - leur inclusion dans le document final - constituent un exemple parfait annonciateur de beaux jours <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1307">pour</DiscourseConnective> la procédure de coopération renforcée.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1210" docOffset="10">
      <en>I <Alignment alignment="1363" annotation_id="1212">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1212" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> thank the Council for its strong support for our proposal on conducting a rapid review of Brussels IIa, which is essential to find detailed solutions, <Alignment alignment="101" annotation_id="1368">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1368" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">for example</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment>, to questions concerning the need for a forum necessitatis rule, a matter which allows Member States to retain certainty as to the working of their internal legal systems <Alignment alignment="140" annotation_id="1551">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1551" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">while</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> at the same time giving our citizens the hope that in the future they will be able to make a free choice not only of applicable law, but also of court.</en>
      <fr>Je remercie <Alignment alignment="1212" annotation_id="1363">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1363" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> le Conseil <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1384">pour</DiscourseConnective> son soutien de taille en faveur de notre proposition de révision rapide de Bruxelles IIa, un élément essentiel <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1500">pour</DiscourseConnective> trouver des solutions détaillées, <Alignment alignment="208" annotation_id="1539">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1539" sense="Expansion.Instantiation">par exemple</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> aux questions relatives à la nécessité d'une règle de forum necessitatis, un sujet qui permet aux États membres de s'assurer du bon fonctionnement de leurs systèmes juridiques nationaux <Alignment alignment="525" annotation_id="1737">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1737" sense="Temporal.Synchrony">tout en</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> donnant à nos concitoyens l'espoir de pouvoir <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1791">un jour</DiscourseConnective> choisir librement, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1818">non seulement</DiscourseConnective> le droit applicable, <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1853">mais aussi</DiscourseConnective> le tribunal.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
<ParallelChunk annotation_id="1709" docOffset="11">
      <en>I would <Alignment alignment="567807" annotation_id="1717">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1717" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">also</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> like to thank my shadow rapporteurs from the Committee on Legal Affairs and the rapporteurs from the committees which were asked for opinions.</en>
      <fr>Je voudrais <Alignment alignment="0" annotation_id="1889">
          <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1889" sense="Expansion.Conjunction">également</DiscourseConnective>
        </Alignment> remercier mes rapporteurs fictifs de la commission des affaires juridiques <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="1974">et</DiscourseConnective> les rapporteurs des commissions <DiscourseConnective annotation_id="2009">pour</DiscourseConnective> avis.</fr>
    </ParallelChunk>
</Speaker>
</DOCUMENT>
